<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="88" link="http://cnn.com/2014/04/06/business/malaysia-china-relations-trade-mh370/index.html?hpt=bosread" date_published="2014-04-07 00:49:43" category="business" author="Pamela Boykoff and Chan Kok Leong, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Lucrative China-Malaysia relations not derailed by search for MH370</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="17">Chinese officials have been careful not to blame Malaysia for the fate of MH370.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">This is contrast to many of the Chinese relatives of passengers.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="14">Trade between China and Malaysia grew to more than US$63.4 billion last year.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-15 17:55:10" annotation_time="48.162">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">Some of the Chinese relatives of passengers aboard the missing Boeing 777 have been openly critical of the investigation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="3">Trade between the two countries that year grew by 12.5% to US $63.4 billion.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;I don&amp;apost;t see it happening as the Chinese authorities, especially their envoy (Huang Huikang) to Malaysia, has given very measured statements and not blamed Malaysia for MH370,&amp;quot; said Navaratnam, who is currently the chairman of the Center for Public Policy Studies at the Asian Strategy and Leadership Institute.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>If the disappearance of Malaysia Airlines Flight MH370 caused a rift in China-Malaysia relations, the two countries appear to have put it behind them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Recent comments by officials in both Kuala Lumpur and Beijing have emphasized the active cooperation between the two countries, while also downplaying accusations lodged by Chinese families against the Malaysian government.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>According to Hong Kong&amp;apost;s South China Morning Post, China&amp;apost;s Ambassador to Malaysia sought to distance these &amp;quot;radical views&amp;quot; from his country&amp;apost;s official position.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>They &amp;quot;do not represent the views of Chinese people and the Chinese government,&amp;quot; he was quoted as saying.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Some of the Chinese relatives of passengers aboard the missing Boeing 777 have been openly critical of the investigation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>They went so far as to release a statement calling the Malaysian government and its military the &amp;quot;real murderers&amp;quot; of their loved ones.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>In a press conference Saturday, Acting Malaysian Transport Minister Hishammuddin Hussein made it clear China will be an accredited member of the investigation team.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>A few days earlier, he spoke about Malaysia&amp;apost;s duty to keep its Asian neighbor informed about all progress.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>James Chin, professor of political science at Monash University in Melbourne, Australia, said the rift always appeared larger in the media than at an official level.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think among the diplomats they do understand this is just a small thing within the larger context of Malaysia-China relations and this will not alter relationships in the long term.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Trade partners.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>At stake between the two countries is a thriving economic relationship.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>According to Malaysia&amp;apost;s Ministry of International Trade, China was Malaysia&amp;apost;s largest trading partner for the fifth consecutive year in 2013.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Trade between the two countries that year grew by 12.5% to US $63.4 billion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Tourism numbers were equally positive, with 1.79 million people visiting from China last year -- an increase of 14.9% from the previous year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Ramon Navaratnam, former Secretary General of the Malaysian Ministry of Transport, said he did not expect trade between the two countries to deteriorate, despite the initial protests by some of the Chinese families of missing passengers on MH370 in Beijing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;I don&amp;apost;t see it happening as the Chinese authorities, especially their envoy (Huang Huikang) to Malaysia, has given very measured statements and not blamed Malaysia for MH370,&amp;quot; said Navaratnam, who is currently the chairman of the Center for Public Policy Studies at the Asian Strategy and Leadership Institute.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Navaratnam, who has authored several books on economics in Malaysia, said the business environment would not change unless the governments decided otherwise.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Lee Hwok Aun, an economics lecturer at the University of Malaya, agreed bilateral trade is not expected to fall off as Malaysia&amp;apost;s primary exports to China consist of electrical components and raw materials such as crude rubber and palm oil -- critical to China&amp;apost;s own economy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;Tourism may suffer some minor setbacks initially but exports won&amp;apost;t change much as China needs raw materials,&amp;quot; said Lee.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s much harder to organize a boycott of component imports and China too wants a steady supply chain.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>