<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="124" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/06/15/business/airplane-recycling-tarmac/index.html" date_published="2012-06-15 10:13:27" category="business" author="Ayesha Durgahee, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>The place where dead airplanes come back to life</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Tarmac Aerosave recycles disused aircraft at its plant in southern France.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="11">Airbus says around 9,000 planes will be retired or withdrawn from service over the next 20 years.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="12">Tarmac believes recycling old aircraft could save airlines considerable amounts of money.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-23 23:53:23" annotation_time="113.50299">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">Tarmac Aerosave has been dismantling disused aircraft at its base in &amp;quot;Aerospace Valley&amp;quot; -- a cluster of French flight engineering firms near the town of Tarbes in southern France -- since it was formed in 2009.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="2">With Tarmac&amp;apost;s parent company, Airbus, predicting that more than 9,000 aircraft will be retired or withdrawn from service over the next 20 years, there&amp;apost;s a clear need for aging planes to be disposed of in an environmentally friendly manner.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="3">By relieving retired models of their most valuable assets, Tarmac also believes it can transform airplane recycling into a lucrative business and one that makes sense for airlines looking to dispose of old models.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Wings clipped, noses cut off, stripped down to the bone, these old birds will never fly again.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But the giant hangar at the home of Tarmac Aerosave is not a graveyard for planes -- it&amp;apost;s a recycling yard.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Tarmac Aerosave has been dismantling disused aircraft at its base in &amp;quot;Aerospace Valley&amp;quot; -- a cluster of French flight engineering firms near the town of Tarbes in southern France -- since it was formed in 2009.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Although the company&amp;apost;s primary business remains aircraft storage, it has stripped 12 planes completely since its inception.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;We receive an old aircraft ... and completion of this work (is) when all the material can be reused,&amp;quot; says Sebastien Medan, head of dismantling at the French aerospace company.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The parts salvaged during this process are repackaged and repurposed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Landing gear and wing flaps are shipped out to be reinstalled in new planes while cockpits are reborn as flight simulators.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>All parts that are saved can be sold on by the aircraft owners.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The remaining waste and scrap metal, meanwhile, is broken down for resale by Tarmac.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;The percentage of the aircraft to be recycled is around 87% (and) actually we expect to rise that to 90%&amp;quot; says Medan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>With Tarmac&amp;apost;s parent company, Airbus, predicting that more than 9,000 aircraft will be retired or withdrawn from service over the next 20 years, there&amp;apost;s a clear need for aging planes to be disposed of in an environmentally friendly manner.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>By relieving retired models of their most valuable assets, Tarmac also believes it can transform airplane recycling into a lucrative business and one that makes sense for airlines looking to dispose of old models.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The cost of storing a disused aircraft can be as much as €20,000 ($25,000) per month.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>This compares to a one-off cost of between €100,000 and €150,000 (between $125,000 and $185,000) to tear down a plane, stripping it of items that can be reused or sold on at a profit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;All the materials we take out from each aircraft could be used in other industry, especially aeronautical industry,&amp;quot; says Medan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>While the efficiency savings this process brings are obvious, Tarmac also believes that dismantling old planes will allow engineers to better design more efficient aircraft in the future.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Understanding how parts erode, decay or develop over time will allow them to transfer that knowledge into new designs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are collecting in-service aircraft components to asses the remaining characteristics and capability in terms of stress and fatigue,&amp;quot; says Olivier Malavallon, project director of business development and change at Airbus.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s crucial in terms of experienced feedback in better designing the aircraft and providing to the designer some guidance -- how best we can assemble things together where things are fitting better.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>As it stands, Tarmac&amp;apost;s site in southern France can cater for 20 aircraft at a time, the company says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Across the border in northern Spain, however, a new site is being prepared by one of the company&amp;apost;s subsidiaries.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>It will be able to store 200 planes at a time, and strip down between 30 and 40 models a year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>According to Malavallon this expansion will enable Tarmac to prepare for the coming influx of retiring planes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>It will also ensure aircraft are disposed of in a way that is efficient and makes the most of valuable materials.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Instead of &amp;quot;going from cradle to grave,&amp;quot; he says, airplanes will go from &amp;quot;cradle to cradle.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Ayesha Durgahee is the resident reporter on CNN&amp;apost;s Business Traveller.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Follow Ayesha on Twitter at @AyeshaCNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
