<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="94" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2011/12/23/business/coal-south-africa-eskom" date_published="2011-12-23 11:27:40" category="business" author="" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>No coal, no growth, says South African power company chief</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Brian Dames is the CEO of South Africa&amp;apost;s power utility company Eskom.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">He argues that coal has allowed SA to become Africa&amp;apost;s biggest economy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="9">South Africa is committed &amp;quot;to move towards a lower carbon footprint over time,&amp;quot; he says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 07:42:26" annotation_time="40.731">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1, 2">It might be one of the world&amp;apost;s worst polluting energy sources, but coal has allowed South Africa to become the continent&amp;apost;s largest economy, according to the chief executive of the country&amp;apost;s power utility company Eskom.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="3">And then it is about, as we do this, how we can do it in a more cleaner manner and at the same time make sure we deal with issues such as job creation -- can we create green jobs -- so we&amp;apost;re very clear as to where we want to go and what the balance is and that commitment is there -- it is there to move towards a lower carbon footprint over time.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>It might be one of the world&amp;apost;s worst polluting energy sources, but coal has allowed South Africa to become the continent&amp;apost;s largest economy, according to the chief executive of the country&amp;apost;s power utility company Eskom.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Speaking to CNN&amp;apost;s Robyn Curnow, Eskom&amp;apost;s Brian Dames said coal has been key to fueling South Africa&amp;apost;s economic growth and improving the lives of many in the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;ve been very successful in the use of coal in growing one of the largest economies, in bringing electricity to the majority of South Africans -- we&amp;apost;re absolutely not defensive about it,&amp;quot; said Dames.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>South Africa gets 86% of its energy from coal and, despite the criticism that it is bad for the environment -- when burned, coal emits more air pollution and greenhouse gases than other major energy sources -- Dames argued that South Africa will continue to use the natural resource.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>An edited version of the interview follows below.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>CNN: Why is coal important for South Africa?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Brian Dames: It&amp;apost;s about energy security first and foremost for us, it&amp;apost;s about affordable energy, it&amp;apost;s about energy access.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>You would agree with me without those three things there is no economic growth, no poverty alleviation, no job creation in any of our economies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>And then it is about, as we do this, how we can do it in a more cleaner manner and at the same time make sure we deal with issues such as job creation -- can we create green jobs -- so we&amp;apost;re very clear as to where we want to go and what the balance is and that commitment is there -- it is there to move towards a lower carbon footprint over time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>CNN: What percentage of energy do you get from coal?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>BD: It&amp;apost;s more than 80%, about 86% of the energy, and it has put us in a position as a company and as a country to really fuel the economic growth in South Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s why this country has got the largest economy on the African continent, that&amp;apost;s why we operate one of the world&amp;apost;s 10 largest power companies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>CNN: Eighty per cent of all your energy comes from coal -- that is dirty energy and South Africa is the biggest producer of coal in the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Don&amp;apost;t you find that difficult in terms of charting a green future?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>BD: No, it is not difficult.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>We should be quite clear, because South Africa&amp;apost;s emissions is about 1.5% of global emissions, the continent&amp;apost;s emissions is about 3% of global emissions, it&amp;apost;s less than 200 times than what&amp;apost;s in the U.S.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>What you&amp;apost;re asking us to do is not do that, not have electricity, not have energy security and not have energy access.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>CNN: I think the reality is Eskom relies heavily on coal, South Africa historically has relied heavily on coal to produce its electricity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Why do you seem a bit defensive about it?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>BD: No, we&amp;apost;re not defensive, absolutely not.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Coal has been used very successfully and will be used in future in South Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a natural resource that we have, we&amp;apost;ve been very successful in the use of coal in growing one of the largest economies, in bringing electricity to the majority of South Africans -- we&amp;apost;re absolutely not defensive about it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>CNN: But it is dirty energy and there is an excess of reliance on coal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>BD: It&amp;apost;s not a question of being defensive, it&amp;apost;s a question about the ill-informed, because you want us as a country to be cleaner and not have electricity and energy and that is a problem.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>CNN: That&amp;apost;s not what I&amp;apost;m saying, it&amp;apost;s a fact that South Africa relies heavily on coal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>BD: It is a fact and successfully have done so.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>We&amp;apost;ve said clearly growth is important, we have said clearly that we&amp;apost;re committed to a low-carbon future over time, so it is not growth at all costs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>South Africa has got a very clear path and strategy and is fully committed to deal with that.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>South Africa has made very clear commitments in terms of its CO2 emissions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>South Africa has also made it very clear that it is a developing country that must grow, that we must see the establishment of funding to make sure that it is available for us to do so.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>We have a clear path as to how we make sure we grow and how we make sure we respond to the needs of the environment and as a country and as company we&amp;apost;re fully committed to that.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>CNN: Is nuclear still a very big part of your plans?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>BD: South Africa has produced a 20-year energy electricity plan and that plan has got an inclusion of nuclear.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>That plan says, of the additional capacity of the next 20 years, 42% of it will be renewables, 23% of it will be nuclear, because we do have requirement for base-load energy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>We can&amp;apost;t stall electricity -- nuclear as a base-load energy option is a viable option for this continent and again, coming back to my previous point, no one option, whether coal or renewables or hydro will solve our energy problems in the future.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>We need a combination of all of it, and including nuclear for that matter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
