<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="54" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/09/12/business/ambrosetti-forum-european-debt-crisis-mpe/index.html" date_published="2013-09-12 18:06:59" category="business" author="Isa Soares, CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Europe feeling the economic winds of change</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="20">Spain and Greece are both struggling under the weight of 56.1% an 62.9% youth unemployment respectively .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="26">Pirelli CEO Provera said that Europe must work closer together to compete with the likes of India and China.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="16">European Commission VP Tajani prioritizing new jobs for young people by creating a new education policy in Europe.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 16:16:19" annotation_time="16.911499">
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="3">In fact, he tells me this is his project: building new jobs for young people by creating a new education policy in Europe.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="1">It&amp;apost;s refreshing to see youth unemployment hasn&amp;apost;t been ignored, after all, Spain and Greece are both struggling under the weight of 56.1% and 62.9% youth unemployment respectively.</sentence>
      <sentence id="26" ids_highlights="2">Marco Tronchetti Provera, the Chairman and CEO of Pirelli, felt strongly about this subject, arguing that to grow again and compete with the likes of China and India, Europe must work closer together.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>What a difference a year makes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Last year, delegates at the Ambrosetti Forum in Italy had a lot to contend with.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The economic crisis was in full bloom and they had urgent concerns: Will Greece leave the eurozone?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Will the euro survive?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Is the project doomed?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>A year on, it seems those worries have eased; the mood has lightened and the crisis is finally over.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Even if you don&amp;apost;t feel it, the latest economic numbers show the eurozone is growing again and confidence has returned to the continent.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Despite the optimism, concerns remain and I&amp;apost;m told time and time again here that Europe still faces a mighty task.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>That much I&amp;apost;m aware of, but what do the captains of industry feel needs to be done to get Europe growing and competing on the world stage?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Unemployment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Andrea Marescotti, the Managing Director of Brembo, one of Italy&amp;apost;s leading manufacturer of automotive brakes, tells me over an espresso that unemployment is his biggest worry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>He tells me job creation should be Europe&amp;apost;s priority &amp;quot;to have stable growth, with growth of consumption, you need to create jobs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>If you don&amp;apost;t produce, you don&amp;apost;t buy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>So the question is how we can foster a stable increase in jobs.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Antonio Tajani, the Vice-President of the European Commission is of the same opinion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>In fact, he tells me this is his project: building new jobs for young people by creating a new education policy in Europe.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>To do this he says, we need to build &amp;quot;a link between schools and small and medium- size businesses.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>This exists in Germany and Austria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>We need this in every European state.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s refreshing to see youth unemployment hasn&amp;apost;t been ignored, after all, Spain and Greece are both struggling under the weight of 56.1% and 62.9% youth unemployment respectively.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>But whilst the talk is promising, I find it rather strange that the discussion is being led by a group of middle-age men who know little of the challenges young people face.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>I know it, because I too have had to deal with student debt, job applications and random jobs on the side.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>But now I&amp;apost;m veering off-point.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Cohesion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Alongside talk of unemployment, growth and competitiveness, key words crept up time and time again to my surprise: cohesion and political union.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Marco Tronchetti Provera, the Chairman and CEO of Pirelli, felt strongly about this subject, arguing that to grow again and compete with the likes of China and India, Europe must work closer together.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>He candidly told me: &amp;quot;We have a Europe that needs a project that refines more deeply the countries.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>We have a Europe that doesn&amp;apost;t have enough cohesion, there are no common projects on the many issues such as energy.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>His words echo those of European Commission President Jose Manuel Barroso, who this week called for a &amp;quot;Europe that is united, strong and open.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>It all returns to his famous quote: &amp;quot;we swim together, we sink together.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Stability and Complacency.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>This year at the Ambrosetti, there is definitely a sense that Europe is thinking together; acknowledging that there can be strength in their numbers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>But for all the talk of Europe&amp;apost;s economic achievements, of green shoots of recovery, there were reminders, alarm bells of sorts of the risks of complacency.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Francesco Caio, the CEO of Avio Group, was perhaps the most pessimistic on Europe -- warning about political instability and complacency &amp;quot;there is still a need to be very alert.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Stability is a competitive factor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>We don&amp;apost;t need a government crisis right now, &amp;quot; he told me.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Four days later in his State of the Union address, Barroso touched on the same subject when he said that the biggest downside risk to Europe&amp;apost;s recovery is political.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Of course, Barroso didn&amp;apost;t single out any particular country, but the warning could have been directed at Italy whose coalition is facing an uncertain political future after the country&amp;apost;s top court found former prime mnister Silvio Berlusconi guilty of tax fraud.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>There is no doubt that Europe is breathing a bit easier again.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The crisis has abated and our politicians are smiling once more.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>But let&amp;apost;s not start popping the prosecco, cava or Champagne just yet.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>The work is just beginning and the scars have yet to heal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Still, what a difference a year makes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
