<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="75" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/11/20/business/is-there-room-for-women-pilots-middle-east/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2013-11-20 17:02:45" category="business" author="Dean Irvine, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Is there room for women pilots in the Middle East?</title>
  <keywords>alia twal,women in aviation,middle east women in aviation,arab women in aviation,pilots,women pilots,female pilots,arab female pilots,female pilots in the Middle East,Air Arabia,Emirates Airlines,Al Maktoum Airport</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="8">450,000 new pilots will need to be trained by 2020.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">With so many spots up for grabs, some think the time is ripe for women to enter the cockpit.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="21">In the Middle East, there is about one female cadet for every 20 male.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-30 14:20:37" annotation_time="51.301666">
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="1">The Professional Aviation Board of Certification estimates that 450,000 new pilots will need to be trained by 2020, with 184,000 in the Asia Pacific region alone.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">With so many positions up for grabs, some believe the time is ripe for women to enter the cockpit.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="3">As an instructor for Air Arabia, she estimates there is on average one female for every 20 cadets.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The Gulf&amp;apost;s three major airlines have spent the week topping up their fleets with record-breaking plane orders.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>In doing so, they begged the question: who&amp;apost;s going to fly all those new planes?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;We estimate that we&amp;apost;ll need around 6,000 pilots by 2020, depending on new delivery timings and old aircraft retirement,&amp;quot; says Nabil Al Boom, a captain and deputy national cadet pilot manager for Emirates Airlines.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>In fitting with its recent order and general expansion plan, the airline plans to build a suitably large, dedicated flight training academy in the empty desert near the new Al Maktoum airport.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Al Boom says he expects it to take 400 cadets each year on a three-and-a-half-year program that is aimed at turning local Emiratis into some of the best pilots in the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is very rewarding to see someone who you&amp;apost;ve almost taken off the street in their dish-dash years later with their stripes on their shoulders,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Emirates isn&amp;apost;t the only airline on the lookout.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The Professional Aviation Board of Certification estimates that 450,000 new pilots will need to be trained by 2020, with 184,000 in the Asia Pacific region alone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>With so many positions up for grabs, some believe the time is ripe for women to enter the cockpit.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Though the region can sometimes take a traditionalist stance on women in the workplace, some female pilots have already started paving the way.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;When I told my parents I wanted to be a pilot, oh my, that was a complete &amp;apost;no-no&amp;apost;,&amp;quot; says 26-year-old Alia Twal, a first officer for Royal Jordanian Airlines.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>It took a year for Twal to convince her father.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Since then, she hasn&amp;apost;t looked back.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>At the age of 21, she became a flight instructor, and now holds the position of governor of the Arabian chapter of The Ninety-Nines, the International Organization of Women Pilots, which, alas, only has 36 members.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Not surprisingly, women continue to be underrepresented in the industry, not just in the Middle East, but globally.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Women only account for 5% of members of the Air Line Pilots Association -- the trade organization that represents pilots at U.S. and Canadian carriers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>According to Twal, there are only 20 female pilots in all of Jordan (paltry, given the country&amp;apost;s population boasts 6.3 million).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>While Twal says attitudes in Jordan are changing for the better, she admits her gender can prove a barrier, especially when she&amp;apost;s charged with training less experienced pilots who are both older, and male.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;They would not be happy, but then you have to find a way to give your message, make a joke for example, so they look at you as a human and not as a woman,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Kristina Tervo is also helping women in the region to get their wings.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>As an instructor for Air Arabia, she estimates there is on average one female for every 20 cadets.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>She&amp;apost;s hoping that will change one day.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>As vice president of the Middle East chapter of Women in Aviation, she&amp;apost;s seen a great deal of potential during school visits and at talks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re keen to get more women into the industry, and what we&amp;apost;re seeing is very encouraging,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;Ultimately it shouldn&amp;apost;t matter who is flying the plane.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Twal agrees: &amp;quot;The plane does not know who is flying her.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>We are all equal.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>[The Ninety-Nines] are trying to give women a chance to create a change and have a voice; I believe every woman is a hero, whatever she does.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
