<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="49" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/03/21/business/opinion-cyprus-bailout-pissarides" date_published="2013-03-21 12:06:04" category="business" author="Christopher Pissarides, special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>EU bailouts: A vehicle to kick the weak?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="47">Those of us who supported the EU integration movement are disappointed, writes Pissarides.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="36">Pissarides says Russians have been investing money into Cyprus from the early 1990s.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="40">Pissarides: &amp;quot;I have never come across anything non-compliant with European rules&amp;quot; in Cyprus.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-08 16:34:10" annotation_time="26.937002">
      <sentence id="36" ids_highlights="2">Attracted by a corporate tax rate of 10% -- half that of Russia&amp;apost;s -- Russians have been investing money into Cyprus from the early 1990s.</sentence>
      <sentence id="40" ids_highlights="3">I have been involved both with central bank policy and with private banking in Cyprus for years (and at different times) and I have never come across anything non-compliant with European rules.</sentence>
      <sentence id="47" ids_highlights="1">Those of us who supported the European integration movement are disappointed.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The recent financial troubles in Cyprus have attracted a range of alarming headlines around the world, but we must be careful to avoid panic and reckless measures that would exacerbate the crisis.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>For in reality, Cyprus -- one of the smallest economies in the eurozone -- has a manageable fiscal deficit, low debt and until very recently a thriving economy, based on financial services and tourism.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Large reserves of natural gas and possibly oil have been discovered off its southern coast, which would bring a bonanza in three to five years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The roots of the crisis go back to 2006 when the Cyprus Popular Bank, the country&amp;apost;s second biggest bank was taken over by a smaller Greek bank.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The new owners invested very heavily in Greek bonds and loans but kept it as a Cypriot bank, instead of transferring the HQ to Greece.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>This was because of the better corporate environment in Cyprus, where tax rates are just 10%, compared to Greece where it is at least double that.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Three years ago the Bank of Cyprus also bought large quantities of Greek bonds, largely for reasons unconnected with their rate of return or risk, to help out Greece.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>In 2011, when a struggling Greece was allowed to let some of its private bond holders take a loss -- a &amp;quot;haircut&amp;quot; -- Cypriot banks lost money and needed refinancing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>So the big financial institutions like the Bank of Cyprus and Popular Bank asked for a bailout from the government, and the government came to the EU in June 2012 saying it needed a bailout in turn.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Last weekend under an EU plan, Cyprus agreed to raise €5.8 billion to prevent debt from ballooning to unsustainable levels.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>This would have seen a bank levy on all deposits over 100,000 euros in banks in Cyprus and a smaller percentage on deposits of more than 20,000 euros.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The measure sparked fury in the Cypriot parliament, prompting Cypriots to withdraw money from bank cash machines and raising fears of a broader run on ailing banks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Russia, which has extensive business and banking ties to the tiny island, was angered by the move.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Prudent bankers attracted depositors by following low-risk strategies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>But now their depositors are asked to pay for the high-risk strategies of other bankers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>High-risk bankers risked their depositors&amp;apost; money.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>But their depositors will not lose more than the depositors of other banks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>This is the logic of the Cyprus &amp;quot;bailout&amp;quot; by the International Monetary Fund, the German-led Euro group and the European Central Bank.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Delinquent bankers&amp;apost; losses are protected by prudent bankers&amp;apost; gains.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>What is the justification?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s better than letting the two risk takers go bankrupt, the argument goes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>That probably is the case.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>But then Greek banks and those of other nations in trouble were also bankrupt, and yet the same troika lend to them on better terms in order to avoid bankruptcy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Greece got 140 billion euros; the haircut on Cypriot depositors will yield 5.8 billion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>But Cyprus could not have the 5.8 billion out of European funds set up to rescue banks in trouble.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Deposits under 100,000 euros are insured in Europe.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Yet, the terms of the euro group are so harsh, that the government of Cyprus could not raise the money without some haircut on the insured deposits.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>It is important to note that on Tuesday the Cypriot parliament rejected a €10 billion eurozone bailout package due to investor alarm over the proposed tax on existing bank deposits.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>However we don&amp;apost;t know what will come next.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Maybe the tax on the insured deposits will yield 2 billion euros.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Agreed said the euro group: we&amp;apost;d prefer not to tax deposits under 100,000 euros but if you cannot afford to raise the 5.8 billion in any other way, then you have no choice but to tax the small depositors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>What does this tell us about the European project though?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Is the eurozone a partnership of equals who care about each other&amp;apost;s subjects?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Or is it a vehicle for scoring political points by the strong and powerful?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Russia&amp;apost;s involvement with Cyprus as an offshore centre keeps coming up in these discussions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Attracted by a corporate tax rate of 10% -- half that of Russia&amp;apost;s -- Russians have been investing money into Cyprus from the early 1990s.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>The money is then repatriated through investments in Russian ventures -- a legal way of reducing tax.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Cyprus accepted an order last month by the Eurogroup to allow an investigation into possible breaches of money-laundering rules, which is under way.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>But the euro group could not wait for the results before imposing the haircut; not a single case of money laundering has been discovered so far.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>I have been involved both with central bank policy and with private banking in Cyprus for years (and at different times) and I have never come across anything non-compliant with European rules.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>The Russians make Cyprus&amp;apost;s financial sector too large, it is claimed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>But it is still not as large as Luxembourg&amp;apost;s, and not too different from those of other small nations with a highly educated labour force.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>And anyway, when a large system works well except for its involvement in a single and exceptional event like the Greek sovereign debt write-off, you don&amp;apost;t cut off half the system and destroy the sector, causing acute unemployment problems.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>You try to fix it, with better regulation of risk and other vulnerabilities.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>But then they shoot the horses, don&amp;apost;t they?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Sooner or later such policies could backfire on Europe.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Those of us who supported the European integration movement are disappointed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
