<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="73" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/01/24/business/davos-unrest-of-arab-spring-sparked-innovation/index.html" category="business" author="Amir Shihadeh, Special to CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>How the Arab Spring sparked innovation and creativity</title>
  <keywords>arab spring,disrupted society,Jordan</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3, 1">Shihadeh: Post-Arab Spring Mideast is &amp;quot;enriched and awakened society,&amp;quot; not a &amp;quot;disrupted society&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="22">The Arab Spring was simply a call for change, change in ideologies, change in direction, change in hope.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="44">Arab Spring allows for thoughts and ideas to sprout that were once dormant, he writes.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-15 17:54:13" annotation_time="91.454" mapping_time_divergence="30.484667">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">In the wake of the Arab Spring and the global financial crisis, focus has been on the world&amp;apost;s new and so-called &amp;quot;disrupted society.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">While some might point to a &amp;quot;disrupted society,&amp;quot; I call our world an &amp;quot;enriched and awakened society.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="2">The Arab Spring was simply a call for change: change in ideologies, change in direction, change in hope.</sentence>
      <sentence id="44" ids_highlights="3">Such an Arab Spring encourages innovation and creativity; it allows for thoughts and ideas to sprout that were once dormant.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>In the wake of the Arab Spring and the global financial crisis, focus has been on the world&amp;apost;s new and so-called &amp;quot;disrupted society.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But I would avoid using such a negative phrase for Jordan; which is where I live and which has avoided the severity of the uprisings in other Middle Eastern countries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>While some might point to a &amp;quot;disrupted society,&amp;quot; I call our world an &amp;quot;enriched and awakened society.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>It is a society of potential, innovation, and opportunity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Youth dominate the globe -- the 3.5 billion people under the age of 30 make up half of the world&amp;apost;s population.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Therefore, we have an impact on our own lives today, and we are the decision makers of our lives tomorrow.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>So how do we react to such opportunities, and what do we do with such potential that resides within us?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Do we add water and sunlight so it can sprout, or do we suppress it with darkness and ignorance?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>It is said that Arab youth have faced tough challenges since the Arab Spring.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>But this is not unusual.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Youth all around the world have faced unemployment, high tuition fees, and tough economic situations for years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>It is these challenges that allow for innovation and creativity to be born.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>This is when and where we unleash our potential.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Jordan&amp;apost;s youth are not completely satisfied with the performance of the public sector, nor are they satisfied with their ability to participate in the decision making process.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>These frustrations, coupled with difficult economic times, have created an unstable environment and resulted in the launch of initiatives to engage youth as active citizens in political, economic, and social decision-making.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>But unemployment in Jordan and the Middle East did not take us by surprise during the Arab Spring.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>High unemployment was present in the Middle East, and in almost every country around the world, for many years before the uprising.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The impact, however, has been far more painful as the world faltered under the economic downturn.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The domino effect of the economic crisis hit the developed countries first, and then reached the developing nations of the Middle East.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>When it hit Jordan it was, by coincidence, around the same time of the Arab Spring.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Therefore, it is important to note that the Arab Spring wasn&amp;apost;t a mere result of unemployment, nor was it a complete call for democracy and freedom.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The Arab Spring was simply a call for change: change in ideologies, change in direction, change in hope.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Unemployment is a major issue in the Middle East and North Africa region, especially in Jordan.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The official rate is 11%, and unofficial estimates are about twice that figure.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Generous employment opportunities in the public sector have eased the pressure, but the debt crisis facing the government has been hindering its ability to help.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Policy makers are now pressed to come up with solutions to empower the private sector and improve the education system.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Many of the world&amp;apost;s young are uncertain of their future and their ability to find meaningful employment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Jordan&amp;apost;s young have some of the region&amp;apost;s most sought-after talents, due to their high quality of education and hard-working attitudes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Regretfully, their productivity is not contributing to Jordan&amp;apost;s economy, as they cannot find competitive salaries or similar opportunities.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Therefore, many look for jobs abroad, particularly in the Gulf region.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Yet, there is still hope for Jordanians.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The entrepreneurship scene is expanding, and more of the country&amp;apost;s young are establishing companies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>I believe the young can rise and flourish -- especially in today&amp;apost;s tough climate -- by thinking about their &amp;quot;sphere of influence.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>We should collaborate with individuals from our region by crossing borders, creating partnerships, and exploring ideas.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Travel between Middle Eastern counties can be challenging due to visa requirements, but the virtual world eliminates such boundaries.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Technological advances unite us in ways we should be united.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>And we must remember that divided we are as fragile as separate fingers, but united we are a strong fist.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Three years ago, the Arab Spring signified hope.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Now, Jordanian youth have witnessed the negative transformations in neighboring countries such as Egypt and Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Jordanian youth are smart and will not allow their country to head towards that same path.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>But the need for security and stability must be accompanied by reform and growth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>I do not believe the Arab Spring caused a &amp;quot;disrupted society.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Rather, the Arab Spring has created an opportunity that allows things &amp;quot;out of the norm&amp;quot; to occur.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Such an Arab Spring encourages innovation and creativity; it allows for thoughts and ideas to sprout that were once dormant.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Therefore, I advise my fellow Arab to prepare, strategize, and implement with utmost passion, wisdom, and honesty.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>READ MORE:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
