<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="140" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/04/08/business/opinion-lea-thatcher-economcs-legacy/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2013-04-08 16:05:54" category="business" author="Ruth Lea, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Why Britain needs another Thatcher</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Thatcher was a giant in British politics, in large part due to her revolutionary approach to the economy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="17">Thatcher changed Britain&amp;apost;s whole approach to the economy and business.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="30">Thatcher was a politician of enormous skill and, above all else, conviction.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="35">Lea argues we need a new Thatcher with the vision to correct the country&amp;apost;s problems.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-18 13:10:42" annotation_time="34.646">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Margaret Thatcher was a giant in late 20th century British politics, in large part due to her revolutionary approach to the economy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="2">It is absolutely no exaggeration to say that Thatcher changed the whole approach to the economy and business.</sentence>
      <sentence id="30" ids_highlights="3">Thatcher was a politician of enormous skill, determination, courage and, above all else, conviction.</sentence>
      <sentence id="35" ids_highlights="4">We need a new Margaret Thatcher, one with the vision to correct the country&amp;apost;s horrendous problems, as she did in the 1980s.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Margaret Thatcher was a giant in late 20th century British politics, in large part due to her revolutionary approach to the economy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>It is no accident that her economic strategy and policies became known as &amp;quot;Thatcherism.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Her policies revolutionized the domestic economy and also had huge influence abroad -- not least of all in the countries of Central and Eastern Europe, freed from Soviet control in the early 1990s.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>To get an idea of the enormity of her influence it is vital to understand the parlous state Britain was in the 1960s and 1970s.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>It was a country that, in the words of former U.S. Secretary of State Dean Acheson, had &amp;quot;lost an empire and has not yet found a role&amp;quot; and it was a country that was persistently underperforming its European neighbors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Indeed it was the feeling that the six of the European Economic Communities (EEC) were leaving Britain behind economically that was one of the main reasons for its membership in 1973.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>But, EEC membership did not solve Britain&amp;apost;s problems.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Britain&amp;apost;s problems, including the appalling industrial relations, were only tackled when Thatcher became prime minister in 1979.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>When I was a young civil servant in the 1970s in the Treasury, I was told that government in Britain was all about &amp;quot;managing decline.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Defeatism was endemic.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Both the major parties (Labour and Conservative) had adopted a quasi-consensus, Keynesian interventionist approach to the economy post WWII, in which large parts of the productive economy, including the utilities, were state monopolies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Competition was a foreign, if not a dirty, word.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>And high taxes blunted entrepreneurial spirits and business activity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Under these circumstances it should have been of no surprise to anyone, that Britain&amp;apost;s future was indeed was all about managing decline.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The image of an aristocratic family down on its luck, wearing threadbare jackets and scuffed shoes, comes to mind.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Enterprise, profit, low taxes and risk-taking were concepts that were foreign (and especially American) in Britain.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>It is absolutely no exaggeration to say that Thatcher changed the whole approach to the economy and business.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Managing decline&amp;quot; was not for her.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>She was determined to implement the policies, however uncomfortable and unpalatable they were at the time, to inject energy, enterprise and competition into business and into the economy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Tinkering interventionism was out and union reform (long overdue), privatization, competition, sound public finances and low taxes were in.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>All in all, her polices amounted to a &amp;quot;supply side&amp;quot; revolution.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>And it was a revolution.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Businesses and entrepreneurs were now to be seen as the drivers of economic growth and not interfering governments.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The default mechanism of post-war British economic policy was reset.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>It was a staggering success.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>After a rocky start -- there was a nasty recession in the early 1980s from which parts of manufacturing did not recover -- the British economy began to perform significantly better.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Allied with canny policies to free up the City of London and attract inward investment, Britain became the number one destination for overseas investment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The sense of defeatism was consigned, at least at the time, to history.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>In the late 1980s and early 1990s I well remember my Japanese colleagues&amp;apost; admiration for her and all that she had done for Britain&amp;apost;s standing in the international business world, and their sheer bemusement when she was forced out of office.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Thatcher was a politician of enormous skill, determination, courage and, above all else, conviction.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>And she was ably assisted by, amongst others, Lord (Geoffrey) Howe, Lord (Nigel) Lawson, Lord (David) Young and Lord (Norman) Tebbit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>They helped her push through her vision against the most appalling opposition from the unions to the economics profession and the CBI.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Sadly, much of her excellent work was destroyed under the Tony Blair government when chancellor Gordon Brown&amp;apost;s profligacy wrecked the public finances and his ill-advised changes to banking supervision severely damaged the financial system.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Speaking as one who saw the Thatcherite revolution &amp;quot;in action,&amp;quot; I find it immensely saddening.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>We need a new Margaret Thatcher, one with the vision to correct the country&amp;apost;s horrendous problems, as she did in the 1980s.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
