<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="104" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/01/25/business/oprah-winfrey-leadership-academy" category="business" author="Robyn Curnow and Teo Kermeliotis, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Oprah a &amp;apost;proud momma&amp;apost; as first Academy students graduate</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">The first class of Oprah Winfrey&amp;apost;s South Africa-based academy has graduated.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">The 71 girls are all accepted in universities in South Africa and the United States.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="25">The TV host set up the school in 2007 to give education to girls from poor backgrounds.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="24">She plans to continue championing the rights of girls to a better education.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-03 09:50:02" annotation_time="71.479" mapping_time_divergence="17.86975">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;I am one proud mama and for once I think I know what that feels like for real,&amp;quot; Winfrey said before the graduation of the first class of her South Africa-based school last week.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">Five years later, the 71 graduates of the class of 2011 -- all high-achieving young girls who had experienced poverty and personal trauma such as violence, molestation, or loss of a parent -- have all been accepted to continue their studies at universities in South Africa and the United States.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="4">The 57-year-old media mogul, who now runs her own channel, appropriately titled OWN, said her next mission is to continue championing the rights of young girls to a better education.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="3">She aims to use the experience garnered over the past five years as a &amp;quot;force for change&amp;quot; to give educational opportunities to more girls from poor backgrounds in other countries and help raise the next generation of female leaders and entrepreneurs.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Surrounded by the white-clad students of her all-girls academy, Oprah Winfrey is glowing with pride.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>And just like many mothers at a graduation ceremony, the talk show queen cannot hold back the tears as the girls she calls her daughters stroll across the stage to accept their diplomas.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am one proud mama and for once I think I know what that feels like for real,&amp;quot; Winfrey said before the graduation of the first class of her South Africa-based school last week.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;It feels like a real sense of accomplishment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>It is a triumph indeed, considering where all these girls have come from.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The TV star had every reason to be jubilant: In 2007, she had hand-picked all these students as she established the $40 million Oprah Winfrey Leadership Academy for Girls to provide world-class high school education to underprivileged children from South Africa and teach them leadership skills.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Five years later, the 71 graduates of the class of 2011 -- all high-achieving young girls who had experienced poverty and personal trauma such as violence, molestation, or loss of a parent -- have all been accepted to continue their studies at universities in South Africa and the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;When I look at them, I see where they&amp;apost;ve been, I see where they&amp;apost;ve come from.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>I know how hard it is to come up from nowhere and nothing and have almost no support and to have suffered not one or two but on average five, six traumas by the time you actually get in this school,&amp;quot; said Winfrey.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;And now 100% of this class has been accepted into colleges, 10% going to the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>I mean, that&amp;apost;s pretty incredible.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Before the graduation, the girls received intensive financial planning counseling and assistance to help them with life beyond the academy, school officials say.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>A mentoring program has also been put in place to offer them advice during university.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Overall, the boarding school, which spans 52 acres in the small town of Henley-on-Klip near Johannesburg, accommodates 400 South African girls of any race, color or origin, aged 12 to 18.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The students are offered free tuition, uniforms and meals and have access to the academy&amp;apost;s state-of-the-art facilities, which include modern classrooms, computers labs, sport fields and a 10,000-volume library.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>But for all its success and money spent, Winfrey&amp;apost;s academy has not been without its controversies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>A few months after opening, the school was rocked by an abuse scandal when one of its matrons was accused of molesting students.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The women was acquitted in 2010.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Last year, a student concealed her pregnancy and then secretly gave birth at the school.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The baby died and was later found in the student&amp;apost;s school bag.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Winfrey, who lost a child as a teenager and has spoken publicly about abuse she suffered at a young age, said it was her faith in the girls that kept her &amp;quot;steadfast&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;stimulated&amp;quot; amid all the challenges.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;ve always believed in the girls,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;ve known that no matter what we were going through, the girls were worth it -- no matter what happened, the end of the day the girls, the investment in the girls, which is really an investment in the future leadership of this country.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The 57-year-old media mogul, who now runs her own channel, appropriately titled OWN, said her next mission is to continue championing the rights of young girls to a better education.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>She aims to use the experience garnered over the past five years as a &amp;quot;force for change&amp;quot; to give educational opportunities to more girls from poor backgrounds in other countries and help raise the next generation of female leaders and entrepreneurs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;You want to change the world, you change a girl&amp;apost;s life,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;What I intend to do now is ... take that model and to use it in the world to change the lives of 250 million girls around the world who can&amp;apost;t get an education, who don&amp;apost;t have any asset other than their bodies to use, and therefore they&amp;apost;re sold for dowries, they&amp;apost;re sold off into slavery, they&amp;apost;re married at 11 and 12 years old.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Winfrey, who overcame economic hardship as well as racial and gender challenges to become one of the world&amp;apost;s most successful and influential women, says education can help girls from all backgrounds to raise their aspirations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;In the beginning, I think we had teachers who were like, &amp;apost;oh, the girls, they come here disadvantaged.&amp;apost;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>So we&amp;apost;ve eliminated that word &amp;apost;disadvantaged,&amp;apost; because disadvantaged allows other people to look at you like you have some kind of disease, and they lower their expectations for what you can be.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;I said, &amp;apost;nobody has a disadvantaged brain.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Nobody is here with a disadvantaged mind.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Nobody has a disadvantaged spirit.&amp;apost; &amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>For this &amp;quot;proud momma,&amp;quot; the possibilities are endless for her girls.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;You were born in the year that apartheid ended in this country,&amp;quot; Winfrey tells her school&amp;apost;s students.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;That means that you are a child of freedom.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>There is no bar.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
