<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="102" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/05/29/business/portugal-economy-minister/index.html?hpt=ibu_c1" date_published="2013-05-29 09:04:23" category="business" author="Alvaro Santos Pereira, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Portugal economy minister: &amp;apost;We will persevere and succeed&amp;apost;</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="15">Fiscal consolidation and a credible strategy of debt reduction are crucial, writes Pereira.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="19">Pereira: We need reforms to improve our competitiveness as well as to foster investment.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="30">Engines of economic growth should be investment and exports, says Pereira.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-25 08:00:04" annotation_time="21.868">
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="1">In this sense, fiscal consolidation and a credible strategy of debt reduction are crucial not only for us to have sustainable public finances, but also are instrumental to achieve sustainable long-term economic growth and to reduce the burden of debt in our economies.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="2">We need reforms to improve our competitiveness as well as to foster investment.</sentence>
      <sentence id="30" ids_highlights="3">A strategy in which the main engines of economic growth are investment and exports.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The international financial and economic crisis has brought a time of great challenges and difficulties for Europe and its citizens.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>These are, indeed, difficult times.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Times of unprecedented unemployment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Times where our youngest struggle to find jobs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Times where our companies struggle to get financing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Times where hope and confidence have been lacking, but are desperately needed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>In spite of all these problems and challenges, it is also important to recognize that these are times of transformation and sweeping reforms in many European economies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>In this context and in many ways, Portugal has been leading the path to economic reform in Europe.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>In Portugal, we strongly believe that the need to implement structural reforms and fiscal policies oriented to foster sustainable growth and job creation are a priority for our own country and for Europe.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>We have to make the European economy more friendly towards investment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>We have to cut down taxes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>We have to cut down charges.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>And, most of all, we have to cut down red tape, excessive procedures and bureaucracy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>People in Europe need jobs and growing and competitive economies, not growing bureaucracies that stifle entrepreneurship and innovation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>In this sense, fiscal consolidation and a credible strategy of debt reduction are crucial not only for us to have sustainable public finances, but also are instrumental to achieve sustainable long-term economic growth and to reduce the burden of debt in our economies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Why?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Because healthier public finances and a lower debt burden improve a country&amp;apost;s global competitiveness, by ensuring the financing of our States and our SMEs, and as well as by increasing economic agents&amp;apost; confidence and, therefore, boosting job creation and the level of exports.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>However, fiscal consolidation, per se, is not enough.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>We need reforms to improve our competitiveness as well as to foster investment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>This is why in the last two years we have implemented a vast program of reforms that included, among others, a large privatization program, an ambitious labor reform, zero-licensing procedures for industry, commerce and tourism, chapter 11-type provisions to foster company restructuring, a new competition law, port law reforms, reforms in the Justice system, and the liberalization of our energy sectors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>We are confident that these reforms will have a significant impact on our economy in the short term, and will substantially improve our potential GDP growth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>However, in addition to these reforms, we need investment and we need to stabilize financing conditions to our companies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>In this context, the Portuguese government recently approved a Memorandum for Growth, a short- and medium-term strategy to boost economic growth, employment and industrial development.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>This growth strategy has at its core the industrial renewal of our economy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Portugal has a strong industrial base, and we want to strengthen this industrial base rapidly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>This strategy reflects our vision on what the path should be in the next years, and it is structured upon four pillars.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>They are: Lowering business taxes and making the tax system favorable to investment; simplifying requirements and reducing the administrative burden to business activity; strengthening and investing in the dual and apprenticeship training system and fostering and diversifying the financing of Small and Medium Enterprises.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>In short, a growth strategy based on a lower tax burden and a lower bureaucratic burden.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>At the same time, we will invest in our future through innovation, research and development, and vocational training.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>A strategy in which the main engines of economic growth are investment and exports.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>We intend industry to play a key role as a source of job creation, investment, innovation and human capital.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Clearly, getting back to growth is a not a task for government authorities only.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Public authorities have the responsibility to adopt adequate measures, in order to set the right environment and business climate, as well as to make our economies more business friendly and competitive.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>But in order to be successful, we also need our companies, our students, our researchers, and our workers and entrepreneurs to do their share, by innovating, by researching and, most of all, by investing in our economies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>This is exactly what we have been doing in Portugal.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>And in the near future we intent to continue this path by fostering even further our competitiveness and by continuing to cut the costs and barriers to our enterprises.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>We know that this is a difficult task.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>We know that the path is often tortuous and hard.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>But we also know that a nation with almost 900 years of history will once again show the world that we can turn around a difficult situation through social dialogue, perseverance and the courage to reform.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>We know that we can, and we will, succeed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
