<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="62" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/12/13/business/mark-shuttleworth-mandela-space-leweb/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2013-12-13 16:32:17" category="business" author="Irene Chapple, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>From space to software: One man&amp;apost;s journey to</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Software entrepreneur Mark Shuttleworth spoke to Nelson Mandela from space in 2002.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8">He says the anti-apartheid icon taught humankind how to search for the good in others.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="22">Shuttleworth&amp;apost;s company is behind open software operating system Ubuntu.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="24">He is hoping to compete with the likes of Google with plans for &amp;quot;convergence&amp;quot; across mobile .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 13:33:25" annotation_time="167.84567">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">That&amp;apost;s how South African space tourist and software entrepreneur Mark Shuttleworth remembers the day he spoke to Nelson Mandela, the hero of South Africa&amp;apost;s anti-apartheid struggle, who died last week aged 95.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">Mandela&amp;apost;s lasting lesson, Shuttleworth said, is that people should &amp;quot;find the Madiba in our counterpart.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="3">Back on Earth, Shuttleworth&amp;apost;s company has signed its first deal with a phone hardware partner to use its operating system, Ubuntu.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="4">While the operating system market is dominated by giants such as Google and Apple, Shuttleworth sees opportunity in &amp;quot;convergence,&amp;quot; when all mobile devices run seamlessly from one set-up.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The conversation between space cadet and world leader had a simple purpose: To make an ill teenager happy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s how South African space tourist and software entrepreneur Mark Shuttleworth remembers the day he spoke to Nelson Mandela, the hero of South Africa&amp;apost;s anti-apartheid struggle, who died last week aged 95.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;He brought a little girl with him who was very ill, it was such a classic Mandela move,&amp;quot; Shuttleworth told CNN during tech conference LeWeb, being held in Paris.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;Lots of people wanted to be on the phone with a space cadet and I get the impression that for many of them it was about the spotlight being on them, whereas for Madiba (Mandela&amp;apost;s tribal name) the most wonderful thing for him was about making this little girl&amp;apost;s wish come true.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Michelle Foster, 14, was terminally ill with cancer and through the Reach for the Dream foundation had been able to meet Mandela and later link through satellite to Shuttleworth in space.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Foster died less than a month after she&amp;apost;d spoken to him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Shuttleworth, who founded software company Canonical, recalled the conversation ahead of Mandela&amp;apost;s state funeral Sunday, the conclusion of 10 official days of mourning.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Mandela&amp;apost;s lasting lesson, Shuttleworth said, is that people should &amp;quot;find the Madiba in our counterpart.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;Even good societies, societies filled with good people can end up in very dark places,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;We should focus on the rules of society and the norms of society and make sure those aren&amp;apost;t ripe for abuse.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>There could even be lessons for dealing with terrorist organizations, like al Qaeda, Shuttleworth said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Don&amp;apost;t tell me there isn&amp;apost;t somebody in every institution who doesn&amp;apost;t have the capacity to transcend the mess they&amp;apost;ve got themselves into.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Shuttleworth&amp;apost;s conversation with Mandela was in 2002, when space tourism was in its infancy and only two paying guests had gone into orbit.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Shuttleworth reportedly paid $20 million to travel with Russian cosmonaut Yuri Gidzenko and spend a short time at the International Space Station.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>A decade later, Richard Branson&amp;apost;s Virgin&amp;apost;s Galactic is one several companies pushing to make space tourism a reality.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Meanwhile, Shuttleworth predicts, the world will see first &amp;quot;the first commercial suborbital flights in the new two years ... and I think we will see a partly commercial interplanetary flight in the next 10 years.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Eventually, humans will move beyond earth, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think our destiny is in the stars ... there is probably a habitable planet out there within 15 light years of us.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>That, he adds, is &amp;quot;in our neighborhood.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;The galaxy is around 100,000 light years across so 15 light years is very little.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>It may take us a couple hundred years to achieve that but look back a couple of years and you&amp;apost;re at the rebuilding of Paris, so I think this is the sort of timescale we should be dreaming in.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Back on Earth, Shuttleworth&amp;apost;s company has signed its first deal with a phone hardware partner to use its operating system, Ubuntu.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Shuttleworth won&amp;apost;t give details yet -- it&amp;apost;s expected to be made public in 2014 -- but says it&amp;apost;s a step forward from the company&amp;apost;s work with personal computers and could eventually position it to compete with the likes of Android.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>While the operating system market is dominated by giants such as Google and Apple, Shuttleworth sees opportunity in &amp;quot;convergence,&amp;quot; when all mobile devices run seamlessly from one set-up.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
