<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="27" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/01/23/business/davos-opinion-chinas-21st-century-challenge/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-01-23 09:49:16" category="business" author="Damien Ma, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>China&amp;apost;s 21st century challenge: Define the narrative</title>
  <keywords>China,Xi Jinping</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="30">Damien Ma looks for an indigenous idea to carry China forward in the 21st Century.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="16">And its transition into a modern state has been anything but smooth, he writes.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="26">He says few Chinese know or agree on what China should stand for in the 21st Century.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 21:15:29" annotation_time="22.618002">
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="2">And its transition into a modern state has been anything but smooth.</sentence>
      <sentence id="26" ids_highlights="3">But few Chinese know or agree on what China should stand for in the 21st century.</sentence>
      <sentence id="30" ids_highlights="1">It seems that China has little choice but to look to its distant past in search of a continuous narrative and an indigenous idea that can carry the nation forward in the 21st Century.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>If the 21st century belongs to China, as some have argued, then it is worth asking what the defining Chinese idea will be.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>It is unsurprising that this very issue has ginned up ferocious debate within China, as the country&amp;apost;s might grows but its voice remains meek on the global stage.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Economic success alone has yet to evince a self-assured China that it can offer a set of compelling values and ideas to the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>As a country that prides itself on the continuity of its great civilization and cultural force, China seems to grow increasingly dissatisfied with punching below its weight in the world of ideas.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Indeed, much of the 20th century was defined by the rise of the United States and the dominance of the American idea: It was essentially an articulation of what modernity means.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>To be modern meant widespread economic prosperity, a healthy middle class, and technological superiority, combined with values that emphasized individual rights and freedoms to pursue whatever lives, liberties, and happiness that one sought.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>It was a manifestation of the ideals that were enshrined in the Declaration of Independence, a document that, at the young nation&amp;apost;s inception, defined what kind of country the United States ought to strive for.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>In many ways, the country was born out of a few central ideas because its existence could not be predicated on strong ethnic kinships, bloodlines, or the old monarchical order.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>It was not the &amp;quot;Old World&amp;quot; but a new nation that was moving toward collective ideals.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The belief in the very idea of America was the strongest glue that could bind together a diverse, continental nation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>That cohesive idea has anchored the &amp;quot;American Dream&amp;quot; and provided ballast for themes that are readily found in Hollywood and other popular culture products that pervade the global market.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Whether by design or accidental, the genius of the American idea is that it is simply an open source template, or a &amp;quot;default setting,&amp;quot; that can be easily replicated and customized in different cultural and institutional environments.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Its power and universalizing appeal is apparent.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Little wonder that the American idea gained immense market share and is still widely equated with the general aspiration of obtaining a high living standard and human dignity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>China, in contrast, is both of the old world and a young republic -- or as scholar Lucian Pye once rendered it, &amp;quot;a civilization pretending to be a nation-state.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>And its transition into a modern state has been anything but smooth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The modern Chinese state was forged from a nasty civil war, and its recent history since 1949 has been plagued by a series of highly disruptive discontinuities.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>It has had no continuous narrative from which to draw inspiration and to define the soul of a nation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>In fact, the People&amp;apost;s Republic under Mao Zedong primarily defined itself as what it is not -- that is, it wasn&amp;apost;t feudal or traditional.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>For the next six decades, the country lurched from devastating revolution to hyper materialism, breaking with whatever ideological milieu that had existed at the time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>When Deng Xiaoping took power in 1978, the only &amp;quot;ism&amp;quot; that mattered was pragmatism, as the country went to work on nation building and zeroed in on material prosperity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Thirty-five years and several trillions worth of GDP later, an entire generation of Chinese is waking up to the fact that it still has little idea of what kind of nation to strive for.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>All this relentless work has built a dynamic middle-income economy, yet cumulative wealth is no substitute for the richness of a nation, especially for a China that believes it has much to offer the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>After all, this is a country that once brought the world paper, gunpowder, and the compass.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Virtually every Chinese school child knows that.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>But few Chinese know or agree on what China should stand for in the 21st century.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>It is clearly a global economic power, but unlike the United States, China seems to have little desire to stake out social and political values that others might adopt.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The Chinese government, which tightly controls historical narratives, simply cannot look into its recent past to seek out those values because even communism is derived from a Western political philosophy appropriated for Chinese conditions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>And politically, it could be potentially disastrous if the government owned up to all the dark chapters in its recent past.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>It seems that China has little choice but to look to its distant past in search of a continuous narrative and an indigenous idea that can carry the nation forward in the 21st Century.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The new leadership of the Communist Party, particularly President Xi Jinping, has prioritized this effort because it understands that a major source of its political power is derived from ideological legitimacy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>To keep a continental nation together, China, too, needs a ruling party to govern around a set of ideas so that its people can imagine what the country can and should become.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>And so the &amp;quot;great rejuvenation&amp;quot; of the Chinese nation has become the new ideological offering -- an explicit effort to connect today&amp;apost;s China to the glories of a former empire that sat at the center of the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>It revives the traditional ideas of wealth and power that have defined the country through much of its history.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The Chinese leadership is leaving little doubt that China will once again be a global force that garners respect.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Yet it is far from clear what a rejuvenated China means or how that force might be employed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Reestablishing &amp;quot;national greatness&amp;quot; may win over some of the Chinese public, but it hardly serves as an idea or value proposition that can extend beyond Chinese borders.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Each nation is entitled to deem itself unique, exceptional, and &amp;quot;great&amp;quot; -- the United States certainly does.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>But some nations also use their wealth and power to articulate a vision of how to shape the world and aspire to address common challenges.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The tagline for a U.S. Navy advertisement, for example, is &amp;quot;a global force for good.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>China, at least so far, has exhibited little interest in becoming a charge d&amp;apost;affaires with world-shaping responsibilities, even as outside pressures mount for it to assume them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Indeed, it may simply be comfortable with being just China -- an idea that the rest of the world may have to get used to.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Read more: Xi Jinping&amp;apost;s 2014 challenge: Resolving an identity crisis?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>