<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="72" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/11/11/business/greece-economy-on-path-to-recovery/index.html" date_published="2013-11-11 11:16:04" category="business" author="Oliver Joy, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Is Greece finally on the mend after economic crisis?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="13">Over a quarter of the Greek population are without jobs and youth unemployment is at 55%, the highest in Europe.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="25">Since 2010 Greece has received 240 billion euros [$320 billion] from creditors to prevent a sovereign default.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="21">The European Commission expects Greece to emerge from recession next year and robust 2.9% growth in 2015.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-22 14:22:36" annotation_time="156.515">
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="1">But the influx of investment is yet to filter down to an austerity-fatigued electorate with over a quarter of the population without jobs and youth unemployment at 55%, the highest in Europe.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="3">This week, the European Commission released its autumn economic forecast, estimating that Greece will emerge from recession in 2014 and projected solid growth of 2.9% for 2015 if the country maintains its current path.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="2">Since then the southern European nation has received 240 billion euros [$320 billion] from creditors to prevent a sovereign default on its debt and a possible exit from the 17-nation euro area.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Greece is on the way to economic recovery as investor faith returns to the recession-ridden eurozone nation, an executive at Greece&amp;apost;s largest bank has told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Petros Christodoulou, deputy chief executive of the National Bank of Greece, said that a drastic drop in government borrowing costs since the outbreak of the crisis in 2009 marks a &amp;quot;great improvement and a great perception of the country&amp;quot; by foreign investors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Speaking to CNN&amp;apost;s Max Foster in Athens, Christodoulou said: &amp;quot;Are we out of the woods with 8% yields in government debt?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Not yet, but we are on the right path.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>He added: &amp;quot;All this eventually proliferates into everything that happens in Greece, starting from the banking sector which is in the center of the economy and this is good news going forward.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Christodoulou&amp;apost;s comments come in a week of highs and lows for Europe&amp;apost;s worst hit nation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Just seven days ago, Greek stocks, once spurned by investors over fears the country would need to exit the euro, beat every market in the world as the nation&amp;apost;s six-year recession eased.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>While on Tuesday, creditors -- made up of the International Monetary Fund, the European Commission and the European Central Bank -- visited Athens to meet policymakers and assess the country&amp;apost;s finances.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The group known as the &amp;apost;Troika&amp;apost; remains at loggerheads with the government, led by Prime Minister Antonis Samaras, over the country&amp;apost;s continued austerity program.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Christodoulou believes Greece is becoming a business-friendly country as banks and the state sell off assets in a bid to raise capital.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>He added: &amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m not worried about all this bickering here and there between the government and the Troika.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>At the end of the day, we&amp;apost;ve come a long way and we&amp;apost;re now at the tail end.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>But the influx of investment is yet to filter down to an austerity-fatigued electorate with over a quarter of the population without jobs and youth unemployment at 55%, the highest in Europe.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Nicholas Spiro, founder of Spiro Sovereign Strategy, told CNN that investor confidence in detached from the economic reality in Greece and largely based on the country&amp;apost;s eurozone status being secure.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>He added: &amp;quot;The kind of unemployment and the kind of headwinds that Greece is facing are simply too much.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s very difficult to see how Greece is going to stage any kind of meaningful recovery.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>On Wednesdsay, two of the country&amp;apost;s largest public and private sector unions marched on parliament in a general 24-hour strike against the government&amp;apost;s severe cuts to public services.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Christodoulou, second-in-command at Greeks largest and oldest commercial bank, said he wasn&amp;apost;t worried by the protests.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s hardly surprising we&amp;apost;ve had the odd protest,&amp;quot; he added, &amp;quot;you have to look at things in a cumulative way and Greeks have come to accept, in a way, they are resigned to accepting all these measures.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Greece&amp;apost;s economic renaissance.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>This week, the European Commission released its autumn economic forecast, estimating that Greece will emerge from recession in 2014 and projected solid growth of 2.9% for 2015 if the country maintains its current path.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Spiro said that Greece will be &amp;quot;very lucky&amp;quot; to grow next year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is a country that is still struggling to meet the terms of its bailout program,&amp;quot; he added, &amp;quot;they have been kicked into the long grass to keep the euro show on the road.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Greece fell into recession after the collapse of U.S. bank Lehman Brothers in 2008, which sparked a euro-wide debt crisis the following year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Since then the southern European nation has received 240 billion euros [$320 billion] from creditors to prevent a sovereign default on its debt and a possible exit from the 17-nation euro area.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Christodoulou told CNN that the next step for Greece is to reduce state intervention in business.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>He finished by adding: &amp;quot;In the old days, we had the Greek state directly or indirectly involved in about two thirds of Greek business, and it&amp;apost;s the delight of all Greeks when we see this shrinking drastically now.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
