<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="7" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/03/business/thanks-to-amazon-tiny-sellers/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-09-03 07:52:53" category="business" author="Marcus Wohlsen, WIRED" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Amazon helps tiny sellers can reach across the globe</title>
  <keywords>business,smart business,small business,amazon,seller</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">In 2013, Amazon sold 1 billion items from small businesses .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="10">Platform lets entrepreneurs become &amp;quot;micro-exporters&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="25">Amazon says sellers can reach 250 million potential customers globally.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-28 13:01:22" annotation_time="1.41718694E9">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">Last year, about a billion items sold on Amazon weren&amp;apost;t sold by Amazon itself but by other sellers who make their merchandise available on the site.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="2">In 2006, Amazon launched a service that allowed U.S. sellers to use its network of warehouses to ship their goods.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="3">Expand that reach globally and the number of potential customers grows to 250 million.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Go to Amazon.com and the link is right there at the top, nestled between &amp;quot;Gift Cards&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Help.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Chances are, you haven&amp;apost;t noticed it in your frenzy to find the perfect potato peeler.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>But if you click it, a whole different world of Amazon opens up, one where stuff flows away from you rather than to you.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>That link reads &amp;quot;Sell.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Last year, about a billion items sold on Amazon weren&amp;apost;t sold by Amazon itself but by other sellers who make their merchandise available on the site.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>One of them is Bernie Thompson, a former Microsoft engineer who worked to ensure the Windows operating system played nicely with USB, the standard means of connecting peripherals to PCs and laptops.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Thompson now runs his own business, Plugable Technologies, which makes a variety of USB and Bluetooth hardware, from charging stations to docks that connect tablets to desktop monitors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>With fewer than 100 employees, the company isn&amp;apost;t huge.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>But Thompson has no trouble running a truly global business.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>In 2006, Amazon launched a service that allowed U.S. sellers to use its network of warehouses to ship their goods.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>More recently, Jeff Bezos and company have rolled out the Fulfillment by Amazon program globally, enabling entrepreneurs like Thompson to move goods through fulfillment centers in other parts of the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;It really changes the paradigm when you&amp;apost;re able to ship the goods in bulk to a warehouse in Europe or Japan and have those goods be fulfilled in one day or two days,&amp;quot; Thompson says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>While not all merchants are thrilled with their experience selling on Amazon, the company&amp;apost;s logistical network has enormous reach and breadth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>A guy like Thompson can click that &amp;quot;sell&amp;quot; link and -- without much time or effort -- get his hardware nearly anywhere in the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>In effect, he becomes a &amp;quot;micro-exporter.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Amazon&amp;apost;s global selling program, which has evolved along with the rest of its international footprint in recent years, works much like its domestic counterpart in the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Merchants can use the site to make their inventory available to purchase anywhere Amazon sells.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>But the real power of the system doesn&amp;apost;t come into play until merchants also opt to use Amazon to fulfill and ship its orders, as Thompson does.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Merchants in the United States who want to expand globally can list their products in Amazon&amp;apost;s nine international Amazon marketplaces -- the United Kingdom, Germany, France, Italy, Spain, India, China, Japan, and Canada.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>As they do domestically, sellers can export their goods in bulk to Amazon warehouses in those hubs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>From those, Amazon says it ships goods to about 180 countries around the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;The small seller suddenly has access to the global marketplace,&amp;quot; says Tom Taylor, Amazon&amp;apost;s vice president of seller services.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Taylor says the power of global selling and shipping is huge.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Goods from sellers targeting only U.S. consumers can be seen by about 100 million potential customers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Expand that reach globally and the number of potential customers grows to 250 million.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>And it&amp;apost;s not just U.S. merchants selling globally.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Taylor says sellers from 89 countries use Fulfillment by Amazon to sell goods to U.S. customers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>But the advantages Amazon gains by enabling micro-exports extend beyond the fees charged for its services.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>As Taylor puts it, a global network of small sellers can be incredibly nimble in response to shifts in demand around the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Sellers can move their inventory from one hub to another according to their perceptions of where demand is greatest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The result is a global agility for Amazon without the need to pull levers itself.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>An army of sellers becomes deputized to build out the long tail of global retail.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;We often can see patterns in what they&amp;apost;re doing faster than what we see in our own business,&amp;quot; Taylor says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>For Thompson, the ability to send bulk inventory to cross-border hubs saves money compared to shipping individual packages overseas, an approach he says is less error-prone than shipping piecemeal.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;We basically get the leverage, the huge scale that Amazon has in negotiating with shipping partners,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Outsourcing everything from taking and shipping orders to converting currencies, accepting payments, and handling taxes lets Plugable focus on customer service, which Thompson calls a key way to set itself apart in the crowded gadget market.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Turnkey global selling and shipping also lets Plugable take the temperature of truly global demand before committing to any inventory at all.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Thompson runs ideas for new products through Kickstarter, which not only allows Plugable to see what consumers want but where in the world demand is strongest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>If the Kickstarter campaign succeeds, he says, he divides up the inventory of new products rolling off the assembly line according to relative demand in different parts of the globe.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Instead of sending individual orders all over the world, Plugable ships in bulk to the international hubs where Amazon has facilities.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>From those locations, most of the world opens up to Thompson and his business -- a scale he says his business needs in order to make it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;They&amp;apost;re very cool products and very cool technologies, but they&amp;apost;re a bit niche-y,&amp;quot; Thompson says of his USB lines.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>&amp;quot;If you were selling on just local channels, there&amp;apost;s not enough of a market to justify the costs.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Read more from WIRED:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
