<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="128" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/08/28/business/threat-of-military-strike-sends-ripples-through-global-oil-market/index.html" date_published="2013-08-28 14:43:46" category="business" author="John Defterios, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Threat of military strike sends ripples through global oil market</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">Energy traders acknowledge the return of the so-called Middle East risk premium -- $10 to $15 dollars a barrel.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="11">Military attacks on Syria is pushing crude well above what oil kingpin Saudi Arabia believes is a fair price of $100.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="21">The higher prices will hit the economies which are running current account deficits and are subject to the capital flight.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 17:55:10" annotation_time="8.5055">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">Energy traders acknowledge the return of the so-called Middle East risk premium -- calculated to be $10 to $15 dollars a barrel.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="2">An escalation of violence triggered by military attacks on Syria is pushing crude well above what oil kingpin Saudi Arabia believes is a fair price of $100.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="3">While regional oil producers may be swimming in additional funds, the higher prices will hit the economies which are running current account deficits and are subject to the capital flight we see today.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The oil market is caught in a pricing tug of war.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>It is clear emerging markets are beginning a slowdown which will likely cut demand for crude oil over the next year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The panic selling in equity markets from Indonesia to India, Dubai to Sao Paolo is a leading indicator of what may be ahead in 2014.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>But at this juncture, the likelihood of military intervention in Syria, daily bombings and killings in Iraq, and uncertainty about the flow of crude through Egypt&amp;apost;s Suez Canal are far outweighing concerns about the developing world&amp;apost;s waning thirst for energy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Energy traders acknowledge the return of the so-called Middle East risk premium -- calculated to be $10 to $15 dollars a barrel.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>It is based on whether supplies might indeed be interrupted or, in the case of Iraq after four months of intense bombings, production has fallen below market expectations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>For a record three years running, North Sea Brent crude has averaged more than $100 barrel.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>As a result, the dozen members of OPEC, dominated by the major producers of the Gulf, earned one and a quarter trillion dollars in 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>This was, in part, because of the cloud of uncertainty that hovers over the region.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>It is a difficult balancing act.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>An escalation of violence triggered by military attacks on Syria is pushing crude well above what oil kingpin Saudi Arabia believes is a fair price of $100.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>This fills the coffers of the six Gulf states, who in a post-Arab Spring- environment are spending record amounts to fund economic development, create jobs and buy internal peace.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>If crude gyrates higher -- as it did in 2008, when it surged past $145 a barrel -- future demand could plummet and so too could oil prices.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>This is what happened in the second half of that year, when prices fell to below $40.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Oman&amp;apost;s long-serving central bank chief, Hamood Sangour Al Zadjali, told me that many attempts are being made behind the scenes to return calm to the region.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>But when asked if there could be a further push on the upside for crude as a result of what is transpiring regionally, he said: &amp;quot;That could be true, and that would be beneficial for us because we still depend largely on oil prices for our budget revenues.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Oman sits near the mouth of world&amp;apost;s busiest oil shipping lane, the Strait of Hormuz.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>It is now producing about 935,000 barrels a day, according to energy officials who spoke to me on background.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The Sultanate&amp;apost;s 2013 budget was built on oil projections of $85 a barrel, with energy making up 80% of total revenues.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The near $25 premium over Oman&amp;apost;s projections will wipe out a planned budget deficit, officials told me.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>While regional oil producers may be swimming in additional funds, the higher prices will hit the economies which are running current account deficits and are subject to the capital flight we see today.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Indonesia, India, Turkey top the list of the most vulnerable.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>With their currencies under severe pressure, there is the added danger of skyrocketing inflation due to higher imported energy costs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>It may all sound a bit alarmist at this stage, with the mad dash of money out of emerging markets, but strategists suggest this is not the 1997--1998 Asian financial crisis all over again.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Two years ago, countries such as Brazil complained their currencies were overvalued and that in turn was undermining export growth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Now we are in midst of the pendulum, and perhaps overshooting in the other direction.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>That may be today&amp;apost;s narrative in a climate of so much uncertainty, but policymakers and energy planners in the region say it is way too early to call an end to the long term trend of rising emerging market demand.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Oman&amp;apost;s central banker is one of those.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;We think the growth momentum will continue in these countries and there will be demand for Omani oil,&amp;quot; Al Zadjali told me.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The country is banking on it, with BP and the government putting up to $20 billion into a new natural gas field.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>More tenders for additional exploration are in the pipeline, officials tell me.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Oman, perched on the edge of the Arabian Sea, sees itself outside the region&amp;apost;s real danger zones, Syria, Iraq and Egypt.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>But it is too early to suggest in this geo-political climate whether that will remain the case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
