<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="133" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/01/21/business/pissarides-eurozone-unemployment/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2013-01-21 15:40:04" category="business" author="Christopher Pissarides, special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Unemployment in Europe: Is there a solution?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="21">Germany keep youth unemployment low by apprentices and subsidized employment, writes Pissarides.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12">Pissarides says deep recession and high unemployment tear into the fabric of society.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="11">The policies needed to combat unemployment in Europe go against the thrust of fiscal consolidation.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-06 11:32:35" annotation_time="34.4065">
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="3">The policies needed to combat unemployment go against the thrust of fiscal consolidation; it is not only an economic problem but a serious social problem.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">Deep recession and high unemployment tear into the fabric of society.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="1">Two measures that helped Germany keep youth unemployment low are apprentice training and subsidized employment for young people, including self-employment.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The recession in Europe is entering its fifth year and unemployment doesn&amp;apost;t look like it will be returning to normal levels anytime soon.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>In the countries with debt problems, especially Greece and Spain, unemployment skyrocketed in the last couple of years and is now at unprecedented levels.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>One in two young workers is out of a job.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Are we losing a whole new generation of young workers?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Are we wasting hard-earned skills?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Some countries are actually doing better than in previous recessions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>For instance, unemployment in Germany and the Netherlands is no longer a big problem.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>But the countries that are doing better tend also to be the countries whose sound fiscal finances allowed them to avoid a deep recession.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>It is clear unemployment will not recover fully before the debt crisis is over and Europe&amp;apost;s economy improves.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The fiscal consolidation programs, although necessary in the long term, are making the unemployment problem worse -- and policy is needed to offset their impact on jobs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The policies needed to combat unemployment go against the thrust of fiscal consolidation; it is not only an economic problem but a serious social problem.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Deep recession and high unemployment tear into the fabric of society.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Unemployment causes misery to families, destroys their self-esteem and wastes their potential.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>It is both a waste and a regression.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Jobless youth often feel rejected by society, and react either by withdrawing, by wasting themselves or by lashing out violently, as we have already seen in some southern countries.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Spending money on policies that can combat the problem until the economy recovers is a good investment in the future of our societies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>It is a better investment than building a new road or airport.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The road construction can be postponed without lasting damage to the project; a job cannot be postponed without lasting damage to the person.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>For the young, excluding the education and training budget from the fiscal consolidation programs is essential.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>I would go further during recession and stress the importance of increasing spending on training and job subsidies for new job creation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Two measures that helped Germany keep youth unemployment low are apprentice training and subsidized employment for young people, including self-employment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>There is a lot of creativity and entrepreneurship in young people that can be unleashed if initial financing can be found.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Governments can help in this, just as they help with student loans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>I am in favor of extending the student loan scheme to start-ups by young people, subject to approval of the start-up by the appropriate government department.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>In recession the government should become the &amp;quot;angel&amp;quot; of young entrepreneurs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Unfortunately if left alone employers will not create enough jobs in recession to keep unemployment low.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Of course, to some this is the essence of recession but the jobless rate depends also on many other factors, not just on the fall in demand.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Just as government should help reduce the impact of recession on unemployment through programs, workers and their unions should be prepared to take pay cuts and share out work in recession.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The alternative is much worse: it shifts the burden of recession onto the few who have been unfortunate enough to lose their jobs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>It is appalling to hear sometimes that even in recession there are people who earn overtime wages.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Work should be shared out, even if it means lower pay for those who would have kept their jobs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>