<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="92" link="http://cnn.com/2014/01/03/business/malta-can-no-longer-support-refugees/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-01-03 11:47:46" category="business" author="Isa Soares and Oliver Joy" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Malta foreign minister: Country &amp;apost;cannot offer&amp;apost; migrants opportunities</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="10">Malta receives a subsidy from the European Refugee Fund to deal with the influx of asylum seekers.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8">Between January and September of last year, 31,000 migrants are believed to have entered the European Union illegally.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="12">European nations such as Germany and Sweden have already opened there doors to refugees fleeing war in the home nations.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-12 12:02:43" annotation_time="139.07">
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">Between January and September of last year, 31,000 migrants are believed to have entered the European Union illegally by crossing the Mediterranean to land on Italian soil or the island of Malta, according to the European Union border agency Frontex.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="1">Malta gets assistance from the European Refugee Fund to deal with the influx of asylum seekers.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="3">European nations such as Germany and Sweden have already opened their doors to refugees fleeing war in the home nations, particularly in the face of civil war in Syria.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Malta cannot afford to continue supporting migrants from war-torn countries in its over-crowded detention camps, the country&amp;apost;s foreign minister has told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Speaking with CNN&amp;apost;s Isa Soares, George Vella said that while he didn&amp;apost;t want to blame the migrants, they &amp;quot;do not help themselves&amp;quot; in the immigration enclosures as they &amp;quot;break toilets&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;smear the place.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>When asked what the government can do to improve living conditions in the detention camp, Vela responded: &amp;quot;They don&amp;apost;t care for the facilities they have... we cannot afford to carry on looking after all these numbers, and utilizing our resources.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Vella continued: &amp;quot;We cannot offer these people the opportunities for which they left their countries and risked their lives to get a better life, many of them don&amp;apost;t want to come to Malta, they come by chance as the boat drifts.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The minister called on European Union member states for &amp;quot;solidarity&amp;quot; in the face of increasing numbers of asylum seekers crossing the Mediterranean, particularly from North and East Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>He said: &amp;quot;When these individuals qualify for protection, asylum seekers and they become refugees, they are protected.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Then there would be a system where they would be relocated proportionally, possibly among the other European Union member states.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Between January and September of last year, 31,000 migrants are believed to have entered the European Union illegally by crossing the Mediterranean to land on Italian soil or the island of Malta, according to the European Union border agency Frontex.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;We sincerely believe that given our size and our density of population, if you compare, we are taking a bigger strain proportionally than all the other countries in the European Union,&amp;quot; Vella said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Malta gets assistance from the European Refugee Fund to deal with the influx of asylum seekers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>In 2013, the Mediterranean island received 4.8 million euros [$6.5 million] from the fund, established in 2007.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>European nations such as Germany and Sweden have already opened their doors to refugees fleeing war in the home nations, particularly in the face of civil war in Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>But Vella believes that measures to manage border control do not go far enough and said more needs to be done to tackle the root of the problem in troubled countries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>He added: &amp;quot;The problem is manning the border on the eastern side of Libya, which borders Sudan, which takes you to Eritrea and Somalia, from [where] most of them come.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>On Thursday, more than 200 migrants were rescued from an overcrowded boat in rough waters in the Mediterranean Sea, according to the Italian navy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The boat was spotted about 80 miles south of the Italian island of Lampedusa, another refugee hotspot.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The migrants, from Eritrea, Nigeria, Somalia, Pakistan, Zambia and Mali, were all moved safely.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Vella said: &amp;quot;You&amp;apost;ve got to look at the help you can give the countries of origin, you can look at the problems in the transfer of these people through countries where they fall prey to criminal gangs that make money in human trafficking.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
