<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="57" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/08/06/business/five-food-brands-reinvented-women/index.html" date_published="2013-08-06 15:42:28" category="business" author="Lauren Said-Moorhouse, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Five trailblazing women who reinvented their brand</title>
  <keywords>how food companies have reinvented their brand,Campbell Soup,PepsiCo,Martha Stewart,Donna Hay,denise morrison,Milagros Leelin Yee and Clarita Leelin Go ,indra nooyi,food brands,food brands reinvented by women,trailblazer ceos</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7, 3">Campbell Soup Company CEO Denise Morrison revamped brand to suit younger generation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="16, 15">She has also diversified the company&amp;apost;s healthy products by acquiring Bolthouse Farms.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">CNN charts the evolution of five female-led food and drink brands.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-08 11:42:27" annotation_time="90.108">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">This month CNN&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;Leading Women&amp;quot; sits down with Denise Morrison, the CEO and President of Campbell Soup Company to discuss how she took the firm forward by reinventing the iconic brand.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">In addition to Morrison, CNN also charts the evolution of four female-led food and drink brands.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">Since being named CEO in 2011, she&amp;apost;s made it her mission to revamp the brand and ensure it appeals to a Millennial generation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="2">In her time at the firm, the Indian-born CEO has led the company towards acquisitions of Tropicana and European dairy company Wimm-Bill-Dann.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="2">She was also behind the company&amp;apost;s merger with Quaker Oats.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>(CNN) -- How do you reinvigorate a heritage brand?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a question that has long marred CEOs, business strategists and some of the world&amp;apost;s most astute marketeers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>This month CNN&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;Leading Women&amp;quot; sits down with Denise Morrison, the CEO and President of Campbell Soup Company to discuss how she took the firm forward by reinventing the iconic brand.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>In addition to Morrison, CNN also charts the evolution of four female-led food and drink brands.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Denise Morrison -- CEO and President, Campbell Soup Company.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Denise Morrison joined the 144-year-old soup company a decade ago.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Since being named CEO in 2011, she&amp;apost;s made it her mission to revamp the brand and ensure it appeals to a Millennial generation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>While at the helm, Morrison orchestrated one of the largest acquisitions in the company&amp;apost;s history when it bought Bolthouse Farms for $1.55 billion in July 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The move allowed the company to expand its offering into healthy beverages as well as the highly profitable $12 billion arena of package fresh products.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>While innovation is at the heart of Campbell Soup&amp;apost;s strategy, Morrison says the company will also continue to focus on what they are known for.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Over the last 12 months Campbell&amp;apost;s has added a further 32 soups to their range on offer including Moroccan-style chicken with chickpeas and spicy chorizo flavors to satiate a generation of more adventurous food lovers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Consumers can also expect 200 new products to hit shelves over the next year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Indra Nooyi -- Chairman and CEO, PepsiCo.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>When she took the position of CEO of PepsiCo in 2006, Indra Nooyi had a formidable task ahead of her -- to manage one of the world&amp;apost;s largest food and drink companies which has 22 &amp;quot;billion-dollar&amp;quot; brands (each earn at least $1 billion in annual retail sales) in its extensive portfolio, including Gatorade and Frito-Lay.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>In her time at the firm, the Indian-born CEO has led the company towards acquisitions of Tropicana and European dairy company Wimm-Bill-Dann.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>She was also behind the company&amp;apost;s merger with Quaker Oats.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Nooyi&amp;apost;s strong business acumen has seen the food and drink giant go from strength to strength with the company&amp;apost;s annual net revenues totaling $65 billion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Martha Stewart -- Founder, Martha Stewart Living Omnimedia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Martha Stewart has become a household name internationally thanks to an illustrious career as a TV chef, cook book author, magazine editor and more recently, chat show host.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Now synonymous with lifestyle and homeware, Stewart first began her career in the food industry as a caterer but soon moved in to publishing in 1982 with her first cook book &amp;quot;Entertaining.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>By 1990, she had signed a deal with Time Publishing Ventures to develop &amp;quot;Martha Stewart Living&amp;quot; magazine which continues to be popular.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>One of Stewart&amp;apost;s strongest business moves was establishing her company, Martha Stewart Living Omnimedia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Through the firm, Stewart has been able to put all her publishing, television and merchandising ventures under one umbrella giving her greater control over her brand.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Donna Hay -- Food editor and cookbook author.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Donna Hay began her career in food at the age of 19 as a food writer.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>By 25, the Australian had been named food editor of &amp;quot;Marie Claire.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>These days, Hay spends much of her time on her own bi-monthly publication &amp;quot;Donna Hay Magazine,&amp;quot; which she launched in 2001.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Her approach to food is simple, classic and sophisticated which has proven to be a hit with magazine subscribers in 82 countries in addition to the 384,000 in Australia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Not only did Hay open a homeware store in Sydney, but she&amp;apost;s also become a best-selling author of 18 cookbooks, which have sold 4 million copies worldwide.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Milagros Leelin Yee and Clarita Leelin Go -- Co-founders, Goldilocks Bakery.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>In 1966, two Filipino sisters, Milagros Leelin Yee and Clarita Leelin Go set up a small bakery putting a family-oriented spin on traditional local delicacies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Almost 50 years later, Goldilocks Bakery now boasts of 340 outlets in the Philippines with 24 stores in the U.S. and five in Thailand.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The much-loved family bake shop has expanded to offer food choices and in 2010 underwent a full rebranding in an effort to keep up with other competitors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Meanwhile the sisters have continued their success venturing into publishing with their recipes in &amp;quot;Goldilocks Bakebook.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
