<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="87" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/01/25/business/davos-boris-johnson-eu-referendum/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2013-01-25 05:06:23" category="business" author="Kevin Voigt, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>London mayor enters UK-EU debate from Davos &amp;apost;cyclotron of egos&amp;apost;</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="12">London Mayor Boris Johnson believes Britain would vote to stay part of EU &amp;quot;one way or another&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">Prime Minister David Cameron said he plans to hold a national referendum on membership.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="14">Johnson also condemned attempts in Europe to build financial trading hubs away from London.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="2">Johnson on World Economic Forum in Davos: &amp;quot;It is this great cyclotron of egos isn&amp;apost;t it?&amp;quot;.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 16:36:20" annotation_time="106.480995" mapping_time_divergence="53.240498">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="4">&amp;quot;I think if you ask most international business leaders, bankers whether they wanted to abolish elections to remove any element of uncertainty in the commercial world, well of course they would love to do that,&amp;quot; Mayor Boris Johnson told CNN&amp;apost;s Richard Quest at the World Economic Forum in the Swiss ski resort of Davos, which he described as the &amp;quot;cyclotron of egos.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">Cameron told CNN&amp;apost;s Christiane Amanpour that he has no regrets over the referendum promise, despite unhappiness among some European partners.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="1">Johnson believes any vote would result in Britain remaining in the EU.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="3">Johnson also condemned attempts in Europe to build financial trading hubs away from London.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>While Prime Minister David Cameron&amp;apost;s speech this week -- voicing his intent to let the British people vote on whether to stay in the European Union -- has caused concern on the continent, the mayor of London says it&amp;apost;s all part of democracy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think if you ask most international business leaders, bankers whether they wanted to abolish elections to remove any element of uncertainty in the commercial world, well of course they would love to do that,&amp;quot; Mayor Boris Johnson told CNN&amp;apost;s Richard Quest at the World Economic Forum in the Swiss ski resort of Davos, which he described as the &amp;quot;cyclotron of egos.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;You&amp;apost;ve got to consult the people from time to time, the British people haven&amp;apost;t been consulted since 1975, the French have, the Dutch have, the Irish have -- now is the moment.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Cameron made headlines Wednesday by promising the British people a vote on European Union membership if he wins the next general election in 2015.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Cameron told CNN&amp;apost;s Christiane Amanpour that he has no regrets over the referendum promise, despite unhappiness among some European partners.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s really important that we&amp;apost;ve set out a plan for how we get change in Europe that will benefit all of Europe, making it more open, more competitive, more flexible, and how we secure Britain&amp;apost;s place within that,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The European Union is already changing to meet the needs of the 17 members who are part of the euro single currency, Cameron said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Britain is not in that group.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>After Cameron&amp;apost;s speech on Wednesday, the President of the European Parliament Martin Schulz tweeted: &amp;quot;#Cameron&amp;apost;s Europe a la carte not an option.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>We have to focus on jobs &amp;amp; growth rather than getting lost in treaties discussions.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>French Foreign Minister Laurent Fabius used similar language in an interview on France Info radio saying Europe could not be &amp;quot;a la carte,&amp;quot; Agence France-Presse (AFP) reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Johnson believes any vote would result in Britain remaining in the EU.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think most people can see that the overwhelming likelihood, in fact the certainty, is that Britain one way or another will be part of the free trade zone,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Johnson also condemned attempts in Europe to build financial trading hubs away from London.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Last month, the governor of the Banque de France told the Financial Times the City of London should be deposed as the euro&amp;apost;s main financial center so the single currency club can &amp;quot;control&amp;quot; most financial business in the eurozone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;All these thing come and go, of course it will always be and always has been a historic aim of the French in particular, other countries certainly, to try and chip away at the financial dominance of the city,&amp;quot; Johnson told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;That is always going to be their objective and you have to forgive them for that, they are bound to use what bureaucratic tools they can to achieve those goals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>They haven&amp;apost;t succeeded I the past, I don&amp;apost;t believe they will succeed,&amp;quot; he added.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think the key reason is actually in the end most sensible people in other European capitals know that it is in their interest, in the interest of the EU, to have a massive global powerhouse in London rather than in Singapore or New York.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>And what did London&amp;apost;s mayor think of the World Economic Forum in Davos?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s all a bit intoxicating isn&amp;apost;t it?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>It is this great cyclotron of egos isn&amp;apost;t it, everybody is bumping into each other and having an enormous ghastly, nauseating, mutual feelings of self-regard,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;But you know it is important, I never come away feeling without having met people that could put a lot of money into London, and that is generally what we achieve.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
