<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="96" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/03/14/business/oneill-ambrosetti-marketplace-europe/index.html?iref=allsearch" date_published="2013-03-14 17:30:41" category="business" author="Anna Stewart and Nina dos Santos, CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>O&amp;apost;Neill: Euro may not exist by 2020</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="14">Roubini believes eurozone break-up risk has been reduced, in large part, by ECB measures.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="15">European Union faces a &amp;quot;political backlash&amp;quot; with austerity fatigue, says Nouriel Roubini.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="17">Political cohesion around a drive for austerity was common to many delegates&amp;apost; views.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-18 13:10:06" annotation_time="43.569996">
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="1">Roubini believes these risks have been reduced, in large part, by the European Central Bank&amp;apost;s commitment to purchase sovereign bonds in the secondary markets.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="2">Now, Roubini told CNN, the European Union faces a &amp;quot;political backlash&amp;quot; with austerity fatigue from the likes of Italy, Portugal, Ireland, Spain and Greece, and bailout fatigue from Germany.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="3">The need for political cohesion around a drive for austerity was common to many delegates&amp;apost; views, as was a desire for closer fiscal union.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Jim O&amp;apost;Neill, the Goldman Sachs economist who famously captured the globe&amp;apost;s shifting economic power when he coined the &amp;quot;BRIC&amp;quot; acronym, now says the euro may not exist by 2020.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>O&amp;apost;Neill&amp;apost;s views were aired at the Spring Ambrosetti Forum, where delegates gathered by the peaceful Lake Como.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>But unlike its serene waters, many delegates felt the future of the European Union -- which has been destabilized by economic crisis and political infighting -- remained murky.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>O&amp;apost;Neill, speaking to CNN at the forum, said: &amp;quot;If we carry on the same way as we are, by 2020 the euro might not exist.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>According to O&amp;apost;Neill, &amp;quot;Germany will be exporting twice as much to China as it does to France by the end of 2020.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>He added, &amp;quot;I have joked to some of the European policy makers that in such an environment, Germany would want to be in a monetary union with China, not with France.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Villa d&amp;apost;Este plays host to the Ambrosetti forum twice a year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>It is an elite gathering of European economists and business leaders, and for two days they have just one item on the agenda: The state of the global economy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Some have compared the Ambrosetti Forum to Davos; albeit a much smaller version.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>With serene views of Lake Como, a warmer climate and fine-dining, it&amp;apost;s certainly a deluxe version.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Light from chandeliers dance over the delegates as they sit in their four closed-door sessions a day, which are broken up with coffee breaks and three course meals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Nouriel Roubini, the economist also known by the name &amp;quot;Dr Doom&amp;quot; for predicting the credit crunch, was a little less gloomy about the eurozone than O&amp;apost;Neill when he spoke to CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;Compared to a year ago, when there was a risk that Greece would exit the eurozone, that the eurozone would break up, that Italy and Spain would lose market access, those tail risks have been reduced,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Roubini believes these risks have been reduced, in large part, by the European Central Bank&amp;apost;s commitment to purchase sovereign bonds in the secondary markets.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Now, Roubini told CNN, the European Union faces a &amp;quot;political backlash&amp;quot; with austerity fatigue from the likes of Italy, Portugal, Ireland, Spain and Greece, and bailout fatigue from Germany.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;There is a toxic nexus between a lack of competitiveness, unsustainability, low potential growth and an ongoing recession,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The need for political cohesion around a drive for austerity was common to many delegates&amp;apost; views, as was a desire for closer fiscal union.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Europe is in the middle,&amp;quot; Andrea Canino, the chairman at MC Partners, told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;We don&amp;apost;t know where the power is, it is not any more in the national state and it is not in Brussels.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Such uncertainty would kill Europe, he added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Guiseppe Recche, the chairman of Eni, the Italian multinational oil and gas company, said his business continues to struggle in its European market.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;Wherever we do business, and we work in over 80 countries, we do well, except for Italy and Europe,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;Is that because Europe is not competitive?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Is that because Europe doesn&amp;apost;t have technology to sell?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Probably not.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;It needs to manage its expenses, austerity needs to be spoken of, and of not just in negative terms, a fiscal balance of expenses is needed.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The Ambrosetti Forum will reconvene in the autumn, the mist will have lifted over the lake, and, for the delegates, perhaps the future for the European Union will be looking clearer too.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
