<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="111" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/10/11/business/imf-lagarde-schauble/index.html" date_published="2012-10-12 00:25:47" category="business" author="Claire Jones and Peter Spiegel, FT.com" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Schäuble and Lagarde clash over austerity</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">High-level splits over the handling of the eurozone crisis burst into the open .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Germany&amp;apost;s finance minister rebuked the head of the International Monetary Fund .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">Christine Lagarde warned that EU leaders should ease demands for tighter austerity .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="6">Lagarde said eurozone countries should not blindly stick to tough budget deficit targets .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-29 13:53:06" annotation_time="66.387665">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1, 2, 3">High-level splits over the handling of the eurozone crisis burst into the open on Thursday when Germany&amp;apost;s finance minister rebuked the head of the International Monetary Fund after she warned that EU leaders should ease demands for tighter austerity in peripheral economies.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="4">Ms Lagarde said eurozone countries should not blindly stick to tough budget deficit targets if growth weakens more than expected.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>High-level splits over the handling of the eurozone crisis burst into the open on Thursday when Germany&amp;apost;s finance minister rebuked the head of the International Monetary Fund after she warned that EU leaders should ease demands for tighter austerity in peripheral economies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Wolfgang Schäuble said Christine Lagarde had appeared to contradict the IMF&amp;apost;s own stance in advocating an easing of austerity, noting that the fund had &amp;quot;time and again&amp;quot; warned that high debt levels threatened economic growth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;When there is a certain medium-term goal, it doesn&amp;apost;t build confidence when one starts by going in a different direction,&amp;quot; Mr Schäuble said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;When you want to climb a big mountain and you start climbing down the mountain, then the mountain will get even higher.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Mr Schäuble spoke on the sidelines of a meeting of finance ministers and central bankers in Tokyo just after Ms Lagarde, the IMF managing director, backed a new study that found Brussels and the IMF had consistently underestimated the impact of austerity measures on economic growth during the eurozone crisis.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Ms Lagarde said eurozone countries should not blindly stick to tough budget deficit targets if growth weakens more than expected.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>She argued that they should allow &amp;quot;automatic stabilisers&amp;quot; -- higher welfare spending and lower tax revenues -- to kick in if the economy deteriorated.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is sometimes better to have more time,&amp;quot; Ms Lagarde said, noting that if countries tried to cut their budgets simultaneously it could multiply austerity&amp;apost;s impact on the economy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The IMF&amp;apost;s warnings against an overreliance on austerity came as Angela Merkel, the German chancellor, held out the prospect of government action, including possible tax cuts, to stimulate domestic demand.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Ms Merkel said she was determined to revive Germany&amp;apost;s flagging growth, not least because of the country&amp;apost;s role &amp;quot;to do something for the stimulation of the economy in Europe&amp;quot;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Eurozone leaders have called for tougher austerity measures in both Spain and Greece, even as their economies shrink rapidly.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Both countries are expected to be discussed at a high-profile summit of EU leaders next week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Ms Lagarde advocated giving Greece two more years to hit the tough budget targets contained in its €174bn bailout programme, becoming the most senior official publicly to back to a request from the government in Athens this summer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Europeans are braced for a new age of austerity as governments across the region take action to eliminate unsustainable budget deficits.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Her call for slower adjustment, coupled with a highly symbolic visit to Athens by Ms Merkel is a boost to Greece, which is trying to persuade its eurozone partners to give it more time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>However, slower deficit reduction in Athens would mean Greece&amp;apost;s international creditors would have to give it more help in a politically fraught overhaul of Greece&amp;apost;s bailout programme.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Ms Lagarde said she also supported the European Commission&amp;apost;s decision to give Spain another year to bring its budget deficit down to 3 per cent of economic output but she would not comment on whether Madrid should ask for extra financial assistance from the EU.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>José Viñals, head of the IMF&amp;apost;s monetary and capital markets department, appeared to warn Berlin against blocking any Spanish request for assistance.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Mr Schäuble has insisted that Madrid does not need additional financing aid even as Brussels has been pushing it to ask for assistance.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Mr Viñals, in an interview with Reuters, said creditor countries, including Germany, should not &amp;quot;negate&amp;quot; a Spanish request that would activate the European Central Bank&amp;apost;s new bond-buying assistance programme, bringing down Spanish borrowing costs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Yields on benchmark 10-year Spanish bonds fell nearly 1 per cent on Thursday despite an overnight downgrade by Standard &amp;amp; Poor&amp;apost;s, the rating agency.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
