<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="107" link="http://cnn.com/2014/03/20/business/europe-russia-sanctions-dos-santos" date_published="2014-03-20 15:58:41" category="business" author="Nina dos Santos, CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Russia sanctions: EU should leave trade alone</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="14">Nina dos Santos says Europe must be ready to accept sanctions will hurt both sides.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="15">Targeting Russia&amp;apost;s business community would be one way of sapping their support for President Putin, she says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="20">But she says Europe would have a hard time keeping its factories going without power from the east.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-27 08:53:06" annotation_time="42.097">
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="1">As such EU leaders must be ready to accept sanctions are a two-way street and will hurt both sides.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="2">Targeting Russia&amp;apost;s peripatetic business community would be one way of sapping their tenuous support for President Putin.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="3">But Europe - with its hefty reliance on Russian gas - would have a hard time keeping its factories going and citizens warm without power from the east.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>With a breezy sweep of his pen President Vladimir Putin wrote a new chapter into Crimea&amp;apost;s turbulent history, committing the region to a future returned to Russian domain.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Sixty years prior, Ukraine&amp;apost;s breakaway peninsula was signed away just as swiftly by Soviet leader Nikita Khrushchev.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>But dealing with such a blatant land grab on its eastern flank won&amp;apost;t be anywhere near as quick and easy for Europe&amp;apost;s 28-member union.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Because, unlike Crimea&amp;apost;s rushed referendum, everyone has a say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>After initially slapping visa restrictions and asset freezes on a limited number of little known politicians and military men, Europe is facing urgent calls to widen the scope of its measures to target the Russian business community in particular.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The logic of this is that those who run Russia and own it are essentially two sides of the coin.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Alexei Navalny, one-time Moscow mayoral contender now under house arrest for opposing the current regime, called for Europe&amp;apost;s leaders to ban everyone -- from Vladimir Putin&amp;apost;s personal banker to Chelsea Football Club owner Roman Abramovich from keeping their money and loved ones abroad.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Asset freezes and visa restrictions are especially palatable options for the EU because they can be rolled out on a discretionary basis, without requiring cumbersome legal procedures and recourse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>In fact Russia cancels visas for people it doesn&amp;apost;t like all the time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Just look at Hermitage Capital founder Bill Browder who lost both his right of entry and Moscow-based money in 2005 and dare not go back.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Russia also banned the adoption of its orphans by Americans in retaliation for the US&amp;apost;s implementation of an anti-corruption law named after Sergei Magnitsky, Browder&amp;apost;s lawyer who died after a year in a Moscow detention center, apparently beaten to death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Yet in playing the &amp;apost;money talks&amp;apost; card, Europe must be ready for the consequences of such action.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Because money also walks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>As such EU leaders must be ready to accept sanctions are a two-way street and will hurt both sides.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Targeting Russia&amp;apost;s peripatetic business community would be one way of sapping their tenuous support for President Putin.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>And such a strategy might also turn out to have a silver lining: awarding EU countries a chance to finally deal with some of the more unpleasant sides of their patronage, including money laundering and corruption, which have inflated prize assets like London property and Picasso paintings for years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Where Europe should hold fire though is trade.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Two decades of post-Soviet rapprochement and almost $500 billion worth of commerce is a lot to put at stake.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s true that any trade war would hurt Russia far harder than it would the EU - not least because 15% of the former&amp;apost;s GDP comes from exports to the bloc.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>But Europe - with its hefty reliance on Russian gas - would have a hard time keeping its factories going and citizens warm without power from the east.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>And while Putin flexes his political muscle, open trade channels keep the dialogue going giving all sides a chance to change the subject and talk less tensely.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>No one can afford to cut off that lifeline, especially now with Europe&amp;apost;s economy on the rebound and Russia&amp;apost;s one on the wane.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
