<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="31" link="http://cnn.com/2014/01/22/business/davos-crown-prince-haakon-dignity-unites-worlds-youth/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-01-22 15:46:43" category="business" author="Crown Prince Haakon of Norway, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Crown Prince Haakon: Dignity unites world&amp;apost;s youth</title>
  <keywords>WEF,Davos,youth,norway,prince Haakon</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Norway&amp;apost;s Crown Prince Haakon: It is dangerous not to let youth help reshape the world.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="11">He says global youth networks are far ahead what established leaders had in their youth.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="28">Youth find it incredibly easy to operationalize dignity into practical action, he writes.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-08 06:42:48" annotation_time="14.618335">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">It is dangerous not to let today&amp;apost;s youth be a part of the reshaping of the world.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="2">The global networks of youth are far ahead what established leaders of today had when they were young.</sentence>
      <sentence id="28" ids_highlights="3">Youth find it incredibly easy to grasp the idea of dignity -- and even better: how it can be operationalized into practical action.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Davos is a stimulating place to be, to discuss and to learn.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Hopefully, by coming together, we will find ideas and solutions that will bring the world forward.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>In my opinion, one of our challenges is that we are about to lose a whole generation of resources because of the growing unemployment of youth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>It is dangerous not to let today&amp;apost;s youth be a part of the reshaping of the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>In 2013, according to the World Bank, 73% of the labor force between the ages 15 and 24 was without work, but available for and seeking employment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Many of the people I have admired over the last few years have been young people I have met in very different situations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>They have become role models for leadership and high ethical standard.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Some fantastic young people I have met have shown leadership under such hard conditions that I can picture them taking a leading position within a wide range of fields.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>I believe today&amp;apost;s youth -- the ones you find at almost any school almost anywhere in the world -- are highly competent people with knowledge and experience that would be in the best interests of established leaders to utilize.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Youth today live in an extreme world regarding diversity, conflict, opportunities and technical means of connecting with others.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The global networks of youth are far ahead what established leaders of today had when they were young.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Since 2006 I have been visiting schools and talking to students all around the world together with my fellow Young Global Leaders John Hope Bryant and Pekka Himanen.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>We have arranged so called Dignity Days -- which is the main activity of our organization Global Dignity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>We have three goals: To spur a global conversation on dignity, to arrange Global Dignity Days at schools and promote dignity-based leadership.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>This year, Dignity Day will be held for more than half of the Norwegian first year high school pupils -- and in around 50 countries world wide.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>What strikes me during my very diverse meetings with youth around the world is how similarly they define dignity -- and how relevant it feels for most young people to discuss this issue as a core value of our time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>These are some of the dignity stories we have been told:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>In Jordan, a girl stood up and told how annoyed she had been when she got a visually impaired teacher.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The girl was very ambitious, and thought she would get less quality training because of the teacher&amp;apost;s disability.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>When the teacher later became the first visually impaired person in Jordan to earn her PhD, the student completely shifted her perspective.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>She realized that she was proud that this had been her teacher and that she had learned something more important from her than from any of her other teachers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>In South Africa a girl told how, during the riots in 2009, her grandmother covered and hide some of the immigrants in her home, who were targets of the riots.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>In Norway, a Muslim student told how her friend had started to walk to and from school together with a Jewish boy who was being bullied -- to support and protect him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>I particularly like this third story.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>It shows the genius of youth in beautiful simplicity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>It hits the core of what the world&amp;apost;s leaders have been struggling so hard over so many years to achieve.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>I believe youth is an important target group for positive change -- indeed the real driver of positive change.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Youth find it incredibly easy to grasp the idea of dignity -- and even better: how it can be operationalized into practical action.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>They are truly Champions of Global Dignity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>So what do we need to do to create positive change?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>It is not enough to merely accept the inherent dignity of all human beings.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Our actions must reflect the dignity of others.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>In my view dignity consists of two main parts: Firstly, inherent dignity and secondly, perceived dignity -- a sort of dignity capital.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>We all have the ability to increase other people&amp;apost;s dignity capital -- and thus increase our own.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>This is about doing all we can to become our best selves -- by making conscious decisions -- and making the best out of our resources.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Take action, see potential, and give unemployed youth the opportunity to use their resources as a response to this both current and emerging challenge.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
