<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="29" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/11/30/business/asian-art-market-curiel/index.html" date_published="2012-11-30 07:48:07" category="business" author="Anjani Trivedi, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Christie&amp;apost;s: Evolution of the Asian art market</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Asian art market has typically been driven by savvy investors and China&amp;apost;s nouveau riche.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">Christie&amp;apost;s 2012 annual autumn auction in Hong Kong grossed $334 million.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="16">With a market of burgeoning art buyers, artists from the region are making their mark.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="23">Hong Kong is now the world&amp;apost;s third largest art market by auction sales.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-25 20:51:10" annotation_time="121.745">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">The Asian art market has typically been driven by savvy investors and China&amp;apost;s nouveau riche.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">Christie&amp;apost;s annual autumn auction in Hong Kong, which ended Wednesday, grossed $334 million.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="3">With a market of burgeoning art buyers, artists from the region are making their mark, too.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="4">Hong Kong is now the world&amp;apost;s third largest art market by auction sales, according to the Hong Kong government&amp;apost;s investment department.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Chinese artists are painting the globe red and the regional art market is no longer hostage to fickle buyers, the Asia president of auction house Christie&amp;apost;s told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The Asian art market has typically been driven by savvy investors and China&amp;apost;s nouveau riche.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;Some invest in art as though it were a stock market, with artworks that are virtually split into multiples of dematerialized shares,&amp;quot; according to Artprice, an art auction research firm.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Hong Kong&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;success has been marred by the poor reputation of Chinese buyers,&amp;quot; according to a recent report by Artprice.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;In Hong Kong, Christie&amp;apost;s and Sotheby&amp;apost;s have both experienced non-payment problems that have led to court proceedings... so much so that to avoid such problems, the major auction houses are now asking buyers to pay a HK$1 million (US$129,000) advance deposit for the more expensive items.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>However, Christie&amp;apost;s Francois Curiel sees this paradigm changing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;What was interesting this weekend is that with the exception of this picture (&amp;quot;La foret blanche II&amp;quot; by Chu The-Chun) and maybe one or two others, there were no other records,&amp;quot; Curiel told CNN&amp;apost;s Patricia Wu.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;There were good, strong, solid prices and it seems that the speculative buyers have left town.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Christie&amp;apost;s annual autumn auction in Hong Kong, which ended Wednesday, grossed $334 million.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Although art sales in the region were down by 15% to 25% the first half of the year, sales in the second half of the year bounced back, according to Curiel, Christie&amp;apost;s Asian head.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Asia&amp;apost;s growing art scene is reinforced by various government initiatives and local auction houses.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;The relationship between art and money is totally uninhibited in China and generates ever more ambitious projects,&amp;quot; the Artprice report says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The &amp;quot;world&amp;apost;s first financial center for art&amp;quot; is under construction in the city of Xiamen and is expected to be completed by 2014.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The $260 million project promises auction sales, exhibitions, appraisal services, galleries, art restorers and other related businesses, according to the developer Beijing Huachen Auctions Co.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Hong Kong is also developing a $3 billion &amp;quot;integrated arts and cultural district,&amp;quot; in the West Kowloon district, according to a Hong Kong government report.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>With a market of burgeoning art buyers, artists from the region are making their mark, too.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Their art is being sold for record hammer prices -- this year, a Chinese artist Chu The-Chun&amp;apost;s work sold for a record price -- the highest ever for this artist at US$7.7 million.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Zeng Fanzhi and Zhang Xiao Gang are now the two Chinese artists in this very elite list of the top 10 living artists bringing more than $10 million in the world,&amp;quot; said Curiel, 60, who is a renowned auctioneer in his own right.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;It was unthinkable five years to think they will be in the top 10 living artists in the world -- two Chinese artists -- but now it&amp;apost;s done, which shows the interest of Chinese contemporary art, not only in China but also in Europe and America.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Five Chinese artists, including Zeng Fanzhi, figure on Artprice&amp;apost;s list of top 500 contemporary artists in 2012, along with the likes of Damien Hirst.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>For Christie&amp;apost;s -- which had global auctions and private sales totaling $3.5 billion in the first half of 2012 -- Asian market share is skyrocketing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Three years ago, Hong Kong accounted for only 3% of global sales; last year, Hong Kong accounted for 20% of sales, Curiel said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Hong Kong is now the world&amp;apost;s third largest art market by auction sales, according to the Hong Kong government&amp;apost;s investment department.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;Few years ago, it was London, Paris and New York,&amp;quot; Curiel said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;Now, it&amp;apost;s London, Paris, New York and Hong Kong.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
