<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="123" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/05/13/business/numbers-showing-africa-entrepreneurial-spirit/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-05-13 11:27:58" category="business" author="Teo Kermeliotis and Milena Veselinovic, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>The numbers that show Africa is buzzing with entrepreneurial spirit</title>
  <keywords>africa business,africa entrepreneurship, Global Entrepreneurship Monitor</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="39">Experts say Africa has to rely on small businesses to provide employment.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="13">The continent has the highest rates of early-stage entrepreneurship in the world.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">It&amp;apost;s a leader for female entrepreneurship, says Global Entrepreneurship Monitor.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="25">Yet countries with many new startups also see high levels of discontinuance.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-11 14:51:20" annotation_time="383.13135">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;The entrepreneurial landscape in sub-Saharan Africa is absolutely excellent,&amp;quot; says Mike Herrington, executive director of Global Entrepreneurship Monitor (GEM) and professor at the University of Cape Town in South Africa.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="2">Overall, the continent has a much higher proportion of female entrepreneurs compared to other regions, with Nigeria and Zambia (both 40.7%) coming on top and countries like the United States (10.4%), the UK (5.5%), Norway (3.6%) and France (3.1%) lagging far behind.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="4">As a result, countries like Malawi and Angola that see many new businesses also experience high numbers of people abandoning their efforts after failing to make profits.</sentence>
      <sentence id="39" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;Africa is going to have to rely on small businesses (SMEs) to provide the bulk of the employment,&amp;quot; he says.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>From ambitious teens taking on the world and tech pioneers breaking boundaries to maverick slum dwellers dreaming big and trailblazing innovators tackling social problems, CNN&amp;apost;s African Start-Up has been following the efforts of the continent&amp;apost;s innovative and determined entrepreneurs to make their business dreams become reality.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Indeed, all across the continent, a growing wave of grassroots self-starters are taking risks and defying obstacles to bring their money-making ideas to life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Armed with a can-do attitude and hopes of striking it big, they&amp;apost;re navigating a conundrum of challenges to pursue opportunities at a time when many African countries enjoy unprecedented levels of economic growth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;The entrepreneurial landscape in sub-Saharan Africa is absolutely excellent,&amp;quot; says Mike Herrington, executive director of Global Entrepreneurship Monitor (GEM) and professor at the University of Cape Town in South Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s on the increase because Africa, at last, has been emerging and the economies are booming -- several countries are starting to really increase entrepreneurial activity and move to opportunity entrepreneurship, rather than necessity entrepreneurship,&amp;quot; he adds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;Opportunities abound and a positive spirit is emerging amongst the population of these countries.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>So, Africa&amp;apost;s entrepreneurial spirit is alive and thriving -- but how does it compare to the rest of the world?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Earlier this year, GEM published its annual report looking at the state of entrepreneurship globally.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>It found that sub-Saharan Africa is the region with by far the highest number of people involved in early-stage entrepreneurial activity (TEA), with Zambia and Nigeria leading the world rankings.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a woman&amp;apost;s world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Africa also leads the world in the number of women starting businesses, with almost equal levels of male and female entrepreneurs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>In fact, in countries like Ghana, Nigeria and Zambia the women outnumber the men.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Overall, the continent has a much higher proportion of female entrepreneurs compared to other regions, with Nigeria and Zambia (both 40.7%) coming on top and countries like the United States (10.4%), the UK (5.5%), Norway (3.6%) and France (3.1%) lagging far behind.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>According to Herrington, the main reason for this is because women in Africa &amp;quot;need to earn an extra income&amp;quot; to be able to afford &amp;quot;to send their children to school.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Getting off the ground.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Yet, does the high number of both male and female entrepreneurs tell the whole story?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>And do these impressive figures translate to sustainable startups that are able to grow and provide employment to the continent&amp;apost;s young population?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>In its analysis, GEM groups countries into geographic regions, but also according to their development stage: factor-driven, efficiency-driven and innovation-driven, each suggesting an increasing level of sophistication in the operation of the economy (see fact box on the left).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Most African nations surveyed are placed into the factor-driven stage, where early-stage entrepreneurial activity rates tend to be higher than the rates of owner-managers in established businesses (running more than three and a half years).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>In other words, &amp;quot;a high entrepreneurship rate does not necessarily mean the creation of a lot of jobs,&amp;quot; explains Herrington.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;Those countries with low GDP per capita tend to have a very high entrepreneurial rate, because the larger corporations are not taking up a lot people to provide them with the so-called formal employment,&amp;quot; he adds.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Calling it a day.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Similarly, the continent might be buzzing with startups, but how long do these last?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>According to GEM, the rate of business discontinuance tends to decrease as economic development increases.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>As a result, countries like Malawi and Angola that see many new businesses also experience high numbers of people abandoning their efforts after failing to make profits.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;The discontinuance of businesses in the factor-driven economies is very high,&amp;quot; says Herrington, citing &amp;quot;the lack of education, market research and access to funding&amp;quot; as the main reasons.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Fearless entrepreneurs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>There are several factors hindering the survival and growth of small businesses in Africa -- little government support, bureaucracy and lack of financial backing to cite a few more.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Yet, all these constraints do little to prevent the continent&amp;apost;s budding entrepreneurs from trying their luck.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>True, entrepreneurs might be optimistic by nature, but nowhere else in the world is this key drive toward success as present as in Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The continent&amp;apost;s entrepreneurs boast the lowest levels of &amp;quot;fear of failure,&amp;quot; with just 24% responding that it would stop from starting a business and seizing business opportunities.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>In countries like Zambia, Uganda and Malawi the figure drops to as little as 15% -- compare that to countries like the UK (36.4%) and the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>(31%).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>All you need is confidence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s no surprise then that African entrepreneurs are also the most confident in the world in their ability and skills to start a business.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>In comparison, people in Malawi feel twice as self-assured about launching a startup as those in the UK.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Likewise, sub-Saharan Africa claims the top five spots for countries where people see good opportunities for starting a business and feel positive about entrepreneurship.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Herrington says that it&amp;apost;s these qualities, coupled with a need for better education and a focus on moving entrepreneurs from necessity to opportunity, that will drive the continent&amp;apost;s development.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;Africa is going to have to rely on small businesses (SMEs) to provide the bulk of the employment,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;In a lot of countries the SMEs contribute more than 50% of the GDP and more than 50% of employment, so if you&amp;apost;re going to employ people in Africa and other developing countries it&amp;apost;s SMEs are the ones that are going to provide that.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>