<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="66" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/07/11/business/prince-charles-fisheries/index.html" date_published="2014-07-11 11:02:56" category="business" author="Ivana Kottasova, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>How $50 billion can be found in fishing -- if the world does it better</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">A new report backed by Prince Charles says fisheries could bring $50 billion.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">The aim is to bring in businesses and transform the way the conservation efforts are funded.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="16">Prince Charles: &amp;quot;Economy and ecology do not have to be locked into an irreconcilable struggle&amp;quot;.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-21 22:34:43" annotation_time="25.898333">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Oceans around the globe could inject an extra $50 billion into the world&amp;apost;s economy -- if fisheries were sustainably managed, a new report backed by Prince Charles shows.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">The aim was to transform the way the conservation efforts are funded -- from philanthropic and public sources of money, to business investment.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;Economy and ecology do not have to be locked into an irreconcilable struggle,&amp;quot; the Prince said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Oceans around the globe could inject an extra $50 billion into the world&amp;apost;s economy -- if fisheries were sustainably managed, a new report backed by Prince Charles shows.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Prince Charles, a keen environmentalist, hosted a meeting in London Thursday bringing together representatives of the fishing industry, governments, campaigning groups and investors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The aim was to transform the way the conservation efforts are funded -- from philanthropic and public sources of money, to business investment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;Success would provide a much-needed example of how to regenerate our planet&amp;apost;s dangerously depleted, threadbare and under-performing natural capital while also providing a realistic economic return,&amp;quot; Prince Charles said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Fisheries contribute more than $270 billion to global GDP and employ hundreds of millions of people around the world, according to the report from the Prince of Wales charity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>An additional $160 billion comes from related businesses, such as ship building or fish processing industries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>But environmentalists argue the world&amp;apost;s oceans are being exploited, and that will eventually cost the industry billions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The report points to the Canadian Grand Banks cod fisheries, where unsustainable fishing led to its collapse, as an example of the impact.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The report argues global demand for fish and seafood have pushed prices up since early 2000s -- but stocks have remained constrained.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>It says sustainable fishing would ensure a bigger and healthier fish stock, producing yields in the longer term.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;Oceans are the single most important resource in human history,&amp;quot; Fred Krupp, the President of Environmental Defence Fund said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;We can transform our oceans into a sustainable, enduring resource -- one that provides more fish in the sea, more food on the plate, and more economic prosperity,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The Global Ocean Commission has also sounded warnings about the high seas, saying in June that there was a risk of exploitation in oceans outside national jurisdictions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;There are &amp;apost;too many boats trying to catch too few fish&amp;apost; yet, despite this clear overcapacity, governments still grant at least US$30 billion a year in fisheries subsidies,&amp;quot; the commission said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The commission said the majority of sustainable fishing in these waters is done by only 10 countries -- most of them developed countries that can afford subsidizing the expensive operations of sending large boats into remote corners of the oceans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;Economy and ecology do not have to be locked into an irreconcilable struggle,&amp;quot; the Prince said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Prince Charles, along with the Environmental Defense Fund and a fisheries network 50in10, is now calling for investors to transform the industry into a more sustainable model -- and find that extra $50 billion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
