<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="93" link="http://cnn.com/2014/03/25/business/julia-hobsbawm-names-not-numbers/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-03-25 10:57:59" category="business" author="" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Names Not Numbers: How to network offline in a digital age</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2, 1">Julia Hobsbawm is the founder of knowledge networking business Editorial Intelligence.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">She promotes live networking meetings, increasingly necessary in the digital age.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="8, 17">The annual conference Names Not Numbers is a three-day long brainstorming retreat.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 15:11:10" annotation_time="197.06702" mapping_time_divergence="131.378">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Her passion for public speaking and networking have earned Julia Hobsbawm the moniker &amp;quot;queen of networking&amp;quot; and made her one of the most influential people in the UK.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1, 2">As the founder of knowledge networking business Editorial Intelligence she aims to create more face-to-face meetings and live debates in a digital age where many opinion-formers are far too isolated in their corporate silos.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="3">Each year, 150 to 200 participants from diverse backgrounds such as business, politics, law, or arts set off on a three days long journey to talk about the things that really matter.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="3">JH: The &amp;quot;ideas conference&amp;quot; is still relatively young -- the TED conferences celebrate their 30th anniversary this year; Names Not Numbers is seven years old.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Her passion for public speaking and networking have earned Julia Hobsbawm the moniker &amp;quot;queen of networking&amp;quot; and made her one of the most influential people in the UK.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>As the founder of knowledge networking business Editorial Intelligence she aims to create more face-to-face meetings and live debates in a digital age where many opinion-formers are far too isolated in their corporate silos.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>To that end, Hobsbawm founded the Names Not Numbers ideas festival in 2009 to connect people from &amp;quot;different walks of life -- business, culture, media, politics, academia, with each other in a very intensive setting.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>CNN&amp;apost;s Route to the Top caught up with Hobsbawm to talk about the brainstorming retreat she&amp;apost;s created, the rising popularity of ideas conferences and the importance of intellectual stimulation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>An edited version of the interview follows.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>CNN: What is Names Not Numbers?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Julia Hobsbawm: It&amp;apost;s a mini-festival about ideas -- that&amp;apost;s the best way I can describe it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Each year, 150 to 200 participants from diverse backgrounds such as business, politics, law, or arts set off on a three days long journey to talk about the things that really matter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>What makes it attractive to people is that in this environment where everything is busy and rushed, actually slowing down is a counter-intuitively refreshing and rewarding thing to do.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>CNN: Is your conference aimed at connecting mind, body and soul?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>JH: It seems that something happens physically and chemically when you go for a journey.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>When people relax, they give more of themselves.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Rather than just dropping out of the office for an hour and then rushing back, you are with a small family of people for a period of time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>All sorts of ideas begin to exchange really fruitfully, friendships and business developments form.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>What people really want is to be looked after, as if they were going to a sort of &amp;quot;ideas holiday.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>CNN: Why do you think that events like this proved so popular over the past decade?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>JH: The &amp;quot;ideas conference&amp;quot; is still relatively young -- the TED conferences celebrate their 30th anniversary this year; Names Not Numbers is seven years old.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>I think it is no accident that we see more public and private festivals in the decade that&amp;apost;d seen Facebook.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>So, as a knowledge networking company, we explore how people crave a face-to-face connection in a Facebook age.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Whilst technology enables everybody to connect, what actually moves the dial on relationships and connections is that when you speak to someone, you look in their face, you take a read of their body language.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>I think this is why the intensity and the immediacy of an elongated conference work so well.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>CNN: Names Not numbers has been described as an &amp;quot;intellectual Viagra.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>What does that mean to you?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>JH: In a working world, we sometimes forget that people like to be intellectually stimulated.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Many don&amp;apost;t often get the opportunity in their day jobs to use all the bits of their brain and their emotions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>We hope we allow that to come out a bit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>CNN: Do you think that idea conferences may pose a risk of over-stimulation in today&amp;apost;s information age?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>JH: I think the age of overload is a real risk for people.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>And one of the benefits of coming away for two or three days of content that other people put together for you is that it actually allows you to relax.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>You don&amp;apost;t have to fervently read and go online, screen a million emails and worry about what you&amp;apost;ve missed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>So, in a curious way, actually having a very rich, immersive period of time is reassuring -- the programming has been done for you.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
