<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="37" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/09/06/business/designer-takes-bull-by-horns/index.html" date_published="2013-09-06 09:54:06" category="business" author="Nicola Goulding, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Designer takes bull by the horns ... and makes jewelry from them</title>
  <keywords>zanaa ,cow horn jewelry,uganda,cow horns,ankole</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Zanaa is a Uganda-based company making jewelry from ankole cow horns.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8">Its high-end products are sold in the United States and Europe.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">&amp;quot;Africa has abundance of beautiful materials,&amp;quot; says Zanaa&amp;apost;s founder.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-17 12:08:08" annotation_time="38.729">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">Once in the country, the British-born designer started Zanaa, a luxury label producing high-end jewelry and accessories made from a variety of materials, including ankole cow horns.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">From horn bangles and chic rings to eye-catching necklaces and earrings, Zanaa&amp;apost;s growing jewelry line is sold to high-end buyers in the United States and Europe.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;Zanaa means illuminate the source, the source being Africa, where we have an abundance of beautiful materials, an abundance of amazing craftsmanship,&amp;quot; says Lwanga.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>All that glitters is not gold, and not all designer jewelry is made from precious metals and gemstones.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>A few years ago, Linda Lwanga&amp;apost;s love of traditional African designs led her to her ancestral home in Uganda&amp;apost;s capital of Kampala, giving up her career in electrical engineering in the UK.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Once in the country, the British-born designer started Zanaa, a luxury label producing high-end jewelry and accessories made from a variety of materials, including ankole cow horns.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Used for centuries for their milk and meat, ankole cows are indigenous to east Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Yet once they are slaughtered their striking long horns are usually discarded -- and this, Lwanga thought, represented a sustainable business opportunity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;If it weren&amp;apost;t for making something out of cow horn it would have been disposed of,&amp;quot; says Lwanga.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;Typically in Africa we tend to burn a lot -- our garbage, our waste is burnt and it&amp;apost;s not environmentally friendly at all so I just thought of collecting it and transforming it into something beautiful.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>From horn bangles and chic rings to eye-catching necklaces and earrings, Zanaa&amp;apost;s growing jewelry line is sold to high-end buyers in the United States and Europe.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Lwanga says that all the products are handmade by a small dedicated team of local artisans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;Zanaa means illuminate the source, the source being Africa, where we have an abundance of beautiful materials, an abundance of amazing craftsmanship,&amp;quot; says Lwanga.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are losing a lot of our heritage, our culture and our artisans, in a sense, are kind of losing hope,&amp;quot; she adds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;So we are trying to get that artisanal craftmanship and keep it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Alongside the cow horn, Lwanga sources other traditional materials for her designs, such as imported leather from Ethiopia and beads from South Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Yet doing business from Kampala has not been without problems.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;I would say timeliness is the biggest challenge,&amp;quot; says Lwanga.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;Trying to get your products to market in a short space of time and be competitive.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Regional trade.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Uganda, often described as the &amp;quot;pearl of Africa,&amp;quot; is one of the continent&amp;apost;s most beautiful nations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The landlocked country, however, is also one of Africa&amp;apost;s poorest -- according to a 2009 report by the World Bank, 38% of the population lives below the poverty line.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The country is part of COMESA, a trading bloc of 19 nations in east and southern Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Its free trade arrangements are designed to allow regional trade to flow easily between the member countries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Uganda&amp;apost;s trade within COMESA is worth $1.2 billion annually, according to the country&amp;apost;s ministry of trade.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>But transporting goods is one of the key problems due to crumbling roads and expensive air travel.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>For Zanaa, accessing information and understanding how the trade bloc can benefit young entrepreneurs has been problematic.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;I had to go directly to the ministry of trade to find out about the tariffs for example, how to import,&amp;quot; explains Lwanga, who already trades with many of the countries in the COMESA trading bloc.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;So it was more proactive, actually going out to seek that information.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Putting businesses on the map.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Uganda&amp;apost;s ministry of trade says it knows the system is far from perfect but insists much is being done to improve the availability of information to businesses in the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have promoted the district commercial offices because some of these small and medium-sized enterprises are out in the rural areas,&amp;quot; says Amelia Kyambadde, minister of trade, industry and cooperatives.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;So they are able to access them and give them information about the market standards and the necessary facilitation that they need.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Although still a work in progress, Lwanga says she sees the potential for her future if Uganda&amp;apost;s regional trading relations continue to grow, especially when it comes to distributing her products.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;It will impact the business greatly,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;If we can get import and export of the products smoothly and in a timely manner, an affordable manner and understanding what tax breaks we can get from doing business in such a way that will be fantastic,&amp;quot; adds Lwanga.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;It will enable us to be put on the map.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
