<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="142" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/01/24/business/davos-shareholder-value-is-dumbest-idea/index.html" date_published="2014-01-24 11:36:56" category="business" author="Andre Spicer, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Why shareholder value is &amp;apost;the dumbest idea in the world&amp;apost;</title>
  <keywords>shareholdres,corporations,profit</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="40">Executives should be incentivized on different dimensions -- not just shareholder value, Spicer says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">Corporations with strict focus on maximizing shareholder value tend to employ managers with short-term commitment.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="42">He argues that impacts on customers, suppliers, communities and employees all need to be discussed.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-12 18:19:49" annotation_time="193.98201">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">Corporations with a strict focus on maximizing shareholder value tend to employ a cadre of generalist managers who have relatively short-term commitment to the firm.</sentence>
      <sentence id="40" ids_highlights="1">Executives should be measured and incentivized on a number of different dimensions -- only one of which would be shareholder value.</sentence>
      <sentence id="42" ids_highlights="3">Questions such as how this impacts on customers, suppliers, communities and employees all need to be equally valid topics of discussion in the new corporation.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>If you ask a class of aspiring managers in a business school for the purpose of the corporation, you get a remarkably rapid response.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The purpose of the corporation, they will tell you, is to maximize shareholder value.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>But like any simple answer, it is not only wrong, it is also profoundly damaging.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>To paraphrase Jack Welch, the legendary ex-CEO of GE, the idea that purpose of the corporation is to maximize shareholder value is &amp;quot;the dumbest idea in the world.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Corporations with a strict focus on maximizing shareholder value tend to employ a cadre of generalist managers who have relatively short-term commitment to the firm.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Because their compensation and future prospects are directly tied to share price, executives spend much of their time courting financial analysts.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>CEOs will often go to any lengths to keep this relatively small audience happy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>This means announcing all manner of initiatives which will boost the share price -- including mergers and acquisitions, restructuring, and downsizing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Usually these initiatives look good on paper, and therefore deliver a rapid boost to the company&amp;apost;s share price.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>However, actually delivering the value these initiatives promise is much more tricky.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The result is that up to 80% of these initiatives fail to deliver on their promises.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Meanwhile, the executives who started them years earlier have banked their bonus, sold their share options and moved on, often to start similar restructuring initiatives at another company.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The people left behind -- such as longer term shareholders and employees -- are left to pick up the pieces.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Many large corporations are remarkably resilient.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The people working for them are often able to get over failed initiative and get back to delivering the results which matter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>But this resilience can be rapidly eroded if the company -- driven by a relentless search for shareholder value -- goes through rounds of appointing heroic new CEOs who implement promising initiatives, create temporary share price boosts, then deliver disappointing or disastrous long-term results.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>When this happens repeatedly, a corporation can easily go into a death spiral.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Employees become bitter and cynical.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The best leave, while the worst stick around.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The quality of products and services suffer, and customers become dissatisfied.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The company diverts resources from innovation into providing immediate returns to shareholders.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>This can mean the company gets quickly overtaken by competitors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Over time, analysts begin to sniff the creeping signs of corporate decline and begin making more sell recommendations than buy ones.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The result is that the share price begins to decline.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Ever more change and turnaround efforts seem to add fuel to the fire.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Eventually the firm goes out of business, or is taken over.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>There are many groups who lose from this process.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Employees lose jobs, customers lose loved products and services, suppliers lose value customers, governments lose tax revenues and investors lose the value of their investment portfolio.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>One group who gains from this are the senior executives who keep moving between companies to get away from impending disasters and increase their pay packet.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The other group are many professionals who skim the transaction costs off the multiple restructuring efforts, change initiatives and other activities designed to increase shareholder value.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Pulling companies out of these death spirals is notoriously difficult, and senior executives&amp;apost; responses can make matters worse.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>They usually launch flashy initiatives designed to appeal to the markets, which ultimately fail to deliver value in the long term.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>But one of the biggest steps which we can take to avoid the fate of companies like the banks or Blackberry is to drop the myopic focus on maximizing shareholder value.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Instead, it is vital we recognize corporations have multiple goals -- such as creating fulfilling jobs, building up industry, satisfying consumers and delivering returns to shareholders.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The task of senior business leaders should be about balancing these multiple goals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>To ensure corporations drop their shareholder value myopia, there are some immediate practical steps that can be taken.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Corporate boards might include a range of representatives which goes beyond just shareholders.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>They might include employee, customer and community representatives.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Corporations should report not just their financial performance to shareholders, but also how they perform along other important metrics such as customer satisfaction, social and environmental benefits.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Executives should be measured and incentivized on a number of different dimensions -- only one of which would be shareholder value.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>The corporation itself needs to take active steps to repudiate a broad culture where share price is the only thing which matters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Questions such as how this impacts on customers, suppliers, communities and employees all need to be equally valid topics of discussion in the new corporation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>The most damaging practices designed to boost shareholder value in the short term, such as share buyback schemes, could be banned.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>These measures are likely to create an environment where plans are rigorously tested against different criteria before they are hastily rolled out.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>READ MORE:CNN&amp;apost;s complete coverage from Davos.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
