<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="53" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/05/03/business/ecb-rate-cut-monetary-policy/index.html" date_published="2013-05-03 14:54:42" category="business" author="Oliver Joy, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Euro recession deepens: So what can the ECB do now?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Speaking in Bratislava, Slovakia, ECB President Mario Draghi said the central bank is &amp;quot;ready to act if needed.&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12">Rahman said ECB may be reluctant to announce new support measures because it breeds political inertia.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="17">Greece, Spain are both suffering with unemployment above 27% while Italy struggling with high government debt.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 07:41:22" annotation_time="17.067">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">Speaking in Bratislava, Slovakia, ECB President Mario Draghi said the central bank is &amp;quot;ready to act if needed.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">Rahman added the ECB may be reluctant to announce new support measures because it breeds inertia among politicians looking to push through changes, such as a banking union, needed to bring Europe closer together.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="3">Greece and Spain are both suffering with unemployment above 27% while Italy is drowning in a government debt of almost 2 trillion euros ($2.6 trillion), according to Eurostat -- the European Commission&amp;apost;s data service.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Backed into a corner and desperate; That&amp;apost;s the view of some economists watching the European Central Bank&amp;apost;s latest attempts to curtail the euro bloc&amp;apost;s recession.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Thursday&amp;apost;s interest rate cut, designed to combat a three-year debt crisis, will not stimulate economic growth in the bloc, they say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Less than a year after the ECB President Mario Draghi buoyed the markets with his promise to do &amp;quot;whatever it takes&amp;quot; to keep the currency together, the central bank&amp;apost;s governors move has left some economists questioning whether the ECB has reached the limits of its power.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Speaking in Bratislava, Slovakia, ECB President Mario Draghi said the central bank is &amp;quot;ready to act if needed.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>But the Italian shied away from announcing any extraordinary policy measures such as another &amp;quot;big bazooka&amp;quot; to increase bank liquidity or the unlimited purchases of government debt -- known as OMTs -- for troubled eurozone nations that sparked controversy in September.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Joerg Rocholl, president of the European School of Management and Technology, told CNN that the rate cut is &amp;quot;a desperate move,&amp;quot; and means the ECB can avoid criticism that it is &amp;quot;overstretching its mandate.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Despite the ECB&amp;apost;s commitment to bankroll ailing eurozone nations who request a full sovereign bailout by buying up government bonds, it has so far resisted the temptation to implement aggressive monetary stimulus.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>That intransigence puts it at odds with many of its peers around the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The Bank of Japan, the Federal Reserve and the Bank of England have all embarked on a process of quantitative easing -- increasing the supply of money in the economy -- while also introducing other policies such as an unemployment benchmark and a funding for lending scheme, intended to encourage banks to loan to small businesses.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Mujtaba Rahman, head of research firm Eurasia Group&amp;apost;s Europe practice, said Draghi &amp;quot;exhausted&amp;quot; his political capital when he introduced the OMT program in September.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Italian and Spanish bonds, which had been been weighed down by market uncertainty, rebounded.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Rahman added the ECB may be reluctant to announce new support measures because it breeds inertia among politicians looking to push through changes, such as a banking union, needed to bring Europe closer together.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>He said: &amp;quot;The wind has gone out of the sails on banking union.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Once you announce intervention, you remove the incentive for countries to put the necessary structures in place.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>He told CNN that &amp;quot;shovelling money&amp;quot; to small businesses in peripheral Europe is the most likely next step for the ECB, but says the German elections and legality of the ECB&amp;apost;s current bond-purchasing program are obstacles to any extraordinary policy announcements in future.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>With the worst hit countries in Europe in a depression and unemployment rising, the ECB could be forced to take more action, in addition to the current measures, to prevent the crisis worsening.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Greece and Spain are both suffering with unemployment above 27% while Italy is drowning in a government debt of almost 2 trillion euros ($2.6 trillion), according to Eurostat -- the European Commission&amp;apost;s data service.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Joerg Kraemer, chief economist at Commerzbank -- Germany&amp;apost;s second-largest bank -- would expect the ECB to cut the deposit rate to negative territory before putting in place any other non-standard measures such as a loan scheme for small businesses.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>He said that the central bank is &amp;quot;in a corner&amp;quot; and has already exceeded its mandate significantly.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Peripheral countries must stop expecting the ECB to come up with solutions to problems that should be solved by governments, he added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are already seeing drastic action,&amp;quot; Kraemer told CNN, &amp;quot;the ECB has a very expansionary monetary policy, which I personally think, is too expansionary.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>He added: &amp;quot;This immediately puts the reform pressure off the peripheral countries and especially Italy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Without far reaching reforms you don&amp;apost;t solve the reasons and the causes for the sovereign debt crisis.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
