<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="5" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/10/08/business/quest-air-alliances/index.html" date_published="2012-10-08 16:50:05" category="business" author="Richard Quest, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Airlines of the gulf: Shaking up the skies</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">CNN&amp;apost;s Richard Quest says the carriers of the Persian Gulf are causing mischief again .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">They have eschewed airline alliances but are forces with which to be reckoned .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="39">Quest predicts changes including Air Berlin leaving oneworld.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="42">Throughout it all the Gulf carriers will continue doing ad hoc deals where necessary .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 11:30:52" annotation_time="837.893">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Trust the carriers of the Persian Gulf to cause mischief again.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">The reality is the three gulf carriers, Emirates, Qatar and Etihad are forces with which to be reckoned.</sentence>
      <sentence id="39" ids_highlights="3">I predict that Air Berlin will eventually leave oneworld and join Skyteam to tidy up its relationship.</sentence>
      <sentence id="42" ids_highlights="4">And throughout all of this the gulf carriers continue doing ad hoc deals where necessary (Emirates talking to American, for instance) and re-writing the rules.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Trust the carriers of the Persian Gulf to cause mischief again.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Having already destroyed the economics of the cosy international airline world, previously dominated by the European airlines, now the gulf carriers seem set to mess up the airline alliances too.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>All the major European airlines are now part of one of the three big alliances.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>There is Star (the biggest) based around Lufthansa and United Airlines; Skyteam based around Air France/KLM and Delta; Oneworld based around BA and American Airlines.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The gulf airlines have until now eschewed the alliances.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Firstly because competitively the alliances didn&amp;apost;t want them, and secondly because they were growing very nicely, thank you, without them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The reality is the three gulf carriers, Emirates, Qatar and Etihad are forces with which to be reckoned.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Strategic investments by co-operative governments have given them large fleets and huge airports.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>They have created a flourishing environment while established carriers languish.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Where London, Paris and Frankfurt were the traditional change-hubs, today Dubai, Doha and Abu Dhabi are perfectly placed at the crossroads of east and west.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>They are able to open up vast new markets in the Indian and Asian continent, as anyone who has been in those airports in the middle of the night can see.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Over the past year the gulf airlines have expanded their investments and routes and in doing so are slowly disrupting, some say destroying, the airline alliances.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>It is oneworld that is feeling the effects most.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>First, James Hogan&amp;apost;s Etihad bought an equity stake in Air Berlin, a oneworld member.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>That deal raised eyebrows but it is workable within the alliance.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Then, rival Tim Clark&amp;apost;s Emirates set up a 10-year partnership with Qantas -- another oneworld member -- which will clearly have major implications on relations with other alliance members such as BA and Cathay.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>But everyone put a brave face on it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Today Akbar Al Bakar&amp;apost;s Qatar Airways joins oneworld and comes within the fold.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>So, all three gulf carriers are now, in some shape or form, in bed with oneworld airlines.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>That would be confusing enough, but now another nail has been hammered into the alliance coffin.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Oneworld&amp;apost;s Air Berlin (and its paymaster Etihad) is entering a relationship with Air France/KLM, a member of Skyteam.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>And it&amp;apost;s not just a codeshare, but a long-standing strategic tie-up.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Hang on.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>How on earth can a oneworld Air Berlin do a strategic tie up with the leading carrier in a rival airline and keep its loyalty to oneworld?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Even allowing for the fact oneworld is a looser federation of airlines than Star, this is a nonsense.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The oneworld members are now either in bed with rival gulf carriers or hitched to rival alliance members in strategic partnerships.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>It beggars belief to think that oneworld can be more than a frequent flyer earn-and-burn alliance under those circumstances.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The one who has most right to be annoyed is Al Bakar at Qatar.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Once he is a full member he can rightly ask after the loyalties of Qantas and Air Berlin.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Are they to his airline as a oneworld member?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Or to Emirates and Etihad as their respective partners?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>We know the answer.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>It is a mess.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Clark at Emirates has always said the alliances&amp;apost; days are numbered.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>At this year&amp;apost;s IATA conference he sparked a lively debate with the view that the alliances were passed their sell by date because they couldn&amp;apost;t address the competitive demands of today&amp;apost;s market.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>He may be right.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>They were a creation of necessity because global airlines cannot legally consolidate.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>However, as we are now seeing, the gulf carriers are either joining the alliances (Qatar) picking them off one by one (Emirates) or simply creating split loyalties (Etihad).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>I predict that Air Berlin will eventually leave oneworld and join Skyteam to tidy up its relationship.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>I predict Qantas will slowly but surely drift away from oneworld but keep one foot in the camp because of its relationship with American Airlines and U.S. routes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>And I predict Star loses Brazil&amp;apost;s TAM to oneworld next year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>And throughout all of this the gulf carriers continue doing ad hoc deals where necessary (Emirates talking to American, for instance) and re-writing the rules.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>The point here is that the gulf carriers are in the left seat.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>They have the planes, the hubs, the connections and are opening up the new markets.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Now the alliances have to learn how to deal with it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>It won&amp;apost;t be pretty.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
