<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="16" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/02/22/business/bersani-elections-economy/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2013-02-22 11:52:51" category="business" author="Oliver Joy, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Can a Bersani-Monti coalition work for Italian economy?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="19, 18">Bersani wins he may be forced to form a coalition with incumbent PM Mario Monti.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="13">Center-left leader Bersani says he plans to make the property tax &amp;quot;more progressive&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="31">Berlusconi is using his showman charm to mount a comeback for his PDL party.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-17 10:55:32" annotation_time="14.161">
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="2">In an interview with CNN, Bersani says he plans to make the tax &amp;quot;more progressive&amp;quot; and focus on the owners of large properties if his party wins.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="1">If Bersani wins he may be forced to form a coalition.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="1">An alliance with the flamboyant center-right leader Silvio Berlusconi is unthinkable -- which leaves Monti the most likely candidate to support a Bersani-lead government.</sentence>
      <sentence id="31" ids_highlights="3">Berlusconi is using his showman charm to mount a comeback for his People of Freedom party and holds key regions in Veneto and Lombardy that could prove crucial, particularly in the battle for the Senate.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Italy&amp;apost;s electoral run-off between an ex-communist and a former cruise ship singer threatens to throw the country back into the spotlight of the European debt crisis.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The enigmatic leader of the center-left Democratic Party, Pier Luigi Bersani, goes head-to-head with scandal-laden former Prime Minister Silvio Berlusconi -- back from the political grave following his resignation in November 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Incumbent technocrat premier and eurozone darling Mario Monti, meanwhile, is lagging behind in the polls.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The cigar-chomping Bersani is favorite for Italy&amp;apost;s top job and proposes to steer the country&amp;apost;s battered economy through a debt crisis that is still plaguing the eurozone three years on.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Following six consecutive quarters of recession and with unemployment at 11.2%, Bersani is pursuing the euro area&amp;apost;s latest fad to revive Italy&amp;apost;s ailing economy; a pro-growth agenda.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Such policies are a stark contrast to Monti&amp;apost;s cocktail of cuts and taxes served up to woo policymakers in Brussels and Frankfurt.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Growth will be the &amp;quot;golden rule&amp;quot; to attract foreign investment, according to Democratic Party number two Enrico Letta.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>A similar sentiment was key in sweeping socialist French President Francois Hollande into the Elysee Palace in 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>But Letta stresses that Bersani will not follow Hollande&amp;apost;s lead by proposing a 75% income tax for the country&amp;apost;s wealthiest residents.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Speaking to CNN, Letta said: &amp;quot;It will be different, we already have a very high level of taxation...the main point is not to increase taxes.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Bersani -- who promises to stick to the outgoing government&amp;apost;s plans for pension and labor market reform -- will also keep Monti&amp;apost;s reviled property tax, known as IMU.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a policy that Berlusconi pledges to scrap if elected.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>In an interview with CNN, Bersani says he plans to make the tax &amp;quot;more progressive&amp;quot; and focus on the owners of large properties if his party wins.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>But for all Bersani&amp;apost;s talk of change, bond strategist Nicholas Spiro dismisses the 71-year-old as no reformer and says he is &amp;quot;not up to the task&amp;quot; of hauling the Italian economy out of a &amp;quot;knee deep&amp;quot; recession.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Spiro, managing director of Spiro Sovereign Strategy, says &amp;quot;Bersani could very well go for taxes on the rich, but Italy has a massive tax evasion and compliance problem, that could be difficult.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Can a political marriage survive?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Politics in Italy is complicated and outright victory for any party is unlikely.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>If Bersani wins he may be forced to form a coalition.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>An alliance with the flamboyant center-right leader Silvio Berlusconi is unthinkable -- which leaves Monti the most likely candidate to support a Bersani-lead government.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>But Monti is viewed with suspicion Bersani&amp;apost;s far-left partners, Left Ecology Freedom, who believe the technocrat would pull a left government too far to the economic right.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>If the parties can strike a deal Monti would be offered &amp;quot;an important role&amp;quot; to be discussed &amp;quot;Monday afternoon,&amp;quot; Letta told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>He refused to say if the technocrat would be appointed finance minister.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Monti, a former European Commissioner in financial services, wields the power to reassure European leaders that Italy is on the right track and can act as a counterbalance to a leftist government.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Bersani, by contrast, is a mystery on the international stage, according to Paola Subacchi, an economist at London-based think tank Chatham House.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;He is not known abroad and he doesn&amp;apost;t speak English... But his whole agenda is pro-Europe and pro-euro.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>A Bersani-Monti marriage is unlikely to be smooth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The two could clash over unpopular austerity measures implemented by Monti as part of a European agreement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Filippo Cavazzuti, former Italian senator and economist at the University of Bologna, believes Bersani will be forced to maintain Monti&amp;apost;s policies under the European fiscal compact.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>He said: &amp;quot;Otherwise Monti leaves [the coalition], the spread [on bond yields] rises and the credibility with the eurozone will immediately disappear.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>A coalition agreement is crucial to stifling a power-grab by Italy&amp;apost;s political bad boy, Berlusconi, is gaining on Bersani&amp;apost;s seemingly unassailable lead in the polls.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Berlusconi is using his showman charm to mount a comeback for his People of Freedom party and holds key regions in Veneto and Lombardy that could prove crucial, particularly in the battle for the Senate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The election will hand down a &amp;quot;damning verdict&amp;quot; to the policymakers of northern Europe that Italians are fed up with austerity, according to Spiro.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The electoral campaign, Spiro added, has been: &amp;quot;Very ugly, devoid of substance and purely based on personalities.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
