<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="89" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/10/16/business/china-luxury-superyachts/index.html" date_published="2012-10-17 03:53:07" category="business" author="Katie Hunt, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Made-in-China superyachts reflect changing tide of economy</title>
  <keywords>superyachts,china,luxury goods market,asian economy</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Chinese ship builder hopes to create super yacht brand.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="15">Yachts cost a third of international brands like Azimut and Sunseeker.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">Move reflects China&amp;apost;s changing industrial base.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="34">Yachting industry may be limited by taxes, regulation and lack of marinas.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-26 09:24:30" annotation_time="570.4377">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Armed with glossy sales catalogs and a shy swagger, Samuel Wong hopes to transform his family-run firm from a manufacturer of hum-drum fishing vessels and houseboats into a maker of sophisticated super yachts.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">Wong&amp;apost;s attempt to move upmarket is a reflection of China&amp;apost;s changing industrial base and the challenges many Chinese companies face as they try to move away from mass-produced goods to higher-value, branded products.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="2">Wong, who is based in Hong Kong, says that China&amp;apost;s cheaper labor costs are the main reason Accelera&amp;apost;s vessels cost a third of those produced by the likes of Sunseeker and Azimut .</sentence>
      <sentence id="34" ids_highlights="4">But he warned that yachting&amp;apost;s long-term development may be limited by steep taxes, onerous regulation and a lack of marinas.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Armed with glossy sales catalogs and a shy swagger, Samuel Wong hopes to transform his family-run firm from a manufacturer of hum-drum fishing vessels and houseboats into a maker of sophisticated super yachts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>His company makes up to six 86-foot and 98-foot yachts a year at its shipyard in Zhuhai, southern China, under its Accelera brand.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The name was coined by Wong because it &amp;quot;sounded Italian.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The company aims to compete in a marketplace currently dominated by European yacht makers like Azimut and Sunseeker and count billionaires among its clients.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;Li Ka-shing would never buy our brand but I hope in 10 years time he might consider it,&amp;quot; said Wong, 36, referring to Asia&amp;apost;s richest man, who is rumored to keep an 84-foot Italian-made Riva yacht at an exclusive Hong Kong marina.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Wong&amp;apost;s attempt to move upmarket is a reflection of China&amp;apost;s changing industrial base and the challenges many Chinese companies face as they try to move away from mass-produced goods to higher-value, branded products.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The company sold seven vessels to buyers in Hong Kong and China in the last financial year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>It remains to be seen whether the brand-conscious ranks of China&amp;apost;s newly affluent will embrace a home-grown yacht-builder with little pedigree - though a cheaper price tag may appeal as the country&amp;apost;s economic growth begins to slow.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>What&amp;apost;s more, Accelera and China&amp;apost;s other budding yacht makers such as IAG Yachts and Kingship, face stiff competition from European and U.S. rivals, who see China as a much-needed money spinner while their traditional markets struggle.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Located in a sleepy corner of the Pearl River Delta, the shipyard where Accelera&amp;apost;s yachts are produced is a world away from the luxury marinas where these rich man toys end up.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The drive from the nearest city passes through villages dotted with ponds filled with lotus flowers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Fishing nets and the odd fish hang to dry by the roadside.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The shipyard employs around 100 people and is run by Wong&amp;apost;s father and brother.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Workers are busy spray-painting a house-boat and crafting the interior of a three-storey, 86-foot yacht that will be delivered to a Hong Kong businessman by the end of the year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Wong, who is based in Hong Kong, says that China&amp;apost;s cheaper labor costs are the main reason Accelera&amp;apost;s vessels cost a third of those produced by the likes of Sunseeker and Azimut .</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Skilled workers at the shipyard earn, on average, 6,000 yuan ($957) a month but Wong says it can be difficult to find staff with the right experience.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The 98-foot yacht costs around $5 million and takes up to 15 months to build, while the 86-foot model costs around $1.2 million.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The workers, some wearing only plastic sandals, deftly make their way along narrow, five-meter high concrete platforms that divide the slipways and cranes that keep the vessels steady while they&amp;apost;re being built.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>At the center of the shed, which is littered with building materials, is a red shrine where apples, tea and incense have been made as offerings to a folk god for construction workers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>When I first came across Accelera&amp;apost;s yachts at a boat show in Hong Kong in May 2011, the vessels did not look out of place in the marina full of Italian and British-made yachts, but the interior smelt synthetic and compared poorly to the richly hued timber and buttery leather used by the European brands.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Wong says he has since employed Italian consultants to improve the yacht&amp;apost;s design both inside and out.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are focused on matching our customer&amp;apost;s preference,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>He says that many of his clients use the boats for business and entertaining -- a karaoke den is a common request.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Ryan Swift, editor of Asia-Pacific Boating magazine, says that Chinese yacht builders are a &amp;quot;mixed bag&amp;quot; but some, such as Kingship&amp;apost;s steel and aluminum hulled vessels, are beginning to gain recognition.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;Their products are at the lower end of the scale,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;At half the price or less of international names, you have to sacrifice in terms of quality.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Gordon Hui, the Asia managing director of UK yacht builder Sunseeker, said Chinese yacht builders are credible competitors, especially for smaller, family boats.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>However, he said they are yet to mount a serious challenge in the corporate market where premium brands are most coveted.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Read: Inside the mind of a yacht cartoonist.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Other Chinese companies are taking a different approach to grass-roots brands like Accelera, opting instead to scoop up foreign yacht brands as a shortcut to global success.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Earlier this year, Shandong Heavy Industry Group, best known for its bulldozers, took a 75% stake in luxury Italian yacht maker Ferretti, which also makes Riva and Pershing yachts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>It plans to open an assembly plant in Qingdao, a major port in northern China and the site of the 2008 Olympic sailing regatta, to customize yachts for China&amp;apost;s market.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Swift says that European brands like Azimut and Sunseeker have &amp;quot;made a killing&amp;quot; in China as the country&amp;apost;s elite discovers the pleasures of messing about on boats.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>But he warned that yachting&amp;apost;s long-term development may be limited by steep taxes, onerous regulation and a lack of marinas.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>For Wong and his Accelera yachts, the next step is to build a larger shipyard, with state-of-the-art facilities, that would allow for up to 15 yachts to be made a year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Currently, electronics and other finishing touches are installed in Hong Kong, which means the yachts incur customs duties for Chinese buyers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>But with China&amp;apost;s economy experiencing its slowest growth in more than a decade, Wong is concentrating on promoting his brand:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;The biggest difficulty, we think, is to convince customers to spend their money on yachts that have been manufactured in China.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
