<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="143" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/02/07/business/opinion-beatles-coudnt-happen-today/index.html" date_published="2014-02-07 14:11:08" category="business" author="Andre Millard, Historian, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Why the Beatles couldn&amp;apost;t happen in today&amp;apost;s digital age</title>
  <keywords>Beatles,Ringo Starr,Paul McCartney ,John Lennon,George Harrison,technology,beatlemania</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="13">Historian Andre Millard says nobody will be able to recreate the excitement of Beatlemania.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="13">The fractured digital world makes it impossible to completely command the media as the Beatles did back in 1964.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="15">Beatlemania&amp;apost;s anniversary might be the time to mark an end of the era, when records were something you treasure, he says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-14 15:35:29" annotation_time="32.729336">
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="1, 2">In the fractured and endlessly expanding digital world, nobody will be able to recreate the excitement of Beatlemania because it is no longer possible to completely command the media as the Beatles did back in 1964.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="3">Beatlemania&amp;apost;s anniversary might be the time to mark an end of that era, when records were something you treasured.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Fifty years ago this weekend, a four-piece guitar band from Liverpool touched down at Kennedy airport in New York and changed the course of popular culture in the twentieth century.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>That much we can be sure of, and since the days of Beatlemania that guitar band has been credited with changing music, fashion, culture and everything else that really counted in the sixties.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The trans-Atlantic entertainment industry is gearing up for an avalanche of tributes and events to commemorate this anniversary.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The dyspeptic rock critic Lester Bangs once railed against the never-ending re-release of the Beatles catalog by asking: &amp;quot;I&amp;apost;d like to know what I have missed by not missing the Beatles.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The answer over the next few weeks is plenty: concerts, exhibits, panel discussions, documentaries, conferences and a pre-recorded Grammy tribute featuring a &amp;quot;reunion&amp;quot; of Paul and Ringo.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>For that generation lucky enough to be swept along by Beatlemania, it was a unique event, a turning point for some.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>There are still plenty of Americans of a certain age who can tell you exactly what happened when they first saw the Beatles on The Ed Sullivan Show that chilly February night: &amp;quot;I was two inches from the screen, screaming.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The run-up to this anniversary feels a little like the preparations for the Beatles arrival in 1964, when there was a continual stream of tidbits, teasers and promotions which announced &amp;quot;The Beatles are Coming!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>But instead of radio bulletins, high-school gossip, and those flyers that Capitol records distributed to record stores nationwide, this time the news comes to us on mobile phones and lap tops, in web casts and posts on the internet.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>If you miss the rebroadcast of the Ed Sullivan show this weekend you can easily retrieve it from numerous sites on the world wide web, but back in 1964 you had to wait a whole week for the next Ed Sullivan Show.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>This of course added to the tension and increased the expectation of another television event which could not be missed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>If a note of self-congratulation enters into the celebrations, you can hardly blame the record and television companies for waxing nostalgic for a time when Americans were locked into watching three channels and still buying records.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>In the fractured and endlessly expanding digital world, nobody will be able to recreate the excitement of Beatlemania because it is no longer possible to completely command the media as the Beatles did back in 1964.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The triumph of Beatlemania was essentially a triumph of the record -- the seven inch vinyl disc -- and a demonstration of its potency in diffusing culture and creating value.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Beatlemania&amp;apost;s anniversary might be the time to mark an end of that era, when records were something you treasured.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>In the digital world sound recordings are cheap and disposable; you won&amp;apost;t be able to relive the giddy excitement of returning home with that priceless copy of &amp;quot;I Want to Hold Your Hand&amp;quot; with an MP3 download.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The anniversary of Beatlemania will doubtless see more praise heaped on the musicians and their timeless music.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>But who were the architects of Beatlemania?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Brian Epstein planned the campaign, perfected the look and made the deals (some strokes of genius, others not).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Above all he saw the American market as the pinnacle of success: &amp;quot;We knew that America would make us or break us as world stars...In fact, she made us.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>How ironic that what began as an exercise in American exceptionalism ended in a &amp;quot;British Invasion&amp;quot; of imported music, fashion and design that swept all before it and made the sixties look and sound like the sixties.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Beatlemania marked the ascendancy of British-based television producers who created a new type of music program -- live, frenetic, engaging -- and made the Beatles its most able practitioners.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Beatlemania was powered by radio: not crystal-clear broadcasts from corporate headquarters but crackling, crummy AM, with crazed disc jockeys like Murray the K providing a running commentary of Beatlemania and whipping the fans into a frenzy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Those tiny transistor radios that the girls carried with them connected them to a larger community of Beatle lovers, a radio family who dressed alike, thought alike and shared the same obsession.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Fifty years on that community sees Beatlemania as a special moment in time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>There was an air of expectation in the crowd awaiting the Beatles at Kennedy: &amp;quot;At the airport you could really feel that something was happening...you felt like this was the beginning of the earthquake.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>And it was.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The Beatles touched teenagers like no other band before or after, lifting their fans&amp;apost; gaze above the buying and selling of a commodity to an aura of hope and a state of transcendence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>In 1964 music could change your life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The Beatles proved it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
