<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="153" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/05/09/business/world-trade-organization-defterios-analysis/index.html?iref=allsearch" date_published="2013-05-09 14:59:26" category="business" author="John Defterios, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>WTO: Emerging markets get the nod</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Brazil&amp;apost;s Roberto Azevedo took the flag after voting becoming its first ever Director General from South America.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="25">Defterios: Brazil is a prime example of how a lack of reforms has undermined the economy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">As the new DG, Azevedo did not overplay the significance of what his backing meant, writes Defterios.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-17 12:11:10" annotation_time="19.891499">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">Brazil&amp;apost;s Roberto Azevedo took the flag after voting from the 159 members of the World Trade Organisation, becoming its first ever Director General from South America.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">As the new DG, Azevedo did not overplay the significance of what his backing meant.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="2">Brazil is a prime example of how a lack of reforms has undermined the economy.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>It did not happen when the top job opened up at the International Monetary Fund: Christine Lagarde of France won out over candidates such as Mexico&amp;apost;s Central Bank Governor Agustin Carstens, who put up a good fight.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>It did not happen at the World Bank either: Washington leaned on the members of the developed world to back their man Jim Yong Kim, the former president of Dartmouth College.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>But the third time was the charm for those in emerging markets to finally run a post-World War II institution in modern times.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Brazil&amp;apost;s Roberto Azevedo took the flag after voting from the 159 members of the World Trade Organisation, becoming its first ever Director General from South America.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>He outpolled Herminio Blanco of Mexico -- another highly experienced trade veteran -- who had the backing of other NAFTA members the United States and Canada.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>As the new DG, Azevedo did not overplay the significance of what his backing meant.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>But in his first television interview since securing the job he acknowledged the shift to the emerging markets.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is important to have the developing world and the emerging economies being participants, active participants even in a leadership role as well,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Not surprisingly he came out of the starting gate in the role saying that resuscitating the Doha Round of free trade talks is priority number one.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have a very large trade agenda to push forward, but we can&amp;apost;t because we are paralyzed,&amp;quot; said the veteran trade negotiator, who noted that the rules governing the WTO are outdated.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The job will not be easy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>For his predecessor, Pascal Lamy, the term was a frustrating one.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>In the midst of the worst financial crisis in a generation, free trade slipped right off the global agenda.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Some would contend the crisis reignited protectionist tendencies, especially in emerging markets.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>According to the World Bank, Argentina topped the list of countries that filed the most measures to guard certain sectors and products from competition.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>It was joined by the BRIC countries and the U.S., rounding out the top six places.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Azevedo will have to take a nuanced approach to navigate demands at home in Brazil and at the same time chart a new course to build a consensus.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Brazil&amp;apost;s President Dilma Rousseff raised the tenor of the protectionist debate when she accused Washington of driving down the value of the U.S. dollar to the detriment of developing countries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The new Director General suggested in our interview that the topic of currency fluctuations could also be included in the WTO&amp;apost;s agenda, even if other institutions such as the IMF keep it on theirs as well.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am optimistic that the organisation can look at these very important issues that are a big part of today&amp;apost;s business world,&amp;quot; he said, adding that the WTO needs to avoid a &amp;quot;disconnect&amp;quot; between business and the multi-lateral trading system.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>To get the Doha Round moving forward as opposed to sitting in neutral where it has been for years, top trade officials told me emerging economies need to embrace market opening measures.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Their resistance to change is what allowed them to stumble badly in the past two years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Azevedo said it is important to move forward: &amp;quot;We cannot look backwards.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>What we have to do is raise our heads, look forward, roll up our sleeves and work.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Brazil is a prime example of how a lack of reforms has undermined the economy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>After growing seven and a half percent in 2010, the vast emerging market just managed to grow less than one percent last year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>That may be Roberto Azevedo&amp;apost;s prime argument to revive free trade.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Now he has to get at home and in other emerging markets to embrace that concept as well.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
