<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="275" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/12/28/health/cochlear-implants" date_published="2012-12-28 16:19:22" category="health" author="Saundra Young, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Hope for hearing: Cochlear implants</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="18">Cochlear implants are electronic hearing devices.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="22">An implant does not restore normal hearing and is very different from a hearing aid.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="42">About 210,000 children and adults around the world have received these implants.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-04 10:22:11" annotation_time="22.648666">
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="1">Cochlear implants are electronic hearing devices for people with profound deafness or severe hearing loss who get no benefit from a hearing aid.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="2">An implant does not restore normal hearing and is very different from a hearing aid.</sentence>
      <sentence id="42" ids_highlights="3">It&amp;apost;s unknown how many elderly patients get a cochlear implant, but according to NIH, about 210,000 children and adults around the world have received these implants.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Six years ago Hope Koch&amp;apost;s life began to change dramatically.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>A pianist since the age of 5, she knew something was wrong when listening to music became difficult.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s when the 70-year-old wife and mother of three clearly remembers her hearing loss began.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;That&amp;apost;s the first thing that got all jumbled.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>I couldn&amp;apost;t understand it anymore and then I couldn&amp;apost;t understand my children, my adult children and then the grandchildren came along and I missed out what they were saying.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>At first she didn&amp;apost;t tell anyone, not even her husband Frank.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>She pretended nothing was wrong.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>But soon she could no longer understand movies, and needed closed captioning.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>She lost her confidence and began to shy away from people because she couldn&amp;apost;t understand them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Eventually she stopped answering the phone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;I felt like I was putting them to a lot of trouble to have to repeat and repeat,&amp;quot; Koch said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;All of the things that you enjoyed doing, you shied away from.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Koch saw an audiologist and was fitted for hearing aids.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>They helped, for a while.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>But the hearing loss continued.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>At the end of last year, her audiologist presented her with one final option.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Since the hearing aids couldn&amp;apost;t help her any more, he suggested she consider a cochlear implant.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Cochlear implants are electronic hearing devices for people with profound deafness or severe hearing loss who get no benefit from a hearing aid.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>There is an external part that is worn behind the ear with a microphone that picks up sounds from the environment, a speech processor and a transmitter that gets signals from the processor and turns them into electric impulses.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>It is attached to a receiver and electrode system which is surgically implanted into the inner ear.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s typically done as an outpatient procedure.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>An implant does not restore normal hearing and is very different from a hearing aid.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Hearing aids amplify sound so that damaged ears can hear them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Implants bypass the damage and directly stimulate the auditory nerve which then sends the signals to the brain.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Koch had the surgery at the University of Maryland Medical Center in Baltimore in September.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;It was easy, comfortable, the recovery was good.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>I mean I&amp;apost;m very pleased with it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>I had no negative effects from the surgery, no pain.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>CNN was there when her implant was activated for the very first time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>A range of emotions crossed her face -- then came tears.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;I thought maybe I&amp;apost;ll be disappointed today, maybe it won&amp;apost;t work for me,&amp;quot; Koch said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;I was straining to hear something, anything and when I could hear something in this ear that has been without any sound for years, it was overwhelming that way, and then to hear my voice, I&amp;apost;m listening to it talking and it&amp;apost;s just so, it&amp;apost;s just wonderful.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Koch&amp;apost;s husband Frank has high expectations for this implant.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;That we can go back to the normal way we use to be and spend the rest of our years that way.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Our expectations, 12 weeks from now or 12 months from now is she&amp;apost;s going to be totally normal and that&amp;apost;s what we&amp;apost;re hoping and that&amp;apost;s where she&amp;apost;s going to go.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Koch is sure of it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;The quality of life is gonna be so good now, it&amp;apost;ll be good again.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Dr. Ronna Hertzano, assistant professor at UMMC, did Koch&amp;apost;s surgery.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>She says over the last few years, more and more seniors are choosing cochlear implants to combat their hearing loss.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>In fact the oldest person she performed the surgery on was in his late 80s.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>She even knows of cases involving folks in their 90s.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s unknown how many elderly patients get a cochlear implant, but according to NIH, about 210,000 children and adults around the world have received these implants.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>According to the FDA, in the United States roughly 42,600 adults and 28,400 children have received them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;It seems that more senior individuals are aware that there are alternatives to hearing aids, and once the hearing aids are not sufficient, they can improve their hearing and almost regain most of their hearing ability at least when it comes to speech, with a cochlear implant,&amp;quot; Hertzano told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>&amp;quot;We used to do older individuals just maybe once or twice a year, and now I would say that we do older individuals maybe every month.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>At UMCC, surgeons perform about 50 procedures a year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Hertzano, an expert on the devices, has done about 100 implant surgeries.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>She says anyone who has hearing aids, but cannot understand at least 50% of sentences spoken in normal conversation is a good candidate.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Once implanted, she says, many implantees can understand up to 90% of sentences.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>When Hertzano met Koch she could only understand 20% of sentences in a conversation and was using visual cues.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>Hertzano says age is not a factor in the surgery, but the candidate must be healthy enough to undergo surgery with general anesthesia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>And they can&amp;apost;t have dementia, which could make it difficult to adapt to learning to understand speech with a cochlear implant.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>According to The American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, it&amp;apost;s rare that a patient does not benefit from a cochlear implant.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>But the procedure can be pricey.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>The total cost, they say, can be as much as $100,000 for the evaluation, surgery, the device itself and the rehabilitation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>However, most insurance companies and Medicare will cover that cost according to AAO-HNS.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>For Koch, it was all worth it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>She says she&amp;apost;s hearing much better again, but at the same time acknowledges she still has a way to go.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="59">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s been a learning experience.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="60">
          <content>This is going to take at least a year or longer.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="61">
          <content>It gets down to your brain retraining itself.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="62">
          <content>This year, the holiday season was extra special -- she heard her family&amp;apost;s voices for the first time in years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="63">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s wonderful to hear them speak.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="64">
          <content>It was fantastic, the best Thanksgiving/Christmas that I&amp;apost;ve had in a number of years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="65">
          <content>My sons, they have low voices, but I can hear them now.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="66">
          <content>I&amp;apost;m understanding everything better.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="67">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s just a world of difference.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
