<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="174" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/08/09/health/kerner-too-tired-sex/index.html" date_published="2012-08-09 11:15:29" category="health" author="Ian Kerner, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Are you too tired for sex?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Study: 1 in 4 Americans say they&amp;apost;re often too tired for sex.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="11, 9">It&amp;apost;s possible that boredom or a low sex drive are to blame.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="31">A regular sleep schedule or making a date with your partner can help.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-12 12:11:29" annotation_time="137.15933">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">According to a recent study by the National Sleep Foundation, about one in every four married or cohabitating Americans claim they&amp;apost;re so sleep-deprived that they&amp;apost;re often too tired to have sex.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;Boredom could be to blame,&amp;quot; Levine says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="2">Also likely: a low sex drive.</sentence>
      <sentence id="31" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;Make your arousal pattern work with your schedule and that of your partner so you can enjoy physical intimacy.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>According to a recent study by the National Sleep Foundation, about one in every four married or cohabitating Americans claim they&amp;apost;re so sleep-deprived that they&amp;apost;re often too tired to have sex.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s not surprising why sleep trumps sex: Between work, family and social obligations, our need for shuteye often suffers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Add in problems such as financial stress, health issues and relationship woes, and you can see why sex tends to drop to the bottom of our &amp;quot;to do&amp;quot; list -- if it&amp;apost;s on there at all.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>And when we do finally hit the sheets, many of us are more apt to hold onto our smart phone, tablet or other gadget than our partner&amp;apost;s hand.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;Many of us are multitasking throughout the day for extended periods of time -- constant stimulation that can allow for enriching experiences,&amp;quot; says Amy Levine, sex coach and founder of Ignite Your Pleasure.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;However, that can also take its toll on our sex lives.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>In some cases, though, simple exhaustion isn&amp;apost;t the only reason why sex takes a backseat to sleep.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Unless you&amp;apost;ve been diagnosed with a health condition that saps energy, such as chronic fatigue syndrome, it&amp;apost;s possible that factors other than a busy lifestyle are at play.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;Boredom could be to blame,&amp;quot; Levine says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;If you think or feel sex is going to be status quo, it will feel like a chore rather than something that&amp;apost;s satisfying.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Also likely: a low sex drive.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>According to a 2008 study published in the Archives of Internal Medicine, between one-third and one-half of all women will find themselves coping with low sexual desire at some point in their lives.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>And while we&amp;apost;re lacking such strong statistics for men, I and many other experts believe that low libido is increasingly becoming a problem for guys, too.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Although any number of factors could be to blame for these dips in desire, many of the same triggers that make us exhausted -- like stress, anxiety, worry -- are also linked to decreased desire in both men and women.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Some people may confuse a low libido with being too tired for sex; for others, exhaustion itself seems to trigger a lower sex drive.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;A lot of women are satisfied with their relationships and enjoy sex once it&amp;apost;s under way but are just too tired and stressed to feel sexual desire,&amp;quot; explains Laurie Mintz, a University of Florida professor of psychology and the author of &amp;quot;A Tired Woman&amp;apost;s Guide to Passionate Sex.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The book was shown in a published study of 45 women to significantly increase sexual desire, arousal, satisfaction and overall sexual functioning in those who followed the book&amp;apost;s program.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Fortunately, there&amp;apost;s much you can do to create both the time and energy to make sex a regular part of your routine again.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Try these steps to get back on track:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Get on a regular sleep schedule.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s the end of a long day, the kids are finally in bed, and all you and your partner want to do is -- well, veg out in front of the TV, or putter around on the Internet, or play a few rounds of Words with Friends.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Says Patty Brisben, educator and founder of PureRomance.com, &amp;quot;The average American spends 2.7 hours a day watching TV, according to the American Time Use Survey.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>So you have to ask yourself which is more important to you: your relationship or American Idol?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Try to stick to a regular bedtime, and devote the last hour or so of your waking time to your partner.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Even if you do nothing more than cuddle, you&amp;apost;re setting a schedule that allows time for more when you&amp;apost;re ready.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Eventually, your mood will follow.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Think outside the box.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s easy to say, &amp;quot;Let&amp;apost;s have sex tonight,&amp;quot; early in the day when your energy is still high.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Yet most of us wait until nighttime to get intimate, and by then we&amp;apost;re often too tired to make a move.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;Some people are more aroused during the day than at night,&amp;quot; Levine says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;Make your arousal pattern work with your schedule and that of your partner so you can enjoy physical intimacy.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>That might mean indulging in morning sex before work or a lunchtime quickie -- whatever works for you.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Make a date.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Think scheduled sex is boring?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Not necessarily.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>There&amp;apost;s a common assumption that spontaneous sex is best, but &amp;quot;planned encounters help build anticipation and relieve tension within your relationship,&amp;quot; Mintz says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Get a sitter and head out for date night, play hooky from work, or make time for sex when the kids are at a friend&amp;apost;s house, for example.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Adds Brisben, &amp;quot;Scheduling sex is great for someone who loves to make a &amp;apost;to-do&amp;apost; list.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>You know you&amp;apost;re not going to sleep until that box is checked off.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Plus, it&amp;apost;ll establish a pattern of healthy sexual behavior.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>They say it takes 21 days to form a habit.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Once that habit is formed, you won&amp;apost;t want to go to sleep unless you&amp;apost;ve had sex.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Just do it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>It can be tough to feel aroused when all you want to do it sleep.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>But stick with it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Like other forms of exercise, &amp;quot;sex can give you an energetic buzz,&amp;quot; Levine says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>&amp;quot;You just have to be willing to push past the feeling of tiredness to experience the pleasure that will ultimately recharge you.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>&amp;quot;If you shift your schedule so you get enough sleep and reprioritize your day to the essentials,&amp;quot; Levine says, &amp;quot;being tired doesn&amp;apost;t have to be a factor that influences your sex life.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>And remember, sex begets sex.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Once you get back into the swing of things, you&amp;apost;re likely to start wanting to get -- and stay -- intimate more often.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>When you wake up and smell the coffee, it will smell all the better for having had sex the night before.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
