<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="274" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/07/07/health/hookah-teen-popularity/index.html" date_published="2014-07-07 15:30:36" category="health" author="Dr. Chethan Sathya, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Hookah gains popularity: Nearly 1 in 5 teens have tried</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">Study: 18% of high school seniors have tried hookah.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">With hookah, water pipes burn charcoal, which heats up tobacco and produces smoke.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="24">Experts say hookah can be just as dangerous as smoking cigarettes.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-04 10:21:43" annotation_time="30.906336">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">A new study published Monday in the journal Pediatrics finds about 18% of high school seniors have tried hookah.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">Waterpipes burn charcoal, which then heats up tobacco and produces smoke.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="3">But experts say hookah can be just as dangerous as smoking cigarettes.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The United States may be winning the war on cigarettes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>After decades of public service announcements about the dangers of smoking, fewer teens are lighting up.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>But if you ask young Americans about smoking tobacco through a hookah, also called a waterpipe or shisha, there&amp;apost;s a good chance you won&amp;apost;t find the same level of awareness.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;ve smoked hookah since college, and I can tell you, most of my friends think it&amp;apost;s safer than cigarettes,&amp;quot; said Bruce Kafil, an avid hookah smoker and the owner of Lotus hookah lounge in Los Angeles.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>A new study published Monday in the journal Pediatrics finds about 18% of high school seniors have tried hookah.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Researchers used survey data taken between 2010 and 2012 from 5,540 high school seniors around the country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>They found that teens of higher socioeconomic status -- those who had a weekly income or whose parents were well-educated -- were more likely to be hookah smokers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Hookah originated in the Persian Empire in the 16th century.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Waterpipes burn charcoal, which then heats up tobacco and produces smoke.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The fumes are cooled by bubbling through a water-filled chamber before being inhaled.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Hookah smokers traditionally use tobacco without added flavoring.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>But mixing tobacco with flavors like green apple, coconut and even bubble gum is now all the rage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Appealing flavors mask the harsh nature of hookah tobacco and attract younger smokers, says Dr. Vinayak Prasad, senior adviser for the World Health Organization&amp;apost;s Tobacco-Free Initiative.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Kafil says there&amp;apost;s a &amp;quot;cool&amp;quot; factor to hookah, and the fruit-scented smoke makes it hard to fathom dangerous consequences.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;I don&amp;apost;t smoke cigarettes because I can&amp;apost;t handle the terrible smell,&amp;quot; Kafil said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;Hookah smoke is pleasant.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Even the parents of college students who smoke (at the Lotus hookah lounge) are surprised at how nice it smells.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The CDC says the drop in cigarette use is being offset by other forms of tobacco, including hookah, e-cigarettes and smokeless tobacco products.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Between 2011 and 2012, hookah use rose from 4.1% to 5.4% among high school students, according to the CDC.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Even middle school students are joining in; a 2013 CDC report says 1.3% of middle schoolers reported recent hookah use.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>And studies show around 40% of American college students have tried hookah.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Hookah is a great way to socialize because several friends can share one pipe for hours, says Kafil.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;When I was in college, smoking at hookah lounges was a great option since none of my friends or I could drink at bars,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>But experts say hookah can be just as dangerous as smoking cigarettes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Burning charcoal and tobacco means the smoke contains high levels of metals, carbon monoxide and cancer-causing chemicals, says Dr. Norman Edelman, senior medical adviser for the American Lung Association.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Hookah users may be exposed to even higher concentrations of toxins than cigarette users -- because they inhale more deeply, puff more often, and tend to smoke for longer periods of time, according to the CDC.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>A typical hookah session lasts an hour and involves 200 puffs, while an average cigarette is only 20 puffs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Hookah users are exposed to significant amounts of addictive nicotine and cancer-causing toxins after just a single smoking session, according to a study published in the journal Cancer Epidemiology, Biomarkers, &amp;amp; Prevention in June.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>That study was the first of its kind to measure toxin levels in people smoking at hookah bars, rather than in an artificial environment like a laboratory, says Dr. Gideon St. Helen, lead author of the study and a researcher at the Center for Tobacco Control Research and Education at the University of California, San Francisco.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Researchers measured levels of toxic substances in urine samples from hookah users before and after they smoked in hookah bars.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The average time spent smoking a hookah was just over an hour for most participants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;There was a 73-fold increase in nicotine levels and a substantial increase in cancer-causing compounds in the urine immediately after smoking,&amp;quot; St. Helen said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>In the United States, hookah bars are flourishing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>In 2007, maybe 300 hookah bars were in business.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Today, searching &amp;quot;hookah bar&amp;quot; on Yelp will yield you nearly 400 hits in Los Angeles, 500 in New York, and even 17 in Louisville, Kentucky.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Despite anti-smoking legislation in more than 35 states, hookah bars continue to thrive because of loopholes and laws that exempt or don&amp;apost;t specifically address waterpipes, says Thomas Carr, the director of national policy for the American Lung Association.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Three-fourths of 100 U.S. major cities have laws banning cigarette smoking in bars -- but nearly 90% have loopholes that make it easy for hookah lounges to set up shop, according to a study published in the American Journal of Public Health in September 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Some areas in the United States, like San Francisco, have curbed the practice.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Roughly 73 municipalities and some states across the country have specifically banned hookah, says Bronson Frick, associate director of Americans for Nonsmokers&amp;apost; Rights.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The FDA also proposed new rules in April that would allow the agency to regulate the manufacturing and marketing of hookah and other tobacco products.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
