<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="296" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/07/04/health/mental-health/awaken-brain-manage/index.html" date_published="2012-07-04 12:00:49" category="health" author="Charlotte Tomaino, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Manage your brain -- it&amp;apost;s your most important asset</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="12">&amp;apost;Neurochoices&amp;apost; are your options for brain change by choice.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="31">The brain loves a question and will search for the answer if you provide the focus.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="21">Automatic behavior is developed or changed by the neurochoices we make.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2015-01-16 18:57:43" annotation_time="27.094501">
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="1">Neurochoices are your options for brain change by choice, because you know enough about your brain and care enough to make choices to focus it in healthy, growth-producing ways.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="3">The brain is trained by our choices, and automatic behavior is developed or changed by the neurochoices we make.</sentence>
      <sentence id="31" ids_highlights="2">The brain loves a question and will search for the answer if you provide the focus.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>What does it mean to manage your own brain?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The field of neuropsychology -- the applied form of neuroscience -- is now offering an emerging consciousness about the brain&amp;apost;s inner workings.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>As with everything, it is when we know how the brain works that we can have something to say about how to work it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>In my new book, &amp;quot;Awakening the Brain,&amp;quot; I discuss the possibility of managing the brain and the questions of how to do it, and why we should want to.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The billions of neurons and the trillions of connections between them in each of our brains keep changing with every experience, even when we sleep.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>We are in a state of constant change that can happen by choice or will happen by chance.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>We are evolving in every moment with the chemistry of each sound, sight, thought and emotion that passes through the brain.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>As you begin to understand the dynamic nature of you and the movement of chemistry that never ceases, you glimpse the importance of being conscious and making choices.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Change is inevitable.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The only question is whether you are going to have something to say about it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>As neuroscience has revealed the functions of those inner structures in our heads that create who we are, the capacity for making a &amp;quot;neurochoice&amp;quot; is now available.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Neurochoices are your options for brain change by choice, because you know enough about your brain and care enough to make choices to focus it in healthy, growth-producing ways.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>A key concept that reveals your power of influence comes from Canadian psychologist Donald Hebb, who said, &amp;quot;the neurons that fire together, wire together.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>This is the neuroscience version of &amp;quot;practice makes perfect.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Anything you do repetitively will activate the neurons in your brain, which makes the action more likely to be repeated in the future.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Neuroplasticity, the adaptability of the brain, is operating at all times.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>You can have neuroplasticity working for you if you target your outcome, or it can work against you if you allow yourself to just react.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The downside of neuroplasticity is evident in the insidious nature of addictions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Habits that control us start subtly, sneaking up until they take over.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The first drink to relieve stress can lead to a need for two drinks to be able to relax.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The brain is trained by our choices, and automatic behavior is developed or changed by the neurochoices we make.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>However, there are many examples of the upside of neuroplasticity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Engaging in new behaviors to enhance our health like regular exercise will lead to improved muscle tone, cardiac function, stronger bones, better respiratory function, more balanced emotions and calmer nerves, greater mental clarity and a better night&amp;apost;s sleep.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Once you start an exercise program, you will notice that after a while, you just feel better on a regular basis and feel worse when you miss a day.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Just getting into the habit of regular exercise is a neurochoice that will improve your health and quality of life.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>You can manage your brain in times of stress as well.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>There are three easy steps to keep your balance and stay in touch with your best self to achieve your best outcome.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Shift your focus.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>As tension mounts and you notice a problem looming large in your mind, shift your focus from a reactive position about the conflict to a focus on the solution.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Ask a question like: How would you like this to work out?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The brain loves a question and will search for the answer if you provide the focus.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>All thoughts produced will then follow a different path if you are seeking an answer to your question.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Breathe, breathe, breathe.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>As you breathe in and out at a consistent pace, you will notice your heart rate slowing, regulated to a calmer and more even state.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>As the heart automatically speeds up under stress, it affects the nervous system and hyperfocuses you on reacting to the problem rather than thinking through the solution.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Make a conscious choice.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Relax your muscles, which spontaneously tense up in the face of conflict or danger.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>In the &amp;quot;fight or flight response,&amp;quot; your body is ready to keep you safe but is often overreacting to events that can be better resolved from a more relaxed state.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>There is greater creativity and more access to your intelligence in ease.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Remember, you invent your own life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>The more aware you are of the outcomes you are creating, the more you can achieve the life you want.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Stay smart in life by managing your own brain.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
