<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="375" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/12/14/health/school-shooting-trauma/index.html" date_published="2012-12-14 20:23:20" category="health" author="Elizabeth Landau, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Support crucial for kids after trauma</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Children need to be with their families as quickly as possible after exposure to tragedy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">Getting back to routines and having proper support enables children to do well.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="14">Kids who were already having issues at home may be more severely affected.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-26 11:09:51" annotation_time="67.98">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Children need to be with their families as quickly as possible after exposure to such horrific events, said Steven Marans, director of the National Center for Children Exposed to Violence/Childhood Violent Trauma Center at Yale University&amp;apost;s Child Study Center.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">If children can get back into their normal routines and get proper support, he said, they will do well.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="3">In addition, &amp;quot;Kids who are having difficult lives before the event are the ones most likely to have issues,&amp;quot; Garbarino said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>School shootings such as the one at Sandy Hook Elementary in Newtown, Connecticut, may have long-lasting consequences, but with proper support, many children are able to move on, experts say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Children need to be with their families as quickly as possible after exposure to such horrific events, said Steven Marans, director of the National Center for Children Exposed to Violence/Childhood Violent Trauma Center at Yale University&amp;apost;s Child Study Center.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Marans and colleagues are making themselves available to Connecticut officials, including the governor&amp;apost;s office and state police.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The good news is that most kids do bounce back from a single incident of trauma, said James Garbarino, professor of psychology at Loyola University Chicago and author of &amp;quot;Lost Boys: Why Our Sons Turn Violent and How We Can Save Them.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>If children can get back into their normal routines and get proper support, he said, they will do well.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Declan Procaccini, father of a third-grade student at Sandy Hook, told CNN&amp;apost;s Wolf Blitzer his daughter was in a reading class on Friday when she and a teacher &amp;quot;heard bangs.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The teacher locked his daughter and another teacher in a bathroom until police escorted them out through a messy scene.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;I don&amp;apost;t know if my daughter&amp;apost;s in shock or not, but from what she told me she saw, she&amp;apost;s doing incredibly well,&amp;quot; Procaccini said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Procaccini&amp;apost;s 10-year-old son is also doing well, he said, but there are still fears of a repeat incident.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;My kids are already asking, &amp;apost;When is this going to happen again?&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>It was only a week ago that we were talking about this type of situation, and I said the chances of it happening are one in a zillion at Sandy Hook.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>I was wrong about that.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Long-term issues are more likely for children who were very close to someone who died in a shooting, who witnessed the event or who were in close physical proximity to it, Garbarino said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>In addition, &amp;quot;Kids who are having difficult lives before the event are the ones most likely to have issues,&amp;quot; Garbarino said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>For instance, if a child&amp;apost;s parents are going through a divorce or if the child had been fighting with a parent on the day of the event, he or she may feel more of an impact from a traumatic event such as a school shooting, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Moreover, if a child is frequently exposed to violence, such as by living in an abusive household or a dangerous neighborhood, a school shooting may add to existing trauma that child has stored up, Garbarino said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>In those situations, it&amp;apost;s hard to lean on the idea of &amp;quot;going back to normal.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>There is evidence that elementary-school children are particularly vulnerable to trauma, more so than teenagers or adults, Garbarino said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>This may be because although these children have enough awareness of a situation to appreciate danger, their brains and bodies haven&amp;apost;t matured to manage the effects in the way teenagers and adults can.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Symptoms.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Trauma from a school shooting can manifest itself in physical ways, such as stomachaches, headaches and sleeping difficulties, said Nancy Rodda, senior director of clinical services for Genesee County Community Mental Health in Flint, Michigan.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>In Rodda&amp;apost;s county, a 6-year-old boy shot a 6-year-old girl to death at an elementary school in 2000.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Stress can instigate a variety of behaviors: For instance, anxiety can lead to poor eating, which can lead to stomach discomfort, Rodda said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Alexis Wassick, a student at Sandy Hook Elementary, said Friday that &amp;quot;people were even like, they kind of got a stomachache.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Kids may start depending on their parents for things they&amp;apost;re normally able to do on their own, Marans said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>They may also become more irritable.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s not only a single event that puts children at risk for developing long-term mental health problems such as post-traumatic stress disorder, anxiety and depressive disorders, Marans said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>How well they were doing before a school shooting will have a big impact.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>There also is the issue of survivor&amp;apost;s guilt, Rodda said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Children who have lost friends may wonder why they themselves lived.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Support.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>One of the best predictors for good outcomes is when kids have adequate support from their families and communities, Marans said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Parents should listen to their children, reassure them that they are safe and look out for any changes in behavior, Rodda said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Let children ask questions, and don&amp;apost;t force anything on them, Garbarino said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;There&amp;apost;s a balance between talking about it but also not dwelling on it too much,&amp;quot; Rodda said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;Overexposure can increase stress.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Procaccini said he&amp;apost;s been talking to his children, explaining what happened.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;You do your best to communicate with them,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Getting back to routines is key for children to move on, Garbarino said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>If Friday is usually pizza night, have pizza.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>If swim practice usually happens on Saturday, take your child to swim practice at the normal time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>If children are too scared to return to school, parents should try to go with them as far as they will go, Garbarino said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>If a child becomes hysterical upon arrival, take him or her back to the car and see if you can ease the fear, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Avoid reinforcing the fear.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>&amp;quot;Hopefully by the time they do go back to school, I&amp;apost;ll have done a good enough job at talking to my kids and make them feel at least the most comfortable they could,&amp;quot; Procaccini said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s important for adults to get the help they need, too, Marans said, so they can be resources for the children who need them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s such a convergence between our worst nightmares coming true, and there is a sense of helplessness and loss of control that we need to address,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Interventions include helping parents understand the emotional consequences of an event like this and what to look for in their children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>The Child &amp;amp; Family Traumatic Stress Intervention program, which was developed at Yale at Marans&amp;apost; center, aims to increase communication between parents and children and prevent longer-term disorders.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>When other risk factors are present that make recovery more difficult, there are other strategies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>These include trauma-focused cognitive behavioral therapy, a specific type of psychological therapy that targets thinking and behaviors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>&amp;quot;With the right help, children are very resilient,&amp;quot; Rodda said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have many different ways to help people who have experienced a trauma now that allow them to come out on the other side as survivors.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>Based on experience, Garbarino estimates that 85% of kids would return to normal functioning, from a mental health standpoint, within a year after an event like the Connecticut shooting.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>&amp;quot;Not to say they would have forgotten it,&amp;quot; he said, &amp;quot;They may still make life choices because of it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
