<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="340" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/06/19/health/ama-obesity-disease-change/index.html" date_published="2013-06-19 16:17:32" category="health" author="Jacque Wilson, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Physicians group labels obesity a disease</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">The American Medical Association adopts a new policy on obesity.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="14">The change diagnoses nearly one-third of Americas with a medical condition.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="15">AMA decision could increase funding for future research, doctor reimbursement.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-22 14:29:30" annotation_time="40.500668">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">The American Medical Association has adopted a new policy that officially labels obesity as a disease &amp;quot;requiring a range of medical interventions to advance obesity treatment and prevention,&amp;quot; according to an AMA statement.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="2">Some experts worry suddenly declaring one-third of Americans &amp;quot;ill&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;sick&amp;quot; will increase the desire for quick interventions or medications and discourage people from making the lifestyle changes known to combat obesity.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="3">On the other hand, AMA&amp;apost;s declaration could help increase funding for future obesity research.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>One word could have a big impact on the way doctors treat obesity in the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The American Medical Association has adopted a new policy that officially labels obesity as a disease &amp;quot;requiring a range of medical interventions to advance obesity treatment and prevention,&amp;quot; according to an AMA statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The physicians&amp;apost; group voted to approve the obesity policy, among others, on Tuesday during its annual meeting in Chicago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The U.S. obesity rate increased almost 50% between 1997 and 2012, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Today, nearly 30% of American adults are considered obese, and the problem is almost as prevalent in kids.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Childhood obesity has more than doubled in the past 30 years, the CDC says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Obesity for adults is defined as having a body mass index, or BMI, of 30 or higher.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>BMI is a way to measure body fat based on your weight and height.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>(Calculate your BMI here).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Being obese increases your risk factor for developing many serious conditions, including heart disease, type 2 diabetes, high blood pressure, stroke, liver disease, sleep apnea and osteoarthritis.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>In fact, obesity has been linked to almost every chronic disease in some way or another.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Recognizing obesity as a disease will help change the way the medical community tackles this complex issue,&amp;quot; AMA board member Dr. Patrice Harris said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Obesity has long been recognized as a disease by other groups, but this move by the AMA sends a strong signal to the medical community, said CNN chief medical correspondent Dr. Sanjay Gupta.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Some experts worry suddenly declaring one-third of Americans &amp;quot;ill&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;sick&amp;quot; will increase the desire for quick interventions or medications and discourage people from making the lifestyle changes known to combat obesity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>On the other hand, AMA&amp;apost;s declaration could help increase funding for future obesity research.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>It could also lead to payment for doctors who want to simply talk to patients about nutrition or exercise -- time that&amp;apost;s not currently reimbursed by insurance plans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Identifying obesity as a disease may also help in reducing the stigma often associated with being overweight, said Joe Nadglowski, president and CEO of the Obesity Action Coalition.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Obesity has been considered for a long time to be a failure of personal responsibility -- a simple problem of eating too much and exercising too little,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;But it&amp;apost;s a complex disease... we&amp;apost;re hoping attitudes will change.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Nadglowski thinks the AMA&amp;apost;s support is also an important step in helping people gain access to obesity treatment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Most forms of insurance do not cover obesity alone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>For instance, an obese patient cannot hire a nutritionist or a trainer and have it covered by his or her plan simply to lose weight.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;We do cover treatment connected with a co-morbidity,&amp;quot; says Don McLeod, a spokesman for the Centers for Medicare &amp;amp; Medicaid Services.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;For example, if you have diabetes and obesity is aggravating the diabetes, we might cover obesity treatment as a way of treating the diabetes.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Obesity-related health care expenses cost Americans between $147 billion to $210 billion per year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Preventing and treating obesity before it leads to more serious diseases could help combat these costs, Nadglowski says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>AMA&amp;apost;s decision comes at an interesting time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The Obesity Action Coalition has been working to introduce the Treat and Reduce Obesity Act in Congress.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The bill was re-introduced in the House on Wednesday and will be re-introduced in the Senate on Wednesday afternoon, according to the office of Sen. Tom Carper, D-Delaware, one of the measure&amp;apost;s sponsors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>A similar bill last year stalled in committee.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The bill would increase obesity treatment options for Medicare patients, expand the types of providers who can offer obesity counseling and take away some obesity medication limits.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
