<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="222" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/03/23/health/beauty-dieting-men/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2012-03-23 11:24:52" category="health" author="Emma Lacey-Bordeaux and Gavin Godfrey, CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Dieting companies now targeting men</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="25">Weight Watchers, Nutrisystem, featuring men in ad campaigns.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">More than 30% of men older than 20 are overweight.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="17">Estimates say only one-quarter of overweight men actively seek to lose weight.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 18:02:37" annotation_time="16.7195">
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">More than 30% of men older than 20 are overweight, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="3">Burwick estimated that only one-quarter of men who have weight problems actively seek to lose weight.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="1">Dinwiddie said he applauds Weight Watchers and other companies that focus on men&amp;apost;s health, but an &amp;quot;average Joe&amp;quot;-style spokesman would work better than a Charles Barkley or Mariah Carey, who have trainers and chefs to keep them focused.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Jeff Romig kept putting it off.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>He knew the doctor would give him bad news.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>He&amp;apost;d known it for years; he needed to lose weight.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>But as he sat in the doctor&amp;apost;s office a few weeks ago and listened to his numbers -- cholesterol and blood pressure, both too high -- he resolved to change.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>This time, he decided to do something different, something drastic.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>After 10 years of talking about losing weight without much success, Romig decided to put his health and family first by leaving his high-pressure politics job.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;I knew I was doing the right thing, but I felt terrible,&amp;quot; said Romig, 34, who lives in Georgia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>While the tactic might be unusual, Romig is hardly alone in his struggle with weight gain or his reluctance to try to lose it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>More than 30% of men older than 20 are overweight, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Men face the issue at the same rate as women, but until recently, ads for weight loss products mostly featured female faces and voices.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>According to ad industry watchers, the female-centric advertising had the inadvertent effect of scaring men away.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Enter a slew of new ads from the biggest names in dieting: Weight Watchers, Nutrisystem and Jenny Craig.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Weight Watchers took a direct approach, with television spots that explicitly tell men it&amp;apost;s OK to diet.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>One commercial proclaims &amp;quot;Weight Watchers online is for men, too,&amp;quot; and, as a nod to the brand&amp;apost;s more feminine advertising of yore: &amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s not all rainbows and lollipops.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;Women really appreciate the fact that we are recognizing it as a widespread societal problem,&amp;quot; said David Burwick, president of Weight Watchers North America.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Beyond the multimillion-dollar campaign lies the hope for company expansion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Burwick estimated that only one-quarter of men who have weight problems actively seek to lose weight.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>That means plenty aren&amp;apost;t spending money on weight loss products and programs, at least not yet.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Aside from the attention paid by Madison Avenue, some men said they&amp;apost;re learning they need more than just a plan; they need people to hold them accountable and to relate to their struggles.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Lloyd Dinwiddie, an entertainment correspondent who goes by the name Gyant, said men don&amp;apost;t often talk about their diets with other men, something he said he wishes would change.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Though his nickname comes from his 6-foot-8-inch frame, Dinwiddie said not everyone appreciates his desire to slim down, and after years of diets, he&amp;apost;s trying new techniques.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;Women look at me like I&amp;apost;m crazy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>They say, &amp;apost;You&amp;apost;re just big, Gyant,&amp;apost;&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;At 310 pounds, every book in the world is telling me I need to lose weight.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Dinwiddie said he applauds Weight Watchers and other companies that focus on men&amp;apost;s health, but an &amp;quot;average Joe&amp;quot;-style spokesman would work better than a Charles Barkley or Mariah Carey, who have trainers and chefs to keep them focused.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Dinwiddie&amp;apost;s current dieting effort includes a lot more chicken salads and outdoor activities, with a goal of losing 80 pounds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>He has turned to an online community, hoping the discussion will serve as communal motivation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s actually been a collective support system in a roundabout way &amp;apost;cause in six months, if I&amp;apost;m not following it, they are going to be like, &amp;apost;Yo, what&amp;apost;s going on?&amp;apost;&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Romig, the man who quit his politics job, said he started using Weight Watchers in 2003, after his weight grew to 225 pounds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>He lost 30 pounds then, but the positive momentum slowed after a big move and a new, stressful job.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Through a few more jobs and one more move, Romig kept his Weight Watchers account, although he wasn&amp;apost;t using it much.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;Every month, there goes that $16.95,&amp;quot; he joked.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Work and volunteer commitments soaked up his time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>To make decisions about lifestyle changes, he sat with his wife of nine years and ran through scenarios, including how to handle fatigue and soreness during weight loss, and questions about whether he could keep up the momentum.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>It all added up to one thing: Making time to get healthy, even if it meant reducing his work hours and relying more heavily on the income of his wife, an attorney.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Social media has already proven to be helpful on the journey, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>When he shared news of his resignation and intention to run in a 5K on Facebook, he got all positive comments, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Romig keeps himself honest with his phone and other technology that allows him to keep tabs on his progress; his goal is to go from 241 to 180 pounds.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>But those hyper-masculine ads?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Romig said they didn&amp;apost;t have much effect on him.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>The real motivation came from his wife, who told him, &amp;quot;I worry that you&amp;apost;re not going to be here.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Since last week, Romig has lost 9 pounds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>He said everything else, even his job, is now secondary.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>