<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="247" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/04/24/health/fda-e-cigarette-regulations" date_published="2014-04-24 04:50:14" category="health" author="Saundra Young, CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>FDA proposes crackdown on e-cigarettes</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="11">E-cigarettes deliver nicotine to the user as a vapor .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">FDA has regulatory authority now only over cigarettes, smokeless tobacco .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">Age limit to buy e-cigarettes is expected to be 18 when rules are final.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-25 21:05:57" annotation_time="51.334">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">Currently, only cigarettes, smokeless tobacco and roll-your-own tobacco come under the FDA&amp;apost;s regulatory authority.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">When these recommendations are finalized following a 75-day public comment period, the age limit to buy the products is expected to be at least 18, although individual states could choose to set it higher.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="1">E-cigarettes deliver nicotine to the user as a vapor.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The Food and Drug Administration is making another attempt at regulating electronic cigarettes and other tobacco products.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>On Thursday, the agency proposed rules that call for strict regulation of electronic cigarettes, cigars, pipe tobacco, nicotine gels, water pipe tobacco and hookahs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Currently, only cigarettes, smokeless tobacco and roll-your-own tobacco come under the FDA&amp;apost;s regulatory authority.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>When these recommendations are finalized following a 75-day public comment period, the age limit to buy the products is expected to be at least 18, although individual states could choose to set it higher.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Health warnings would also be required, and the sale of the products in vending machines would be prohibited.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Initially, the only health warning required for e-cigarettes would be about the potential for addiction to nicotine.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Manufacturers would be required to register all their products and ingredients with the FDA.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>They would be able to market new products only after an FDA review, and they would need to provide scientific evidence before making any direct or implied claims of risk reduction associated with their product.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Companies would also no longer be allowed to give out free samples.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>After the public comment period, and once the proposed rules are finalized, manufacturers will have 24 months to submit applications to allow their products to remain on the market or to submit new product applications.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>E-cigarettes deliver nicotine to the user as a vapor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>They are usually battery-operated and come with a replaceable cartridge that contains liquid nicotine.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>When heated, the liquid in the cartridge turns into a vapor that&amp;apost;s inhaled.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Most look like cigarettes, cigars or pipes, but some resemble pens or USB memory sticks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Because they have not been fully studied, the FDA says it&amp;apost;s unknown what health risks they pose, how much nicotine or other chemicals are actually being inhaled, or whether there is any benefit to using them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Last year, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention reported that the percentage of high school students who reported ever using an e-cigarette more than doubled in one year, from 4.7% to 10% between 2011 and 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>As electronic cigarettes have increased in popularity, so have the number of related calls to poison control centers nationwide.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>According to a recent CDC report, poison control centers logged 215 calls involving e-cigarettes in February alone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Of those calls, 51% involved children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s really the wild, wild West out there,&amp;quot; said Margaret Hamburg, FDA commissioner.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;Because e-cigarettes are increasingly in the marketplace.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>They&amp;apost;re coming in different sizes, shapes and flavors in terms of the nicotine in them, and there&amp;apost;s very worrisome data that show that young people in particular are starting to take up e-cigarettes, especially the flavored ones -- and that might be a gateway to other harmful tobacco products.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Hamburg said officials don&amp;apost;t know how many types are on the market, another reason why regulation is critical.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re already conducting research and working with partners in the research community to better understand patterns of use of these e-cigarettes and to learn more about the way in which they work and the delivery of the nicotine through e-cigarettes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>But until we can really regulate them, we can&amp;apost;t have all the information we need and we can&amp;apost;t take all the actions that we might want to, to be able to best address the public health issues associated with them.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Miguel Martin, president of LogicTechnology Development -- considered the second-largest electronic cigarette company in the U.S. -- said he is encouraged by the FDA announcement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;We look forward to being a part of this process and believe that science-based and responsible regulations are good for both adult consumers and responsible electronic cigarette manufacturers,&amp;quot; Martin said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Logic opened its doors in 2010.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The company has nine products on the market, both disposable and rechargeable, but no flavored nicotine products.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Logic implemented rules a year ago similar to the ones the FDA has proposed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;We support and have already implemented those steps to ensure that adult smokers are the audience and consumer base of our products,&amp;quot; Martin said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;We work with the retailers to ensure the product is sold to adult consumers of legal smoking age.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Experts have said that e-cigarettes, if properly regulated, could help reduce the number of people who use conventional cigarettes and die of tobacco-related disease.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>But a lot of unanswered questions remain, according to Michael Eriksen, dean of the School of Public Health at Georgia State University, one of 14 U.S. institutions conducting FDA-funded research on electronic cigarettes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Nicotine is a drug, and poison experts say the concentrated liquid form used in e-cigarettes is highly toxic, even in small doses.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>It can be inhaled or absorbed through the skin.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;How concentrated is liquid nicotine?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Are there impurities in it?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Is it properly handled like a pesticide?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Eriksen asks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;Nicotine is a pesticide, fundamentally, and we take so many precautions about pesticides for our lawns and how to wear gloves.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>But what precautions do consumers take when they put the nicotine vials in?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>People treat it (liquid nicotine) as sugar when it&amp;apost;s a toxin.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Harold Wimmer, president and CEO of the American Lung Association, believes nicotine is highly addictive whether used in a regular cigarette or an e-cigarette.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>So how safe are e-cigarettes?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Hamburg said it&amp;apost;s buyer beware.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>&amp;quot;We think that there&amp;apost;s a lot of information that needs to be understood about e-cigarettes and their use.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>We&amp;apost;re trying to help provide some of that information through research that we&amp;apost;re conducting,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>&amp;quot;But we need the tools that regulation provides to be able to get critical new knowledge about e-cigarettes and to be able to put in place a framework that will protect the American public and potentially e-cigarette users, and really address the issues of what are the health consequences and what are the potential benefits.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Hamburg believes these new rules will change the landscape.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>If the FDA broadens its authority to regulate tobacco products, she said, it will make a major contribution to the health of Americans.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>But big changes could come slowly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>&amp;quot;It may be years before much regulation is imposed,&amp;quot; said Carl Tobias, a law professor at the University of Richmond.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>&amp;quot;The lobbying at FDA and Congress will be intense.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>And some believe the FDA has already waited too long.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is inexcusable that it has taken the FDA and the Administration so long to act,&amp;quot; Matthew L. Myers, president of the Campaign for Tobacco-Free Kids, said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>&amp;quot;This delay has had serious public health consequences as these unregulated tobacco products have been marketed using tactics and sweet flavors that appeal to kids, and their use has skyrocketed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>&amp;quot;The FDA and the Administration must now move as quickly as possible to finalize this rule.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
