<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="276" link="http://www.cnn.com/2011/09/22/health/chlorine-indoor-swimming-pools/index.html" date_published="2011-09-22 11:14:21" category="health" author="Jacque Wilson, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>How safe is your indoor swimming pool?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="11">Researchers trying to determine the long-term effects of the chemicals in pool water.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="20">Contaminants mix with chlorine to form chloramines, which give off a strong odor.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="32">Swimming in indoor chlorinated pools has been linked to asthma and bronchitis in children.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-06 12:38:41" annotation_time="24.4015">
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="1">Researchers are examining the longterm effects of the chemicals in pool water.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="2">Those contaminants -- sweat, hair, urine, makeup, sunscreen, etc. -- combine with chlorine to form chloramines, said pool consultant and researcher Alan Lewis.</sentence>
      <sentence id="32" ids_highlights="3">Bernard has also substantiated previous studies&amp;apost; claims of a link between swimming in indoor chlorinated pools and the development of asthma and recurrent bronchitis in children.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Catherine Garceau doesn&amp;apost;t go to the pool anymore.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The former Olympic swimmer has trained at many fitness centers over the years that smelled strongly of chlorine.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>While most would assume that means the water is clean, Garceau now knows it&amp;apost;s just the opposite.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>After winning bronze in 2000 with the Canadian synchronized swimming team in Sydney, Australia, Garceau was a &amp;quot;mess.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Her digestive system was in turmoil, she had chronic bronchitis and she suffered from frequent migraines.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Garceau retired in 2002 and began looking into holistic medicine.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Experts suggested detoxifying her body to rid it of chemicals, including what fellow teammates used to jokingly refer to as &amp;quot;eau de chlorine -- the swimmer&amp;apost;s perfume.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;As part of my journey to determine the factors that affected my health, I delved into the possible effects of chlorine and discovered some shocking facts,&amp;quot; Garceau writes in the appendix of her upcoming book, &amp;quot;Heart of Bronze.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Outdoor pool season is ending in many parts of the country, and competitive swimmers are heading indoors for their workouts and team meets.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>But how safe are the waters they&amp;apost;re diving into?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Researchers are examining the longterm effects of the chemicals in pool water.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Chlorine inactivates most disease-causing germs within a fraction of a second.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s why it&amp;apost;s found in our drinking water as well as 95% of pools in the United States, said Dr. Tom Lachocki, the CEO of the National Swimming Pool Foundation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>As Lachocki points out, access to clean water is what often separates first and third world countries.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Without chlorine, swimmers are at risk of contracting many dangerous waterborne illnesses.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>But the chemical compounds formed in pools have some scientists worried.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;When you open up a tap and pour yourself a glass of water, you don&amp;apost;t normally put someone&amp;apost;s backside in it,&amp;quot; Lachocki said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;But in a pool there are people getting into that water.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Every time a person gets in they&amp;apost;re adding contaminants.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Those contaminants -- sweat, hair, urine, makeup, sunscreen, etc. -- combine with chlorine to form chloramines, said pool consultant and researcher Alan Lewis.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Chloramines are what bathers smell when they enter a pool area; a strong smell indicates too many &amp;quot;disinfectant byproducts,&amp;quot; or DBPs, in the water.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Indoor pools create an additional a danger because of the enclosed atmosphere.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Volatile chemicals from the water are transferred, often via vigorous activity like a swim team&amp;apost;s kicks, to the air.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Without a proper ventilation system, the chemicals can hang around to be inhaled by coaches, lifeguards or spectators.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Some DBPs, like chloroform, are known as trihalomethanes, and are considered carcinogenic, Lewis said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>They&amp;apost;ve been linked specifically to bladder and colorectal cancer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Dr. Alfred Bernard is a professor of toxicology at the Catholic University of Louvain in Brussels and one of the world&amp;apost;s leading researchers on aquatic environments.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>He has published a series of studies documenting the effects of chlorine and its byproducts in swimming pools.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>In June, Bernard published a study in the International Journal of Andrology linking chlorine with testicular damage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Swimming in indoor, chlorinated pools during childhood was shown to reduce levels of serum inhibin B and total testosterone, both indicators of sperm count and mobility.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Bernard notes in the study summary that the &amp;quot;highly permeable scrotum&amp;quot; allows chlorine to be absorbed into the body.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Bernard has also substantiated previous studies&amp;apost; claims of a link between swimming in indoor chlorinated pools and the development of asthma and recurrent bronchitis in children.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>His 2007 study showed airway and lung permeability changes in children who had participated in an infant swimming group.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Reading these studies, it&amp;apost;s easy to forget that swimming itself is a great aerobic exercise that puts less stress on your joints than activities like running.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>In fact, it&amp;apost;s a sport often recommended for children with asthma because the humid, moist environment makes it easier for athletes to inhale and the breathing techniques can improve lung function.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;There&amp;apost;s an opportunity to throw the baby out with the bathwater,&amp;quot; Lachocki said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;Is chlorine perfect?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>The answer is no.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>[But] it&amp;apost;s fabulous, and if anyone comes up with something better they&amp;apost;ll be a millionaire.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Dr. Ernest &amp;quot;Chip&amp;quot; Blatchley studies water disinfection systems with his team at Purdue University in Indiana.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>In their research, the team analyzes DBPs and other chemicals formed when chlorine and contaminants mix in pools.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>A swimmer himself, Blatchley believes the answer lies in finding a better system for water disinfection.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>&amp;quot;The fact that these chemicals are being formed is, to me, a cause for concern,&amp;quot; Blatchley said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;A lot of this chemistry is just not known, and we need to do a better job at defining that chemistry.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Blatchley is currently studying the effects of UV radiation on pool water.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Other alternatives include ozone or salt water pools.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>But even salt water pools contain chlorine -- the salt is used to generate chlorine in the water instead of a pool operator adding chlorine directly.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>While it reduces the danger of storing chemicals in the facility, the water chemistry is very similar, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Perhaps the simplest solutions, Blatchley and Lachocki agree, can come from pool operators and patrons.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Chlorine is effective when used in proper amounts and tested regularly.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>The National Swimming Pool Foundation offers training for professional and personal pool owners.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s also important for swimmers to minimize the amount of contaminants in the water.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>Almost 85% of the urea found on human skin can be dispelled by showering with soap before getting in the pool.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s a public education thing,&amp;quot; Blatchley said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>&amp;quot;Swimmers and the general public need to recognize that there&amp;apost;s a link between their hygiene habits and the health of everyone who uses the pool.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>And of course, the other preventive measure is common sense (although you&amp;apost;d be surprised how many people admit to doing it).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>&amp;quot;If you don&amp;apost;t pee or poop in the pool, that&amp;apost;s cool too,&amp;quot; Lachocki said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
