<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="211" link="http://us.cnn.com/2014/04/24/health/conjoined-twins-will-stay-together/index.html" date_published="2014-04-24 20:28:31" category="health" author="Jen Christensen, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Conjoined twins: When parents have to make a difficult decision</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="11">About 33% of conjoined twins are connected from breastbone to waist.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="20">Conjoined twins occur once in every 200,000 live births.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="13">No separation surgery has successfully been performed on twins connected at the heart.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-24 21:45:51" annotation_time="39.2755">
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="1">Some 33% of conjoined twins are connected in this manner.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="3">Sharing a heart makes a separation surgery particularly risky.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="2">They occur once in about every 200,000 live births.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The chances that conjoined twins will survive are minimal.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The chances that both conjoined twins will survive surgical separation are even tinier.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s why a Pennsylvania couple says they will keep their two newborns together.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m thankful they were able to survive this long, and they&amp;apost;re still going strong,&amp;quot; their 25-year-old father, Kody Stancombe, told CNN affiliate WTAE.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;It would hurt us to lose one and have the other,&amp;quot; the twins&amp;apost; mother, Michelle Van Horne, said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;They were born together; they can stay together.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The couple from Indiana, Pennsylvania, gave birth to the twins on April 10.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Andrew Donovan Lee and Garrett Lee Donovan Stancombe are connected from the breastbone to the waist.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>They share a heart and a liver.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The medical term for that is omphalopagus.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Some 33% of conjoined twins are connected in this manner.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>In most of these cases, the twins rarely share a heart.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Sharing a heart makes a separation surgery particularly risky.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>There are no known cases where twins with hearts joined at the pumping chamber have survived that surgery, according to the University of Maryland Medical Center.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Doctors have gotten better at separating children who share other organs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>In 2006, surgeons successfully separated Utah twins Kendra and Maliyah Herrin.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The 4-year-olds were attached at the abdomen and shared a pelvis and kidney.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>It took doctors 16 hours to separate them, but the operation went smoothly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Conjoined twins are extremely rare.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>They occur once in about every 200,000 live births.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Conjoined twins happen when a woman produces a single egg that does not separate completely after it is fertilized.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>If it did divide completely, then the woman would give birth to identical twins.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Fraternal twins are born from two separate fertilized eggs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The overall survival rate of conjoined twins is from 5% to 25%, with about 75% of surgical separations resulting in at least one twin surviving.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Approximately 200 pairs of conjoined twins are born alive each year, and about half die before their first birthday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The first known case of surviving conjoined twins happened in England in 1100.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Mary and Eliza Chulkhurst were joined at the hip and lived for 34 years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Conjoined twins were at one time called &amp;quot;Siamese twins,&amp;quot; named for two brothers, Eng and Chang Bunker, who came from Siam, the country now known as Thailand.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>After appearing in circuses and sideshows all around the world, they settled in the United States and become successful ranchers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>They had 21 children between them after marrying two sisters.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The term &amp;quot;Siamese twins&amp;quot; is no longer used since it is considered racially insensitive.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The Bunker brothers lived until 63.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Andrew Donovan Lee and Garrett Lee Donovan Stancombe seem to be doing well.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>They are breathing on their own and are doing all the things healthy babies do -- sleeping, crying and eating.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;For me, (the best part) is being able to hold them and hear them cry and know they&amp;apost;re here with me,&amp;quot; Van Horne told CNN&amp;apost;s affiliate WTAE.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;Definitely, changing their diapers and bathing them is a two person job for me.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
