<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="259" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/06/05/health/gellar-pertussis/index.html" date_published="2013-06-05 12:21:19" category="health" author="Sarah Michelle Gellar, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Gellar: What we can do to help protect our babies</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">A 2012 pertussis outbreak was one of the largest in about 50 years.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12">Parents, grandparents and others should receive a Tdap vaccine booster.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="13">Estimates indicate there may be more than 3 million adult and adolescent cases yearly.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-25 21:09:55" annotation_time="31.574">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">In 2012, America experienced one of the largest outbreaks of reported pertussis cases in approximately 50 years, according to the U.S. Centers for Disease Control.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">As national campaign ambassador, I am helping raise awareness about pertussis in an effort to educate parents, grandparents, caregivers and others in close contact with infants about the importance of getting vaccinated with an adult Tdap vaccine to help protect themselves and to help stop the spread of the disease to infants.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="3">While I have been fortunate that my family has not been directly affected by pertussis, estimates indicate that there may be as many as 800,000 to 3.3 million adult and adolescent cases of pertussis in the United States in any given year.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>In 2012, America experienced one of the largest outbreaks of reported pertussis cases in approximately 50 years, according to the U.S. Centers for Disease Control.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Also known as whooping cough, pertussis is a highly contagious and often serious disease, especially in young children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>In adolescents and adults, it usually presents as a severe cough that may last for weeks or even months and the milder form is often mistaken for the common cold or bronchitis and can be easily spread, the CDC says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>But in babies, pertussis can be potentially fatal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Severe pertussis usually occurs in babies and young children, who are at higher risk for pertussis-related complications.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Infants are particularly vulnerable against pertussis because they don&amp;apost;t begin receiving their own immunizations until they are 2 months old.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>They might not be protected until they&amp;apost;ve had at least three doses of an infant pertussis vaccine.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>When it could be determined how an infant caught pertussis, family members were responsible for spreading the disease to the baby in up to 80% of cases, researchers found.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>More specifically, parents were responsible up to 50% of the time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>After I learned that more than 83% of pertussis deaths occurred in infants younger than 12 months, I knew I wanted to take action.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>I didn&amp;apost;t think twice when Sanofi Pasteur and March of Dimes asked me to join the Sounds of Pertussis Campaign to help raise awareness about the potential dangers of pertussis and the importance of adult tetanus, diphtheria and acellular pertussis (Tdap) vaccination.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>As national campaign ambassador, I am helping raise awareness about pertussis in an effort to educate parents, grandparents, caregivers and others in close contact with infants about the importance of getting vaccinated with an adult Tdap vaccine to help protect themselves and to help stop the spread of the disease to infants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>While I have been fortunate that my family has not been directly affected by pertussis, estimates indicate that there may be as many as 800,000 to 3.3 million adult and adolescent cases of pertussis in the United States in any given year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>And more than half of babies younger than 1 who get the disease must be hospitalized, the CDC says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>My heart goes out to those parents who have experienced the devastation of having a child affected by this potentially fatal disease.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Before my son Rocky was born in September, I did my own research to make sure I was doing everything I could to help protect my health and the health of my family.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>When I learned the statistics surrounding pertussis, I not only made sure I was vaccinated, but I asked my friends and family to join me in getting the adult vaccine.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>I wanted to make sure I was doing everything I could to help protect myself and to help stop the spread of pertussis to my children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The CDC recommends adults, especially those in contact with an infant, receive a single dose of the Tdap vaccine because immunity from early childhood pertussis vaccinations wears off over time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>After about five to 10 years, adults are left susceptible to the disease, which they can then transmit to others.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>At the end of the day, our children are the greatest gift we can receive.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Although pertussis may be on the rise nationwide, there are simple steps you can take as an adult to help protect yourself and to help stop the spread of the disease to infants.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>This includes making sure everyone who comes in contact with your baby -- including yourself -- is up to date on their vaccinations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Please visit the Sounds of Pertussis site to learn more about pertussis and the Sounds of Pertussis Campaign.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>There, you can access the campaign&amp;apost;s new Facebook application, the Breathing Room, which allows parents to send a brief message to family and friends in their Facebook network asking them to make the pledge to be vaccinated against pertussis.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The responsibility is ours as adults to help protect the babies in our lives.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
