<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="310" link="http://us.cnn.com/2013/12/16/health/multivitamins-studies/index.html" date_published="2013-12-16 22:00:21" category="health" author="Nadia Kounang, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Multivitamins a waste of money? Editorial in medical journal says yes</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="31">The vitamin and supplement industry rakes in $12 billion annually.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">A new editorial, based on three studies, says multivitamins are a waste of money.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="27">One expert says vitamins are necessary to compensate for poor diets.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 11:47:27" annotation_time="114.02433">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">But an editorial published in this week&amp;apost;s Annals of Internal Medicine says that using supplements and multivitamins to prevent chronic conditions is a waste of money.</sentence>
      <sentence id="27" ids_highlights="3">So multivitamins are a backstop against our poor diet.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="31" ids_highlights="1">The vitamin and supplement industry rakes in nearly $12 billion annually, according to the researchers, with multivitamins its most popular product.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>More than half of all adults in the United States take some sort of multivitamin; many do so in hopes of preventing heart disease and cancer or even to aid with memory.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But an editorial published in this week&amp;apost;s Annals of Internal Medicine says that using supplements and multivitamins to prevent chronic conditions is a waste of money.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;The (vitamin and supplement) industry is based on anecdote, people saying &amp;apost;I take this, and it makes me feel better,&amp;apost; said Dr. Edgar Miller, professor of medicine and epidemiology at Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine and co-author of the editorial.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s perpetuated.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>But when you put it to the test, there&amp;apost;s no evidence of benefit in the long term.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>It can&amp;apost;t prevent mortality, stroke or heart attack.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The editorial, &amp;quot;Enough is Enough: Stop Wasting Money on Vitamin and Mineral Supplements,&amp;quot; is based on three studies looking at the effects of multivitamins on preventing heart attacks and cancer, as well as improving cognitive function in men older than 65.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>All three studies were also published in this week&amp;apost;s Annals of Internal Medicine.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The first study was a meta-analysis of 27 studies that covered more than 450,000 participants and found that multivitamins had no beneficial effect on preventing cardiovascular disease or cancer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>In addition, taking vitamins didn&amp;apost;t prevent mortality in any way.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>However, the analysis did confirm that smokers who took only beta carotene supplements increased their risk of lung cancer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>When taking multivitamins to prevent a second heart attack, authors again found no beneficial evidence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The second study looked at 1,700 patients who previously had heart attacks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>They were assigned to take three multivitamins or placebos twice a day for five years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>However, with more than 50% of patients stopping their medications, it was difficult for authors to come to any real conclusions about the vitamins&amp;apost; effectiveness.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>With such a high drop-out rate, &amp;quot;interpretation is very difficult,&amp;quot; said Miller.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The final study followed nearly 6,000 men older than 65, who took either a multivitamin or a placebo for 12 years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The men were administered cognitive functioning tests, and test results found no differences between the two groups.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>However, Gladys Block, a professor of nutrition and epidemiology at University of California Berkeley, pointed out that the group of men followed in the cognitive study were all physicians with no health problems.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;These are very well-nourished, very health-conscious people,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>In fact, she says none of the studies accurately represents the American population.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Block has spent her life studying the role of Vitamin C, in particular, on disease risk factors and says that most Americans are undernourished.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>She says that most Americans don&amp;apost;t have a healthy diet, and therefore don&amp;apost;t get the vitamins and minerals they need.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;You&amp;apost;re not getting any of these micronutrients from Coke and Twinkies,&amp;quot; said Block.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;Two-thirds of us are overweight, a quarter over 50 have two or more chronic conditions, so there&amp;apost;s a substantial population that one would hesitate to call healthy.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Block went on to say, &amp;quot;There&amp;apost;s always a nontrivial minority that&amp;apost;s actually getting a questionable level of some micronutrients.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>So multivitamins are a backstop against our poor diet.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Cara Welch, senior vice president of the Natural Products Association, agreed with Block.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is pretty common that in this day and age with the lifestyle many of us lead that we don&amp;apost;t always take the time to have a balanced diet, and even if you do have a balanced diet, you can still have nutritional deficiencies.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The Natural Products Association is the largest trade organization representing the manufacturers and retailers of the natural products industry, including vitamins.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The vitamin and supplement industry rakes in nearly $12 billion annually, according to the researchers, with multivitamins its most popular product.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;Multivitamins address the nutritional deficiencies in people,&amp;quot; Welch said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;We don&amp;apost;t believe they are the answer to all life&amp;apost;s ailments, as the editorial suggests.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Miller, however, disagreed that the studies didn&amp;apost;t represent the general public.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;They didn&amp;apost;t select people who eat good diets or bad diets,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;You assume that these people selected are the typical American diet.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Taking a supplement in place of a poor diet doesn&amp;apost;t work.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Some groups, however, do need supplements, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;For people with deficiencies, malabsorption issues, and to prevent neural tube defects in pregnancy -- there are a small number of conditions where we prescribe them.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Miller also said the jury is still out on Vitamin D, which can help strengthen bones, and omega-3 fatty acids, including DHA and EPA.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Miller said the studies were unlikely to change any clinical standards, and that focusing on diet and exercise remain key to maintaining a healthy lifestyle.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s something with which Block can agree.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>&amp;quot;Eat fruits and vegetables,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
