<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="205" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/08/22/health/kerner-sex-after-childbirth/index.html" date_published="2013-08-22 11:26:41" category="health" author="Ian Kerner, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>CNN Parents: Fight low sex drive after baby together</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="9">Fatigue and stress are big influences on low sexual desire in co-parents, study finds.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12">Couples experience ups and downs of arousal together after baby&amp;apost;s birth.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="19">But parenthood doesn&amp;apost;t have to signal the end of your love life, Ian Kerner says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-29 13:59:23" annotation_time="41.075665">
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="1">Indeed, the researchers found that fatigue and stress tended to be a greater influence on low sexual desire in partners, rather than issues related directly to the physical and hormonal aspects of childbirth.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;Anyone who is actively involved in the care of their infant has likely experienced the ups and downs of arousal during at least the first few months.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="3">Parenthood, new or not, can be challenging to intimacy, but it certainly doesn&amp;apost;t have to signal the end of your love life.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Women may be the ones to physically go through pregnancy and childbirth, but they&amp;apost;re not alone in the experience.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>From phantom pains to &amp;quot;sympathy&amp;quot; weight gain, partners of pregnant women can develop some of the physical symptoms of pregnancy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Now, a recent study suggests that these partners may undergo the same shifts in sexuality as new mothers do.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The study, published in August issue of The Journal of Sexual Medicine, looked at the sex lives of 114 partners of women who had recently given birth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Researchers at the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor gave these partners (95 men, 18 women, and one unspecified gender) an online questionnaire aimed at assessing their physical, emotional, and relationship experiences during the first three months following their youngest child&amp;apost;s birth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Previous research has mostly focused on postpartum sexuality in new mothers, finding that biological issues such as hormonal changes and breastfeeding can affect libido.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>But few studies have examined the effects of a new baby in the women&amp;apost;s partners (called co-parents).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The results of the current study show co-parents also experience similar shifts in sexuality, suggesting that hormones and other biological causes aren&amp;apost;t the only factors in play.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Indeed, the researchers found that fatigue and stress tended to be a greater influence on low sexual desire in partners, rather than issues related directly to the physical and hormonal aspects of childbirth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>That makes sense, says sex coach Amy Levine.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;When both partners are involved in caring for the baby, sleep deprivation and attending to his or her needs at a moment&amp;apost;s notice takes a toll,&amp;quot; she explains.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Anyone who is actively involved in the care of their infant has likely experienced the ups and downs of arousal during at least the first few months.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The study included some same-sex partners, who tend to experience the effects of parenthood on libido similarly to their heterosexual counterparts.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>However, there are some differences.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;Some gay couples do not have the support of their families, meaning no grandparents to give the couple a break from childcare.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>And in some areas of the country, there is still prejudice against gay people and gay families, a major stressor that straight families don&amp;apost;t face,&amp;quot; says psychotherapist Margie Nichols.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;But same-sex couples have advantages as well.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Studies of gay couples show that they divide childcare and housework tasks more equitably, making it less likely that one parent will feel overwhelmed and possibly resentful.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Parenthood, new or not, can be challenging to intimacy, but it certainly doesn&amp;apost;t have to signal the end of your love life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Here are some steps to help you prioritize sex:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Reignite that spark.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Before you try to jump back into things, take the time to reassess your sex life and revisit what excites and energizes you.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;We all have ways of sexually turning ourselves and our partners on and off,&amp;quot; says sex therapist Megan Fleming.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;Make and share a list of your list of turn-ons with each other, then commit to doing one thing from that list as a healthy daily practice.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Redefine intimacy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Depending on the physical issues a new mom faces after childbirth, it&amp;apost;s not a bad idea to put intercourse on the back burner while enjoying other forms of intimacy, such as hugging, kissing, and touching, until she has fully healed from a C-section, episiotomy, or other concerns, says women&amp;apost;s health expert Dr. Jennifer Wider.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Be creative.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Too busy to even think about getting busy?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Ask friends or loved ones to watch your little one(s), hire a babysitter, or trade play dates with other parents so you and your partner can enjoy your own date nights -- or date days.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>If your child is a baby, take advantage of his or her naps to get frisky.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Talk things out.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>As with almost everything involving your sex life, communication is key.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>When one person in a couple experiences low libido, it definitely affects his or her partner, says Wider.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Communicate openly about your concerns, and discuss solutions to common problems that could be interfering with intimacy, such as vaginal dryness.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Just do it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s normal to find yourself in a sex rut, whether you&amp;apost;ve just welcomed a new baby or are parents to a teen.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>But just as a rut can deepen when you ignore it, sex tends to beget more sex.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>In my experience, if one partner is experiencing decreased desire, it&amp;apost;s crucial for the other partner to stay in the game and not retreat out of rejection.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Happy kids require happy parents.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>So put your relationship -- and intimacy -- at the top of your to-do list.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Your family will thank you.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
