<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="371" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/01/13/health/16-pregnant-teens-childbirth/index.html" date_published="2014-01-13 19:13:55" category="health" author="Jacque Wilson, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Study: &amp;apost;16 and Pregnant,&amp;apost; &amp;apost;Teen Mom&amp;apost; led to fewer teen births</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">MTV&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;16 and Pregnant&amp;quot; may encourage teens to use birth control.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">Teen births in the United States have been steadily declining since 1991.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="34">Part of the decline can be attributed to the recession, expert says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-14 14:04:21" annotation_time="26.424997">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">The next time your teen turns on MTV&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;16 and Pregnant,&amp;quot; avoid any disparaging remarks.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">The declining teen birth rate is a well-documented trend in the United States.</sentence>
      <sentence id="34" ids_highlights="3">About half of the recent dramatic decline can be attributed to the recession, Kearney says.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The next time your teen turns on MTV&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;16 and Pregnant,&amp;quot; avoid any disparaging remarks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The show may actually encourage him or her to practice safer sex, according to a new study.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The study, released Monday by the National Bureau of Economic Research, says &amp;quot;16 and Pregnant&amp;quot; ultimately led to a 5.7% reduction in teen births in the 18 months after its premiere on TV.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>This would account for about one-third of the overall decline in teen births in the United States during that period, researchers Melissa Kearney and Phillip Levine concluded.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>In 2011, a total of 329,797 babies were born in the United States to girls between the ages of 15 and 19; that&amp;apost;s a rate of 31.3 births per every 1,000 girls, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The CDC does not have rates available for 2012; Kearney and Levine say that number dropped to 29.4 per every 1,000 that year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The declining teen birth rate is a well-documented trend in the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Between 1991 and 2008, the rate dropped steadily at an average of about 2.5% a year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>In the past four years, it has dropped even more dramatically at a rate of about 7.5% per year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;We were really curious as to what was going on,&amp;quot; said Kearney, who has been studying teen pregnancy interventions alongside Levine for more than a decade.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>When the researchers learned that Sarah Brown, CEO of the National Campaign to Prevent Teen and Unplanned Pregnancy, thought MTV&amp;apost;s shows may have something to do with it, they thought: &amp;quot;Could that really be true?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;16 and Pregnant&amp;quot; premiered in June 2009 and has been on for five seasons, with a total of 47 episodes through October 2013.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The show features one teen every episode and follows her through several months during and after pregnancy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The documentary-style show inspired several spinoffs, including the popular &amp;quot;Teen Mom.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Both &amp;quot;16 and Pregnant&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Teen Mom&amp;quot; have experienced their share of controversy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The shows are often criticized for glamorizing teen pregnancy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;Instead of really helping viewers understand the day-to-day responsibilities of attending to a new infant -- scrubbing poop stains or spit-up out of clothing -- or dwelling on the &amp;apost;mundane,&amp;apost; MTV chooses to focus on the girls&amp;apost; volatile relationships with the babies&amp;apost; fathers or their new body piercings and tattoos,&amp;quot; Parents Television Council Director Melissa Henson wrote on CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;That makes for better TV.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Kearney and Levine looked at Nielsen ratings as well as search data from Google Trends and Twitter to determine the show&amp;apost;s potential impact on teen birth rates.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>They recorded spikes in Google searches and Twitter mentions about the show when new episodes aired and looked specifically for searches on terms such as &amp;quot;birth control&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;abortion&amp;quot; alongside those spikes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>They then analyzed geographic data to see whether locations with higher search activity and tweets about &amp;quot;16 and Pregnant&amp;quot; showed higher levels of searches and tweets about birth control and abortion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>They did.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The researchers also looked to see whether high viewership in certain areas corresponded with a bigger drop in teen births.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>It did.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;The results of our analysis indicate that exposure to &amp;apost;16 and Pregnant&amp;apost; was high and that it had an influence on teens&amp;apost; thinking regarding birth control and abortion,&amp;quot; the researchers write.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s all well and scientific, but could a TV show really have that big of an impact on teen birth rates?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s an extraordinary study done by two very cautious economists,&amp;quot; said Bill Albert, chief program officer at the National Campaign to Prevent Teen and Unplanned Pregnancy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;I jokingly refer to them as Drs. No because they generally set out to say, &amp;apost;That doesn&amp;apost;t work.&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>For that reason alone, we take it very seriously.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Kearney said that while she and Levine did a lot of &amp;quot;fancy economic work&amp;quot; to make sure their conclusion was right, the most compelling evidence came from the teens&amp;apost; social media language.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;The text of the tweets are phenomenal: &amp;apost;This reminds me to take my birth control.&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;apost;Watching 16 &amp;amp; Pregnant, going to take my birth control,&amp;apost; &amp;quot; she remembered reading.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Of course, no one, including the study authors, is saying that MTV alone is responsible for the declining teen birth rate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>About half of the recent dramatic decline can be attributed to the recession, Kearney says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Research shows that all birth rates fall during slow economic times, including teens&amp;apost;; those who were once ambivalent about using birth control often become more conscientious when they realize that finding -- or keeping -- a job to support a baby would be difficult.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Kearney believes TV shows like &amp;quot;16 and Pregnant&amp;quot; work to deter teens in a similar way.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;Shows that make it clear how hard it can be ... affect girls who might not care otherwise,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;You see she&amp;apost;s fighting with her boyfriend on a daily basis.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>She&amp;apost;s gaining weight.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Her friends are partying without her.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Making the immediate cost clear seems to get through to teens more than statistics that show what happens to teen parents when they&amp;apost;re 25, Kearney says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Teens may turn to TV shows about sex because they&amp;apost;re lacking other options, Albert says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>A recent study published in the medical journal JAMA showed that doctors certainly aren&amp;apost;t spending a lot of time talking about the important topic: The average conversation about sex between doctors and teens in the study lasted less than two minutes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>And parents, Albert says, are often shocked to learn that teens say their parents have a major influence on their decisions about sex.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think the takeaway here is that media can be, and often is, a force for good,&amp;quot; Albert said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have always viewed these particular shows as sex education for the 21st century.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
