<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="386" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/12/04/health/fertility-treatments-multiples/index.html" date_published="2013-12-04 22:03:53" category="health" author="Jen Christensen, CNN" highlights_mapped="false" mapping_error="false">
  <title>The real reason behind the multiples baby boom</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">36% of twins, 77% of triplets, other multiples came from fertility treatments in 2011.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">More multiples are the result of the mother taking fertility drugs rather than having IVF.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="23, 22, 20">The IVF induced triplet trend peaked in 1998 due in part to new medical guidelines.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_time="32.715">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">By 2011, 36% of twin births and 77% of triplets, quads and quintuplets came as a result of fertility treatments including fertility drugs, according to a study published this week in the New England Journal of Medicine.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;We were surprised that non-IVF approaches were more culpable than IVF here,&amp;quot; said Dr. Eli Adashi, a professor of medical science at the Alpert Medical School of Brown University.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="3">The number of triplets and higher-order births increased by a much larger number -- they were up by a factor of 6.7 from 1971 to 1998.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="3">That may in large part be due to doctors following guidelines issued that year by the Society for Assisted Reproductive Technology.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="3">Those guidelines encouraged doctors to limit the number of embryos transferred during an IVF procedure.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s no secret that fertility treatments are behind the increasing numbers of twins, triplets or even quadruplets or quintuplets born in recent years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>However, scientists studying the impact of medical intervention on multiple births were in for a surprise -- in vitro fertilization (IVF), which has anecdotally borne much of the blame for multiple births because more than one embryo is typically implanted, was not the primary cause of multiples.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Instead, fertility drugs appear to be the culprit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>By 2011, 36% of twin births and 77% of triplets, quads and quintuplets came as a result of fertility treatments including fertility drugs, according to a study published this week in the New England Journal of Medicine.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;We were surprised that non-IVF approaches were more culpable than IVF here,&amp;quot; said Dr. Eli Adashi, a professor of medical science at the Alpert Medical School of Brown University.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>He and his colleagues initiated the study because they wanted to find a way to stop the multiples trend.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Why?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Doctors prefer women give birth to a single baby or a &amp;quot;singleton&amp;quot; as they are called in medical lingo.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s because even with medical advances, multiple births are still considered risky for both mother and babies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;By and large, human reproduction is designed for singletons, and the optimum outcome we hope for is a singleton birth to term,&amp;quot; Adashi said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;When you get into a situation with multiple and higher number births, all kinds of concerns creep in.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>We wanted to make a deliberate course correction as opposed to flailing indiscriminately at the problem.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>While doctors recognized the phenomenon was a public health issue, Adashi said, &amp;quot;We didn&amp;apost;t really have the hard numbers and we certainly did not have the kind of detailed insights into what&amp;apost;s driving the increase in the number of multiples.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Researchers arrived at these details by studying the number of times women gave birth to multiples between 1962 and 1966 -- the era before fertility treatments.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>They contrasted this data with the number of multiple births between 1971 to 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>All births are tracked by the National Center for Health Statistics.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>By law, all children born as a result of IVF are also tracked by a national registry.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Children born as a result of some other fertility treatment, such as the use of fertility drugs, are not tracked, so researchers estimated that number.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>What they found, adjusting for maternal age and the national rate of twin births, was that the number of twins increased slightly, by a factor of 1.9 between 1971 to 2009.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The number of triplets and higher-order births increased by a much larger number -- they were up by a factor of 6.7 from 1971 to 1998.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Thankfully, Adashi said, that number peaked in 1998.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>That may in large part be due to doctors following guidelines issued that year by the Society for Assisted Reproductive Technology.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Those guidelines encouraged doctors to limit the number of embryos transferred during an IVF procedure.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Doctors routinely transfer multiple embryos to increase the likelihood that at least one will result in a pregnancy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Since these guidelines went into effect there has been a 70% reduction in the transfer of three or more embryos during IVF, according to the study.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>That has in part resulted in a 33% decrease in the proportion of triplet and higher-order births due to IVF.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;Maybe the worst is behind us in this epidemic of multiple births, when it comes to IVF at least,&amp;quot; Adashi said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>However, non-IVF fertility treatments such as fertility drugs still are causing a disproportionate number of multiple births.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>In such treatments, a woman will take drugs that will encourage her ovaries to release more than one egg a month.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The rate of non-IVF twin births has increased slightly, going from 16% in 1998 to 19% in 2011, according to the study.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Non-IVF triplet births increased from 36% to 45% in the same time period.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;That&amp;apost;s a lot and there is certainly room for improvement there,&amp;quot; said Dr. Jennifer Kawwass, a fellow at the Emory Reproductive Center.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;Because of limited insurance coverage, we see that patients currently have a financial disincentive to go the IVF route, which means they are leaving this up to chance.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Women struggling with infertility may choose the fertility drug route first because it is cheaper.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Often insurance does not cover IVF or caps reimbursement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>With this new data, legislators may want to encourage more insurance companies to cover IVF treatments.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Some states do mandate coverage.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;There are clearly ways by which these non-IVF technologies can be modified and there are more prudent approaches that result in less in the way of multiples,&amp;quot; Adashi said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>He believes education is key to help doctors and their patients understand the negative health impacts of giving birth to multiple children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Adashi said he and others plan to continue to watch this multiple birth trend.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;Hopefully by conducting these types of analyses, we should have a good handle on what is happening in this area,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;We want to see if we will be gaining in success at limiting the number of multiple births or, God forbid, we are losing the battle.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
