<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="179" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/08/23/health/kerner-sex-books/index.html" date_published="2012-08-23 11:57:53" category="health" author="Ian Kerner, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Beyond &amp;apost;Fifty Shades&amp;apost;: Sex experts share their favorite books</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">The blockbuster &amp;quot;Fifty Shades of Grey&amp;quot; has sparked widespread interest.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">Ian Kerner asks some of his favorite sex experts to pick their favorite sex books.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="28">Kerner says the list is only the beginning of many worth exploring and learning from.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-10 23:05:53" annotation_time="25.7585">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">But there&amp;apost;s no denying that &amp;quot;Fifty Shades&amp;quot; has sparked widespread interest in how to improve our sex lives -- and what better way to do that than via a good &amp;quot;how-to&amp;quot; book?</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">So, in the spirit of sharing, I asked some of my favorite sex experts to pick their favorite sex books:.</sentence>
      <sentence id="28" ids_highlights="3">I&amp;apost;ve read and recommend many of these books myself, and this list is only the beginning of many exceptional works worth exploring and learning from.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>With the blockbuster success of &amp;quot;Fifty Shades of Grey,&amp;quot; many people are curious about dipping their toes (not to mention other body parts) into more sexually adventurous waters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>I&amp;apost;m always careful to make clear that while the adventures of Ana and Christian may make for a compelling erotic yarn, their story is by no means an accurate depiction of BDSM relationships (bondage, discipline, dominance, submission, sadism, masochism), nor is &amp;quot;Fifty Shades&amp;quot; any sort of guide book.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>For instruction on that topic, you&amp;apost;ll need to turn to the works of true sex-positive educators such as Clarisse Thorn or Tristan Taormino and their books &amp;quot;The S&amp;amp;M Feminist&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;The Ultimate Guide to Kink,&amp;quot; respectively.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>But there&amp;apost;s no denying that &amp;quot;Fifty Shades&amp;quot; has sparked widespread interest in how to improve our sex lives -- and what better way to do that than via a good &amp;quot;how-to&amp;quot; book?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>If you&amp;apost;re uncomfortable talking about sex to your friends, doctor, therapist or even your partner, such books can be an important resource, whether they impart new information, help you work through an issue, inspire you to become more adventurous or simply turn you on.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>So, in the spirit of sharing, I asked some of my favorite sex experts to pick their favorite sex books:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Debby Herbenick, a research scientist at Indiana University and the author of &amp;quot;Sex Made Easy:&amp;quot;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;Hands down, I recommend &amp;apost;The New Male Sexuality&amp;apost; by Bernie Zilbergeld.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>A classic in the field, it gives a rich picture of men&amp;apost;s sexual lives including myths they&amp;apost;re taught about sex and common problems such as erectile issues, communication blocks and rapid ejaculation as well as solutions for these problems.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Joe Kort, a clinical sexologist and founder of the Center for Relationship and Sexual Health:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;I recommend Jack Morin&amp;apost;s &amp;apost;The Erotic Mind,&amp;apost; which helps remove the shame of sexual behaviors and fantasies by understanding what they mean in a nonsexual way.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Morin addresses where fantasies and desires come from and how shame can be removed and replaced with healthy acceptance for individuals and couples.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Amy Levine, sex coach and founder of Ignite Your Pleasure:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot; &amp;apost;Hot Sex: Over 200 Things You Can Try Tonight&amp;apost; by Jamye Waxman and Emily Morse is a fun, sensual, seductive, creative and tantalizing book filled with more than 200 ways to tease, play, entwine and explore.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>When I coach couples who are in a sex rut, I suggest they use this book as a tool.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Laura Berman, sex educator, researcher and therapist:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;If I had to pick, I would choose either &amp;apost;The Anatomy of Love&amp;apost; by Helen Fisher or &amp;apost;The 5 Love Languages&amp;apost; by Gary Chapman.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Both are extremely helpful for couples to understand how men and women are wired differently and to learn how to love one another in a way that lasts.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Justin Lehmiller, Harvard University social psychologist and online sex columnist at The Psychology of Human Sexuality:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot; &amp;apost;The Technology of Orgasm&amp;apost; by Rachel Maines chronicles the history of &amp;apost;hysteria,&amp;apost; a bogus female medical condition that led to invention of the vibrator.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Maines&amp;apost; book is a meticulously researched, fascinating and humorous look at the origin of hysteria and the birth of the motorized sex toy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;I also adore &amp;apost;Bonk: The Curious Coupling of Science and Sex&amp;apost; by Mary Roach, which traces the history of how scientists have studied sexual arousal and orgasm in a very engaging way that refuses to take itself too seriously and never gets bogged down in jargon or technicalities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;On a personal level, &amp;apost;Bonk&amp;apost; holds a special place in my heart for helping me realize how much fun a career in sex research could be.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Megan Andelloux, certified sexuality educator and sexologist:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot; &amp;apost;America&amp;apost;s War on Sex&amp;apost; by Marty Klein describes ridiculous sex laws and research that Americans are led to believe are true.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a must-read book for anyone interested in sociology, psychology, sexuality education, law and parenting.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m also a fan of &amp;apost;My Secret Garden&amp;apost; by Nancy Friday, which discussed women&amp;apost;s fantasies well before erotica became truly popular.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>I&amp;apost;ve read and recommend many of these books myself, and this list is only the beginning of many exceptional works worth exploring and learning from.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>In my opinion, no list would be complete without Esther Perel&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;Mating in Captivity,&amp;quot; an excellent guide to integrating a sense of sexual mystery into long-term relationships.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>And on a personal note, in 10 years of writing sex books, my first, &amp;quot;She Comes First: The Thinking Man&amp;apost;s Guide to Pleasuring a Woman,&amp;quot; remains my most popular.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>At the time, I often mused that many men -- through no fault of their own -- knew more about what was under the hood of a car than under a woman&amp;apost;s clothes or what was behind her orgasm.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>In writing &amp;quot;She Comes First,&amp;quot; I am grateful to the Federation of Feminist Women&amp;apost;s Health Centers and their book, &amp;quot;A New View of a Woman&amp;apost;s Body&amp;quot; (unfortunately now out of print) and to Rebecca Chalker&amp;apost;s excellent book, &amp;quot;The Clitoral Truth.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Any man or woman truly interested in deepening their knowledge of a woman&amp;apost;s full sexual potential should give this book a read.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>No matter where your sexual interests lie, you&amp;apost;re sure to find something new on the shelves of your local bookstore.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>And if you&amp;apost;re too embarrassed to shop in person -- well, that&amp;apost;s the beauty of the Kindle, Nook and other e-readers -- no plain brown wrapper necessary!</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Any books to add to the list that have helped you improve your sex life?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Tell me about them in the comments below.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>I&amp;apost;m always looking for a good read.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
