<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="322" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/01/29/health/nfl-harvard-study/index.html" date_published="2013-01-29 09:56:36" category="health" author="Stephanie Smith, CNN" highlights_mapped="false" mapping_error="false">
  <title>NFL Players Association, Harvard planning $100 million player study</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Players union negotiating with NFL to fund the study.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="11, 7">It will look at variety of health issues faced by pro football players.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="23, 19">Proposal is to study long-term health of 200 players.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_time="34.913334">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">The National Football League Players Association is negotiating a deal with the league to award $100 million to Harvard University over 10 years to study and treat players&amp;apost; injuries and illnesses, according to a proposal obtained by CNN.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">Nadler said that what distinguishes this study is that it will look at the &amp;quot;whole player across his whole life, not just the brain.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="2">By the end of their careers, NFL players may emerge with all sorts of injuries -- chronic pain, arthritis, joints needing replacement, depression, diabetes, heart problems and concussion-related dementia, among others -- so many they have become a cohort ripe for study.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;We have seen the condition of our players five, 10, 15, 20 years after they play,&amp;quot; said George Atallah, a spokesman for the NFLPA.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="3">The Harvard proposal focuses on studying a core group of 100 unhealthy players -- both current and retired -- and 100 healthy players.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The National Football League Players Association is negotiating a deal with the league to award $100 million to Harvard University over 10 years to study and treat players&amp;apost; injuries and illnesses, according to a proposal obtained by CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>In the last few years, the perception of a typical NFL player has undergone a subtle shift: from lithe titans performing formidable feats on the field to men who may end their careers broken down, their brains addled by a mysterious concussion-related brain disease.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>But the real picture of the typical NFL player is much more complex, and the health problems run much deeper than concussion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>According to the proposal, the funding would be used to &amp;quot;diagnose, treat and prevent&amp;quot; players&amp;apost; injuries and illnesses.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;No one has ever studied these players before,&amp;quot; said Dr. Lee Nadler, dean for clinical and translational research at Harvard Medical School and co-director of the proposed study.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;There have been postmortem studies looking at the brains of previous players but not the players today.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Nadler said that what distinguishes this study is that it will look at the &amp;quot;whole player across his whole life, not just the brain.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The NFL said it looked forward to learning more about the study and hopes &amp;quot;it will play an important role in advancing medical science.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have no higher priority than player health and safety at all levels of the game,&amp;quot; it said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>It is not just the brain that may be damaged after a long career on the playing field.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>By the end of their careers, NFL players may emerge with all sorts of injuries -- chronic pain, arthritis, joints needing replacement, depression, diabetes, heart problems and concussion-related dementia, among others -- so many they have become a cohort ripe for study.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Every player understands the risks associated with playing football,&amp;quot; said Jason Witten, a tight end with the Dallas Cowboys, in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;What we&amp;apost;re trying to do as players through this research is to find ways to lead healthier lives.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s the most important thing we can do off the field.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The proposed research project will be announced at the NFLPA annual Super Bowl press conference on Thursday in New Orleans.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Members of the NFLPA say the proposed research is unprecedented in both scope and resources, at least as it relates to NFL player health.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>If the NFLPA successfully forges this agreement with the NFL, the funding would dwarf a $30 million donation made to the National Institutes of Health by the NFL last year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>That study has a more specific focus on brain injury.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have seen the condition of our players five, 10, 15, 20 years after they play,&amp;quot; said George Atallah, a spokesman for the NFLPA.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;Given the scope of health issues that NFL players are subject to, we are committed to making sure that enough money is allocated to get answers.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Atallah added, &amp;quot;If this was strictly a concussion research program, the right number might not have been $100 million.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>It would have been much less.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The Harvard proposal focuses on studying a core group of 100 unhealthy players -- both current and retired -- and 100 healthy players.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Those two groups will be drawn from an initial larger study group of 1,000 current and former players from across the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>They will have played diverse positions and will have experienced diverse health problems.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The initial group of 1,000 will participate in a series of baseline studies including cardiac function, testing for joint abnormalities and psychosocial tests.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The players will also submit exhaustive playing and injury histories, spanning their entire football careers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>From those preliminary data will emerge the 100 healthiest and least healthy players, who will then continue testing at Harvard over several years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Nadler said the focus will be on cross-institutional collaboration, with hundreds of scientists at Harvard potentially playing roles in the study.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;When you&amp;apost;re talking about NFL players, you&amp;apost;re talking about people in the 99.99% of unusual,&amp;quot; said Nadler.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;These are superathletes who have skills that very few people have, and when you put them in extremely emotional and physical situations, those psychosocial stresses and physical stresses integrate.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>How those stresses coalesce and take shape over the course of long careers playing football is what Harvard researchers, and partners from other institutions, will be trying to pinpoint.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;Typically, when we do a test or medical study, we&amp;apost;re taking a snapshot,&amp;quot; said Dr. Herman Taylor, principal investigator of the Jackson Heart Study at the University of Mississippi Medical Center and one of the scientists enlisted from outside Harvard.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;What we want to do is see the full-length movie of what happens to a player over time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;How is it that two men that play the same position for the same number of years have vastly different lives after playing?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Not everyone suffers from the same types of problems, and not everything can be explained by simple repetitive traumas.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Ideas floated for study include using advanced scanning techniques and genetics to fuel knowledge about who is most at risk for head injury, finding ways to regrow knee ligaments in a lab, identifying injury prevention strategies such as new drugs or new helmets, and addressing ethical issues surrounding player injuries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;One of the broader aims of the research is conflicts of interest when you have a patient who will do anything to get back on the field and a doctor who works for and is paid by a club,&amp;quot; said Sean Sansiveri, NFLPA staff counsel.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>The holistic focus of the research does not obviate the importance of concussion, said Sansiveri.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Work on concussion will be a major focus, &amp;quot;but there are a lot of unique issues that our guys face within a unique context ... other ailments and diagnoses that are prevalent in the football population.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Funding for the study will come from the players&amp;apost; portion of league revenues, currently being negotiated between the NFL and the Players Association.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>The exact figure to be allocated for the study is still to be determined, according to Atallah, and most likely will not be finalized until after the Super Bowl.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>The absence of a finalized plan has not stopped the NFLPA from imagining what a successful study could mean, not just for NFL players but for athletes in other sports.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;If this $100 million of research would have caused a groundbreaking discovery in one critical area of a player&amp;apost;s life or health, then we would have succeeded,&amp;quot; said Atallah.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>&amp;quot;Whether it&amp;apost;s an ACL issue or a mental health issue or a concussion issue, if we find one solution to any of those things we&amp;apost;re studying, it would have been a success.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
