<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="312" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/12/17/health/holidays-food-allergies/index.html" date_published="2013-12-17 13:21:12" category="health" author="Mireille Schwartz, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="false" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Navigating the holidays with food allergies</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Food allergies can present a holiday challenge for hosts and guests .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="33">Hosts can hang on to food labels and take care in the kitchen.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="40">Guests can ship allergy-free food ahead or bring a safe dish.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_time="6.8563333" mapping_time_divergence="6.8563337">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Food-allergic children can feel left out of the traditional festivities, many of which center around food, and allergies can present a challenge for hosts, as they frequently must tend to a wide range of preferences and needs behind the scenes.</sentence>
      <sentence id="33" ids_highlights="2">If a guest brings a food item that contains allergens, and there&amp;apost;s an allergic diner at the table, you could accept the item if it&amp;apost;s well-sealed and donate it later to a friend or a soup kitchen.</sentence>
      <sentence id="40" ids_highlights="3">If you&amp;apost;re allergic and flying to visit friends or family, make some simple allergy-free foods that travel well and ship them to your host&amp;apost;s home a week or more in advance, so you&amp;apost;re sure they&amp;apost;ll arrive in time for your visit.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Holidays are a particularly challenging time for us food-allergic individuals with so many desserts and homemade treats, casseroles and dips laid out on the table -- largely without ingredient labels.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Food-allergic children can feel left out of the traditional festivities, many of which center around food, and allergies can present a challenge for hosts, as they frequently must tend to a wide range of preferences and needs behind the scenes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>All the excitement and good cheer makes it more difficult to be informed about the ingredients in each and every party food.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>There are ways, however, to reduce anxiety through the holidays while staying happy, healthy, and allergy free.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Season&amp;apost;s eatings.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>This is a wonderful time of year for getting together over meals with those closest to you.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>I suffer from fish allergy and my daughter has a peanut and tree nut allergy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Members of our inner circle are the most reliable and trusted food allergy gatekeepers for parties and celebrations, but it&amp;apost;s not possible to assume that friends and family will always remember to avoid reaction-causing foods after you&amp;apost;ve told them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>After all, they don&amp;apost;t live with your food allergy day in and day out and, thus, naturally aren&amp;apost;t yet in the habit of checking every label every time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The holiday season is an optimal time to check in and remind everyone of your allergies prior to the get-togethers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>This season is also an excellent time to ensure your auto-injectors and rescue medications are up-to-date.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The auto-injectors, in particular, have a relatively short shelf life and the product visibly starts to deteriorate at or around the expiration date.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Remaining vigilant is key.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Here are some holiday gathering tips for both hosts and guests:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>For hosts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Hang on to labels.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Keep food labels for everything used to prepare a festive homemade holiday meal so an allergic guest may double-check the ingredient list.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Suggest alternatives.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Request flowers, wine or holiday-themed napkins and plates if guests want to contribute to the party and someone with a food allergy is attending.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Look for &amp;quot;natural&amp;quot; turkey.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Some pre-basted turkeys contain soy, wheat, and dairy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Instead, look for turkeys labeled &amp;quot;natural,&amp;quot; which by law must be minimally processed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Some free-range, all-natural, fresh turkeys are free of antibiotics, hormones, and allergens.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Avoid cross-contamination.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Care with utensils and surfaces when preparing foods is a must.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Rinsing a knife that chopped walnuts is insufficient -- thoroughly scrub all utensils and surfaces with soap and water and wipe clean.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Even trace amounts of a food can cause a reaction for highly allergic people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Use color coding.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>How about trying color-coded cooking utensils this year?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>A bright red silicone spatula or a nifty lime green serving spoon is sure to alert food-allergic guests.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Many large box stores stock seasonal arrays of themed and brightly colored utensils in advance of the holiday season.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Consider donating.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>If a guest brings a food item that contains allergens, and there&amp;apost;s an allergic diner at the table, you could accept the item if it&amp;apost;s well-sealed and donate it later to a friend or a soup kitchen.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Some cities even have volunteer organizations dedicated to alleviating hunger.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>After a free phone call, their volunteers, who deliver sometimes more than 10 tons of food a week to agencies feeding people in need, will pick up your donation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>For guests.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Put thought into contributions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>When in doubt, beautiful fresh flowers are always a welcome hostess gift instead of a pie from a bakery when you&amp;apost;re just not sure about the allergy safety.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Ship ahead.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>If you&amp;apost;re allergic and flying to visit friends or family, make some simple allergy-free foods that travel well and ship them to your host&amp;apost;s home a week or more in advance, so you&amp;apost;re sure they&amp;apost;ll arrive in time for your visit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Bring an allergy-free host gift.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>If your host has food allergies, you can always bring a gift of unpeeled fruit or a prepackaged seasonal safe food, with ingredient lists approved by your host.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Bring a safe dish.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>If you&amp;apost;re food allergic and even if the party you&amp;apost;re invited to is not a potluck, why not offer to bring a safe dish or two so there&amp;apost;s definitely something you can eat.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Your host will be thankful not to have to prepare separate food items, and sharing dishes that are allergen-free will delight everyone there.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Check in beforehand.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>If you are allergic, always let your host or restaurant where you&amp;apost;re celebrating know in advance -- don&amp;apost;t assume they will remember.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Even a restaurant where you frequently dine may not immediately remember you and your medical condition at holiday banquet tables with prix-fixe meals.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Be sure to remember to always carry your rescue medication just in case of emergency.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>And here&amp;apost;s to your good health.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
