<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="261" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/07/03/health/tooth-decay-causes/index.html" date_published="2014-07-03 13:36:31" category="health" author="Paul Frysh, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Good or bad teeth? The genetics of tooth decay</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6">The health of your teeth depends on a combination of genetics and dental hygiene.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">About 60% of the risk for tooth decay appears to be due to genetic factors.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">Scientists have identified five areas where genes play a role in tooth decay.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-08 06:49:55" annotation_time="30.507666">
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">Scientists say the health of your teeth depends on a combination of genetics and dental hygiene.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">About 60% of the risk for tooth decay appears to be due to genetic factors, says Mary L. Marazita, director of the Center for Craniofacial and Dental Genetics at the University of Pittsburgh School of Dental Medicine.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">Though genetic dentistry is still in its infancy, scientists have identified five areas where genes play a role in tooth decay:.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Remember &amp;quot;The Big Book of British Smiles&amp;quot; from &amp;quot;The Simpsons&amp;quot;?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The dentist used it to scare children into proper dental hygiene.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>And let&amp;apost;s be honest, it was funny!</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Because though British tea and good manners have an excellent international reputation, British teeth are mostly used as a punch line.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>But tooth decay is far from only a British problem -- in fact, it&amp;apost;s one of the most common chronic disease worldwide.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Scientists say the health of your teeth depends on a combination of genetics and dental hygiene.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>We all know that person who never brushes, eats tons of candy and rarely (if ever) has a cavity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Then there are those of us who floss regularly, yet still end up breathing in the laughing gas once or twice a year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>About 60% of the risk for tooth decay appears to be due to genetic factors, says Mary L. Marazita, director of the Center for Craniofacial and Dental Genetics at the University of Pittsburgh School of Dental Medicine.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Though genetic dentistry is still in its infancy, scientists have identified five areas where genes play a role in tooth decay:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Sweet preference.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Everyone likes sweets right?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Well sort of, said Marazita.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Though you may believe all children turn into crack-addled lunatics at the sight of the drugstore candy aisle, scientists have identified gene variants that show a range of &amp;quot;sweet preference.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>All other factors being equal, the stronger your genetic &amp;quot;sweet preference,&amp;quot; the more likely you are to develop tooth decay.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>So, two children raised in identical environments may have completely different attitudes to sugar: from &amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m just not that into candy&amp;quot; to &amp;quot;Mom caught me licking the stray candy chips from the grocery store gum ball machine.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Again.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Marazita couldn&amp;apost;t tell us exactly where to find these kids who are &amp;quot;just not that into candy,&amp;quot; but said, &amp;quot;just because they&amp;apost;re not hanging out at your house doesn&amp;apost;t mean they don&amp;apost;t exist.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Tooth enamel.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>This one is a no-brainer.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Some people have softer tooth enamel than others.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The softer the enamel, the easier it is for bacteria to do their excavation, leading to cavities.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Because genes are the primary determinant of enamel structure, they have a big effect on whether you get tooth decay.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Taste ability.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Cilantro, an herb common in Asian and Latin American cooking, is the perfect topping for fresh fish tacos -- at least to some people.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Others would just as soon go home and lick a bar of soap.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>That was the finding of a recent study that identified a gene variant for the ability to enjoy cilantro.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;It tastes like soap&amp;quot; was the most common refrain among those missing the gene variant.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;Taste ability&amp;quot; is a measure of the variety of things you can taste -- not simply whether you are genetically predisposed to enjoy certain flavors (as in the cilantro example), but also whether you are able to perceive certain flavors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>This is a complex process that includes your tongue and is inextricably linked to your sense of smell.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Studies show the greater the variety in your genetic taste ability profile, the less likely you are to develop tooth decay.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Whether that&amp;apost;s because more variety leads to fewer sweets, or whether there are other reasons, is not yet clear, but scientists are continuing to study the connection.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Saliva strength.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Calcium, potassium and other elements are important for strong healthy teeth that resist tooth decay.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>But it&amp;apost;s not as simple as eating the right foods; these elements must be properly metabolized to be useful.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Your saliva plays a big part in this process, and scientists have identified gene variants that make some people better at it than others.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Microbiome.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>There&amp;apost;s a whole field of study called microbial ecology that looks at the various communities of bacteria that live in the human body.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Yeah, that&amp;apost;s right, communities -- plural.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>In your mouth alone there are separate communities of bacteria on your tongue, on the surface of your teeth and below your gum line.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Together, these communities make up what is known as your microbiome.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Don&amp;apost;t worry, it&amp;apost;s all perfectly normal.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>But your body&amp;apost;s immune response to these communities affects, among other things, your risk of developing tooth decay.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>What about the other 40%?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>&amp;quot;So,&amp;quot; you are probably asking yourself, &amp;quot;if my genes are 60% of my cavities, what governs the other 40%?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Answer: Soft drinks and fluoride.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>OK, that might be a slight exaggeration.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>The other 40% has to do with environment: diet, brushing frequency, smoking habits, dental care access, culture, even socioeconomic factors, according to Robert J. Weyant, chairman of the University of Pittsburgh&amp;apost;s Department of Dental Public Health.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>But so far, the single biggest environmental factor scientists have identified that encourages tooth decay is the consumption of sugary drinks, Weyant said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Any sugary treat can hurt, but sugary drinks are particularly adept at spreading sugar to every corner of your mouth to feed the bacteria that cause decay.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>Tea and coffee don&amp;apost;t even rate in comparison.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Alcohol is not even on the list.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>In fact there is very little to suggest that alcoholic drinks have any significant effect on tooth decay -- unless, of course, you like to drink your whiskey in a large glass of soda.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>On the opposite side, the single biggest environmental factor known to protect against tooth decay is fluoride.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>Get it in your city water supply, get it in your toothpaste, get it in periodic treatments from your dentist, but get it somewhere.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>That is the consensus among dentists and public health experts alike, Weyant said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
