<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="413" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2011/11/02/health/obesity-surgery-cuts/index.html" date_published="2011-11-02 11:04:03" category="health" author="Aaron Cooper, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Weight loss surgery funding cut</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="21">Georgia says cut was essential to help balance the budget.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="22">Self-funded health care program had projected deficit of $815 million.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="23">1,577 workers have had the surgery in the 2 1/2 years it has been covered.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-16 13:48:46" annotation_time="53.551666">
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="1">Georgia says cutting surgical weight loss from the state&amp;apost;s plan was essential to help balance the budget.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="2">Their self-funded health care program had a projected deficit of $815 million for the 2012 and 2013 fiscal years.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="3">The state says 1,577 members have had the surgery in the 2 1/2 years it has been covered for a total cost of $30.8 million.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Alice McCormack thought she had the answer to her decades-long battle with her weight: bariatric surgery.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>That was until the state health insurance&amp;apost;s budget shortfall got in the way.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>McCormack, 61, estimates she&amp;apost;s been on 10 to 20 weight loss regimens in her life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;I have been to LA Weight Loss, Weight Watchers,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;At one point in time I actually did human growth hormone shots.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>I did Fen-Phen.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>I did Meridia.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>She says she lost a little bit of weight, but it always came back, plus a little more.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Now, the soft-spoken 5 foot 2 woman weighs 305 pounds and has a body mass index of more than 56.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Why it&amp;apost;s so hard to keep weight off.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>McCormack retired in 2003 after 31 years working in the Walker County, Georgia, school system and now gets her insurance from the state.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>This summer she found out her plan would cover weight loss surgery.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;I thought that was probably an answer,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;As I get older it gets more and more imperative that I find an answer, or else I&amp;apost;m going to end up with some major health problems.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>McCormack already has asthma, arthritis, sleep apnea, high blood pressure and gastric reflux, all conditions caused or made worse by obesity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is the one surgery that seems to fix all of the problems, or at least the majority of them,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>McCormack was set.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>She was at a pre-surgery doctor&amp;apost;s appointment when she found out her insurance was eliminating the surgical weight loss benefit for 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Patients are required to go on a special diet for six months before being eligible for the surgery, so it was too late for her to complete the diet and have the surgery before January.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;You get your hopes up and think everything is OK because you think you&amp;apost;ve done your homework and think you&amp;apost;ve checked things out ahead of time and gotten the low-down and then all of a sudden you don&amp;apost;t,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Georgia says cutting surgical weight loss from the state&amp;apost;s plan was essential to help balance the budget.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Their self-funded health care program had a projected deficit of $815 million for the 2012 and 2013 fiscal years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The state says 1,577 members have had the surgery in the 2 1/2 years it has been covered for a total cost of $30.8 million.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>That works out to a little less than $20,000 per person.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>In a statement to CNN, a spokeswoman for the state&amp;apost;s health plan says, &amp;quot;We examined a number of options to address the projected deficits.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>It was imperative that these options be fiscally responsible, fair to the membership, and feature wellness and choice.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The cuts eliminated the 2012 shortfall and reduced the 2013 shortfall.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The state also points to a wellness plan that it is adding to its coverage this year, saying &amp;quot;the wellness plan options, while voluntary, are designed to educate and engage members in adopting healthy lifestyles through positive behavioral changes.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>CNN legal contributor Holly Hughes says she owes her life to getting obesity surgery while working as a Georgia county prosecutor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;I was able to consult with a surgeon ... and get it taken care of before it got to the point it was going to kill me, literally kill me,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Hughes weighed nearly 300 pounds before the operation and now is at 151.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s frightening to me that you are going to stop all of these state employees from having access to this surgery,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;In the long run it&amp;apost;s going to cost the state more.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>These are folks that are going to develop diabetes, if they don&amp;apost;t already have it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>... things that can kill you.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>For now, the initial cost of the surgeries was too much.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>The state says it is &amp;quot;aware of numerous studies projecting long-term savings over a five- to 10-year period following bariatric surgery but has not had the program in place long enough to realize any significant savings.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>It will continue to monitor to see whether the patients who had the surgery as state employees will end up saving them money.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;National data is very clear this is life-saving and money-saving,&amp;quot; says Dr. Robin Blackstone, the president of the American Society for Metabolic and Bariatric Surgery.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;When people understand the data, we believe they will say we didn&amp;apost;t know.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>She says private companies have been increasing coverage at about 8% a year and Medicaid has covered the procedure since 2006.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>The society&amp;apost;s data also show that 44 states cover the operation for state employees.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Montana, Idaho, Kansas, Oklahoma, Louisiana and Pennsylvania do not currently have the benefit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Missouri&amp;apost;s state Consolidated Health Care Plan cut coverage for weight loss surgery in 2011 but is bringing it back in 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Emily Kampeter, a spokeswoman for the plan, says, &amp;quot;They did realize some short-term savings, but in the long-term decided that the benefits of offering bariatric surgery outweighed the short-term costs.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>McCormack takes seven or eight medicines each day.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>She says if she got the surgery it would not only help her stop taking the expensive prescriptions, but also live a better life.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>In her retirement, McCormack works three jobs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>With her home still in need of repair after this spring&amp;apost;s tornadoes she doesn&amp;apost;t think she can afford to pay for the $25,000 operation on her own.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>She still wants the surgery.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>&amp;quot;Once I get my house finished I can take out a loan or, you know, see what turns out.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Medicare pays for the operation, and she says she may have to wait four years until she is eligible for that program to get the surgery.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
