<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="378" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/07/24/health/survivor-guilt-ptsd/index.html " date_published="2012-07-24 18:01:25" category="health" author="Elizabeth Landau, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Surviving with the guilt of living</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="31">About 8% to 15% of people who experience trauma develop severe PTSD symptoms.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="23">Experts say sitting back and taking time to process the event can help survivors cope.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="25, 24">Seek professional help if you feel depressed or suicidal or can&amp;apost;t function.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-27 16:45:46" annotation_time="101.114">
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="2">Sitting back and taking time to process the event can help survivors cope, Jones said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="3">Seeking support from friends, family and community or faith leaders can help an individual work through difficult feelings.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="3">But if there&amp;apost;s lingering guilt and anxiety, Jones recommends consulting a mental health professional.</sentence>
      <sentence id="31" ids_highlights="1">About 8% to 15% of people who experience trauma develop severe PTSD symptoms that persist and require professional help, Jones said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>In the wake of a tragedy such as the movie theater shooting in Colorado, those who live wonder why they survived when others didn&amp;apost;t.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;You&amp;apost;re happy that you&amp;apost;re alive, but then again, you&amp;apost;re sad because you know certain people died,&amp;quot; said Eric Hunter, a witness to the shooting last week in Aurora.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;You know children died.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>You wish, you know, why not me instead of them?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>You just feel bad.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Jennifer Seeger, another witness, said, &amp;quot;I heard that a 6-year-old was shot.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>And I was just thinking the entire time, you know, &amp;apost;How come I got so lucky?&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>... I&amp;apost;m 22 years old.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>I&amp;apost;ve lived my life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>You know, as far as that goes, I would love to take a bullet for that 6-year-old to live their life.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Among the 12 victims of the shooting were three men who were fatally wounded while saving their girlfriends.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Jansen Young is one of the women who survived because her boyfriend, Jon Blunk, 26, shielded her from bullets.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;I look at that and know that I would do the same thing if the tables had been turned, and if I would have been able to take the bullet for him, I would have,&amp;quot; Young told CNN affiliate KTVX.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>When a person survives a traumatic incident in which others died, especially loved ones, it&amp;apost;s common to feel guilty for living.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Survivor guilt can be an immediate response to a tragedy, and the extent of the feelings depends on the individual, said Russell Jones, a psychologist at Virginia Tech who helped counsel victims at the school after a shooting rampage in 2007.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s important to understand what the survivor guilt means for the person, said Melissa Brymer, director of terrorism and disaster programs at the UCLA Neuropsychiatric Institute in Los Angeles.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>A lot of times, she said, it&amp;apost;s an expression of grief and loss.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>People may feel that someone else got hurt because of them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Maybe they could have been at the event but, by coincidence, didn&amp;apost;t go.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Or it may be that someone did something heroic, perhaps even dying to save that person&amp;apost;s life, and &amp;quot;They&amp;apost;re appreciative of what happened, but they&amp;apost;re struggling with: They are alive, and their loved one isn&amp;apost;t,&amp;quot; Brymer said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>For some people, survivor guilt is just part of working through complex feelings after experiencing a traumatic event involving deaths and a way of mourning.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>But it may become all-consuming and impede functioning.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Sitting back and taking time to process the event can help survivors cope, Jones said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Seeking support from friends, family and community or faith leaders can help an individual work through difficult feelings.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>But if there&amp;apost;s lingering guilt and anxiety, Jones recommends consulting a mental health professional.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>A survivor may experience symptoms of post-traumatic stress disorder and depression that requires formal treatment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;If they&amp;apost;re having changes within their behaviors or in their emotions or with their relationships with others, then we want to make sure that people get help,&amp;quot; Brymer said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Unfortunately, people who need help often don&amp;apost;t seek it, Jones said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;So often, there&amp;apost;s stigma attached to getting help from a mental health professional,&amp;quot; Jones said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;Therefore, they go without seeking treatment, oftentimes until they reach a breaking point.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>About 8% to 15% of people who experience trauma develop severe PTSD symptoms that persist and require professional help, Jones said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>With support, people generally do well, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Classic symptoms include intrusive thoughts, flashbacks and nightmares.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>People may avoid anything that reminds them of the event and have difficulty paying attention.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>It may be paired with depression and suicidal feelings.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>These symptoms can lead to full-blown PTSD over time, especially if a person has a history of mental illness.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Previous trauma, stress, loss of financial stability, and grieving the loss of family and friends are also risk factors, Jones said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>There are several treatment strategies that have been shown to help people with survivor guilt and PTSD symptoms, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Exposure is a central element of these strategies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Getting people to talk about the event and assimilating the event into everyday living are key, Jones said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Therapists may also take the individual back to the setting where the tragedy occurred and allow the person to express his or her thoughts, feelings and emotions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Therapists can teach clients relaxation and breathing skills to alleviate anxiety and to emphasize positive thoughts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>In time, through social support and sometimes treatment, many of the troubling thoughts are fully alleviated, Jones said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>If you know people who may be experiencing survivor&amp;apost;s guilt, check in with them frequently, Brymer said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>How much is this consuming their lives?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Are they able to attend to their basic needs?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Are they so overwhelmed by their feelings that they&amp;apost;re stuck?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>One coping strategy is to do something meaningful for someone else, Brymer said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Organizations that help people who have survived violence or natural disasters, or advocacy groups, may be good options for people who are trying to move on from a tragedy such as the Colorado shooting.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>It can also be important for a survivor to honor those who died, Brymer said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>&amp;quot;If someone has died, is there something that you can do that&amp;apost;s meaningful and representative of that person?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>she asked.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>&amp;quot;Is there something you can do so you&amp;apost;re unstuck, so you can do something powerful and meaningful to someone else?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>Some people may also change expectations for their future as a result of surviving a traumatic incident.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>Young, for example, told NBC&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;Today&amp;quot; that she wasn&amp;apost;t sure whether she should remain in Colorado.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s important to make sure that life changes aren&amp;apost;t negative, Brymer said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>&amp;quot;People need to know that this is very common, but there&amp;apost;s really nothing that you could have done, and move on with their lives,&amp;quot; Jones said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>If you are experiencing suicidal thoughts, call the National Suicide Prevention Lifeline at 1-800-273-8255.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
