<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="187" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/07/31/health/rehab-racket-siu-cir-part-three/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2013-08-01 00:01:04" category="health" author="Christina Jewett and Will Evans, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>California cracks down on rehab clinics after CNN/CIR investigation</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Yearlong investigation by CNN and The Center for Investigative Reporting finds cheating and deception in California&amp;apost;s taxpayer-funded drug rehab program.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">State officials allowed a man convicted of organized crime to run a clinic despite a state law barring felons from doing so.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="18">Department of Health Care Services announces a crackdown, suspending 16 clinics suspected of violating laws.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="27">California state senator calls for independent review of the rehab program by the state auditor.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-21 11:16:36" annotation_time="296.3615">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1"> A yearlong investigation by CNN and The Center for Investigative Reporting found widespread cheating and deception in California&amp;apost;s taxpayer-funded drug rehab program for the poor.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">State officials allowed a man convicted of organized crime to run a clinic despite a state law barring felons from doing so.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="3">A month later, the Department of Health Care Services announced a crackdown, suspending 16 clinics suspected of violating laws.</sentence>
      <sentence id="27" ids_highlights="4">A California lawmaker said the department&amp;apost;s recent actions were a good start, but he advocated for the state auditor to conduct an independent review of the rehab program.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A yearlong investigation by CNN and The Center for Investigative Reporting found widespread cheating and deception in California&amp;apost;s taxpayer-funded drug rehab program for the poor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The problem is exacerbated by weak oversight of Drug Medi-Cal, part of the nation&amp;apost;s largest Medicaid program.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>State officials allowed a man convicted of organized crime to run a clinic despite a state law barring felons from doing so.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The state approved another clinic operator even though he officially was blacklisted from billing Medicaid.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>And time and again, clinics accused of fraud and cited for serious violations have nonetheless managed to draw increasing amounts of government money.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Yet answers for the failures have been hard to come by.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Clinic operators facing fraud allegations refused to answer detailed questions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>So did top state health officials.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>CNN and CIR spent weeks seeking a sit-down interview with authorities overseeing the Drug Medi-Cal program but were turned down.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Federal Medicaid authorities rely on the Department of Health Care Services to combat fraud in the health insurance program for the poor, which uses state and federal funds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Toby Douglas, the agency&amp;apost;s director, declined an interview.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>His boss, Diana Dooley, secretary of the Health and Human Services Agency, also declined interview requests.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Approached outside a public meeting at a state office building, Dooley said accusations of fraud are taken seriously.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;All allegations are given full and fair consideration, and you caught me running because I am late for a meeting,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have a budget that we are just completing, and we have many priorities on our time,&amp;quot; she added.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;Information has been provided, answers have been provided.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Dooley abruptly ended the brief exchange, asking the guards to call security.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>A month later, the Department of Health Care Services announced a crackdown, suspending 16 clinics suspected of violating laws.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are going to be fanning out statewide,&amp;quot; Karen Johnson, the department&amp;apost;s chief deputy director, said in an interview.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are not going to stop just with those 16 clinics.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>We are going to review all of the Drug Medi-Cal providers in the state of California.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Officials would not identify the targeted clinics, saying the information would compromise the investigation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>On Tuesday, Norman Williams, spokesman for the Department of Health Care Services said the state has now suspended 29 clinics in all, and expects to refer even more to prosecutors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Williams said he could not immediately determine whether the 29 included satellite sites of clinics.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Johnson vowed to tighten state oversight but disputed the notion that it has been lacking until now.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;I would say that&amp;apost;s not a fair characterization,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>A California lawmaker said the department&amp;apost;s recent actions were a good start, but he advocated for the state auditor to conduct an independent review of the rehab program.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;I want to know how this happened for so long, how pervasive is the fraud, and more importantly what can we do to change laws or regulations so the fraud doesn&amp;apost;t occur in the future,&amp;quot; state Sen. Ted Lieu, who represents parts of Los Angeles County, told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Lieu said he was motivated by his belief in rehabilitation programs as a crucial tool for reducing crime and the prison population.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;I became very concerned,&amp;quot; he said, &amp;quot;that if we don&amp;apost;t fix this fraud immediately, it would undercut the public support for this entire program.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Those who run troubled rehab clinics declined to give detailed interviews.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>For more than a decade, George Ilouno has been banned from drawing state or federal funds in the Medicaid program due to a prior conviction of student loan fraud.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Still, his rehab clinic, GB Medical Services, has received rising sums of money since it opened in 2007, with its most recent annual funding at $440,000.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>He was arrested in March and charged with grand theft, filing false Medicaid claims and paying kickbacks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Ilouno pleaded not guilty.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>He still was billing Medicaid in April when CNN and CIR confronted him in the parking lot of his Long Beach counseling center.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Ilouno said little more than &amp;quot;no, no, no,&amp;quot; got in his Mercedes and sped off.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>His attorney later faxed a letter on Ilouno&amp;apost;s behalf saying that counselors acted without the clinic&amp;apost;s consent and that GB Medical will work on paying restitution, &amp;quot;if any.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>The attorney also said Ilouno was a certified counselor &amp;quot;and was thus authorized to bill for medical services rendered.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Los Angeles County authorities said that they were not aware of the arrest and that the clinic notified them that it would close effective July 1.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>A sign on the clinic door says it is no longer providing Drug Medi-Cal services.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Former employees of Tim Ejindu&amp;apost;s clinics in Riverside and Los Angeles counties said they were pressured to falsify documents.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>A Los Angeles County audit of his clinic, the Pomona Alcohol and Drug Recovery Center, found evidence of what the county considers fraudulent practices.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>At his red-tile-roofed counseling center in Pomona, Ejindu declined to answer questions and closed the clinic door on a reporter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>A third operator, Alexander Ferdman, was permitted to open a rehab clinic even after his felony conviction in 2000 for engaging in organized crime in Texas.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>State law calls for felons to be suspended from running Medi-Cal clinics.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Still, Ferdman has drawn millions since opening his clinic in 2003 -- and this year, it got a raise to nearly $2 million in annual funding.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Ferdman stopped in the parking lot of his Panorama City rehab clinic, Able Family Support, to defend his record.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>&amp;quot;I was convicted, but it&amp;apost;s not what it seems,&amp;quot; Ferdman said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>&amp;quot;There was no fraud, and there was no record of it in any way.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a very long story.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>The medical director for Able Family told CNN that the clinic is among those temporarily suspended by the state.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>Ejindu, Ilouno and Ferdman did not reply to letters outlining reporters&amp;apost; findings and seeking additional comment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>