<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="197" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/06/16/health/tony-gwynn-chewing-tobacco/index.html" date_published="2014-06-16 19:16:59" category="health" author="Jacque Wilson, CNN" highlights_mapped="false" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Chewing tobacco in the MLB: Tony Gwynn wasn&amp;apost;t the only one</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="20">Tony Gwynn died at age 54 after battling salivary gland cancer.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="24">He&amp;apost;s not the only MLB player to battle oral cancer.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="7">MLB implemented rules in 2011 but hasn&amp;apost;t banned tobacco use on the field.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_time="26.970001">
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="3">But it wasn&amp;apost;t until 2011 that MLB implemented rules related to smokeless tobacco products.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="1">ESPN reported at the time that the then-50-year-old faced chemotherapy and radiation to fight the &amp;quot;slow-moving but aggressive&amp;quot; cancer in his salivary gland.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="2">Gwynn isn&amp;apost;t the only former ballplayer to battle oral cancer.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>San Diego Padres fans remember Hall of Famer Tony Gwynn&amp;apost;s hitting prowess: 3,141 hits, a .338 batting average and an intense focus at the plate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>What they probably don&amp;apost;t remember is Gwynn using smokeless tobacco throughout his career -- a habit, Gwynn told ESPN in 2010, that he believed gave him cancer.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Gwynn&amp;apost;s use doesn&amp;apost;t specifically come to mind because so many of his fellow Major League Baseball players had the same habit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>A survey administered in 1999 found that close to one-third of rookies starting in the major leagues were already regular smokeless tobacco users.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>More than two-thirds had tried smokeless tobacco.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Other studies found similar rates -- about 30% -- in the majors in the &amp;apost;70s and &amp;apost;80s, though smokeless tobacco use among players began declining in the late 1990s (PDF).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>But it wasn&amp;apost;t until 2011 that MLB implemented rules related to smokeless tobacco products.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Worried about the message it was sending to young fans, MLB collaborated with the Major League Baseball Players Association to prohibit teams from providing tobacco to players.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Players cannot have tobacco tins in their uniforms or do interviews while using chewing tobacco.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Yet the players&amp;apost; union stopped short of banning tobacco use on the field.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Smokeless tobacco is the general term for two products: chewing tobacco and snuff.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Though snuff can be inhaled, most users place smokeless tobacco in their mouth and suck on it, periodically spitting out the juices.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Smokeless tobacco contains 28 carcinogens, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, and is a known cause of oral cancer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Smokeless tobacco is primarily a male habit, the CDC says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>In 2012, approximately 11% of high school boys used smokeless tobacco; only 1.5% of girls did.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Nationally, an estimated 6% of adult men use smokeless tobacco, compared with just 1% of adult women.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;Current use of smokeless tobacco is about half of what it was in the mid-1990s,&amp;quot; the CDC Youth and Tobacco use website states.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;However, only a modest decline has occurred since 2010 and no change occurred between 2012 and 2013.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Gwynn was diagnosed with cancer in 2010.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>ESPN reported at the time that the then-50-year-old faced chemotherapy and radiation to fight the &amp;quot;slow-moving but aggressive&amp;quot; cancer in his salivary gland.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>There is no scientifically established link between smokeless tobacco and salivary gland cancer, according to the American Council on Science and Health.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Doctors don&amp;apost;t know what causes salivary gland cancer, but the Mayo Clinic lists old age and radiation as known risk factors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;The kind of chewing tobacco Gwynn used does have some risk of oral cancer, but not parotid (salivary) gland cancer, which is the kind that took his life at such a young age,&amp;quot; said Dr. Gilbert Ross, the council&amp;apost;s medical director.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Gwynn isn&amp;apost;t the only former ballplayer to battle oral cancer.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Most notably, Babe Ruth, Brett Butler and Bill Tuttle were all diagnosed after years of chewing tobacco use.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Butler became a passionate advocate against tobacco after he returned to the field following treatment, according to the Oral Cancer Foundation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Still, players say the habit is hard to break.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;I use it as a stimulator when I go to hit,&amp;quot; Boston Red Sox star David Ortiz told the Boston Globe.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;But the minute I finish my at-bat, I spit it out.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>It keeps me smooth and puts me in a good mood.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>I don&amp;apost;t do it in the off season.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>I don&amp;apost;t really like it that much, to be honest with you.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Nicotine, the addictive substance found in cigarettes, occurs naturally in all tobacco.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;Over time, a person becomes physically dependent on and emotionally addicted to nicotine,&amp;quot; according to the American Cancer Society.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Those who do try to quit experience withdrawal, often for weeks after their last spit or chew.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Withdrawal symptoms can include irritability, dizziness, depression, headaches and weight gain, according to the American Cancer Society.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
