<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="381" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/09/health/teen-marijuana-use/index.html?hpt=hp_c4&amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;imw=Y" date_published="2014-09-09 22:00:46" category="health" author="Saundra Young, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Teen marijuana use linked to issues later in life</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Study: Teens who use marijuana daily are less likely to get high school diploma.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">Daily teen users 18 times more likely to become dependent on pot, study says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">Study: Adolescents who frequently use marijuana also more likely to use other drugs.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="13">Study fails to show that marijuana use causes these problems, advocate says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-25 08:06:45" annotation_time="43.4385">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Teens who use marijuana daily before age 17 are more than 60% less likely to get their high school diploma than those who&amp;apost;ve never used pot, according to a new study published Tuesday in the journal The Lancet Psychiatry.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2, 3">The study found daily adolescent users were 18 times more likely to become dependent on marijuana, seven times more likely to attempt suicide, and eight times more likely to use other illegal drugs in the future.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="4">Mason Tvert, communications director with the Marijuana Policy Project, said the study doesn&amp;apost;t show using marijuana causes any of these problems; it just underscores a link between individuals who use marijuana and those who experience these types of problems.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Teens who use marijuana daily before age 17 are more than 60% less likely to get their high school diploma than those who&amp;apost;ve never used pot, according to a new study published Tuesday in the journal The Lancet Psychiatry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The study, done by researchers in Australia and New Zealand, is a meta-analysis of three previous long-running studies that included nearly 4,000 participants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Researchers looked at links between frequent cannabis use and seven developmental outcomes up until the age of 30.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>They looked specifically at whether the teens completed high school, got a college degree, were dependent on marijuana, had attempted suicide, were diagnosed with depression, used other illegal drugs and/or relied on welfare to support themselves.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The study found daily adolescent users were 18 times more likely to become dependent on marijuana, seven times more likely to attempt suicide, and eight times more likely to use other illegal drugs in the future.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Researchers also found that while a causal link to depression and welfare dependence was unlikely, heavy marijuana use increased the odds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Evidence was not sufficient, according to the study authors, to support a causal link between marijuana use and suicide.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;The results provide very strong evidence for a more direct relationship between adolescence cannabis use and later harm,&amp;quot; said lead author Edmund Silins with the National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre at the University of New South Wales, Australia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;The findings are particularly timely given the growing movement to decriminalize or legalize cannabis because this has raised the possibility the drug might become more accessible to young people.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The risks increased as the amount of marijuana used increased, according to researchers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>They say those who used marijuana daily are at the greatest risk of poorer outcomes later in life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>However, they admit these studies are limited in their ability to explain what&amp;apost;s behind the associations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Mason Tvert, communications director with the Marijuana Policy Project, said the study doesn&amp;apost;t show using marijuana causes any of these problems; it just underscores a link between individuals who use marijuana and those who experience these types of problems.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;The article expressly states that there remains no evidence that using marijuana causes depression, suicide or dropping out of school,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;It simply shows that teens who are prone to developing these problems are more likely to have used marijuana.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;Nobody wants teens to use marijuana, but it&amp;apost;s quite clear that it poses far less harm to the consumer and to others than the abuse of alcohol or prescription drugs.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The study authors said preventing or delaying cannabis use by teens is likely to have broad health and social benefits.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Policy makers need to be aware that the early use of cannabis is associated with a range of negative outcomes for young adults that affect their health, well-being and also their achievement,&amp;quot; Silins said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;The findings strongly suggest that any reforms to cannabis legislation should be carefully evaluated to make sure they reduce adolescence cannabis use and prevent potentially adverse effects on adolescent development.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>According to the 2013 Monitoring the Future survey done in the United States, approximately 7% of high school seniors are daily or near-daily cannabis users.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The annual study, funded by the National Institute on Drug Abuse, looks at behaviors and attitudes of eighth, 10th and 12th graders.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>NIDA Director Dr. Nora Volkow says she was not surprised by the study&amp;apost;s conclusions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;This analysis is consistent with findings that show heavy marijuana users generally report lower life satisfaction, poorer mental and physical health, more relationship problems, and less academic and career success compared to non-marijuana-using peers,&amp;quot; Volkow said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;The risk of addiction is also higher when use initiates as a teen.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>It is important that we continue to discourage young people from using marijuana.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
