<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="405" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/11/19/health/mental-health-violence/index.html" date_published="2013-11-19 21:41:17" category="health" author="Ashley Hayes, CNN" highlights_mapped="false" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Warning signs parents can&amp;apost;t ignore</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="28, 3">There is hope for parents with a mentally ill child.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="16, 13">Warning signs include anger, depression, withdrawal.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="26">Substance abuse can exacerbate symptoms and paranoia.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_time="15.851001">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">But for many parents of children struggling with mental illness -- a wrenching experience in itself -- it can be a truly chilling scenario.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="2">Increased anger, suicidal thoughts.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="2">Moodiness, depression, substance abuse.</sentence>
      <sentence id="26" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;Typically, the rate of violence among the mentally ill is actually lower than the general population,&amp;quot; he said, but substance abuse can exacerbate existing symptoms such as paranoia, isolation or impulsiveness.</sentence>
      <sentence id="28" ids_highlights="1">There is hope, experts said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A state senator stabbed, his son dead from a gunshot wound.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>A tragedy, to be sure.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>But for many parents of children struggling with mental illness -- a wrenching experience in itself -- it can be a truly chilling scenario.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Virginia State Police on Tuesday said Sen. Creigh Deeds was stabbed after an altercation with his 24-year-old son, Austin &amp;quot;Gus&amp;quot; Deeds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The younger man then shot himself, authorities said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Austin Deeds withdrew from The College of William &amp;amp; Mary last month after being enrolled off and on since 2007, according to a statement from the school.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The Richmond Times-Dispatch reported Tuesday that he had received a mental health evaluation under an emergency custody order on Monday, but was released because no psychiatric bed could be found in the area.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The vast majority of young adults with mental health issues do not become violent, although young adulthood is typically when symptoms of mental illness, including schizophrenia or bipolar disorder, surface, experts say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>However, parents and others can be on the lookout for warning signs of violence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>It can be difficult to predict, said Daniel Davis, a forensic psychologist in private practice in Columbus, Ohio.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>But &amp;quot;over the past 20 years, perhaps especially the past 10, we&amp;apost;ve gotten a lot better at being able to pick up what would be risk factors for aggressive and violent behavior in youth,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Some of those red flags might include:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Increased anger, suicidal thoughts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>A young adult might be increasingly angry or talk of suicide, Davis said, making statements such as &amp;quot;the world would be better off without him&amp;quot; or that his life doesn&amp;apost;t matter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>They may develop an increasing fascination with violence or aggression, and may show contempt for others.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Moodiness, depression, substance abuse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Adults may isolate themselves and withdraw from friends and peers, experts said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Their school or work performance may decline and they may become paranoid.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>They may begin abusing alcohol or drugs, or their use may increase.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>A sign of a psychotic disorder may be the development of seemingly odd interests and beliefs -- in UFOs, for instance, or predicting the future, according to CNN mental health expert Dr. Charles Raison.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is not necessarily predictive of aggression, but these are all things that should not be ignored and should be responded to,&amp;quot; Davis said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Physical changes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>A person may lose sleep because of brain chemistry changes, Dennis Embry, president and senior scientist at the Paxis Institute in Tucson, Arizona, told CNN in 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In the case of psychosis, their appearance may actually change and become stranger and disturbing, according to Raison.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Any of these factors are more concerning, said Davis, if a person has a history of aggressive behavior or substance abuse -- and if they have access to weapons.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;Typically, the rate of violence among the mentally ill is actually lower than the general population,&amp;quot; he said, but substance abuse can exacerbate existing symptoms such as paranoia, isolation or impulsiveness.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>What to do?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>There is hope, experts said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have good evidence-based treatments for these sorts of issues,&amp;quot; Davis said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Those might include cognitive behavioral therapy, substance abuse treatment or medication.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Parents or friends can attempt to discuss problems or symptoms matter-of-factly with a young adult.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>If they are unwilling to seek help, &amp;quot;consult a mental health professional yourself to see if they have suggestions&amp;quot; or specific guidelines for actions you can take, Davis said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Reach out to a mental health center or your primary care doctor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>If the child is in college, consult the college&amp;apost;s counseling center.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Groups like the National Alliance on Mental Illness may be able to provide referrals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Although state laws vary -- and beds are scarce, as seen in Deeds&amp;apost; case -- people can usually be hospitalized against their will if there is clear evidence they intend to commit violence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;In my experience, such hospitalizations can often short-circuit the danger and get people into much-needed treatment,&amp;quot; Raison wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;Of course, this is not always the case.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>But it is the best we can do, and it is a lot better than nothing.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
