<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="201" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/08/08/health/chilean-crusade-legalize-marijuana/index.html" date_published="2013-08-08 11:19:40" category="health" author="Rafael Romo, Senior Latin American Affairs Editor" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Chilean psychiatrist leads crusade to legalize marijuana</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Dr. Milton Flores has gained notoriety in Chile for his crusade to legalize marijuana.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="20">Flores was recently convicted of growing 116 plants of marijuana on his property.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="25">Some Chilean politicians are sympathetic to Flores&amp;apost; cause.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="30">Others favor a tough law-enforcement approach on drugs.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-11 14:53:57" annotation_time="38.859333">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">But in this South American country, it&amp;apost;s his crusade to legalize marijuana that has earned him notoriety.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="2">More recently, Flores was found guilty of growing 116 plants of marijuana on his property in Aguila Sur; he was sentenced last week to 541 days, or more than 18 months, of probation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="3">Some Chilean politicians are sympathetic to Flores&amp;apost; cause.</sentence>
      <sentence id="30" ids_highlights="4">On the one hand, countries such as the United States and Colombia favor a tough, law-enforcement approach on drugs.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>We found him in the foggy mountains of central Chile, near the town of Aguila Sur, conducting a ritual at dusk with two assistants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Dr. Milton Flores, 58, is not the leader of a religious sect or underground cult.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s a psychiatrist who&amp;apost;s unusual in many respects.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>But in this South American country, it&amp;apost;s his crusade to legalize marijuana that has earned him notoriety.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>When asked to describe marijuana, he says it&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;a tool and a medicine.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Flores has used cannabis for years to treat patients with different conditions, including depression and anxiety.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>He also admits he has smoked pot since he was 14.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Flores is Chile&amp;apost;s main advocate for the legalization of marijuana and similar drugs including peyote, ayahuasca and San Pedro.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Flores and other experts call these drugs entheogens.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>They&amp;apost;re all psychoactive plants that were used in Latin America by shamans and healers in religious ceremonies well before the arrival of European conquerors in the 16th century.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Flores&amp;apost; main contention with these drugs&amp;apost; illegal status is that the state gains nothing by criminalizing individuals who use them for medicinal or spiritual purposes the way he does.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Cannabis is neither good nor bad,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;Its use can be appropriate or inappropriate.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a tool that can have very significant effects.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Throughout his career, the psychiatrist has spoken publicly about his position regarding these drugs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s gone to great lengths to make his point.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>His property has been raided twice by Chilean authorities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>In March, police confiscated several marijuana plants at his mountain retreat.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>His case went all the way up to the Chilean Supreme Court, but it was dismissed on a technicality.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>More recently, Flores was found guilty of growing 116 plants of marijuana on his property in Aguila Sur; he was sentenced last week to 541 days, or more than 18 months, of probation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;There&amp;apost;s no willingness to hear the pleas of a citizen who decides to exercise his freedom of conscience and his freedom to grow what is sacred to care for his life,&amp;quot; Flores told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;This to me is the most serious violation that has become evident [by this ruling].&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Not surprisingly, Flores has a significant number of fans among young Chileans, including Oscar Bustamante, a 27-year-old student at the University of Chile in Santiago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;Consuming marijuana, whatever the reason, is totally and absolutely a personal choice and should not be banned as long as the individual doesn&amp;apost;t harm anybody else,&amp;quot; Bustamante says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Some Chilean politicians are sympathetic to Flores&amp;apost; cause.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>A few years ago, a government minister acknowledged he smoked marijuana.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Some senators and representatives followed suit.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>And even though smoking marijuana no longer has the stigma it once had, and smoking it is rarely prosecuted, the country still bans the production, sale, distribution and large-scale possession of marijuana.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The Chilean government is getting pressure from two sides.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>On the one hand, countries such as the United States and Colombia favor a tough, law-enforcement approach on drugs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>On the other hand, liberal politicians advocate making a distinction between public health and national security when it comes to dealing with drugs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a debate that leaders in the United States and other South American countries know well.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Uruguayan legislators have been arguing for nearly a year over a bill that would legalize marijuana.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The bill would give the Uruguayan government the power to regulate the production, sale and distribution of marijuana.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Leftist President Jose Mujica is said to favor the legislation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Former Latin American presidents Fernando Henrique Cardoso of Brazil, Cesar Gaviria of Colombia and Vicente Fox of Mexico have all publicly spoken in favor of legalizing not only marijuana, but several other drugs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>The war on drugs, Fox told CNN in November, &amp;quot;costs a lot of money.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>It costs a lot of lives and blood; it costs a lot of foreign investment lost, a lot of tourism that we have lost in Mexico.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Its effectiveness, the former president says, is questionable at best and countries should take a public health approach to the drug problem.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Patricio Navia, a Chilean-born professor of liberal studies at New York University, says a growing number of legislators in his country favor the idea of decriminalizing marijuana so law enforcement can concentrate efforts on more addictive drugs such as crack.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;The drug problem in Chile has to do with crack,&amp;quot; Navia says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;Among the low-income population, crack is the biggest problem that&amp;apost;s associated with crime.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>People who smoke marijuana don&amp;apost;t go and assault other people in order to get more money to keep on smoking marijuana.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Flores&amp;apost; biggest fan is, perhaps, his own daughter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Carola Flores-Fernandez, a 33-year-old anthropology doctoral student at the University of California-Santa Barbara, says her father&amp;apost;s crusade has opened an important national debate on drugs -- a topic that used to be taboo.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m very proud, and I think it&amp;apost;s something that is slowly changing the perspective of many people in different levels in this country,&amp;quot; Flores-Fernandez says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Back at his mountain retreat near Aguila Sur, Flores says he&amp;apost;s no longer growing marijuana, although he keeps small plants of San Pedro and ayahuasca.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>His hope is that his crusade will allow him to grow and consume these drugs without fear in the near future.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
