<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="213" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/08/30/health/ivf-outlawed/index.html" date_published="2012-08-30 11:10:51" category="health" author="Nadia Kounang, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Could &amp;apost;personhood&amp;apost; bills outlaw IVF?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">An act in Congress says human life begins with fertilization.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">&amp;quot;Personhood&amp;quot; bills have also been attempted at the state level.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="8">These bills could criminalize in vitro fertilization, critics say.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="33">A personhood organization supports freezing and future use of embryos.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 13:15:27" annotation_time="88.195">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">Vice-presidential nominee Paul Ryan was a co-sponsor last year of HR 212, the Sanctity of Human Life Act, which states that &amp;quot;human life shall be deemed to begin with fertilization.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">Similar legislation, known as &amp;quot;personhood&amp;quot; bills, has also been attempted at the state level.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="3">Crtitics say bills like these could also criminalize in vitro fertilization.</sentence>
      <sentence id="33" ids_highlights="4">Personhood USA encourages &amp;quot;snowflake adoption&amp;quot;: the freezing and use of embryos for future use, by either the original parents or another family.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>For the past two weeks, since Missouri Senate candidate Todd Akin uttered the phrase &amp;quot;legitimate rape,&amp;quot; Republicans have had to face questions about their attempts to end abortion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But could these same attempts also outlaw in vitro fertilization?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The Republican Party&amp;apost;s platform states: &amp;quot;We assert the sanctity of human life and affirm that the unborn child has a fundamental individual right to life which cannot be infringed.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Vice-presidential nominee Paul Ryan was a co-sponsor last year of HR 212, the Sanctity of Human Life Act, which states that &amp;quot;human life shall be deemed to begin with fertilization.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Similar legislation, known as &amp;quot;personhood&amp;quot; bills, has also been attempted at the state level.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>According to Resolve, the national infertility association, there are efforts to get personhood ballot initiatives in at least eight states this year alone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Seven states tried to pass bills through their state legislatures this year, but all of them died in the legislature or never passed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Crtitics say bills like these could also criminalize in vitro fertilization.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Both the American Society of Reproductive Medicine and Resolve oppose personhood legislation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;If one of these passes and a physician or lab tech drops an embryo on the floor, have they just committed homicide?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Manslaughter?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>asked Sean Tipton, spokesman for the American Society of Reproductive Medicine.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;In a typical in vitro cycle, there&amp;apost;s more than one embryo created,&amp;quot; explained Dr. Daniel Shapiro, a fertility specialist with Reproductive Biology Associates.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>He appeared last weekend on &amp;quot;Sanjay Gupta, MD&amp;quot; to discuss the issue with CNN&amp;apost;s chief medical correspondent, Dr. Sanjay Gupta.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Shapiro went on, &amp;quot;If you&amp;apost;re being safe and cautious, you only put one embryo -- at most two -- back into a patient at a time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>So what happens with the leftover embryos?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Many of them are frozen, and many of them are never used. &amp;quot;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Keith Mason, president of Personhood USA, agrees that a personhood statute would change IVF.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Personhood USA is a national organization supporting personhood efforts at the state and national level.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;I do believe that declaring a pre-born baby could impact IVF,&amp;quot; Mason said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>He added, &amp;quot;In creating 30 to 60 embryos, and then choosing three or four embryos, that&amp;apost;s selective reduction.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>I think these practices would be affected.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Fertility specialists like Shapiro say they would never create 30 to 60 embryos in a cycle.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>A woman younger than 35, on average, generates only eight to 10 embryos a cycle, he said, and has one or two embryos transferred, while another three are usually frozen.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;Bottom line is, you&amp;apost;re bestowing legal and constitutional rights from the time of fertilization.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>This law won&amp;apost;t ban IVF, but it will ban (doctors) from doing it right,&amp;quot; Tipton said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Reproduction is naturally an inefficient process.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;If a woman is 40 years old and she is fortunate enough (to make) 10 embryos, it is likely only zero or one of them is capable of making a baby,&amp;quot; Shapiro said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>IVF doesn&amp;apost;t make the process any more efficient.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Physicians fear that limiting what happens to the embryos may in turn hinder how physicians work.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Specialists fear that if a bill like this becomes law, it would prompt doctors to limit the number of eggs they take from a donor, as well as the number of embryos they create.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>According to Tipton, &amp;quot;It makes it impossible to do it in the safest and most effective manner.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Personhood USA encourages &amp;quot;snowflake adoption&amp;quot;: the freezing and use of embryos for future use, by either the original parents or another family.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Currently, there is no federal legislation mandating what happens to embryos, but a personhood statute could change that.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;At one extreme, we could be accused of homicide, or negligent homicide, because we&amp;apost;re not taking care of an embryo.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>At the more reasonable level, we could be considered negligent in general,&amp;quot; Shapiro said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Ryan and Republican presidential nominee Mitt Romney did not respond to request for comment on the issue.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Romney actually has a personal stake in reproductive medicine -- in the form of two grandchildren.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>On May 4, his son Tagg Romney posted on Facebook, &amp;quot;Jen and I are happy to announce the birth of twin boys, David Mitt and William Ryder.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Everyone is healthy and happy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>... A special thanks to our gestational surrogate who made this possible for us.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Life is a miracle.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Gestational surrogates usually receive a couple&amp;apost;s IVF embryos and carry the pregnancy to term.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>CNN also reached out to all 54 sponsors of HR 212, the Sanctity of Human Life Act, along with the GOP Doctors&amp;apost; Caucus and the Congressional Pro-life Caucus, and got no response.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>HR 212 has sat in the House Committee on the Judiciary since it was introduced in January 2011 and is believed to have little chance of making it out of committee.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>However, as abortion and reproductive rights continue to make headlines this political season, it maybe worth considering what the outcome beyond abortion may be.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m a little bit dismayed that the folks who are trying to find a wedge against Roe v. Wade are using this particular approach, because it walks right over the backs of about one in eight American couples,&amp;quot; Shapiro said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>&amp;quot;That&amp;apost;s how many people are infertile in this country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>So we&amp;apost;re not talking about a small number of people.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>We are talking about hundreds of thousands of people who seek care in the United States for fertility concerns.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>And these bills interfere with their ability to get good care.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
