<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="362" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/12/22/health/santa-claus-weight/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2012-12-22 14:05:54" category="health" author="Jacque Wilson, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Should Santa Claus still be fat?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="9">CDC: About 12.5 million children age 2 to 19 are obese in the United States.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12, 7">Kids learn healthy habits from those they admire most, and Santa is a role model.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="47">Culture may already be changing with Santa races, healthy gifts .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 16:46:20" annotation_time="33.162" mapping_time_divergence="11.054">
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;Santa is a role model, and kids don&amp;apost;t want to have a role model that&amp;apost;s fat.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="1">Approximately 12.5 million children age 2 to 19 are obese; that extra weight can lead to serious health problems, including type II diabetes, cardiovascular disease and psychosocial issues such as peer discrimination or poor self-esteem.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">Children learn healthy (or unhealthy) habits from those they admire.</sentence>
      <sentence id="47" ids_highlights="3">It&amp;apost;s possible our culture is already changing.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Roy Pickler lay on the floor, dripping with sweat, as trainer Bob Harper quipped, &amp;quot;You look like you got run over by a reindeer.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Pickler&amp;apost;s job as a professional Santa was a constant joke on the latest season of &amp;quot;The Biggest Loser.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>With his long white beard and protruding stomach, the 63-year-old looked every bit the part he played.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>By the time he was voted off the show, Pickler had lost 88 pounds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>During his elimination interview, he donned a Santa hat and told viewers his toned physique wouldn&amp;apost;t stop him from bringing Christmas joy to children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;The world is going to have to change their acceptance of what Santa looks like,&amp;quot; Pickler said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;Santa is a role model, and kids don&amp;apost;t want to have a role model that&amp;apost;s fat.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Since 1980, obesity rates among children and adolescents have almost tripled, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Approximately 12.5 million children age 2 to 19 are obese; that extra weight can lead to serious health problems, including type II diabetes, cardiovascular disease and psychosocial issues such as peer discrimination or poor self-esteem.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The epidemic has gotten a lot of attention in the past few years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Everyone from first lady Michelle Obama to Shaquille O&amp;apost;Neal is trying to figure out the best way to inspire kids to get and stay fit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Children learn healthy (or unhealthy) habits from those they admire.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>And Santa is one of the most recognizable figures in America.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>For at least a month every year, he appears on billboards, storefronts and TV commercials.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Millions of kids stand in line to sit on his comfortably padded lap and whisper secrets in his ear.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>They write letters to him, sing songs about him and read stories about him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>We worry about the effect fast-food advertisements have on students in school.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>With all his free publicity, should Santa still be fat?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;Let&amp;apost;s put it this way,&amp;quot; registered dietician Beth Kitchin said with a laugh.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;I don&amp;apost;t think Santa should be skinny.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>There are a lot of other markers to consider in measuring health.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Research shows that people can have a higher body mass index and still be healthy, Kitchin said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>One can assume Santa is pretty active, wrangling hundreds of elves and nine reindeer every year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>And his cheery disposition says a lot about his stress level, which could relate to low blood pressure.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Of course, Santa does have a penchant for sugary treats.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>One fan estimated the big man eats more than 5,000 tons of cookies on Christmas Eve alone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>If Santa isn&amp;apost;t diabetic, Christmas magic really does exist.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>A 2009 study published in the British Medical Journal determined that Santa could very well be a &amp;quot;public health pariah.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The light-hearted research by Nathan Grills of Monash University in Australia found a correlation between countries that recognize Santa and a high rate of childhood obesity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Santa&amp;apost;s weight is a longstanding tradition, said Tom Kliner, founder of Santas Across the Globe and the Fraternity of International Real Bearded Santas.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The character originated with St. Nicholas, who lived in Turkey during the fourth century.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Nicholas was a wealthy young bishop who started giving away all his gold after his parents died.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;Back in those days, extra weight was a sign of wealth and affluence,&amp;quot; Kliner said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Hollywood used to have a set of numbers -- waist circumference, face shape, beard length -- that Santas were supposed to adhere to, Kliner said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>But around the world, the legendary giver comes in all shapes and sizes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Coca-Cola&amp;apost;s Santa, whom many in America try to emulate, is very round: round face, round nose, round stomach.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>The Santa imitated in Europe is a thinner man with more squared-off features.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Kliner said he sees Santa as more of a public figure than a role model.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;ve never seen anybody aspire to become Santa Claus.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Changing Santa&amp;apost;s iconic image would be hard, said Meg Cox, author of &amp;quot;The Book of New Family Traditions.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Comfort and security come with seeing the same character year after year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;We carry these traditions forward from our childhood,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>&amp;quot;Some of us are pretty emotional about them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>And yet I think there&amp;apost;s nothing wrong with having a sense of play about it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>If you want Santa to be skinny, Cox said, make it happen: Tell your kids Santa is tired of eating cookies, and leave an apple out instead.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>&amp;quot;Having your own take on Santa might be the ultimate personalized Christmas.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s possible our culture is already changing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Santa races are becoming as much of a tradition as candy canes and Christmas lights.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Kids are finding active video games under the tree alongside step counters and organic cookbooks for Mom or Dad.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Pickler recently called a couple of companies he has contracts with and asked whether they were OK with a trim Santa.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>&amp;quot;They both said, &amp;apost;We want you just the way you are.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Your idea of a healthy Santa is the one we want to go with.&amp;apost; &amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>Since &amp;quot;The Biggest Loser&amp;quot; finale, Pickler and his wife, Chris, have spoken to kids across the Midwest about nutrition and exercise.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>Pickler often walks in to schools dressed as Santa Claus and then takes off his suit, Superman-style, to reveal his new fit self.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>In an upcoming documentary about Santas titled &amp;quot;They Wore a Red Suit,&amp;quot; Pickler implores his colleagues around the country to get fit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>&amp;quot;We cannot use (our role) as an excuse, because it influences kids in the wrong direction,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>Maybe one day, instead of a belly that shakes like a bowl full of jelly, Santa will have a six-pack.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>Maybe his cheeks will glow not from the cold but because he&amp;apost;s consuming the recommended doses of omega-3 fatty acids.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="59">
          <content>Maybe Mrs. Claus will take up gardening.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="60">
          <content>(Granted, that would be hard to do at the North Pole, but surely the elves can build a greenhouse or two.).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="61">
          <content>Eventually, in addition to being a role model for the Christmas spirit, our beloved St. Nick could become a healthy role model for kids.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="62">
          <content>Until then, save some cookies -- Santa Claus is comin&amp;apost; to town.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
