<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="155" link="http://www.cnn.com/2011/12/16/health/fistula-tanzania-women-ghfn/index.html" date_published="2011-12-16 19:40:14" category="health" author="David Lindsay, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>&amp;apost;Dead women walking&amp;apost; find hope in corrective surgery</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6">Fistula is a tear between the birth passage and the bladder or rectum.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8, 7">Without corrective surgery, fistulas can leave women incontinent.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="9">Smell and perception of uncleanliness often lead to social isolation .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 16:36:43" annotation_time="55.176334" mapping_time_divergence="18.39211">
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">During the protracted delivery, she suffered an obstetric fistula, which is a tear between the birth passage and the bladder or rectum.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">It leaves the woman, or in this and many cases, girl, incontinent.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">Without corrective surgery it is almost impossible to keep clean and live a normal life.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="3">The smell and perception of uncleanliness often lead to social stigmatization, as it did with Shabiby.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Rukia Shabiby&amp;apost;s shy but cheerful disposition belies an existence seared with pain, embarrassment and isolation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Two-thirds of her 39 years have been spent in a state of despair.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>At age 13, living in Zanzibar off the coast of mainland Tanzania, she was married and became pregnant.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>With her body still developing, Shabiby was unable to bear the child, which was stillborn.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>But that was just the start of her problems.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>During the protracted delivery, she suffered an obstetric fistula, which is a tear between the birth passage and the bladder or rectum.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>It leaves the woman, or in this and many cases, girl, incontinent.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Without corrective surgery it is almost impossible to keep clean and live a normal life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The smell and perception of uncleanliness often lead to social stigmatization, as it did with Shabiby.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The worst part is Shabiby thought she was the only one.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>In fact, the United Nations estimates there are more than 2 million women living with the condition in developing countries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Now, 26 years later, Shabiby is ready for a fresh start.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>She heard a radio commercial by a disability hospital called Comprehensive Community Based Rehabilitation in Tanzania, which is based in the country&amp;apost;s commercial capital, Dar es Salaam.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>There, she could get a free operation to fix her problem.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;One World Bank report called them &amp;apost;dead women walking,&amp;apost;&amp;quot; says Tom Vanneste, the hospital&amp;apost;s deputy director.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;That&amp;apost;s how horrible their condition is, how they&amp;apost;re completely socially excluded and embarrassed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>So they come here very much depressed, very scared, unsure of what their future is.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Later, says Vanneste, they feel liberated: &amp;quot;After surgery they go back home with their dignity restored as new ladies and mothers who can go back out there and have a wonderful life ahead of them.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>As Shabiby sits on a bench outside the fistula ward on her last day at the hospital, she patiently shows Eric Ndambiri a skill she learned while there: crocheting.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Ndambiri is a registered nurse who works on the fistula ward, soothing the women&amp;apost;s fears before surgery and preparing them for a return to society afterward.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>He says Shabiby, like many of the women, is leaving with a mission: &amp;quot;When she goes back she&amp;apost;s thinking that she&amp;apost;s going to be a good ambassador to tell others that even you, who feels the condition is incurable, that somewhere there is a solution for your problem.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Many women in developing countries who get fistulas are from poor rural areas.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Even if they hear they can be cured, they often don&amp;apost;t have the resources to pay the bus fare to Dar es Salaam.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>To solve that problem, the hospital employs what it calls &amp;quot;ambassadors&amp;quot; to look out for ostracized women with fistulas.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>When they find a possible case, they contact the hospital for advice and bus fare.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;When we are sure it&amp;apost;s a fistula patient,&amp;quot; says Vanneste, &amp;quot;we actually use mobile phone money transfer system technology to transfer the money for transport to the ambassador, who basically gets an SMS that says &amp;apost;Look, you&amp;apost;ve received $20 from CCBRT hospital.&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>He converts the e-money into cash, collects the cash, buys the bus ticket for the patient, helps the patient get on the bus, and basically we pick up the patient here at the bus station and operate on her the next week.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>During the two-to-four week rehabilitation after surgery, the women and girls get a chance to bond and hear each others&amp;apost; stories.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Many of them remain in touch once they return home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Others stay in Dar es Salaam for one year, preparing to be more self-sufficient when they return to a world that turned its back on them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Each year, 18 women who have fistula surgery at the hospital are selected to join the Mabinti Training Center, where they learn sewing, printing and jewelry-making.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>They&amp;apost;re also taught how to speak English and run a small business.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;When I came here I said, &amp;apost;Wow this is my new beginning.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>And I have to stick on this so that I can rebuild my life again,&amp;apost;&amp;quot; says Jane Rugalabamu, one of the trainees.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>That new life won&amp;apost;t be alone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Rugalabamu plans to join with several of the Mabinti women to start a business.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>In addition, Rugalabamu plans to spread the word, ensuring that other women and girls don&amp;apost;t spend years, sometimes decades, in isolation for a condition that can be cured with an operation that takes less than two hours.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>David Lindsay is the managing editor of Global Health Frontline News.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
