<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="563" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/09/14/justice/capitol-plot-sentencing/index.html" date_published="2012-09-14 21:29:54" category="justice" author="Carol Cratty, CNN Senior Producer" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Man gets 30 years in U.S. Capitol bomb plot</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Moroccan man was arrested in sting and later pleaded guilty to bombing charges.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">Prosecutors said Amine El Khalifi had donned suicide vest, which was disabled .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="15">Lawyer said El Khalifi has no ill will toward Americans, was relieved plot was thwarted .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-05 13:32:08" annotation_time="129.83266" mapping_time_divergence="43.277554">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Alexandria, Virginia A Moroccan man who admitted to a plot to bomb the U.S. Capitol was sentenced Friday to 30 years in prison.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">El Khalifi was arrested in an FBI sting last February after authorities said he donned a suicide vest and accepted an automatic weapon in a parking garage near the Capitol complex.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="3">El Khalifi has no ill will toward Americans and was relieved his plot was thwarted and no one was injured, Troccoli said, adding that his client admitted culpability to a serious offense but was &amp;quot;enabled&amp;quot; in the plot by two men who he didn&amp;apost;t know were working for the FBI.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Alexandria, Virginia A Moroccan man who admitted to a plot to bomb the U.S. Capitol was sentenced Friday to 30 years in prison.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;I just want to say that I love Allah.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s it,&amp;quot; Amine El Khalifi said before his sentencing at U.S. District Court in Alexandria, Virginia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>El Khalifi, 29, agreed to plead guilty in June to attempting to use a weapon of mass destruction against government property.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Prosecutors and defense lawyers agreed to a sentencing range of 25 to 30 years as part of a plea agreement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>El Khalifi was arrested in an FBI sting last February after authorities said he donned a suicide vest and accepted an automatic weapon in a parking garage near the Capitol complex.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The vest and the gun had been rendered inoperable by law enforcement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;This case is the first suicide bomber in America,&amp;quot; said Assistant U.S. Attorney Gordon Kromberg in arguing for the higher sentence to send a message.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;We cannot wait until there are real dead victims.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Kromberg also referred to the attack on Tuesday by armed militants on the U.S. Consulate in Benghazi, Libya, that killed Ambassador Chris Stevens and three other Americans on the anniversary of the al Qaeda attacks of September 11, 2001.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;We just had an ambassador killed in Libya,&amp;quot; said Kromberg.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;These things can&amp;apost;t be tolerated.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>El Khalifi&amp;apost;s lawyer, Kenneth Troccoli, argued his client should get the lower range of the sentence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;His motive was to do what he thought God had told him to do,&amp;quot; Troccoli said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>El Khalifi has no ill will toward Americans and was relieved his plot was thwarted and no one was injured, Troccoli said, adding that his client admitted culpability to a serious offense but was &amp;quot;enabled&amp;quot; in the plot by two men who he didn&amp;apost;t know were working for the FBI.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Kromberg stressed at the sentencing hearing that El Khalifi was driving the plot and was not pushed into it by undercover officers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>But Troccoli said the undercover agents offered to send martyrdom payments to El Khalifi&amp;apost;s parents in Morocco and also paid off his debts.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>El Khalifi&amp;apost;s religion would not allow him to give up his life while in debt or leave his family in financial trouble, Troccoli said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The attorney also described his client as a young man who came to the United States at 16 as a visitor and liked it so much he stayed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>El Khalifi overstayed his visa and was in the country illegally at the time of his arrest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Troccoli said El Khalifi&amp;apost;s main interest was in mixing music but that led him to a lifestyle that included spending time in night clubs and using drugs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>At his mother&amp;apost;s urging, El Khalifi became more religious and started regularly attending a mosque and reading the Quran, the attorney said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>According toTroccoli, his client thought his religion required him to mount his attack but it didn&amp;apost;t matter if it was successful.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;He has no desire to ever do this again,&amp;quot; said Troccoli.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>But U.S. District Judge James Cacheris asked: &amp;quot;What if God tells him to do this again when he gets out?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Troccoli said El Khalifi believed he had &amp;quot;satisfied his faith&amp;quot; and also noted the plea agreement called for his client to be deported to Morroco after he serves his time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Cacheris nevertheless imposed the maximum sentence under the plea agreement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>According to a statement of facts in the case, El Khalifi changed his mind about what to target and at various times considered a restaurant, a military installation and a synagogue.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>He eventually decided to try to blow himself up in the Capitol, according to the court document, and said &amp;quot;he would be happy killing 30 people.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>El Khalifi admitted performing surveillance at the Capitol and asking an associate, who was secretly part of the FBI sting, to remotely detonate the bomb if he ran into problems with security.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
