<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="508" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/08/29/justice/belfair-school-pta-child-porn/index.html" date_published="2013-08-29 06:15:36" category="justice" author="Leslie Bentz, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Ex-PTA president accused of making child porn at elementary school</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7">School district says the man passed a background check.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8">&amp;quot;This is not something the school could reasonably have prevented,&amp;quot; it says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">Feds were tipped off by investigators in Denmark and Australia.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-12 14:35:27" annotation_time="52.319">
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">North Mason School District Superintendent David Peterson issued a statement Wednesday, describing Navarro as a &amp;quot;school volunteer&amp;quot; who passed a &amp;quot;State Patrol&amp;quot; background check in 2011.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">He also said he has been in contact with the lead FBI investigators, saying &amp;quot;the FBI informed us today that this is not something the school could reasonably have prevented.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">U.S. Federal authorities were tipped off to the information by investigators in Denmark and Australia, who came across a &amp;quot;large number of files&amp;quot; of suspected child pornography, which had been appearing on sites across the globe.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A Washington man is facing federal child pornography charges after allegedly recording and posting online the sexual assault of an 8-year-old girl at an elementary school where he was once the PTA president.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Federal prosecutors say David M. Navarro, 37, shot a cellphone video of the girl performing oral sex at Belfair Elementary School -- and shared it on the web.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Court documents don&amp;apost;t say whether Navarro was the man in the video.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>At the time of the incident, Navarro was the president of Belfair&amp;apost;s parent-teacher association.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Navarro faces multiple charges, including the production, ownership, and distribution of child pornography.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Court documents reveal Navarro was arrested and charged in San Diego in 2009 for &amp;quot;lewd and lascivious acts with a child&amp;quot; as well as &amp;quot;indecent exposure,&amp;quot; but the charges were dismissed due to a lack of evidence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>North Mason School District Superintendent David Peterson issued a statement Wednesday, describing Navarro as a &amp;quot;school volunteer&amp;quot; who passed a &amp;quot;State Patrol&amp;quot; background check in 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>He also said he has been in contact with the lead FBI investigators, saying &amp;quot;the FBI informed us today that this is not something the school could reasonably have prevented.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Peterson assured parents that the North Mason School District &amp;quot;takes the responsibility of the safety and welfare of all students extremely seriously.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>U.S. Federal authorities were tipped off to the information by investigators in Denmark and Australia, who came across a &amp;quot;large number of files&amp;quot; of suspected child pornography, which had been appearing on sites across the globe.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Upon closer inspection, investigators discovered a GPS stamp in one of the videos, with the coordinates matching those of Belfair Elementary School.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Investigators then alerted the FBI, who arrested Navarro four days later.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Court documents indicate authorities were worried that the assaults were ongoing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>An FBI special agent, submitting a letter to the court, alleges that Navarro&amp;apost;s e-mail account was linked to an &amp;quot;account on a website known by law enforcement to post . . . child pornography.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The agent said Navarro appears to have posted at least 14 photos to the website, including one of the girl who appears in the video.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Authorities believe Navarro created at least six videos in which the 8-year-old girl was sexually assaulted.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>U.S. investigators also searched Navarro&amp;apost;s Belfair home Friday, and seized two pairs of boxer shorts, at least 10 computers, and an iPhone 5, which they suspect was used to make the illegal videos.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Navarro is currently jailed, pending a detention hearing, which is scheduled for Thursday at a federal courthouse in Tacoma, Washington.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
