<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="452" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/06/01/justice/florida-supremacists-charges/index.html" date_published="2012-06-01 19:42:11" category="justice" author="the CNN Wire Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Alleged members of white supremacist group charged in Florida</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">More than a dozen alleged members of American Front face charges.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">They are accused of participating in paramilitary training.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">Police documents say they were plotting disruptions in an effort to attract new members.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="15">They were also preparing for a race war, the documents say.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-11 17:14:54" annotation_time="824.28534" mapping_time_divergence="125.0">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1, 2">More than a dozen alleged members of American Front, a down-on-its-luck white supremacist group, were charged Friday in Florida with participating in paramilitary training, prosecutors said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">Faella, police documents say, wanted to stir up media attention to help gain new recruits for American Front, which hate-tracking groups says has been faltering since the death of its leader, David Lynch, in California.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="4">&amp;quot;Faella has stated his intent during the race war is to kill Jews, immigrants and other minorities.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>More than a dozen alleged members of American Front, a down-on-its-luck white supremacist group, were charged Friday in Florida with participating in paramilitary training, prosecutors said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The alleged ringleader of the group, Marcus Faella, was also charged with directing the activities of a gang and teaching paramilitary training, they said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Nine members of the group, including Faella and his wife, Patricia Faella, were charged with conspiracy to shoot at, within or into a building.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>According to police, Faella was planning to stage provocative disruptions at the Orlando City Hall and at a Melbourne, Florida, anarchist gathering that included members of anti-racist skinhead groups.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Faella, police documents say, wanted to stir up media attention to help gain new recruits for American Front, which hate-tracking groups says has been faltering since the death of its leader, David Lynch, in California.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>All but one of the 14 people accused in the investigation have been arrested, according to prosecutors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>That person&amp;apost;s identity is being held pending arrest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;Today, Central Floridians sent a strong message to our communities: the message that criminal behavior whose thesis is hate and intolerance will not be allowed to flourish in our neighborhoods,&amp;quot; said Lawson Lamar, state attorney for the Ninth Judicial Circuit Court of Florida.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Nationally, American Front has had a long and violent history, including the beating death of a Salt Lake City man and a string of 1993 bombings in California, according to hate-tracking groups.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The 25-year-old group enjoyed a resurgence in 2007 under Lynch, described by the Southern Poverty Law Center as a charismatic leader who helped form it in 1987.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>But Lynch was shot to death in his home in March 2011, leaving the group with no clear leader, according to the Anti-Defamation League.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>It has shrunk significantly in the past year, according to the Southern Poverty Law Center.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Most of the group&amp;apost;s 50 or so members appear to live in Florida, according to the ADL.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;Faella views himself and the other members of the AF as the protectors of the white race,&amp;quot; investigators wrote in an affidavit, referring to the group by its initials.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;Faella has stated his intent during the race war is to kill Jews, immigrants and other minorities.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Faella bonded out of jail on Saturday, according to Osceola County, Florida officials.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>His wife was released on Sunday, they said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>According to police, Faella&amp;apost;s group watched videos training them in fighting and the use of AK-47s and other weapons at the compound, which the affidavit said is ringed with barbed wire and protected by pit bulls and firing positions facing the driveway.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The property was meant to become a refuge for white supremacists after the fall of the U.S. government during a race war, investigators wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The group was making body armor and sniper suits and stocking up on supplies in preparation, according to police.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>On at least one occasion, a group member who also belonged to the National Guard provided training to American Front members that he had learned in the military, according to the affidavit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The arrests came on the heels of a two-year investigation based on the reports of a confidential informant who had to flee the fortified compound on April 28, according to the arrest affidavit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>At a meeting to plan the attack on rival skinheads that day, Faella nearly discovered secret recordings the informant had been making of training exercises, according to an affidavit released by police.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
