<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="647" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/05/09/justice/california-police-beating/index.html" date_published="2012-05-09 16:12:10" category="justice" author="Michael Martinez, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Trial ordered for 2 California police officers in beating death of homeless man</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="8">NEW: &amp;quot;This kind of incident is very damaging to the community,&amp;quot; D.A. tells reporters.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">A judge orders two Fullerton police officers to stand trial on all charges.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">Kelly Thomas, 37, who was homeless, was beaten last year in Fullerton, California.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="2">Officer Manuel Ramos and Cpl. Jay Patrick Cicinelli are charged in the death.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-16 16:59:53" annotation_time="39.961666">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2, 3">Santa Ana, California A California judge ordered Wednesday that two Fullerton police officers stand trial in the beating death last year of Kelly Thomas, a homeless man with a mental illness.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="4">Officer Manuel Ramos is charged with second-degree murder and involuntary manslaughter, and Cpl. Jay Patrick Cicinelli is charged with involuntary manslaughter and felony use of excessive force.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;This kind of incident is very damaging to the community -- to everybody, the police, the community -- because it erodes that trust.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Santa Ana, California A California judge ordered Wednesday that two Fullerton police officers stand trial in the beating death last year of Kelly Thomas, a homeless man with a mental illness.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Officer Manuel Ramos is charged with second-degree murder and involuntary manslaughter, and Cpl. Jay Patrick Cicinelli is charged with involuntary manslaughter and felony use of excessive force.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Orange County Superior Court Judge Walter Schwarm scheduled the next hearing in the case on May 22.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Schwarm&amp;apost;s ruling came after a three-day preliminary hearing that ended Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Orange County District Attorney Tony Rackauckas, who&amp;apost;s prosecuting the case, told reporters that he expected defense attorneys to challenge Wednesday&amp;apost;s ruling in a motion and possibly an appeal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Rackauckas said the case &amp;quot;was a terrible incident, and we&amp;apost;re going to proceed forward and get justice.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is a hard thing to file, a case of this nature against police officers, because we have tremendous law enforcement in Orange County,&amp;quot; Rackauckas told reporters.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;This kind of incident is very damaging to the community -- to everybody, the police, the community -- because it erodes that trust.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;It brings down the image of the entire community,&amp;quot; the county&amp;apost;s elected prosecutor said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Ron Thomas, the father of Kelly Thomas, told reporters after the ruling that the Fullerton Police Department &amp;quot;is full of good officers.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s just this band of criminals, these hoodlums,&amp;quot; Ron Thomas added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Ron Thomas noted he and others in his family have worked in law enforcement for &amp;quot;generations.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>He said his son would have &amp;quot;never thought a police officer would beat him to death.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The three-day hearing included attorneys repeating a profanity that Ramos uttered to Kelly Thomas, who had schizophrenia, before a total of six police officers were involved in subduing and beating him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Rackauckas said he repeated the obscenity several times in court to show how Ramos&amp;apost; conduct was &amp;quot;a very far departure from professional and reasonable police&amp;quot; practices.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Kelly Thomas was shirtless and with a backpack when Ramos first approached him in response to a police call that a transient male fitting that description at the Fullerton bus depot was &amp;quot;trying door handles,&amp;quot; attorneys for both sides said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The incident evolved into a police inquiry into &amp;quot;a minor property crime&amp;quot; possibly involving receiving stolen property, Rackauckas told the court.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>During testimony earlier Wednesday, Orange County coroner&amp;apost;s pathologist Dr. Aruna Singhania continuing answering questions for a second day from attorneys for Ramos and Cicinelli about the autopsy she performed on Thomas, 37, after the July incident.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Ramos and Cicinelli have pleaded not guilty to the charges.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Later, in presenting arguments before the court ruling was issued, Rackauckas told the judge that there&amp;apost;s sufficient evidence to put the two officers on trial.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s a very bad day in Orange County when we have to charge two police officers with these kinds of terrible crimes,&amp;quot; the county&amp;apost;s elected prosecutor told the judge.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;They&amp;apost;re sworn to uphold the law, and they&amp;apost;re entrusted with the authority given to them by the state of California.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Defense attorneys objected when Rackauckas continued his comments and started speaking of the &amp;quot;awesome power&amp;quot; with which police officers are entrusted.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is not a press conference,&amp;quot; said attorney Michael Schwartz, representing defendant Cicinelli.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The prosecutor discontinued that line of argument and began addressing other topics after the judge told him: &amp;quot;The court does understand the powers that police officers have, and the level of trust that society places in police officers.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>John Barnett, the attorney for Ramos, argued that prosecutors didn&amp;apost;t provide sufficient evidence to order his client to stand trial.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>On Tuesday, Singhania provided the court with nearly two dozen autopsy photos, prompting Thomas&amp;apost; mother and father to leave the courtroom, as they did on Monday when a videotape of the beating was played.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The 16 minutes of video came from a surveillance camera at a downtown Fullerton bus depot where the incident occurred.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Singhania testified Tuesday that based on her autopsy, medical records and the videotape, she determined mechanical chest compressions with blunt cranial injuries caused Thomas&amp;apost; death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Singhania also testified that Thomas suffered a complete hemorrhaging of his left eye.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Thomas was beaten by police during the July 5, 2011, incident and died five days later, prosecutors say.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The FBI is investigating civil rights violations in the case, as well.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Rackauckas has said that Thomas suffered brain injuries, facial fractures, rib fractures and extensive bruising and abrasions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The county coroner listed his manner of death as a homicide and said he died because he was unable to breathe after having his chest compressed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Ramos, 37, a 10-year veteran of the police department, would face a maximum sentence of 15 years to life if convicted, authorities said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Cicinelli, 39, a 12-year Fullerton police veteran, would face a maximum of four years in prison if convicted.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
