<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="595" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/07/16/justice/zimmerman-verdict-protests/index.html?hpt=hp_t2" date_published="2013-07-16 09:26:17" category="justice" author="Michael Pearson. Holly Yan and Cheri Mossburg, CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Passions on display over Zimmerman verdict</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="32">NEW: Protesters demanding changes to Florida law stage sit-in at governor&amp;apost;s office.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="36, 35">NEW: &amp;quot;This is not over, all is not lost,&amp;quot; Atlanta civil rights leader says at Tuesday event.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="17">Protests against Zimmerman verdict planned in 100 U.S. cities on Saturday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="13">&amp;quot;On Saturday night we lost the battle but the war is not over,&amp;quot; the Rev. Al Sharpton says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 16:52:15" annotation_time="79.628334" mapping_time_divergence="59.721252">
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="4">&amp;quot;Anyone walking or committing no crime can be followed or approached by another civilian and they can use deadly force and say it was self-defense,&amp;quot; the Rev. Al Sharpton said Tuesday in Washington.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="3">Sharpton&amp;apost;s National Action Network is planning 100 protests across the country Saturday calling for civil rights charges against Zimmerman.</sentence>
      <sentence id="32" ids_highlights="1">-- Protesters in Florida staged a sit-in Tuesday at the governor&amp;apost;s office, demanding a special legislative session to consider changes to the Stand Your Ground law, a spokeswoman told CNN.</sentence>
      <sentence id="35" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;Our message to the public is clear,&amp;quot; the Rev. Markel Hutchins said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="36" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;This is not over, all is not lost.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Los Angeles Dismayed, angry but saying they&amp;apost;ll fight in a new struggle for civil rights, protesters marched peacefully Tuesday in Houston, Atlanta and Florida while thousands of Americans found other ways to demonstrate their feelings.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Pro boxer Terrell Gausha told the entertainment news site TMZ that he would no longer wear the American flag.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>News filtered out that entertainer Stevie Wonder said he will no longer perform in Florida so long as the state&amp;apost;s controversial Stand Your Ground self-defense law remains in effect.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>A mocked-up image of Martin Luther King Jr. wearing a hoodie went viral on the Internet.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>And a page on the popular blogging service Tumblr drew hundreds of often poignant essays from people -- many of them white, middle-class and far removed from the civil rights struggle -- who said the death of 17-year-old Trayvon Martin, and Zimmerman&amp;apost;s acquittal, had moved them profoundly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think if I looked like Trayvon I could&amp;apost;ve been shot or arrested or antagonized and hated.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>I could&amp;apost;ve been dead at 17,&amp;quot; wrote one poster who identified himself as a 31-year-old white man.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think if Trayvon looked like me he could&amp;apost;ve grown up to be someone that did something wonderful for the world.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>A Florida jury acquitted Zimmerman Saturday following a nearly four-week trial.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The Hispanic former neighborhood watch volunteer acknowledged shooting and killing Martin last year, but said he did so in self-defense after the teenager attacked him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Critics of the verdict, however, say they believe the jury got it wrong -- that Zimmerman was an overzealous wannabe police officer who racially profiled Martin and hatefully shot him down.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>They want federal civil rights charges and changes to laws like Florida&amp;apost;s Stand Your Ground, fearing a spate of similar incidents.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;Anyone walking or committing no crime can be followed or approached by another civilian and they can use deadly force and say it was self-defense,&amp;quot; the Rev. Al Sharpton said Tuesday in Washington.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;That is something that is frightening and cannot be allowed to sustain itself in our society.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Although Zimmerman&amp;apost;s attorneys did not seek a Stand Your Ground hearing before trial, the judge&amp;apost;s instructions to the jury did allude to provisions of the law, and a juror interviewed by CNN&amp;apost;s Anderson Cooper on Monday said it came into play during deliberations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Call for change.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Sharpton&amp;apost;s National Action Network is planning 100 protests across the country Saturday calling for civil rights charges against Zimmerman.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Similar calls echoed across the Internet.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>As of Tuesday afternoon, more than 490,000 people had signed a MoveOn.org petition started by the NAACP asking for the Justice Department to file civil rights charges against Zimmerman.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Two petitions to the White House seeking such charges had more than 30,000 signatures between them Tuesday morning.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Petitions in support of Zimmerman had a few thousand signatures.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Protests nationwide.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Since the Saturday verdict, protests have occurred across the country, including New York, Washington, Boston, Atlanta, Houston, Las Vegas and Kansas City.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;I was devastated, a little bit heartbroken.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>But this is as much as we can do,&amp;quot; protester Kennan Blair told CNN affiliate WSB during Monday night&amp;apost;s protest there.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>In Cleveland, protesters gathered on the steps of the Cuyahoga County Justice Center carrying bags of Skittles -- the candy Martin had just bought before he was killed, CNN affiliate WEWS reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;I could have been Trayvon Martin,&amp;quot; one African-American teen wearing a hoodie -- the same garment Martin was wearing -- told the station.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;But this case isn&amp;apost;t about racial issues.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>This case is about violence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>This case is about the judicial system.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>On Tuesday:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>-- Protesters in Florida staged a sit-in Tuesday at the governor&amp;apost;s office, demanding a special legislative session to consider changes to the Stand Your Ground law, a spokeswoman told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>-- In Houston, police on horseback and bicycles shepherded protesters staging a protest outside the Harris County Courthouse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>-- In Atlanta, civil rights leaders gathered to denounce the verdict and announce their participation in Sharpton&amp;apost;s planned rallies Saturday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;Our message to the public is clear,&amp;quot; the Rev. Markel Hutchins said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is not over, all is not lost.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>There is still hope and we must continue to fight.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Some protests have turned violent.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>In Los Angeles, police went on emergency footing for the third night in a row Monday after violent demonstrations wracked part of the city, CNN affiliate KCAL reported.They warned over stricter enforcement beginning Tuesady.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>In Oakland, demonstrators threw rocks, bottles and firecrackers at police, Officer Johnna Watson said early Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Authorities arrested nine people there, she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Appeals for calm.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Civil rights leaders appealed for calm out of respect for Martin and his family.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;His name and memory should not be smeared by reckless violence,&amp;quot; Sharpton said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Civil rights leader, John Mack, now a member of the Los Angeles police commission, said those behind the violence &amp;quot;have their own agendas that have nothing to do with justice, and very little to do with Trayvon Martin.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Taking Zimmerman&amp;apost;s side.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Of course, not everyone disagreed with the jury&amp;apost;s verdict.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>On a Facebook page dedicated to discussion of the trial, Facebook user Lorraine Keeley said the jury got it right.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>&amp;quot;The jurors have spoken.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>... kudo&amp;apost;s to this great defense team,&amp;quot; Keeley wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>More controversially, conservative rock singer Ted Nugent called Martin a &amp;quot;dope smoking, racist gangsta wannabe&amp;quot; in defending the verdict in a column for the website Rare.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>&amp;quot;Here&amp;apost;s the lesson from all this, America,&amp;quot; Nugent wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>&amp;quot;Teach your children to not attack people for no good reason whatsoever.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>Conduct yourself in a responsible, civil manner, and everything will be just fine.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>Try to kill someone and that someone just may be exercising his or her Second Amendment rights and you could get shot.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s called self-defense, and it is the oldest, strongest and most righteous instinct and God-given right known to man.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>Meanwhile, Zimmerman&amp;apost;s parents, Robert and Gladys Zimmerman, offered more conciliatory words in an ABC interview.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are deeply sorry for this tragedy,&amp;quot; Gladys Zimmerman said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
