<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="627" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/10/28/justice/aaron-hernandez-mike-pouncey-subponea/index.html" date_published="2013-10-28 12:45:55" category="justice" author="Susan Candiotti and Laura Dolan, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Source: Aaron Hernandez investigation turns to gun trafficking</title>
  <keywords>Mike Pouncey subpoena,Aaron Hernandez investigation</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="8">Source: Grand jury that handed up murder charges considers gun trafficking allegations.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Sources: Former college teammate Mike Pouncey served subpoena after game Sunday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">Second case concerns weapons transported across state lines, second source says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="7">Aaron Hernandez also is charged with murder in the June death of Odin Lloyd.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-12 15:19:25" annotation_time="96.27533">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">The news comes one day after Massachusetts State Police served one of Hernandez&amp;apost;s former college teammates, Mike Pouncey, with a subpoena related to the investigation, sources confirmed to CNN.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">The gun trafficking investigation deals with illegally transporting weapons across state lines and, in part, involves the discovery of an assault-style rifle hidden in a vehicle rented in Florida and later found in Massachusetts, according to a separate law enforcement source.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="4">Hernandez, 23, was charged in August with first-degree murder in the June shooting death of his friend Odin Lloyd.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="1">The grand jury investigating the allegations of gun trafficking is the same one that handed up the murder charge, a source said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Former New England Patriots tight end Aaron Hernandez is being investigated by a Massachusetts grand jury for possible gun trafficking, a source with knowledge of the investigation told CNN on Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The news comes one day after Massachusetts State Police served one of Hernandez&amp;apost;s former college teammates, Mike Pouncey, with a subpoena related to the investigation, sources confirmed to CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>After the Patriots defeated the visiting Miami Dolphins 27-17 at Gillette Stadium, police officers in suits gave Pouncey, a center for the Dolphins, a piece of paper in a hallway between a locker room and the Dolphins&amp;apost; bus, Sports Illustrated first reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The gun trafficking investigation deals with illegally transporting weapons across state lines and, in part, involves the discovery of an assault-style rifle hidden in a vehicle rented in Florida and later found in Massachusetts, according to a separate law enforcement source.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>CNN requested comment from the Dolphins, the NFL, the Massachusetts State Police and the district attorney&amp;apost;s office prosecuting the Hernandez cases in Bristol County, Massachusetts.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Representatives from each declined to comment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Hernandez, 23, was charged in August with first-degree murder in the June shooting death of his friend Odin Lloyd.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The grand jury investigating the allegations of gun trafficking is the same one that handed up the murder charge, a source said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Pouncey, 24, has not been charged in any possible wrongdoing and was asked to appear as a witness.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>He and his twin brother, Maurkice, both attended the University of Florida with Hernandez.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>After Hernandez was arrested in June after the execution-style killing of Lloyd, a photo of the Pouncey brothers at a night club wearing baseball caps that read &amp;quot;Free Hernandez&amp;quot; was posted on Twitter July 14.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Maurkice Pouncey, a center for the Pittsburgh Steelers, later posted a statement, apologizing and saying it &amp;quot;made light of a serious situation.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>According to Sports Illustrated, a Steelers spokesman declined to comment when asked whether Maurkice Pouncey had been served.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The Steelers will play at Gillette Stadium on Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Hernandez was arrested in late June, 10 days after authorities say Lloyd, a 27-year-old semi-pro football player, was killed in North Attleborough, Massachusetts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Authorities have said that Hernandez, Ernest Wallace and Carlos Ortiz picked Lloyd up from his Boston apartment in a rental car shortly before he was found shot to death on June 17 in an industrial park not far from Hernandez&amp;apost;s home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Hernandez pleaded not guilty in September to a charge of first-degree murder.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Wallace and Ortiz have pleaded not guilty to charges of being an accessory to murder after the fact.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Hernandez is also under investigation by a different grand jury in Boston looking into the unsolved 2012 double homicide of Daniel Abreu and Safiro Furtado outside a Boston nightclub.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
