<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="539" link="http://us.cnn.com/2014/10/04/justice/virginia-hannah-graham-case/index.html?hpt=hp_inthenews" date_published="2014-10-04 16:15:53" category="justice" author="Jason Hanna, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Hannah Graham&amp;apost;s mother: Tell us where she can be found</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Parents of missing college student Hannah Graham release video asking for information.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Somebody knows where she is or knows someone who does, mother says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">&amp;quot;Please, please, please help end this nightmare for all of us,&amp;quot; mother says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="8">Suspect is in jail, charged with abduction.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-27 16:49:14" annotation_time="19.08">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">The parents of missing University of Virginia student Hannah Graham issued a new appeal for the whereabouts of their daughter on Saturday, saying despite an arrest in the case, thousands of tips and hours of searches, someone must have critical information yet to be revealed.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;Somebody listening to me today either knows where Hannah is, or knows someone who has that information,&amp;quot; the mother, Sue Graham, says in a video released by the city of Charlottesville, home to the university.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;Please, please, please help end this nightmare for all of us,&amp;quot; she continues.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="4">Matthew, who investigators say is the last person believed to be with Graham, was extradited to Virginia, where he was charged with abduction with intent to defile and is being held in jail.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The parents of missing University of Virginia student Hannah Graham issued a new appeal for the whereabouts of their daughter on Saturday, saying despite an arrest in the case, thousands of tips and hours of searches, someone must have critical information yet to be revealed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;Somebody listening to me today either knows where Hannah is, or knows someone who has that information,&amp;quot; the mother, Sue Graham, says in a video released by the city of Charlottesville, home to the university.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;We appeal to you to come forward and tell us where Hannah can be found.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;Please, please, please help end this nightmare for all of us,&amp;quot; she continues.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;Please help us to bring Hannah home.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Hannah Graham, an 18-year-old in her second year at the university, was last seen September 13 in area of Charlottesville known as the Downtown Mall.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Eleven days later, police in Texas arrested a suspect in the case, Jesse Matthew, 32.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Matthew, who investigators say is the last person believed to be with Graham, was extradited to Virginia, where he was charged with abduction with intent to defile and is being held in jail.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Still, authorities say they don&amp;apost;t know where Graham is.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>They are offering a $100,000 reward leading to her safe return.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>More than 3,000 tips about her possible whereabouts have come in, police spokesman Carter Johnson said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>In the video released Saturday, Sue Graham, standing with her husband, John, thanks everyone who has participated in the search, contributed money to the reward fund, and given tips to police.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>But with their daughter still missing, the Grahams said they felt compelled to plead with anyone who might be hiding information.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;John has already said that this is every parent&amp;apost;s worst nightmare.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>That is true, but it is also a nightmare for our son, James, for Hannah&amp;apost;s grandparents and other members of our family, as well as for all of Hannah&amp;apost;s many friends here in Charlottesville and beyond,&amp;quot; Sue Graham said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>As part of the search effort, police asked owners of large parcels of property in surrounding counties to search their land and report back.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>And searchers have used an aerial drone in the search -- the first time, according to authorities, one has been used to look for a missing person in the state.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The drone, with a high-quality camera, has been used to help searchers check vast tracts of land in the area.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;apost;Link&amp;apost; between Graham case, death of another woman.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Earlier this week, law enforcement sources told CNN that DNA links Matthew to the 2009 death of a different woman in Virginia, Morgan Harrington.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Virginia State Police have said only that there is a &amp;quot;new forensic link&amp;quot; between Harrington&amp;apost;s case and Graham&amp;apost;s.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Harrington, a 20-year-old student at Virginia Tech in Blacksburg, went missing after attending a Metallica concert in Charlottesville in October 2009.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>She was last seen hitchhiking along U.S. 29 outside of Charlottesville, and her remains were found on a farm months later.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>No arrests have been made in Harrington&amp;apost;s case, and the cause of her death still is under investigation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
