<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="620" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/03/26/justice/pennsylvania-church-abuse-trial/index.html" date_published="2012-03-26 17:35:34" category="justice" author="Sarah Hoye, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Sex abuse trial opens for archdiocese official, priest</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Monsignor William Lynn is accused of covering up evidence of sexual abuse.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">Lynn served as the secretary for clergy under the former Philadelphia archbishop .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="11">A grand jury report accused the archdiocese of failing to investigate accusations.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 13:20:08" annotation_time="86.27067">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Philadelphia Opening arguments started Monday in the first case in which a Roman Catholic archdiocese official is accused of covering up evidence of suspected sexual abuse of children.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">Lynn, 61, who served as the secretary for clergy under former Philadelphia Archbishop Anthony Bevilacqua, is charged with endangering the welfare of a child in connection with the alleged assaults.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="3">Last year, a Philadelphia grand jury report accused the archdiocese of failing to investigate claims of sexual abuse of children by priests.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Philadelphia Opening arguments started Monday in the first case in which a Roman Catholic archdiocese official is accused of covering up evidence of suspected sexual abuse of children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Monsignor William Lynn and the Rev. James Brennan appeared before Common Pleas Judge Teresa Sarmina inside a nearly filled Philadelphia courtroom.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The attendees had to pass through a metal detector and surrender all electronic devices before entering the courtroom.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Commonwealth prosecutor Jacqueline Coelho told jurors in her nearly hour-long opening statement that Lynn&amp;apost;s role was to protect priests, the church and privacy &amp;quot;at any cost.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Lynn, dressed in all black and wearing a priest collar, listened intently as Coelho argued that he knowingly covered up incidents of sexual abuse, including alleged acts by Brennan, and &amp;quot;ignored common sense and placed children at risk.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Lynn, 61, who served as the secretary for clergy under former Philadelphia Archbishop Anthony Bevilacqua, is charged with endangering the welfare of a child in connection with the alleged assaults.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>From 1992 until 2004, Lynn was responsible for investigating reports that priests had sexually abused children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Brennan, 48, is accused of assaulting a 14-year-old boy in 1996.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Both pleaded not guilty in April.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Their defense attorneys were slated to give their opening statements Monday afternoon.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Last year, a Philadelphia grand jury report accused the archdiocese of failing to investigate claims of sexual abuse of children by priests.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The grand jury report led to the Philadelphia district attorney&amp;apost;s office criminally charging four Philadelphia priests and a parochial school teacher with raping and assaulting boys in their care, while Lynn was accused of allowing the abusive priests to have access to children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Defrocked priest Edward Avery was slated to go on trial with Lynn and Brennan, but he pleaded guilty last week to involuntary deviate sexual intercourse and conspiracy to endanger welfare of child, according to court documents.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Avery was sentenced to two and a half to five years in prison.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>He is scheduled to report for his sentence on April 2.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The plea agreement does not require Avery to testify against Lynn.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Judge Sarmina advised jurors to &amp;quot;keep an open mind&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;not speculate about&amp;quot; Avery&amp;apost;s absence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The Philadelphia scandal could open a historic chapter in the abuse crisis, church watchers say, by changing the way the American criminal justice system deals with church abuse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The charges are unusual because they go beyond accusations against priests and included a church higher-up charged with covering up the abuse, which church experts say has never happened in the United States before.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Avery and Charles Engelhardt are charged with assaulting a 10-year-old boy at St. Jerome Parish in Philadelphia in 1998 and 1999.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Avery was defrocked in 2006.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Bernard Shero, a teacher at the school, is charged with assaulting the same boy there in 2000.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Engelhardt and Shero, who pleaded not guilty to sexual abuse and conspiracy charges in April, are facing sex abuse charges and will be tried separately in September.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Cardinal Bevilacqua, who died on January 31, testified 10 times before grand juries in 2003 and 2004.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>A final grand jury report said it had no doubt that the cardinal knew about the danger posed by the accused priests and his actions endangered thousands of children in the archdiocese.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Bevilacqua served as archbishop of Philadelphia from February 11, 1988, to October 7, 2003, the archdiocese said in announcing his death.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>He was elevated to the College of Cardinals on June 28, 1991.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Lynn would face a maximum of 14 years in prison if convicted of all charges, according to the district attorney&amp;apost;s office.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>After the release of the January 2011 grand jury report, Cardinal Justin Rigali, who later resigned as Philadelphia&amp;apost;s archbishop, placed Lynn on administrative leave.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>A total of 23 priests in the Philadelphia area have been placed on administrative leave by the archdiocese, 21 on March 7, 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The two other priests, who were retired but were allowed to assist in priestly duties, were placed on leave 23 days later.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>A gag order imposed by a Philadelphia judge remains in effect.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>It bars all parties involved in the criminal case from talking to the media.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
