<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="586" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/08/07/justice/massachusetts-aaron-hernandez/index.html" date_published="2013-08-08 02:08:03" category="justice" author="Susan Candiotti, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Official: Lake search didn&amp;apost;t turn up weapon in Aaron Hernandez case</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">A police search of a Connecticut lake doesn&amp;apost;t turn up the gun, an official says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">A dive team will return to the area next week and search a smaller body of water.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="19">Hernandez&amp;apost;s cousin was charged with contempt of court and jailed.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-26 15:24:26" annotation_time="58.559998">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">The latest police search for the weapon -- at a lake in Bristol, Connecticut -- didn&amp;apost;t turn up the gun, a law enforcement official told CNN Wednesday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">Investigators with a Connecticut State Police dive team who&amp;apost;ve been looking for the gun plan to return to the area next week to search a smaller body of water nearby, the law enforcement official said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="3">Singleton was arrested and jailed on a contempt of court charge, according to jail records.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Weeks after they found Odin Lloyd&amp;apost;s bullet-riddled body in a Massachusetts industrial park, investigators are still searching for a key piece of evidence: the gun used to kill him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Prosecutors have accused former New England Patriot Aaron Hernandez, 23, of orchestrating the death of Lloyd, who was shot five times with a .45 caliber handgun.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The latest police search for the weapon -- at a lake in Bristol, Connecticut -- didn&amp;apost;t turn up the gun, a law enforcement official told CNN Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Investigators with a Connecticut State Police dive team who&amp;apost;ve been looking for the gun plan to return to the area next week to search a smaller body of water nearby, the law enforcement official said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The former standout NFL tight end has pleaded not guilty to murder.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>He is being held without bail.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Authorities have said Hernandez, Carlos Ortiz and Ernest Wallace picked Lloyd up from his Boston apartment in the early morning of June 17.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Surveillance cameras showed the car at an industrial park near Hernandez&amp;apost;s North Attleborough, Massachusetts, home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Lloyd&amp;apost;s body was found in the industrial park later that day.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Ortiz has told authorities that Wallace said Hernandez fired the shots that killed Lloyd, according to a court document.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>As part of their investigation into the high-profile case, police have homed in on Hernandez&amp;apost;s hometown of Bristol.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>And a house there where Hernandez&amp;apost;s uncle and cousin live has become one focal point.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The house is near the lake that police have been searching.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>And court documents say that Hernandez&amp;apost;s cousin, Tanya Singleton, learned of Lloyd&amp;apost;s death at the house, where she allegedly spoke with Ortiz.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>A search warrant affidavit states that Ortiz -- who sources say is cooperating with authorities - says that he and Wallace drove to the Connecticut home, where he told Singleton about Lloyd&amp;apost;s death.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The affidavit also says that Singleton later bought a bus ticket for Wallace.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Wallace was charged with accessory after the fact to murder and has pleaded not guilty.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Ortiz has pleaded not guilty to a weapons charge.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Singleton was arrested and jailed on a contempt of court charge, according to jail records.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The charge is for allegedly failing to comply with a grand jury investigating Lloyd&amp;apost;s killing, the law enforcement official said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>She was released from the Bristol County Sheriff&amp;apost;s Office Women&amp;apost;s Center in Massachusetts on August 1, according to jail records.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>She was transferred to the South Bay Correctional Facility in South Boston the same day and has been held there since, according to Peter Van Delft, spokesman for the corrections facility.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Attempts to reach Singleton and her family were unsuccessful.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>At the Connecticut home, authorities also discovered a dusty SUV suspected of being linked to an unsolved double homicide in Boston last summer, sources told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Hernandez has not been charged with anything in that case, but a law enforcement source has told CNN that Boston police were &amp;quot;very active&amp;quot; -- and making progress -- in trying to connect the dots that could link him to the shooting.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
