<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="579" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/02/23/justice/alabama-honeymoon-trial/index.html" date_published="2012-02-23 20:48:26" category="justice" author="the CNN Wire Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Murder case dismissed in death of newlywed wife</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="13">NEW: Tina Watson&amp;apost;s father says his family is &amp;quot;very disappointed&amp;quot; with the judge&amp;apost;s decision.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">The accused man&amp;apost;s father says, &amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m just thrilled for Gabe&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="7">Gabe Watson&amp;apost;s 26-year-old wife, Tina, died in 2003 while the newlyweds were scuba diving.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="16">He pleaded guilty in Australia to negligent manslaughter and was charged in Alabama.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-26 15:23:25" annotation_time="136.66133">
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="3">His 26-year-old wife, Tina, died October 22, 2003, while the pair were diving at a historic shipwreck off the Great Barrier Reef -- some 9,000 miles from Birmingham, where the two had wed 11 days earlier.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m just thrilled for Gabe, and I just hope everybody can begin to heal, get their lives back together,&amp;quot; said David Watson, calling his son a &amp;quot;good kid.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="1">That sentiment was echoed by Tommy Thomas, Tina&amp;apost;s father, who said &amp;quot;we&amp;apost;re very disappointed&amp;quot; by Nail&amp;apost;s decision.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="4">That same year, in 2008, he pleaded guilty in Australia to criminally negligent manslaughter and subsequently served 18 months in prison in that country.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>An Alabama judge on Thursday abruptly dismissed the murder case against a man accused in the scuba-diving death of his newlywed wife off Australia&amp;apost;s coast.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The decision from Judge Tommy Nail came near the end of the second full week of David Gabriel &amp;quot;Gabe&amp;quot; Watson&amp;apost;s trial in Birmingham.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>According to Ken Glass, the judge&amp;apost;s judicial assistant, Nail dismissed the case &amp;quot;after the state rested its case against Gabe Watson (and) the defense filed a motion for a judgment of acquittal due to a lack of evidence.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m going to grant the defendant&amp;apost;s motion for acquittal.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>This case is dismissed,&amp;quot; Nail said, prompting an outburst of applause in the courtroom.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Afterward, a visibly emotional Watson put his face in his hands, then began hugging people around the room.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>His 26-year-old wife, Tina, died October 22, 2003, while the pair were diving at a historic shipwreck off the Great Barrier Reef -- some 9,000 miles from Birmingham, where the two had wed 11 days earlier.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>His father, David Watson, called the entire situation &amp;quot;terrible, it&amp;apost;s tragic,&amp;quot; while expressing satisfaction with the judge&amp;apost;s decision.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m just thrilled for Gabe, and I just hope everybody can begin to heal, get their lives back together,&amp;quot; said David Watson, calling his son a &amp;quot;good kid.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Prosecutor Don Valeska said &amp;quot;this case is over forever,&amp;quot; since there is no appeal possible.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;I strongly disagree with him,&amp;quot; Valeska said of Nail.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m just extremely stunned, and I&amp;apost;m at a loss for words.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>That sentiment was echoed by Tommy Thomas, Tina&amp;apost;s father, who said &amp;quot;we&amp;apost;re very disappointed&amp;quot; by Nail&amp;apost;s decision.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;There just seems to be a lot more protection for the accused than there does consideration for the victim, which in this case was Tina,&amp;quot; Thomas said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>After his wife&amp;apost;s death, Watson returned from Australia -- where media dubbed him &amp;quot;The Honeymoon Killer&amp;quot; -- to the United States and remarried five years later.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>That same year, in 2008, he pleaded guilty in Australia to criminally negligent manslaughter and subsequently served 18 months in prison in that country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>In October 2010, an Alabama grand jury indicted Watson on two counts -- murder for pecuniary gain and kidnapping where a felony occurred.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Those charges were based on the premise that Watson hatched the plot to kill his wife while in Alabama.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The doctrine of double jeopardy -- which says that a person cannot be tried or punished twice for the same crime -- did not apply because two separate sovereigns, a state government and a foreign government, were seeking to prosecute, said John Lentine, a Birmingham criminal defense attorney and law school professor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>After his sentence was complete, the Australian government held Watson for a short time in immigration detention in light of its policy of not extraditing anyone who might face the death penalty.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Australian authorities deported him back to the United States after getting assurance from U.S. authorities that &amp;quot;the death penalty would not be sought, imposed or carried out,&amp;quot; said Sandi Logan, a spokesman for the Australian Department of Immigration and Citizenship.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Watson was then arrested, in November 2010, in Los Angeles.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>In the opening arguments of Watson&amp;apost;s U.S. trial earlier this month, Assistant Attorney General Andrew Arrington told jurors that Watson had changed his story on what happened several times.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The prosecution also alleged that Watson had expected to gain about $210,000 in insurance and death benefits due to his new wife&amp;apost;s death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;This whole case ... is about murder and gain,&amp;quot; Arrington said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>But defense attorney Brett Bloomston said that Tina&amp;apost;s father was the beneficiary on her workplace insurance policy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Watson filed for some expenses from a travel policy, but it was denied on a technicality, Bloomston said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>His client did sue an insurance company when it denied him an accidental death benefit, the attorney said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;Gabe never stood to gain anything from Tina&amp;apost;s death; he lost,&amp;quot; said Bloomston.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The defense argued that Tina Watson was wearing too much weight with her suit when she died, and that a strong current, her relative diving inexperience and a pattern of anxiety during dives were contributing factors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>During the trial, Judge Nail spelled out what he believed were the basics of the prosecution&amp;apost;s case -- that Gabe Watson had schemed in Alabama to kill his new wife.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;The defendant buys an engagement ring.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>He gives it to his future bride.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>He marries her.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>He plans a trip halfway around the world that&amp;apost;s paid for by him or his family,&amp;quot; Nail said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;And he did all of that, and planned it all here, so he could go over there and kill her so he could get the same engagement ring he purchased?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>After Thursday&amp;apost;s decision, Bloomston called the entire ordeal a &amp;quot;nightmare for Gabe and his family (and) a nightmare for Tina and her family.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;We all wanted justice, we all wanted the court to hear what little information was presented, and the judge determined that it wasn&amp;apost;t enough,&amp;quot; the lawyer told reporters outside the court.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re just very, very happy that Gabe can get some closure and move on, start his life over.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Amanda Phillips, a friend of Tina Watson, said outside the court that she wanted the jury to decide the case and feels that the &amp;quot;only justice that comes is the one that God provides, and we will never be there for that day.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;(Watson) knows everything that happened, he knows how it went down, he knows what was involved, he knows what the intent was, he knows what the feelings were, the motives were,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;He doesn&amp;apost;t need to have a jury tell him what happened.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
