<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="444" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/11/27/justice/voice-of-elmo-lawsuit/index.html" date_published="2012-11-27 20:18:02" category="justice" author="Brad Lendon, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>2nd suit claims Elmo puppeteer had sexual contact with minor</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="19">Plaintiff&amp;apost;s lawyer says client &amp;quot;felt he had a duty to come forward&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">An attorney for Kevin Clash says the cases against his client have no merit.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="20">Clash resigned from &amp;quot;Sesame Street&amp;quot; after the first lawsuit was filed.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="10">Earlier allegations of sexual relationship with a minor against Clash were withdrawn.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 20:05:37" annotation_time="31.052002">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">Clash&amp;apost;s lawyer said the federal cases against his client are without merit.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="4">The suit alleges that the plaintiff suffered psychological and emotional injuries from his sexual relationship with Clash as a teenager and asks for damages from Clash.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="1">Speaking to CNN, Herman said the latest plaintiff &amp;quot;felt he had a duty to come forward&amp;quot; to &amp;quot;shed a light on the truth.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="3">Clash, 52, resigned from his job on &amp;quot;Sesame Street&amp;quot; after the first lawsuit was filed.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A second lawsuit has been filed accusing Kevin Clash, the puppeteer who provided the voice of Elmo on &amp;quot;Sesame Street,&amp;quot; of engaging in a sexual relationship with a minor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>In a lawsuit filed Tuesday in U.S. District Court in New York, a Florida man referred to as John Doe says Clash lured him into a sexual relationship in 2000, when the then-16-year-old came to the New York area from Florida to pursue modeling opportunities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Clash&amp;apost;s lawyer said the federal cases against his client are without merit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;The cases and Mr. Clash&amp;apost;s reputation will be defended vigorously,&amp;quot; attorney Michael Berger said in a written statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Clash made contact with the teen through a gay chat line, posing as a 30-year-old named Craig, the second lawsuit alleges.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>After a couple of phone conversations, Clash invited the teen, who had been staying with relatives in New Jersey during his modeling visit, to spend time with Clash at his Manhattan apartment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>It was there that the sexual contact occurred after Clash supplied the boy with alcohol, the lawsuit says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Clash kept in contact with the teen until the boy graduated from high school, turned 18 and moved to New York City to pursue his modeling career, the suit says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The pair had a sexual relationship at that time, the suit says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The suit alleges that the plaintiff suffered psychological and emotional injuries from his sexual relationship with Clash as a teenager and asks for damages from Clash.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The plaintiff is asking for a jury trial.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s the second lawsuit to be filed against Clash this month.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>In a suit filed November 20, Cecil Singleton alleges that Clash &amp;quot;persuaded, induced, coerced or enticed&amp;quot; him to meet for sexual encounters when he was 15 years old.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>That suit seeks $5 million in damages from Clash, alleging that Singleton &amp;quot;suffered severe injuries, including but not limited to mental, psychological and emotional trauma.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Singleton has said the case is not about the money.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;In fact, I&amp;apost;d like to make him (Clash) an offer.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>If he would acknowledge the relationship we had when I was 15 years old, as well as apologize to any prospective victim out there, and agree to never work around minors, as well as pay my attorneys&amp;apost; fees, I drop the $5 million lawsuit,&amp;quot; Singleton told HLN&amp;apost;s Dr. Drew Pinsky.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Singleton and the latest plaintiff are being represented by attorney Jeff Herman, whose practice is limited to sexual abuse cases.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Speaking to CNN, Herman said the latest plaintiff &amp;quot;felt he had a duty to come forward&amp;quot; to &amp;quot;shed a light on the truth.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Clash, 52, resigned from his job on &amp;quot;Sesame Street&amp;quot; after the first lawsuit was filed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am resigning from Sesame Workshop with a very heavy heart,&amp;quot; Clash said in a written statement at the time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;I have loved every day of my 28 years working for this exceptional organization.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Personal matters have diverted attention away from the important work Sesame Street is doing and I cannot allow it to go on any longer.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>I am deeply sorry to be leaving and am looking forward to resolving these personal matters privately.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Despite his stepping down, Clash&amp;apost;s voice will be used for Elmo through 2014, as the next season of &amp;quot;Sesame Street&amp;quot; has already been filmed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Season 44 will begin airing September 2013 and air for the year, according to a show representative.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Earlier in November, another man who had accused Clash of engaging in a sexual relationship with him as a teenager recanted that claim, issuing a statement saying that it was &amp;quot;an adult consensual relationship.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>When the first accusation emerged, Clash acknowledged a relationship between &amp;quot;two consenting adults&amp;quot; but said the man otherwise was making a &amp;quot;false and defamatory allegation.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am a gay man,&amp;quot; Clash said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;I have never been ashamed of this or tried to hide it, but felt it was a personal and private matter.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Clash was the high-pitched voice of the iconic furry red Elmo, whom he played since 1984, winning Emmy Awards along the way.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>He was the third Muppeteer to take on the role.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
