<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="555" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/04/10/justice/albuquerque-police-brutality-report/index.html" date_published="2014-04-10 21:40:21" category="justice" author="Eliott C. McLaughlin, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Justice Department slams Albuquerque PD&amp;apost;s excessive, deadly force</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6">Justice Department outlines Albuquerque PD&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;practice of excessive force&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">In 2009, officers killed unarmed teen after he&amp;apost;d been shot and was motionless on back.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="28">In nonlethal incident, Taser used on man who doused himself in gas, setting him ablaze.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="15">Report: APD&amp;apost;s failure to ensure officers respect Constitution undermines public trust.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 18:16:40" annotation_time="30.517">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2">Albuquerque, New Mexico, police officers killed a 19-year-old as he &amp;quot;lay motionless on his back,&amp;quot; an unarmed drugstore robber who was walking away from officers and a 25-year-old veteran suffering from post-traumatic stress disorder who threatened to shoot himself in the head.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">The February 2009 incident, which resulted in a $4.25 million payout to Lopez&amp;apost;s estate, is one of several incidents the Justice Department cites in concluding that the Albuquerque Police Department &amp;quot;has engaged in a pattern or practice of excessive force, including deadly force.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="4">The police department&amp;apost;s failure to ensure that officers respect the Constitution undermines public trust,&amp;quot; the report&amp;apost;s summary says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="28" ids_highlights="3">In one instance, officers used Tasers on a man who had doused himself in gasoline, setting him on fire and endangering everyone in his vicinity.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Albuquerque, New Mexico, police officers killed a 19-year-old as he &amp;quot;lay motionless on his back,&amp;quot; an unarmed drugstore robber who was walking away from officers and a 25-year-old veteran suffering from post-traumatic stress disorder who threatened to shoot himself in the head.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>So says the U.S. Justice Department, which on Thursday issued a report lambasting the Albuquerque Police Department for a longstanding history of police brutality and unnecessary deadly force.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The 19-year-old, Andrew Lopez, caught Albuquerque police officers&amp;apost; attention while driving with dim headlights and no taillights; when police tried to pull him over, he led them on a low-speed chase before parking and taking off on foot, the report said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Five officers gave chase, and when Lopez reached a fence and began to turn around, one of the officers fired three times, hitting Lopez once.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The nonlethal shot put Lopez on his back, the report said, and the officer approached him and fired a fourth shot into his chest, killing him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The February 2009 incident, which resulted in a $4.25 million payout to Lopez&amp;apost;s estate, is one of several incidents the Justice Department cites in concluding that the Albuquerque Police Department &amp;quot;has engaged in a pattern or practice of excessive force, including deadly force.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Requests for comment sent to the police department and New Mexico Gov. Susana Martinez&amp;apost;s office were not immediately returned, and Phil Sisneros, a spokesman for state Attorney General Gary King, said in an e-mail, &amp;quot;Our office did not have a role in the DOJ&amp;apost;s report or investigation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>We are looking into a couple of the most recent police-involved shootings, but that is in the nascent stages.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Police brutality in New Mexico&amp;apost;s most populous city made headlines last month when protesters clashed with police in riot gear for more than 12 hours over the fatal shooting of the homeless James Boyd, 38.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>After the protests, Kenneth Ellis, the father of the suicidal veteran killed in 2010, told CNN affiliate KOAT that police brutality had reached &amp;quot;crisis&amp;quot; levels in Albuquerque.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;Our police department is out of control.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>They need help with their tactics,&amp;quot; Ellis said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Thursday&amp;apost;s report did not address the Boyd shooting, which is the subject of a separate federal investigation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;The pattern and practice is the result of serious systemic deficiencies in policy, training, supervision and accountability.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The police department&amp;apost;s failure to ensure that officers respect the Constitution undermines public trust,&amp;quot; the report&amp;apost;s summary says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>In the Lopez case, police said they thought he was involved in a prior incident involving a gun, and the officer who shot him said that when he confronted Lopez, he believed Lopez was carrying &amp;quot;the biggest handgun he had ever seen.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The car Lopez was driving did not match the make, color or type of vehicle used in the previous incident, and Lopez turned out to be unarmed, the Justice Department report says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;For too long, Albuquerque officers have faced little scrutiny from their superiors in carrying out this fundamental responsibility,&amp;quot; the report says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;Despite the efforts of many committed individuals, external oversight is broken and has allowed the department to remain unaccountable to the communities it serves.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>To conduct its review, the Justice Department &amp;quot;reviewed thousands of pages of documents, including written policies and procedures, internal reports, data, video footage, and investigative files,&amp;quot; the report says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>It also interviewed command staff, rank-and-file officers and community members, and held four community meetings where residents &amp;quot;provided their accounts of encounters with officers.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The report had four major findings:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The department&amp;apost;s officers &amp;quot;too often used deadly force in an unconstitutional manner,&amp;quot; and of the 20 fatal police shootings since 2009, most were not constitutional.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Albuquerque police not only use deadly force when there&amp;apost;s no imminent threat of bodily harm or death, they also &amp;quot;used deadly force against people who posed a minimal threat, including individuals who posed a threat only to themselves or who were unarmed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Officers also used deadly force in situations where the conduct of the officers heightened the danger and contributed to the need to use force.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The department&amp;apost;s officers also use less-than-lethal force unconstitutionally.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>A review of 200 use-of-force reports since 2009 indicates that officers use Tasers on people who are nonthreatening, posing minimal threat, passively resisting or &amp;quot;unable to comply with orders due to their mental state.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>In one instance, officers used Tasers on a man who had doused himself in gasoline, setting him on fire and endangering everyone in his vicinity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Officers also use &amp;quot;takedown procedures&amp;quot; in ways that increase harm, and they &amp;quot;escalate situations in which force could have been avoided had they instead used de-escalation measures.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Officers used a &amp;quot;significant amount of force&amp;quot; against people with mental illness and in crisis.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;APD&amp;apost;s policies, training and supervision are insufficient to ensure that officers encountering people with mental illness or in distress do so in a manner that respects their rights and is safe for all involved.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Instances of officers using excessive force are &amp;quot;not isolated or sporadic.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The pattern of police conduct suggests &amp;quot;systemic deficiencies in oversight, training, and policy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Chief among these deficiencies is the department&amp;apost;s failure to implement an objective and rigorous internal accountability system.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Force incidents are not properly investigated, documented or addressed with corrective measures.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>To that end, the Justice Department investigators said they found &amp;quot;only a few instances&amp;quot; of supervisors scrutinizing use of force and seeking investigations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>In almost all of the cases reviewed, supervisors endorsed their subordinate&amp;apost;s version of events even if an officer&amp;apost;s account was incomplete, inconsistent with evidence or &amp;quot;based on canned or repetitive language,&amp;quot; the report said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>The Justice Department lays out several remedies to address the department&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;deficiencies,&amp;quot; including improving use-of-force policies, training procedures, internal investigations, recruitment protocol and how it deals with individuals suffering from mental illnesses.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>The U.S. Attorney&amp;apost;s Office for New Mexico and the Justice Department&amp;apost;s Civil Rights Division launched their probe in November 2012, and then-Police Chief Ray Schultz released a statement saying his department was cooperating with federal investigators.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;We know that we are not always perfect and that there is always room for improvement,&amp;quot; Schultz said in his statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Schultz stepped down in 2013 and was replaced by Gordon Eden, a former U.S. marshal and state public safety secretary, this year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>