<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="580" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/03/18/justice/new-jersey-parents-lawsuit-dropped/index.html?hpt=hp_t5" date_published="2014-03-18 17:31:35" category="justice" author="Laura Ly and Marina Carver, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>New Jersey student drops lawsuit against parents</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="20, 19">NEW: &amp;quot;The case is over. It&amp;apost;s time to move on,&amp;quot; parents&amp;apost; attorney says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Rachel Canning, 18, had sued her mother and father for financial support, college tuition.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="22">She had returned home last Wednesday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="5">She had alleged she was forced to leavehome; parents said she left on her own.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 15:20:03" annotation_time="244.54701" mapping_time_divergence="61.136753">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2">A high school senior who sued her mother and father for financial support and college tuition dropped the lawsuit Tuesday, according to a decision by a Superior Court judge in Morristown, New Jersey.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="4">Canning alleged in her lawsuit that her parents forced her out of their home and that she was unable to support herself financially.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;The case is over.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="1">It&amp;apost;s time to move on.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="3">Neither Rachel nor her parents were at last week&amp;apost;s news conference to announce that she had returned home.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A high school senior who sued her mother and father for financial support and college tuition dropped the lawsuit Tuesday, according to a decision by a Superior Court judge in Morristown, New Jersey.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Rachel Canning, 18, who returned home and reunited with her parents in Lincoln Park a week ago, appeared in court and testified that she decided to dismiss her complaint.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Judge Peter A. Bogaard ruled that Canning&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;decision to dismiss the litigation was a knowing and voluntary decision.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Canning&amp;apost;s parents, Sean and Elizabeth, also were in court.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Canning alleged in her lawsuit that her parents forced her out of their home and that she was unable to support herself financially.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The lawsuit asked that her parents pay the remaining tuition for her last semester at her private high school, pay her current living and transportation expenses, commit to paying her college tuition and reimburse her friend&amp;apost;s parents for legal fees.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Her parents said Rachel left home because she didn&amp;apost;t want to obey their rules.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>A judge denied the teenager&amp;apost;s request for high school tuition and current living expenses from her parents two weeks ago, and a date had been set for April on the other issues in the lawsuit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Canning, an honor student and cheerleader at Morris Catholic High School in Denville, said in court documents that she had to leave her parents&amp;apost; home because of emotional and psychological mistreatment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>She alleged, among other things, that her mother called her &amp;quot;fat&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;porky&amp;quot; and that her father threatened to beat her.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Canning was suspended from school for truancy in October, according to court documents filed by her parents&amp;apost; former attorney, Laurie Rush-Masuret.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Her parents told the teen that she could no longer see her boyfriend, who was also suspended from school.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Car and phone privileges were also taken away.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Once she learned of the punishment, Canning cut school again and then decided to run away, her father said in court documents.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>After receiving allegations that Rachel was being abused, New Jersey&amp;apost;s Division of Child Protection and Permanency interviewed the teen, her parents and her two younger sisters, but it ultimately &amp;quot;determined that allegation of emotional abuse was unfounded,&amp;quot; a letter from the agency states.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>CNN&amp;apost;s requests for comment from Tanya Helfand, the attorney representing the younger Canning in the lawsuit, were not returned Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>A request for comment from John Inglesino, whose family had been paying Rachel&amp;apost;s legal fees and housing her for the past four months, also was unanswered.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Angelo Sarno, the attorney representing Canning&amp;apost;s parents, said in a written statement Tuesday that some level of normalcy has returned to the family.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;The case is over.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s time to move on.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The Cannings want nothing more than to resume their lives as a family,&amp;quot; Sarno said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Neither Rachel nor her parents were at last week&amp;apost;s news conference to announce that she had returned home.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Her parents&amp;apost; attorney, Angelo Sarno, did not comment on what brought the reconciliation or whether Rachel was still in a relationship with her boyfriend.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Canning&amp;apost;s case attracted national attention, which Sarno said would probably continue to affect Rachel.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;Nothing good could have come from this case.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Absolutely nothing good.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>This kid is going to be affected long term from the attention,&amp;quot; Sarno said last week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
