<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="657" link="http://us.cnn.com/2014/09/29/justice/oklahoma-beheading-suspect/index.html?hpt=hp_inthenews" date_published="2014-09-29 14:47:13" category="justice" author="Michael Pearson, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Who is Oklahoma beheading suspect Alton Nolen?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">NEW: Suspect felt oppressed at work, law enforcement source tells CNN.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="29">NEW: No indications of link to terror, another source says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="14">Woman who says she&amp;apost;s Alton Nolen&amp;apost;s sister says &amp;quot;he&amp;apost;s never been a violent person&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="34">Worshipers at the mosque he sometimes attended said he was quiet.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 07:52:39" annotation_time="66.234">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">Nolen allegedly told investigators that he felt oppressed at work -- particularly over not getting a raise, a law enforcement official told CNN on Monday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;He&amp;apost;s always been a people&amp;apost;s person, he&amp;apost;s never been a violent person, so for something like this to have happened, we&amp;apost;re all still in shock right now.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="29" ids_highlights="2">And another law enforcement official told CNN on Monday that there was no indication of a link to terror.</sentence>
      <sentence id="34" ids_highlights="4">Leaders at the mosque he sometimes attended said he was quiet, not outgoing, and that there was no sign of violent tendencies in his personality, according to KOCO and The Oklahoman newspaper.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>He calls himself Jah&amp;apost;Keem Yisrael on Facebook.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But he grew up as Alton Nolen, a good kid raised in a loving home, said a woman who identified herself as the mother of the Oklahoma beheading suspect in an online posting.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Nolen, 30, is expected to be formally charged Monday in last week&amp;apost;s fatal attack at the Moore, Oklahoma, food processing plant from which he&amp;apost;d just been fired.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Police accuse him of beheading one woman and attacking another before being shot by the company CEO, also a reserve deputy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Nolen allegedly told investigators that he felt oppressed at work -- particularly over not getting a raise, a law enforcement official told CNN on Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>While his Facebook page included images of Osama bin Laden and an apparent beheading, there&amp;apost;s no indication that Nolen was motivated by terrorism, a second law enforcement official said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Whatever the motivation, the violent image was at odds with the one offered by those who said they were his sister, mother and friends -- none of whom said violence was part of his personality.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;My son was raised up in a loving home,&amp;quot; the woman who identified herself as his mother said in a Facebook posting Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;My son was raised up believing in God.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>My son was a good kid.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>I know what they&amp;apost;re saying he done, but I&amp;apost;m going to tell you this: That&amp;apost;s not my son.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The video was posted to the Facebook page of a woman named Megan Nolen, who said she was Alton Nolen&amp;apost;s sister.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;Alton, my brother, he&amp;apost;s always been a great person, a loving person,&amp;quot; Megan Nolen said in the post.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;He&amp;apost;s always been a people&amp;apost;s person, he&amp;apost;s never been a violent person, so for something like this to have happened, we&amp;apost;re all still in shock right now.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The brutal attack also seemed out of character to Karla Dunn, who was friends with Nolen&amp;apost;s younger siblings, according to CNN affiliate KOCO-TV in Oklahoma City.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;He was really just a normal person,&amp;quot; Dunn told the station.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;He was polite.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>If you asked him to do something, he did it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>It was like no red flags actually that I could ever think of.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>At some point, that no-red-flags life seems to have taken a turn.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>In 2006, CNN affiliate KOKI-TV in Tulsa reported, Nolen was arrested after a police officer saw him throw bags of crack cocaine and marijuana out a car window as he was being pulled over for traffic violations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Out on probation in 2010, he was stopped for an expired tag when a trooper learned he had outstanding arrest warrants, KOKI reported.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>He struggled with the trooper, then escaped only to be arrested 12 hours later, the station reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In 2011, he was convicted on drug, resisting arrest and escape charges and sent to prison.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>In online prison records related to that incident, authorities note that in addition to a &amp;quot;Jesus Christ&amp;quot; tattoo on his chest and praying hands on his right arm, he had the Arabic words for &amp;quot;peace be upon you&amp;quot; tattooed on his abdomen.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The Facebook page where Nolen posted under the name Yisrael -- confirmed by police to be his -- features a cover photo of fighters holding a machine gun and a rocket propelled grenade launcher.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>It also features numerous messages related to Islam but offers no hint he was planning an attack or that it had anything to do with his religion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The law enforcement official who spoke to CNN on Monday said Nolen had watched beheading videos, but it was unclear if they were linked to ISIS.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>And another law enforcement official told CNN on Monday that there was no indication of a link to terror.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Nolen&amp;apost;s problems at work including getting in trouble for his performance and for trying to convert co-workers to Islam, the second official said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>While it&amp;apost;s unclear when Nolen himself converted, his Facebook page abruptly changed from posts featuring song lyrics, talk about football and other topics to posts almost exclusively related to Islam in April 2013 -- shortly after he was released from prison.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Among the posts are screeds condemning the United States as &amp;quot;wicked&amp;quot; for failing to help Palestinians during the recent hostilities with Israel.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>His last post condemned masturbation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Leaders at the mosque he sometimes attended said he was quiet, not outgoing, and that there was no sign of violent tendencies in his personality, according to KOCO and The Oklahoman newspaper.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;The only time I ever said anything to him was one time,&amp;quot; Saad Mohammed, spokesman for the Islamic Society of Greater Oklahoma City, told KOCO.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;He was in the mosque and he had his Quran and prayer rug on the floor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>And I said, &amp;apost;Hey, pick it up because I don&amp;apost;t want the Quran on the floor.&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>And he picked it up and he sat down.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
