<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="540" link="http://www.cnn.com/2011/11/23/justice/amish-beard-charges/index.html" date_published="2011-11-23 17:34:21" category="justice" author="Alan Duke and Chris Welch" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Hate crime charges filed in Amish beard cutting</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Leader Samuel Mullet Sr. is among those charged in the federal complaint.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">Defendants &amp;quot;forcibly restrained ... Amish men and cut off their beards,&amp;quot; officials say.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="11">Several of the defendants have confessed to local investigators, an affidavit says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 20:12:59" annotation_time="28.752668">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">One of the seven men is Samuel Mullet Sr., the leader of the breakaway sect and a man that local law enforcement and other Amish in the area consider a cult leader.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;In doing so, the defendants forcibly restrained multiple Amish men and cut off their beards and head hair with scissors and battery-powered clippers, causing bodily injury to these men while also injuring others who attempted to stop the attacks,&amp;quot; the Justice Department said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="3">Several of the men have confessed their involvement to local investigators, according to a sworn statement by an FBI agent that was attached to the complaint filed in Cleveland.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Seven members of a breakaway Amish group in eastern Ohio were arrested on federal hate crime charges for allegedly shaving the beards and cutting the hair of individuals who refused to support their leader, according to a criminal complaint released Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>One of the seven men is Samuel Mullet Sr., the leader of the breakaway sect and a man that local law enforcement and other Amish in the area consider a cult leader.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Mullet ruled the group with an iron fist, in some cases &amp;quot;forcing members to sleep for days at a time in a chicken coop&amp;quot; and beating those &amp;quot;who appear to disobey&amp;quot; him, according to an FBI affidavit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Mullet had been &amp;quot;counseling&amp;quot; married women in his sect, &amp;quot;taking them into his home so that he may cleanse them of the devil with acts of sexual intimacy,&amp;quot; the sworn statement from an FBI agent said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Law enforcement officials believe he was behind the various beard and hair cutting attacks of the past few months.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The men charged are said to have carried out &amp;quot;a series of assaults against fellow Amish individuals with whom they were having a religiously based dispute,&amp;quot; according to the Justice Department.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The Amish who were attacked are believed to be former members of Mullet&amp;apost;s group who left over various disagreements.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Mullet wanted to &amp;quot;seek revenge and punish the departing families,&amp;quot; the federal documents said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;In doing so, the defendants forcibly restrained multiple Amish men and cut off their beards and head hair with scissors and battery-powered clippers, causing bodily injury to these men while also injuring others who attempted to stop the attacks,&amp;quot; the Justice Department said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;In the Amish religion, a man&amp;apost;s beard and head hair are sacred.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Several of the men have confessed their involvement to local investigators, according to a sworn statement by an FBI agent that was attached to the complaint filed in Cleveland.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The seven men were arrested as part of a raid on Mullet&amp;apost;s 800-acre compound that went down &amp;quot;without incident&amp;quot; early Wednesday morning, according to Mike Tobin, a spokesman for the U.S. attorney in the Northern District of Ohio.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>A combination of &amp;quot;about 40&amp;quot; officials from various agencies, including the FBI, the U.S. Marshals Service, and the Jefferson County and Holmes County sheriffs, were involved in the raid, Tobin said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Jefferson County Sheriff Fred Abdalla, who was at the raid, said they hit Mullet&amp;apost;s home at 6 in the morning.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Everyone was asleep at the time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;Three guys at first didn&amp;apost;t want to come out of their rooms, but the FBI got them out of there,&amp;quot; Abdalla said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Abdulla said he was happy about the arrest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m elated.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>And I tell you what, so is the Amish community...I&amp;apost;m happy for the Amish people who are so fearful of that guy.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Abdalla added that what made arrests so difficult in this case is the fact that Amish generally don&amp;apost;t believe in dealing with law enforcement, so charges had never been pressed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>While he&amp;apost;s generally happy the arrests were made, part of him is also worried some of the people who live on the compound under his rule will remain &amp;quot;brainwashed&amp;quot; and not have enough will power to move away while Mullet is in custody.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>He urged them to seize the opportunity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;Now&amp;apost;s the chance if you want to get out.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Now&amp;apost;s the time to go,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The defendants appeared in federal court Wednesday afternoon.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>A magistrate ordered them held until a detention hearing, Tobin said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>No date has been set for the hearing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Samuel Mullet&amp;apost;s sect is made up primarily of his relatives living on and around the compound in a remote valley outside Bergholz, Ohio, officials say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The alleged religiously motivated physical assaults were a violation of the Matthew Shepard-James Byrd Hate Crimes Prevention Act, the Justice Department said Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Five of the men were arrested last month on charges of kidnapping and burglary stemming from an incident at the home of Myron and Arlene Miller in early October in which a group of men pulled Myron Miller out of the home by his beard, held him down, and cut off large portions of the beard.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The incident at the Millers&amp;apost; home was one of a handful of incidents in several counties in which as many as 30 men and women carried out similar attacks, Jefferson County Sheriff Fred J. Abdalla said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>When CNN asked the senior Mullet last month if he was behind the beard incident, he responded by asking rhetorically, &amp;quot;Beard cutting is a crime, is it?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>He then denied the allegations that he was running a cult.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Asked about what was, at the time, the start of a federal investigation, Mullet said, &amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re not guilty, so we have nothing to hide.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>If they want to come and check us out, we&amp;apost;d be glad to see them here.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
