<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="651" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/10/31/justice/virginia-tech-shooting-negligence-lawsuit/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2013-10-31 18:54:13" category="justice" author="Bill Mears, CNN Senior Producer" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Virginia Tech mass shooting lawsuit dismissed</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">Plaintiffs initially awarded $4 million each in negligence lawsuit.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">Award later reduced to $100,000 each.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="9">Virginia&amp;apost;s highest court said Virginia Tech that slaughter was not &amp;quot;reasonably foreseeable&amp;quot;.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-14 15:55:11" annotation_time="39.841">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">A county jury had awarded the estates of Erin Peterson and Julia Pryde $4 million each, saying the state was negligent.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">The amount was later reduced to $100,000 per family.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;While words cannot express the tremendous sympathy we have for the families who lost their loved ones in the Virginia Tech shootings of 2007-- including the Prydes and the Petersons -- the Virginia Supreme Court has found what we have said all along to be true: The commonwealth and its officials at Virginia Tech were not negligent on April 16, 2007,&amp;quot; said Brian Gottstein.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A multi-million dollar negligence lawsuit filed by the families of two victims of the 2007 Virginia Tech mass shooting has been dismissed by Virginia&amp;apost;s highest court.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The state justices said Thursday that given the initial uncertainty and confusion surrounding the actions of the student gunman, &amp;quot;there was no duty for the Commonwealth to warn students about the potential for criminal acts by third parties,&amp;quot; meaning gunman Seung-Hui Cho.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>He went on a shooting rampage on the Blacksburg, Virginia, campus that left 32 people dead.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The young man then took his own life.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>A county jury had awarded the estates of Erin Peterson and Julia Pryde $4 million each, saying the state was negligent.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The amount was later reduced to $100,000 per family.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The women were students at the state university.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>There was no initial reaction from the families, but a spokesman for state Attorney General Ken Cuccinelli said the justices&amp;apost; conclusions were proper.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;While words cannot express the tremendous sympathy we have for the families who lost their loved ones in the Virginia Tech shootings of 2007-- including the Prydes and the Petersons -- the Virginia Supreme Court has found what we have said all along to be true: The commonwealth and its officials at Virginia Tech were not negligent on April 16, 2007,&amp;quot; said Brian Gottstein.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;Cho was the lone person responsible for this tragedy.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Cuccinelli is the Republican nominee for governor, and the general election is next Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>At issue was the level of responsibility the state -- including university officials, as well as local and campus police -- should bear for the initial handling of Cho&amp;apost;s actions, which eventually spread out over several hours.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Could his final rampage be reasonably foreseen?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Law enforcement on April 16, 2007, received a call of an incident inside a dormitory around 7:30 a.m. Officers arrived to find two gunshot victims, one fatal, and initially believed it be a &amp;quot;domestic homicide,&amp;quot; not a prelude to far more lethal killing spree to come.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;Police believed that this was an isolated incident that posed no danger to others and that the shooter had fled the area,&amp;quot; said the Virginia Supreme Court&amp;apost;s 15-page ruling.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;They did not believe that a campus lockdown was necessary.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Lawyers for the families had argued if such a precautionary lockdown was imposed immediately -- where students and the university community would be told to shelter in place -- the subsequent massacre inside an academic building may have been prevented or minimized.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The court concluded university officials were engaged and kept informed of the situation over time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Two hours after the initial incident, members of the University Policy Group -- consisting of school administrators -- sent out a campus-wide &amp;quot;blast e-mail,&amp;quot; informing students and faculty of the dorm shooting, and urging those to report anything suspicious.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The mass shooting in Norris Hall began about 10 minutes later, prompting another immediate university &amp;quot;blast e-mail&amp;quot; stating &amp;quot;a gunman is loose on campus.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Stay in buildings until further notice.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Peterson, 18, and Pryde, 23 were among those murdered by Cho in Norris Hall.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>He was later linked to both the residence hall and academic building shootings.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In general under state law, someone does not have a legal duty to warn or protect from someone else the criminal acts of a third person, unless a &amp;quot;special relationship&amp;quot; exists between one or more parties.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Such relations might include those between employer/employee, airline/passenger, or innkeeper/guest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>All such claims of wrongdoing in this context are fact-specific, and the Virginia court here determined the state reasonably -- if incorrectly -- determined the shooter had left the area.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;Based on the limited information available to the Commonwealth prior to the shootings in Norris Hall,&amp;quot; said the seven justices, &amp;quot;it cannot be said that it was known or reasonably foreseeable that students in Norris Hall would fall victim to criminal harm.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>School officials expressed satisfaction with the court&amp;apost;s conclusions, saying the jury&amp;apost;s initial verdict was based on a misreading of state law.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;The court&amp;apost;s actions can never reverse the loss of lives nor the pain experienced by so many families and friends of victims of one person.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>In the end, the cause of these heinous acts and continuing heartbreak was a troubled and angry young man with easy access to powerful killing weapons,&amp;quot; said Lawrence Hincker, associate vice president at Virginia Tech.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The case is Commonwealth of Virginia v. Peterson (121717).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
