<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="529" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/04/08/justice/colorado-theater-reporter/index.html" date_published="2013-04-08 20:24:01" category="justice" author="Jim Spellman, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Fox News reporter urged to reveal source in Aurora shooting</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">Jana Winter reported on alleged Holmes notebook days after theater massacre.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">The FoxNews.com reporter says she will not reveal her sources.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">Suspect James Holmes&amp;apost; attorneys have subpoenaed Winters.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 21:30:31" annotation_time="17.916666">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2, 3">FoxNews.com reporter Jana Winter has been subpoenaed by Holmes&amp;apost; attorneys to testify on Wednesday, but on Monday Judge Carlos Samour Jr. put off a ruling on whether Winter must reveal her source.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">Days after the July 20 theater massacre in Aurora, Colorado, Winter scored a major scoop on FoxNews.com, reporting about the existence of the notebook.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Denver The journalist who first reported about a notebook that James Holmes allegedly sent his psychiatrist before last year&amp;apost;s horrific theater massacre could face jail time for not revealing her sources.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>FoxNews.com reporter Jana Winter has been subpoenaed by Holmes&amp;apost; attorneys to testify on Wednesday, but on Monday Judge Carlos Samour Jr. put off a ruling on whether Winter must reveal her source.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Winter has indicated that she has no plans to identify who told her the notebook from the accused Colorado movie theater gunman was, as she reported, &amp;quot;full of details about how he was going to kill people.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;My reputation as a journalist will be irreparably tarnished among my colleagues and perhaps more importantly my future sources,&amp;quot; Winter wrote in a March affidavit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Days after the July 20 theater massacre in Aurora, Colorado, Winter scored a major scoop on FoxNews.com, reporting about the existence of the notebook.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;The parcel may have sat unopened in a mail room for up to a week before its discovery Monday (July 23), a law enforcement source told FoxNews.com,&amp;quot; Winter&amp;apost;s July 25 article stated.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>She cited a source who said the notebook contained &amp;quot;drawings and illustrations of the massacre.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>At the time of the article, the judge in the case had issued a so-called &amp;quot;gag order&amp;quot; barring officials from speaking to reporters about the case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Other media, including CNN, later reported on the existence of the notebook sent by Holmes to Dr. Lynne Fenton, the University of Colorado psychiatrist who had treated him.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>It has since been discussed in open court, though the contents have not been revealed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Samour said Monday he will not rule on the Winter issue until it is decided whether the notebook is admissible as evidence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>If it is not admissible because it is privileged doctor-patient communication, then the credibility of the police officers who handled the notebook may be irrelevant to the case and not rise to the level required by Colorado&amp;apost;s shield law for forcing journalists to testify.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>But if Winter is ordered to reveal her source and does not, she could be found in contempt of court and jailed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Fenton contacted police in June, a month before the massacre, and told them she had treated Holmes and he &amp;quot;had stopped seeing her and had begun threatening her via text message,&amp;quot; according to a search warrant affidavit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Fenton could face lawsuits that blame her and the school for improperly handling Holmes&amp;apost; treatment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Holmes is charged with numerous counts of first-degree murder for allegedly opening fire inside a movie theater, killing 12 people and wounding dozens more at the premiere of the Batman movie &amp;quot;The Dark Knight Rises.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Federal agents have said the 25-year-old former University of Colorado doctoral student planned the attack for months.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>His trial is scheduled to begin in February 2014.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>If convicted, he faces the death penalty.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Holmes&amp;apost; attorneys have filed a series of motions and hearings in an attempt to find out who leaked the information about the notebook, calling to the stand all the police and bomb technicians who had access to the package.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>All have said they did not speak to any reporters about the package.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Within hours of its discovery, a judge ordered the package to be sealed and it has not been viewed by anyone since.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Saying they have exhausted all other avenues to identify the leaker, defense attorneys subpoenaed Winter.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>She appeared in court last week on the same day prosecutors said they would pursue the death penalty against Holmes, although she did not testify.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Fox News declined to comment on the case or make Winter available for interviews, and an e-mail to Winter&amp;apost;s attorney at Fox News went unanswered.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The gag order is still in place, barring the defense team from commenting.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Winter and her attorneys have tried to fight the subpoena.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The New York-based journalist made it clear in last month&amp;apost;s affidavit that her credibility is at stake if she were to reveal her sources.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;I will be unable to function effectively in my profession and my career will be over,&amp;quot; Winter wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is not an exaggeration - it is a provable certainty.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>She also said she has been subjected to threats on the Internet by supporters of Holmes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Derigan Silver, who teaches media law at the University of Denver, expressed concern that Winter&amp;apost;s case could have a chilling effect on investigative journalism and that journalists may be reluctant to pursue challenging stories that rely on confidential sources.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;As a journalist, you ask yourself, &amp;apost;Do I sit in front of Britney Spears&amp;apost; house and snap some pics or do I cover this really important story and maybe go to jail,&amp;apost;&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Silver argued that investigative journalism is in the public interest and Winter&amp;apost;s case should be a rallying point for everyone interested in a free press.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;If people want good important stories, we have to stand up for the reporters doing those stories,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
