<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="589" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/04/24/justice/oklahoma-court-execution-drugs/index.html" date_published="2014-04-24 17:30:44" category="justice" author="Eliott C. McLaughlin, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Oklahoma executions back on; court keeps drug sources secret</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Inmates had challenged state clause keeping source of lethal injection drugs secret.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Clayton Lockett and Charles Warner are now scheduled to be executed Tuesday .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="7">Defense attorney says there&amp;apost;s no way to know if executions will be &amp;quot;humane&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="15">States scrambled for new drugs after European manufacturers announced ban last year.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-12 15:00:26" annotation_time="107.61267">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1, 2">The inmates, who are being held at the Oklahoma State Penitentiary in McAlester, where they are slated to be executed by lethal injection Tuesday, had challenged the state&amp;apost;s so-called secrecy provision, which forbids disclosing the identities of anyone involved in the execution process or suppliers of any drugs or medical equipment.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="3">Attorney Seth Day, who represents both men, called the ruling unacceptable and told CNN affiliate KFOR that there was no way to know if the prisoners&amp;apost; executions &amp;quot;would be carried out in a constitutional and humane manner.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="4">The constitutionality of lethal injection drugs and drug cocktails has made headlines since last year, when European manufacturers -- including Denmark-based Lundbeck, which manufactures pentobarbital -- banned U.S. prisons from using their drugs in executions.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Clayton Lockett and Charles Warner&amp;apost;s executions are back on the schedule for next week after Oklahoma&amp;apost;s high court lifted their stays, saying they had no right to know the source of the drugs that will be used to kill them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The inmates, who are being held at the Oklahoma State Penitentiary in McAlester, where they are slated to be executed by lethal injection Tuesday, had challenged the state&amp;apost;s so-called secrecy provision, which forbids disclosing the identities of anyone involved in the execution process or suppliers of any drugs or medical equipment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Lockett and Warner also challenged the state Department of Corrections&amp;apost; failure to divulge which drugs would be used, but the department disclosed what drugs it intended to use before the high court&amp;apost;s decision: midazolam, which causes unconsciousness, along with pancuronium bromide and potassium chloride, which shut down breathing and the heart.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The Oklahoma Supreme Court said the only remaining issue, then, is whether the state&amp;apost;s failure to disclose its source for the drugs prevents the prisoners from challenging their executions using the Eighth Amendment&amp;apost;s prohibition on cruel and unusual punishment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The court decided it did not.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;This court holds that the secrecy provision ... does not violate the inmates&amp;apost; constitutional right of access to the courts,&amp;quot; the Wednesday ruling said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Attorney Seth Day, who represents both men, called the ruling unacceptable and told CNN affiliate KFOR that there was no way to know if the prisoners&amp;apost; executions &amp;quot;would be carried out in a constitutional and humane manner.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s not even known whether the lethal injection drugs to be used were obtained legally, and nothing is known about their source, purity, or efficacy, among other questions,&amp;quot; he told the station.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;Oklahoma&amp;apost;s extreme secrecy surrounding lethal injection undermines our courts and democracy.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Attorney General Scott Pruitt applauded the decision, saying the state had a longstanding precedent of keeping the drug sources secret to avoid &amp;quot;schemes and intimidation used by defense counsel and other anti-death-penalty groups.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;These death row inmates have not contested their guilt for murdering two innocent victims nor have they contested their sentences of death.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The legal wrangling of the attorneys for Lockett and Warner has served only to delay their punishment for the heinous crimes they committed,&amp;quot; he told KFOR.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Lockett was convicted in 2000 of a bevy of crimes, including first-degree murder, first-degree rape, kidnapping and robbery in a 1999 home invasion and crime spree that left Stephanie Nieman dead and two people injured.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>In 2003, Warner was convicted for the 1997 first-degree rape and murder of his then-girlfriend&amp;apost;s 11-month-old daughter, Adrianna Waller.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The constitutionality of lethal injection drugs and drug cocktails has made headlines since last year, when European manufacturers -- including Denmark-based Lundbeck, which manufactures pentobarbital -- banned U.S. prisons from using their drugs in executions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Thirty-two states were left to find new drug protocols.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;The states are scrambling to find the drugs,&amp;quot; Richard Dieter, executive director of the Washington-based Death Penalty Information Center, said in November.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;They want to carry out these executions that they have scheduled, but they don&amp;apost;t have the drugs and they&amp;apost;re changing and trying new procedures never used before in the history of executions.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>If Lockett and Warner are executed next week, they would be the 194th and 195th inmates Oklahoma has executed since 1915.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
