<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="451" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/06/20/justice/florida-zimmerman-trial" date_published="2013-06-20 18:57:15" category="justice" author="Graham Winch, HLNtv.com" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>All-female jury to try Zimmerman</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">An all-female jury will hear the Zimmerman murder case.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Opening statements are set for Monday morning.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="8">Zimmerman is charged with killing Trayvon Martin in February 2012.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="9">Zimmerman says he shot Martin in self-defense; prosecutors say he profiled the teen.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-30 14:35:47" annotation_time="35.463">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1, 2">An all-female jury will start hearing the murder case against Florida neighborhood watch captain George Zimmerman next week, with opening arguments in the closely watched trial set for Monday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="3">Zimmerman, a former neighborhood watch captain, is charged with second-degree murder for killing 17-year-old Trayvon Martin in Sanford, Florida, on the night of February 26, 2012.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="4">He says he shot the teenager in self-defense, but prosecutors accuse him of unjustly profiling and killing Martin.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>An all-female jury will start hearing the murder case against Florida neighborhood watch captain George Zimmerman next week, with opening arguments in the closely watched trial set for Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The jury was selected Thursday afternoon after defense attorney Mark O&amp;apost;Mara completed his question-and-answer session with the potential jurors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Opening statements are scheduled to begin Monday morning, Judge Debra Nelson said Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The prosecuting and defense attorneys referred to the jury members as five white women and one black or Hispanic woman.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>CNN does not have access to the juror questionnaires and cannot confirm the ethnicities of the jurors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Four alternate jurors -- two women and two men -- will hear the case as well.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Nelson asked Zimmerman if he agreed with the jurors selected to serve on the panel, and he said he did.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Zimmerman, a former neighborhood watch captain, is charged with second-degree murder for killing 17-year-old Trayvon Martin in Sanford, Florida, on the night of February 26, 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>He says he shot the teenager in self-defense, but prosecutors accuse him of unjustly profiling and killing Martin.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>An initial decision by police not to pursue charges in the case led to the dismissal of the town&amp;apost;s police chief and sparked fresh debates about race relations and gun laws in the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Zimmerman is Hispanic; Martin was African-American.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>O&amp;apost;Mara began the day by explaining the definition of reasonable doubt to the jury pool.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>He said it&amp;apost;s a complicated concept that even &amp;quot;third-year law students&amp;quot; can have difficulty understanding.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>O&amp;apost;Mara questioned the 40 potential jurors about a variety of topics, including their beliefs about gun ownership and their thoughts on self-defense.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>O&amp;apost;Mara pointed out that Florida law states that there is no duty to retreat when being threatened, but Nelson admonished O&amp;apost;Mara, saying she did not want the attorneys interpreting the law for the jurors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Nelson then read to the jury the strict definition of justifiable homicide that they must consider during deliberations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Justifiable homicide is a killing where no criminal liability can result, such as when someone acts in self-defense to protect himself or another person.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>O&amp;apost;Mara finished his questioning of the jury before Nelson broke for lunch.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>When court resumed Thursday afternoon, the attorneys began the process of whittling down jury pool to the six jurors and the four alternates needed for the trial.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Under Florida law, six-person juries hear all criminal cases except capital offenses.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The charges against Zimmerman do not make it a capital case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>After the jury was selected, attorneys representing the Martin family released a statement saying with the makeup of the panel, &amp;quot;the question of whether every American can get equal justice regardless of who serves on their jury panel will be answered.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The statement, from the law firm of Parks and Crump, added, &amp;quot;We firmly believe that when these jurors see the overwhelming evidence that will be put before them in the coming weeks, they will find George Zimmerman guilty of murder on the night in question.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Both sides had the chance to keep or strike jurors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Each side had 10 peremptory strikes -- 10 opportunities to eliminate potential jurors without having to disclose their reasons -- and an unlimited number of strikes &amp;quot;for cause,&amp;quot; for such reasons as bias or hardships.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Court will be in session Friday to handle any outstanding issues before opening statements begin, and Nelson said she try to make a ruling Friday on the admissibility of technology used to analyze the screams on a 911 call from the night of the shooting.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The technology may be key to the prosecution&amp;apost;s case, because their experts&amp;apost; testimony may be able to shed light on what was said between Zimmerman and Martin moments before the teenager was shot.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>If the analysis indicates Martin screamed for help, it could hurt the credibility of Zimmerman&amp;apost;s claim that he acted in self-defense.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The law states that for technology to be admissible, it must be &amp;quot;generally accepted&amp;quot; in that particular field.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Zimmerman&amp;apost;s attorneys are arguing the technology does not satisfy that threshold.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>On June 6, defense expert Hirotaka Nakasone, an audio engineer for the FBI, expressed his doubts about using the recordings.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;A screaming voice is too far for us to address,&amp;quot; Nakasone said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;It might mislead in the worst case.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
