<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="625" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/07/24/justice/black-madam-murder-charge/index.html" date_published="2012-07-24 23:39:26" category="justice" author="Sarah Hoye, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Singer charged with murder in botched cosmetic procedure</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Singer known as &amp;apost;Black Madam&amp;apost; charged with third-degree murder in death of woman.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">British woman, 20, died in 2011 after silicone injection at Philadelphia hotel room.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">Padge Victoria Windslowe already jailed on other charges.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="2">Those charges stem from another alleged illegal cosmetic procedure.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-16 11:36:38" annotation_time="47.9765">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Philadelphia A singer known as &amp;quot;Black Madam&amp;quot; has been charged with murder in the death of a British woman who was injected with silicone at a Philadelphia hotel room last year, the city&amp;apost;s district attorney Tuesday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="3, 4">Padge Victoria Windslowe, 42, is already in police custody on separate charges stemming from another alleged illegal cosmetic procedure, also involving a silicone injection.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">The British woman -- Claudia Aderotimi, 20 -- died in February 2011 from a pulmonary embolism because of complications from a silicone injection to her buttocks, according to the district attorney&amp;apost;s office.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Philadelphia A singer known as &amp;quot;Black Madam&amp;quot; has been charged with murder in the death of a British woman who was injected with silicone at a Philadelphia hotel room last year, the city&amp;apost;s district attorney Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Padge Victoria Windslowe, 42, is already in police custody on separate charges stemming from another alleged illegal cosmetic procedure, also involving a silicone injection.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The British woman -- Claudia Aderotimi, 20 -- died in February 2011 from a pulmonary embolism because of complications from a silicone injection to her buttocks, according to the district attorney&amp;apost;s office.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The cause of her death had previously remained uncertain.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Aderotimi came to the United States from England after seeing an online advertisement for body enhancements by Windslowe, according to the district attorney&amp;apost;s office.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Police said Aderotimi paid $1,800 for buttocks enhancements that were performed in a hotel room, then experienced chest pains shortly after the silicone injection and died a short time later.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Philadelphia District Attorney Seth Williams announced Tuesday that Windslowe has been charged with third-degree murder in Aderotimi&amp;apost;s death, as well as conspiracy, reckless endangerment, possessing an instrument of crime and unauthorized practice of medicine.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;Padge Windslowe&amp;apost;s arrogance and blatant disregard for human life is shocking,&amp;quot; Williams said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;Her conduct cost one young woman her life and placed countless others in danger.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The defendant put her own greed above the public&amp;apost;s health and safety, and instead of being remorseful, she bragged about prospective clients.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>A phone call to Windslowe&amp;apost;s attorney, Christopher Mannix, for comment was not immediately returned.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Windslowe was arrested in March before she was about to host a &amp;quot;pumping party,&amp;quot; at which people pay for illegal silicone injections, police said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>She was being held on $750,000 bail on charges of aggravated assault and deceptive business practices after an illegal injection of silicone was pumped into the buttocks of a 23-year-old woman in February, police said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The woman ended up in intensive care with possible silicone in her lung after paying $1,000 for the procedure, police said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Underground cosmetic procedures have become a growing concern for health regulators.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Investigators have had a difficult time tracking these procedures because they are performed by unlicensed providers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s hard to tell how many people are utilizing that [type] of service,&amp;quot; Tina Tan, a New Jersey state epidemiologist, said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Tan has heard reports of caulk and other products being used in the injections, as well as injection substances being purchased outside of medical supply stores, she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Not surprisingly, injecting these materials can result in serious health complications and death, she warned.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;In our cluster, these patients had to be hospitalized,&amp;quot; she said, adding that such injections should be done by licensed health providers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;We do not recommend going in a hotel room with people who you don&amp;apost;t know their credentials.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
