<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="585" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/06/18/justice/new-jersey-dharun-ravi/index.html" date_published="2012-06-19 00:11:40" category="justice" author="the CNN Wire Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Official: Convicted former Rutgers student won&amp;apost;t be deported</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Dharun Ravi was convicted in May of spying on and intimidating his gay roommate.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">The roommate&amp;apost;s suicide thrust the issue of cyberbullying into the national spotlight.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">Officials reviewed Ravi&amp;apost;s criminal record and opted not to deport him, a spokesman says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-22 16:50:59" annotation_time="52.784332">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">The former Rutgers University student convicted of spying on and intimidating his gay roommate -- who later committed suicide -- will not be deported back to his native India, a U.S. immigration spokesman said Monday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;Based on a review of Mr. Ravi&amp;apost;s criminal record, ICE is not initiating removal proceedings at this time,&amp;quot; Immigration and Customs Enforcement spokesman Ross Feinstein said Monday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">The September 2010 death of Tyler Clementi, and Ravi&amp;apost;s trial this year, thrust the issue of cyberbullying and prejudices against homosexuals into the national spotlight.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The former Rutgers University student convicted of spying on and intimidating his gay roommate -- who later committed suicide -- will not be deported back to his native India, a U.S. immigration spokesman said Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;Based on a review of Mr. Ravi&amp;apost;s criminal record, ICE is not initiating removal proceedings at this time,&amp;quot; Immigration and Customs Enforcement spokesman Ross Feinstein said Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Dharun Ravi, 20, was found guilty in May on all counts including invasion of privacy, witness tampering, hindering apprehension and bias intimidation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>His former roommate, 18-year-old Tyler Clementi, killed himself by jumping off New York&amp;apost;s George Washington Bridge into the Hudson River after learning Ravi had secretly recorded Clementi&amp;apost;s intimate encounter with another man.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The September 2010 death of Tyler Clementi, and Ravi&amp;apost;s trial this year, thrust the issue of cyberbullying and prejudices against homosexuals into the national spotlight.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>While Ravi could have been sentenced to 10 years in prison, New Jersey Superior Judge Glenn Berman instead gave him a 30-day jail sentence, three years of probation and must complete 300 hours of community service aimed at assisting victims of bias crimes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The judge said at the time that he took factors including Ravi&amp;apost;s youth and his lack of a criminal record into consideration when handing down his sentence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>He also did not recommend that Ravi be forced out of the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Berman told the Indian national the only reason he did not recommend deportation was because the man involved in the videotaped encounter with Clementi, identified in court only as &amp;quot;M.B.,&amp;quot; said in his victim impact statement that he did not believe Ravi should be made to leave the country -- and would be willing to write a letter to that effect.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Ravi is a citizen of India who graduated from a U.S. high school and had been studying on a visa at the New Jersey university at the time of Clementi&amp;apost;s death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>U.S. immigrations officials commonly deport non-citizens who are convicted of &amp;quot;certain crimes&amp;quot; like an aggravated felony, domestic violence or drug and weapons offenses, Feinstein said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Immigrations and Customs Enforcement are &amp;quot;legally prohibited from removing individuals who are lawful permanent residents of the United States&amp;quot; if they have not been convicted of such crimes, the agency said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Moreover, an immigration judge must decide whether or not to deport someone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Ravi began serving his 30-day jail term on May 31, two days after apologizing in a written statement for spying on Clementi with a webcam.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>His lawyer filed a notice of appeal of his conviction earlier this month, a New Jersey Middlesex County Court spokesman said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
