<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="544" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/03/14/justice/indian-diplomat-indicted/index.html?hpt=hp_t4" date_published="2014-03-14 21:45:44" category="justice" author="Dominique Debucquoy-Dodley, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Indian diplomat Devyani Khobragade indicted again</title>
  <keywords>Indian diplomat indicted</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Devyani Khobragade is indicted on visa fraud and false statement charges.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Diplomat faces arrest if she returns to the United States.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">Indictment comes days after court dismisses the original indictment against her.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="4">Diplomatic immunity is key defense in Khobragade&amp;apost;s case .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-28 13:28:27" annotation_time="58.386333" mapping_time_divergence="14.596583">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2">New York The Indian diplomat whose arrest sparked a diplomatic row with India has again been indicted by the federal government and faces arrest if she returns to the United States, federal prosecutors said Friday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Devyani Khobragade faces one count of visa fraud and one count of making false statements for allegedly lying on a visa application about how much she paid her housekeeper, according to the indictment filed in a Manhattan federal court Friday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3, 4">The fresh indictment comes just days after the original indictment against Khobragade was dismissed by a federal judge who agreed with her lawyers&amp;apost; assertion that she was protected under diplomatic immunity at the time of the first indictment.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>New York The Indian diplomat whose arrest sparked a diplomatic row with India has again been indicted by the federal government and faces arrest if she returns to the United States, federal prosecutors said Friday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Devyani Khobragade faces one count of visa fraud and one count of making false statements for allegedly lying on a visa application about how much she paid her housekeeper, according to the indictment filed in a Manhattan federal court Friday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>An arrest warrant also was issued, said Jerika Richardson, spokeswoman for the United States attorney&amp;apost;s office for the Southern District of New York.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The fresh indictment comes just days after the original indictment against Khobragade was dismissed by a federal judge who agreed with her lawyers&amp;apost; assertion that she was protected under diplomatic immunity at the time of the first indictment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Federal prosecutors signaled Monday that a new indictment was likely.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Khobragade, who left the United States in January, now works for the Indian Ministry of External Affairs in Delhi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Her attorney, Daniel Arshack, declined comment Friday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;The government of India will respond in due course,&amp;quot; he said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>She was originally arrested and strip-searched by federal agents in New York City in December 2013.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>On January 9, a federal grand jury indicted her on one count of visa fraud and one count of making false statements, the same charges she now faces.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Khobragade filed a motion to dismiss the charges, claiming she was &amp;quot;cloaked in diplomatic immunity at the time of her arrest,&amp;quot; according to court documents.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>A federal judge agreed on Monday, ruling that Khobragade was &amp;quot;appointed a Counselor to the Permanent Mission of India to the United Nations, a position that cloaked her with full diplomatic immunity,&amp;quot; according to court documents.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>She was appointed to that position on January 8, one day before her first indictment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;Even if Khobragade had no immunity at the time of her arrest and has none now, her acquisition of immunity during the pendency of proceedings mandates dismissal,&amp;quot; U.S. District Judge Shira Scheindlin wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;The government may not proceed on an indictment obtained when Khobragade was immune from the jurisdiction of the court,&amp;quot; Scheindlin ruled.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Arshack on Monday said Khobragade was pleased &amp;quot;the rule of law has prevailed.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>India&amp;apost;s external affairs spokesman, Syed Akbaruddin, issued a statement then welcoming the ruling.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Khobragade&amp;apost;s case drew international attention, with Indian officials demanding apologies from Washington, and the United States announcing it would withdraw one official from its embassy in New Delhi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
