<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="609" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/05/21/justice/boston-bombing-tsarnaev-documents/index.html" date_published="2014-05-21 23:06:56" category="justice" author="Catherine E. Shoichet and Deborah Feyerick, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Prosecutors: Tsarnaves used Christmas lights to make bomb fuses</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="8">Documents reveal new details about the Boston Marathon bombings and aftermath.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12">Prosecutors argue that information Tsarnaev gave to FBI should be admissible.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="31">Tsarnaev&amp;apost;s attorneys ask judge to throw out evidence, arguing it was coerced.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-10 14:43:39" annotation_time="31.214666">
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="1">It&amp;apost;s not time yet for prosecutors to make their full case against Dzhokhar Tsarnaev, but as attorneys spar over what evidence can be used in the high-profile death penalty case against him, the description of what materials were used to make the bombs was among several new details about last year&amp;apost;s terror attack and its aftermath included in court documents.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">In their 29-page motion, prosecutors detail Tsarnaev&amp;apost;s medical care while at Boston&amp;apost;s Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center, arguing that information from more than 11 hours of FBI interrogations while he was hospitalized should be admissible.</sentence>
      <sentence id="31" ids_highlights="3">Tsarnaev&amp;apost;s attorneys have said that evidence from the hospital interrogations shouldn&amp;apost;t be allowed in court, arguing that he was coerced into making incriminating statements.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The Boston Marathon bombing suspects used Christmas lights and model-car parts to make the explosives, prosecutors said in court documents obtained by CNN on Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Marathon bombs were constructed using improvised fuses made from Christmas lights and improvised, remote-control detonators fashioned from model car parts,&amp;quot; federal prosecutors said in a motion filed Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;These relatively sophisticated devices would have been difficult for the Tsarnaevs to fabricate successfully without training or assistance from others.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>To obtain explosive fuel for the pressure cooker bombs, the filing says, brothers Dzhokhar and Tamerlan Tsarnaev &amp;quot;appeared to have crushed and emptied hundreds of individual fireworks containing black powder.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Authorities say Tamerlan and Dzhokhar Tsarnaev, 20, planted bombs at the finish line of the 2013 race.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Tamerlan Tsarnaev was killed during the manhunt that paralyzed Boston.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Dzhokhar Tsarnaev has pleaded not guilty to killing four people and wounding more than 200.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s not time yet for prosecutors to make their full case against Dzhokhar Tsarnaev, but as attorneys spar over what evidence can be used in the high-profile death penalty case against him, the description of what materials were used to make the bombs was among several new details about last year&amp;apost;s terror attack and its aftermath included in court documents.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The motion also includes additional details about the note Dzhokhar Tsarnaev allegedly wrote while he was hiding out inside a boat in a backyard in Watertown, Massachusetts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;God has a plan for each person,&amp;quot; Tsarnaev wrote, according to the court document.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;Mine was to hide in this boat and shed some light on our actions.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>In their 29-page motion, prosecutors detail Tsarnaev&amp;apost;s medical care while at Boston&amp;apost;s Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center, arguing that information from more than 11 hours of FBI interrogations while he was hospitalized should be admissible.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Prosecutors cite several reasons why they needed to question Tsarnaev without reading him his Miranda rights against self-incrimination and without allowing him access to a lawyer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Evidence law enforcement had at the time, they argue, suggested a possible larger conspiracy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>FBI agents had &amp;quot;reason to believe that the Tsarnaevs had accomplices and that they or others might have built additional bombs that posed a continuing danger to public safety.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The note scribbled inside the boat referred to others, saying, &amp;quot;we are promised victory and we shall surely get it,&amp;quot; according to Wednesday&amp;apost;s motion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Also, a search of the Tsarnaevs&amp;apost; homes failed to uncover traces of the black firework powder used to build the pressure cooker bombs, suggesting that it had been built elsewhere and with help.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The Christmas lights used as fuses and the model-car remote control used to detonate the devices also suggested a level of sophistication that suggested terrorist training, prosecutors said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Tsarnaev was lucid while hospitalized and was not coerced into making any of the statements, they argue.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>According to the court documents, Tsarnaev was questioned about 22 hours after undergoing surgery for multiple gunshot wounds.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>He had been weaned off the sedative propofol but was still on pain medication.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>FBI agents questioned him on and off over a nearly 38-hour period, conducting 14 interviews and giving Tsarnaev frequent breaks, including a 10½-hour stretch so he could sleep, the court documents say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Prosecutors say the FBI&amp;apost;s interview took time because doctors had performed a tracheostomy to allow greater airflow.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Tsarnaev initially answered by nodding or writing in a notebook and then later spoke his answers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Although Tsarnaev denied that anyone else was involved, authorities believed he might be lying or concealing the involvement of others, according to prosecutors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Government officials have maintained that Tsarnaev was questioned under the &amp;quot;public safety&amp;quot; exception to the Miranda warnings, which allows for limited questioning of a suspect by law enforcement to determine whether there is imminent danger of an attack.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;The fact that Tsarnaev was in the hospital recovering from bullet wounds does not mean the interview was coercive or that the agents who conducted it did anything wrong,&amp;quot; the prosecutors&amp;apost; motion says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Tsarnaev, prosecutors allege, wanted to explain the bombings and take credit for them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;As the note he wrote in Watertown on the inside of the boat reflects, Tsarnaev was eager to take credit for his crimes and &amp;apost;shed some light&amp;apost; on their meaning.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>That indeed is a common practice among terrorists,&amp;quot; the motion says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Tsarnaev&amp;apost;s attorneys have said that evidence from the hospital interrogations shouldn&amp;apost;t be allowed in court, arguing that he was coerced into making incriminating statements.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>They argue that the statements were involuntary, that the public safety exception agents used didn&amp;apost;t apply to the interrogation and that Tsarnaev&amp;apost;s first court appearance was postponed to allow for additional questioning.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>FBI agents questioned Tsarnaev, his attorneys argue, &amp;quot;despite the fact that he quickly allayed concerns about any continuing threats to public safety, repeatedly requested a lawyer, and begged to rest as he recovered from emergency surgery and underwent continuing treatment for multiple and serious gunshot wounds.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>They also argue that the FBI agents deliberately misled Tsarnaev about his brother&amp;apost;s death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Prosecutors say that FBI agents didn&amp;apost;t tell Tsarnaev about his brother&amp;apost;s death &amp;quot;or the manner of that death, to spare him emotional trauma.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>CNN first learned of the new court documents from multiple local media reports on Twitter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>