<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="605" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/04/23/justice/pennsylvania-church-abuse-trial/index.html" date_published="2012-04-23 23:09:13" category="justice" author="Sarah Hoye, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Priest&amp;apost;s guilty plea throws wrinkle into Philadelphia sexual abuse trial</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Defense, prosecution argue about which witnesses jurors should be allowed to hear.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">James Brennan accused of attempted rape; William Lynn accused of cover-up .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">Defrocked priest Edward Avery pleaded guilty days before opening remarks.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="8">Jurors were told Avery is no longer on trial; they have not been told why.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 20:17:37" annotation_time="16.907667">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1, 3">Philadelphia Attorneys in the child sexual abuse and conspiracy trial of two Philadelphia priests debated Monday over which potential witnesses jurors would be allowed to hear regarding a third defendant who pleaded guilty to molesting boys just days before opening remarks.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">The Rev. James Brennan is accused of attempted rape of a 14-year-old, and Monsignor William Lynn is accused of covering it up.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="4">Although jurors were told Avery is no longer on trial, they have not been told why.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Philadelphia Attorneys in the child sexual abuse and conspiracy trial of two Philadelphia priests debated Monday over which potential witnesses jurors would be allowed to hear regarding a third defendant who pleaded guilty to molesting boys just days before opening remarks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Defrocked priest Edward Avery of the Philadelphia Archdiocese pleaded guilty to involuntary deviate sexual intercourse and conspiracy to endanger the welfare of child after admitting that he sexually assaulted a 10-year-old altar boy during the 1998-1999 school year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Avery, 69, was sentenced to two-and-a-half to five years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The Rev. James Brennan is accused of attempted rape of a 14-year-old, and Monsignor William Lynn is accused of covering it up.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Lynn is the first high-ranking church figure charged with child endangerment for shuffling predator priests from parish to parish.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Lynn is accused of knowingly allowing Avery and Brennan access to children despite allegations of sexual abuse of minors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Both have pleaded not guilty.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Although jurors were told Avery is no longer on trial, they have not been told why.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>His guilty plea does not require him to testify.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Prosecutors said Monday the former altar boy whom Avery admitted molesting in the church sacristy is scheduled to take the witness stand this week.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>He was abused six years after the archdiocese learned Avery had abused someone else.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Assistant District Attorney Patrick Blessington argued that if Lynn&amp;apost;s defense attorneys &amp;quot;attacked the creditability&amp;quot; of the witness, the Commonwealth would be allowed to tell the jury Avery pleaded guilty.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;Monsignor Lynn put a powder keg out there,&amp;quot; Blessington said while the jurors were out of the courtroom.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Defense attorney Jeff Lindy dismissed that claim, arguing that allowing jurors to hear Avery&amp;apost;s plea or having other witnesses alleging abuse after Lynn left his post as secretary of clergy put his client at a disadvantage.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;It doesn&amp;apost;t shine any light on what Monsignor Lynn knew,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;Things he didn&amp;apost;t know about could not possibly go to his state of mind.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>After listing to both sides in open court, Common Pleas Court Judge M. Teresa Sarmina suggested that perhaps prosecutors call Avery to the witness stand.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Sarmina delayed ruling on also allowing additional victims to testify against Avery.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;I wouldn&amp;apost;t be surprised if there were many, many more,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;Why didn&amp;apost;t they come forward until 2010?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>There&amp;apost;s a myriad of reasons.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>It takes a lot to come forward.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Jurors also heard the remainder of testimony about a former priest accused of abusing a 15-year-old boy for three years, beginning in 1984, engaging in &amp;quot;everything sexually two men can do.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>While in treatment, the priest admitted to having a sexual relationship with the teen.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>He also described a number of incidents where he was the victim of sexual abuse, including a time when he was tied down by several seminarians who tried to rape him and that a friend came to his aide.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>He also revealed another incident when he was 10 and made to &amp;quot;kiss&amp;quot; a group of boys&amp;apost; genitals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Prosecutors also plan to call Monsignor Kevin Quirk to the witness stand.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>A West Virginia judge ordered Quirk to testify, noting he was a &amp;quot;necessary and material witness,&amp;quot; according to court documents obtained by CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Quirk presided over Brennan&amp;apost;s 1996 canonical trial for an alleged sexual abuse of a minor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
