<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="613" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/06/18/justice/pennsylvania-sandusky-trial/index.html" date_published="2012-06-18 04:25:38" category="justice" author="the CNN Wire Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Sandusky case drawing to a rapid close</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">NEW: Closing arguments could come Thursday, judge says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">NEW: Testimony ended early Monday because of &amp;quot;technical issues,&amp;quot; judge says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="15">First defense witness says he never saw any inappropriate conduct.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="41">Sandusky may take the stand in his own defense, his lawyer has suggested.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-11 10:17:19" annotation_time="326.30002" mapping_time_divergence="163.15001">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Closing arguments in the Jerry Sandusky child sexual abuse trial could begin as soon as Thursday, Judge John Cleland said Monday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">The defense case began Monday, but testimony ended early because of &amp;quot;technical issues&amp;quot; involving witnesses, Cleland told jurors.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="3">Richard Anderson said that it was not uncommon for coaches and youths to use the shower at the same time, and that he had never seen anything inappropriate between Sandusky and a child.</sentence>
      <sentence id="41" ids_highlights="4">Lastly, there&amp;apost;s the question of whether Sandusky himself will take the stand.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Closing arguments in the Jerry Sandusky child sexual abuse trial could begin as soon as Thursday, Judge John Cleland said Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>He said the defense will probably end its case midday Wednesday, followed by the prosecution&amp;apost;s rebuttal.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>That should end Wednesday afternoon, clearing the way for closing arguments Thursday, less than two weeks after the start of what had been expected to be a three-week case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The defense case began Monday, but testimony ended early because of &amp;quot;technical issues&amp;quot; involving witnesses, Cleland told jurors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Sandusky, 68, is on trial on 51 counts related to accusations of improper conduct and sexual abuse involving at least 10 boys over a 15-year span.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The former Penn State assistant coach has denied the charges.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>At the conclusion of the trial, jurors will be sequestered in a hotel so outside influences cannot affect their deliberations, Cleland said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Prosecutors wrapped up their case Monday morning with brief testimony from the mother of one of the alleged victims.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;He gave him clothes, he gave him gifts,&amp;quot; the mother of an accuser called Victim 9 testified.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;I just wish he&amp;apost;d given him underwear to replace the underwear I could never find in my laundry.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The final prosecution witness testified Monday that her son seemed to suffer from stomach ailments during the time he was visiting Sandusky and sometimes did not want to visit the former Penn State assistant&amp;apost;s home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>But she said she did not ask him about any possible abuse and still does not know what happened to him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;I didn&amp;apost;t really want to hear,&amp;quot; she said, crying.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The defense then opened its case with a former Penn State coach who testified about Sandusky&amp;apost;s stellar reputation in the community.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Richard Anderson said that it was not uncommon for coaches and youths to use the shower at the same time, and that he had never seen anything inappropriate between Sandusky and a child.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Before Monday&amp;apost;s testimony, Cleland rejected defense arguments that the charges were too vague or the testimony did not support the claims.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Prosecutors did withdraw one charge of unlawful contact with a minor involving one of the defendants.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The law was not in effect during the time the alleged misconduct occurred, prosecutors said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>That left 51 charges pending against Sandusky.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>A main focus of the defense&amp;apost;s strategy may be to attempt to poke holes in the prosecution&amp;apost;s case thus far.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;A lot of people lied,&amp;quot; lawyer Joe Amendola said last Monday in his opening statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Over four days, several people testified that Sandusky forced them to engage in sexual acts with him in various places, including showers in the Penn State coaches&amp;apost; locker room, hotel rooms and the basement of his home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>One told jurors that Sandusky -- whom he met, like many of the accusers, through the Second Mile nonprofit for disadvantaged youths that the ex-coach founded -- had threatened him if he told others about the abuse.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Another said Sandusky warned he might send him home from a trip to Texas, where they&amp;apost;d gone to watch a Penn State bowl game, if he resisted the sexual advances.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;There&amp;apost;s a tsunami of evidence against him,&amp;quot; veteran criminal defense attorney Ron Kuby said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The defense could challenge the accusers&amp;apost; timetable, questioning if Sandusky could have committed the crimes they claim he did, when they say he did them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Some of the accusers have civil attorneys, Amendola noted last week, calling that unusual.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Others, he said, have a financial interest in the case, an allegation that was denied by the accusers and their attorneys.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>But Howard Janet, who represents the accuser known as Victim 6, blasted Amendola&amp;apost;s assertion that his client and others detailed the abuse just so they could sue Sandusky, calling it nonsense.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;Does that mean that none of them are telling the truth, because they&amp;apost;ve gone to hire a lawyer?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;That&amp;apost;s absurd.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The defense is expected to call an expert witness to testify that Sandusky may have histrionic personality disorder, which the National Institutes of Health says describes people who act &amp;quot;in a very emotional and dramatic way that draws attention to themselves.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The prosecution had presented as evidence what one accuser described as &amp;quot;creepy love letters,&amp;quot; written by Sandusky, that they argued were part of &amp;quot;grooming techniques&amp;quot; commonly employed by sexual predators.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Judge Cleland issued an order Friday allowing a defense motion to offer expert testimony from a psychologist who &amp;quot;will explain that the words, tones, requests and statements made in the letters are consistent with a person who suffers from a Histrionic Personality Disorder.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;The goal of a person suffering from this disorder in writing those letters would not necessarily be to groom or sexually consummate a relationship in a criminal manner, but rather to satisfy the needs of a psyche belabored by the needs of such a disorder,&amp;quot; the defense lawyers wrote in their motion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Sandusky was expected to be examined Sunday by a prosecution psychologist related to the personality disorder defense, according to a source with knowledge with the case.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>It was not clear if that happened.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Another person who could testify is Dottie Sandusky, the accused ex-coach&amp;apost;s wife.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>While many alleged victims knew her, she is not accused of having witnessed any sexual abuse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Lastly, there&amp;apost;s the question of whether Sandusky himself will take the stand.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Amendola told jurors last week that Sandusky routinely &amp;quot;got showers with kids&amp;quot; after working out and that he would say so later.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Kuby, the defense lawyer, said having the former coach testify may give him his best chance at avoiding jail time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;Just maybe he can convince one juror to hold out,&amp;quot; the lawyer said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>&amp;quot;A hung jury, right now, is a lot better than life without parole.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
