<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="556" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/06/26/justice/supreme-court-recess-appointments/index.html" date_published="2014-06-26 14:26:52" category="justice" author="Bill Mears, CNN Supreme Court Producer" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Justices rule for Congress in recess appointments fight</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Unanimous ruling could invalidate hundreds of National Labor Relations Board decisions.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">Constitution allows temporary appointments during a recess, without congressional approval.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="7">Lawmakers have sought to stop appointments by technically never shutting down the Senate.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-23 10:03:07" annotation_time="32.460003">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">The justices&amp;apost; unanimous ruling on the narrowest of grounds against the Obama administration could invalidate hundreds of decisions by the National Labor Relations Board, the federal agency at the center of this legal fight.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">The Constitution allows a president to fill temporary appointments during a recess, without congressional approval.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="3">But more recently, lawmakers have sought to thwart certain appointments by never technically shutting down the Senate.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington The Supreme Court sided with Congress on Thursday in the high-stakes power struggle over presidential recess appointments, in which officials are placed in top government jobs temporarily without Senate approval.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The justices&amp;apost; unanimous ruling on the narrowest of grounds against the Obama administration could invalidate hundreds of decisions by the National Labor Relations Board, the federal agency at the center of this legal fight.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>At issue is whether three people named by President Barack Obama to the board were ineligible to serve because their appointments were made while the Senate was technically in a &amp;quot;pro forma&amp;quot; session during the 2011-12 winter holiday break.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>That meant the mostly empty chamber was convening every three days without any business conducted, and with the sessions lasting only minutes at most.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The court majority concluded recess appointments would be valid if those breaks lasted 10 days or more.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The Constitution allows a president to fill temporary appointments during a recess, without congressional approval.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>But more recently, lawmakers have sought to thwart certain appointments by never technically shutting down the Senate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The closely watched constitutional and political confrontation over the practice has accelerated because of partisan gridlock in Congress.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Presidential spokesman Josh Earnest told reporters on Air Force One that the White House was &amp;quot;deeply disappointed&amp;quot; in the decision and said the administration is &amp;quot;still reviewing it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The court&amp;apost;s opinion will not have an immediate effect, since Democrats controlling the Senate imposed rules making it harder for Republicans to block Obama&amp;apost;s nominees.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>But a change in Senate control after November&amp;apost;s midterm elections could renew the disagreements.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;We conclude that the Recess Appointment Clause does not give the President the constitutional authority to make the appointments here at issue,&amp;quot; Justice Stephen Breyer said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;We hold that the Senate is in session, and not in recess, when the Senate says that it is in session.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>But the court said the executive could use his power to make recess appointments even when the vacancy occurred before the Senate goes on break.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>To achieve unanimity, the court took a limited approach, avoiding a decision that could have applied to greater set of recess scenarios, thereby further blunting the executive&amp;apost;s power.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Four conservative justices wanted their colleagues to go farther, and complained the majority &amp;quot;bends over backwards&amp;quot; to preserve some of the President&amp;apost;s options.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>That gives both branches some room to claim even a partial victory.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Senate officials weigh in.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;I welcome the Supreme Court&amp;apost;s important decision today,&amp;quot; Senate Minority Leader Mitch McConnell, R-Kentucky, said just after the ruling.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;This administration has a tendency to abide by laws that it likes and to disregard those it doesn&amp;apost;t.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>His Democratic counterpart blamed the GOP for the current fights.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;Since President Obama took office, Senate Republicans have done everything possible to deny qualified nominees from receiving a fair up-or-down vote,&amp;quot; said Senate Majority Leader Harry Reid, D-Nevada.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;President Obama did the right thing when he made these appointments on behalf of American workers.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>While agreeing with the outcome of the narrow question presented, four more conservative justices worried that the ruling would allow the President to retain a good deal of the &amp;quot;powerful weapon&amp;quot; of making recess appointments.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;The only remaining practical use for the recess-appointment power is the ignoble one of enabling Presidents to circumvent the Senate&amp;apost;s role in the appointment process, which is precisely what happened here,&amp;quot; Justice Antonin Scalia said from the bench.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Other Presidents&amp;apost; recess appointments.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Among recent presidents, Ronald Reagan made 240 recess appointments, George H. W. Bush made 77, Bill Clinton made 139, George W. Bush made 171, and Obama has made 32 so far.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Gen. (later President) Dwight Eisenhower, Judge (later Justice) Thurgood Marshall, Chief Justice Earl Warren and Federal Reserve Chairman Alan Greenspan were all recess appointments.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Some GOP lawmakers also accused the President of flip-flopping on the issue.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>When he was a senator, Obama criticized then-President Bush&amp;apost;s recess appointment of John Bolton as U.S. ambassador to the United Nations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The court&amp;apost;s ruling could also put in jeopardy some decisions made by Richard Cordray, who was appointed to head the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau, a move also being challenged in a separate lawsuit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Cordray was named the same day as the three National Labor Relations Board appointments, which gave the board a full panel for the first time in a year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The lawsuit leading the to the Supreme Court case was brought by Noel Canning, a family-owned Yakima, Washington, bottling company, which complained the board improperly ruled in favor of Teamsters Local 760 during contract negotiations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Company executives said the board lacked a binding quorum because the recess appointments made by Obama were not legal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>How they&amp;apost;ve kept the Senate in session.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Since May 2011, Republicans have been relying on a little-known procedure to keep the Senate in session, even when it was not really conducting any business, in order to stop the President from making those recess appointments.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>The legal basis comes from a 1993 Department of Justice brief saying the president should act only if the Senate is in official recess more than three days.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>So, party leaders have arranged for a single Republican lawmaker to show up every three days and gavel the Senate to order, wait around for about 30 seconds, gavel it to a close, then leave.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Legal experts have disagreed on both the tactical and timing procedures by the Senate, and whether the president has unilateral authority to override those legislative tactics.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The case is NLRB v. Noel Canning (12-1281).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
