<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="562" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/08/11/justice/isis-sympathizer-suspect-arrest/index.html" date_published="2014-08-11 15:36:04" category="justice" author="Evan Perez, CNN Justice Reporter " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Man arrested, accused of sympathizing with ISIS</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Donald Ray Morgan was arrested at New York&amp;apost;s JFK Airport, court documents show.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">A federal grand jury in North Carolina has charged him with illegal weapons possession.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">Prosecutors say he was involved in weapons trafficking in violation of his probation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="4">U.S. officials say Morgan made Twitter postings in support of the ISIS terrorist group.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-19 09:49:53" annotation_time="43.425">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Donald Ray Morgan was arrested on August 2 on arrival at New York&amp;apost;s John F. Kennedy International Airport from Frankfurt, Germany, according to federal court documents.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2, 3">A federal grand jury in North Carolina charged him with illegal weapons possession, and prosecutors say he was involved in weapons trafficking in violation of his probation for a previous felony conviction, the court documents show.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="4">The court documents make no mention of the ISIS connection, but U.S. officials say that part of what drew their attention is Morgan&amp;apost;s online activities, making Twitter postings in support of the terrorist group.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>U.S. authorities arrested an American man returning from overseas who they say is a sympathizer of the terrorist group ISIS.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Donald Ray Morgan was arrested on August 2 on arrival at New York&amp;apost;s John F. Kennedy International Airport from Frankfurt, Germany, according to federal court documents.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>A federal grand jury in North Carolina charged him with illegal weapons possession, and prosecutors say he was involved in weapons trafficking in violation of his probation for a previous felony conviction, the court documents show.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The court documents make no mention of the ISIS connection, but U.S. officials say that part of what drew their attention is Morgan&amp;apost;s online activities, making Twitter postings in support of the terrorist group.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Morgan is not thought to be involved in any active plots inside the U.S. or elsewhere and instead may be more of an &amp;quot;aspirational&amp;quot; supporter of ISIS.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Still, with the rise of ISIS, and more than 100 Americans believed to have traveled to Syria to fight in the ongoing civil war, the FBI is on alert for returning Americans who may be associated with groups fighting there.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The New York Daily News reported Sunday night that at his first appearance in court on August 4, prosecutors opposed bail, citing fears that he was possibly involved with ISIS, which is fighting to establish an Islamic extremist state in parts of Syria and Iraq.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The group calls itself the Islamic State but formerly was known as the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The Daily News report cited officials alleging that Morgan used the moniker Abu Omar al Amreeki to publish tweets in support of ISIS while he spent time in Lebanon.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The newspaper quoted federal prosecutor Nadia Moore as saying in court: &amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s possible that he traffics in guns to people in this organization (ISIS).&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Chief Magistrate Judge Steven Gold denied bond based on the government&amp;apost;s argument, saying the tweets had &amp;quot;clearly implied to me that he is trying to go to Syria or Iraq,&amp;quot; according to the Daily News.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>A public defender assigned to represent Morgan said there was no evidence Morgan tried to support ISIS, the Daily News reported.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The public defender didn&amp;apost;t immediately respond to a request for comment from CNN late Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Morgan is being transferred to Greensboro, North Carolina, to face the weapons charge, court documents show.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>ISIS recruiting on the rise in Sunni areas of Iraq.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
