<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="443" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/07/13/justice/iran-uranium-indictment/index.html" date_published="2012-07-13 18:28:43" category="justice" author="the CNN Wire Staff" highlights_mapped="false" mapping_error="false">
  <title>2 indicted for allegedly trying to supply Iran with nuclear-related materials</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">One of the accused was arrested in May; the other remains at large.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Both face one count of conspiracy to violate the International Emergency Economic Powers Act .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="9">Western nations suspect Iran wants to build nuclear weapons, an assertion Tehran denies.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_time="32.219334">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">The indictment charges Parviz Khaki, an Iranian citizen, and Zongcheng Yi, a resident of China, each with one count of conspiracy to violate the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (IEEPA) by conspiring to export the goods without the required license.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">Khaki, 43, was arrested in the Philippines in May.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="3">As a signatory to the Nuclear Nonproliferation Treaty, Iran has the right, like other countries, to enrich uranium for commercial and research reactors.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A federal grand jury in the District of Columbia has indicted two people for their alleged attempts to supply Iran with U.S. materials for gas centrifuges to enrich uranium, the Justice Department said Friday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The indictment charges Parviz Khaki, an Iranian citizen, and Zongcheng Yi, a resident of China, each with one count of conspiracy to violate the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (IEEPA) by conspiring to export the goods without the required license.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Both also face one count of conspiracy to defraud the United States, two counts of smuggling, two counts of illegally exporting U.S. goods to Iran in violation of IEEPA and one count of conspiracy to commit money laundering, the Justice Department said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The indictment also accuses Khaki of seeking to obtain for customers in Iran radioactive source materials from the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Khaki, 43, was arrested in the Philippines in May.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Yi remains at large.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;This new indictment shows that we have no tolerance for those who try to traffic in commodities that can be used to support Iran&amp;apost;s nuclear program,&amp;quot; U.S. Attorney Ronald C. Machen Jr. said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;It also underscores our commitment to aggressively enforcing export laws.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>As a signatory to the Nuclear Nonproliferation Treaty, Iran has the right, like other countries, to enrich uranium for commercial and research reactors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>But the same facilities that are used for peaceful enrichment can be used to enrich uranium for a bomb.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s what many Western countries suspect Iran is doing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Iran insists its nuclear program is exclusively for peaceful purposes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Among the materials Khaki and Yi are accused of trying to obtain are measuring instruments, pressure transducers, vacuum pumps and maraging steel, a class of high-strength steel.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>All can be used in gas centrifuges for uranium enrichment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The indictment alleges they both also caused the illegal export of lathes and nickel alloy wire to Iran, and it accuses Khaki of trying to obtain radioactive source materials.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>In 2009 and again in 2011, he allegedly contacted an undercover U.S. federal agent, posing as an exporter, asking the agent to purchase radioactive sources.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>A law enforcement official, not authorized to talk to the media, declined to say whether the radioactive and centrifuge materials made it through to Iran.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The lathes and nickel alloy wire were shipped from the United States through China to Iran.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>If convicted, Khaki and Yi could face up to 20 years in prison for conspiring to violate IEEPA, five years for conspiring to defraud the United States, 10 years for each smuggling count, 20 years for each exporting count and 20 years in prison for conspiracy to commit money laundering.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
