<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="614" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/06/20/justice/pennsylvania-sandusky-trial/index.html" date_published="2012-06-20 04:02:36" category="justice" author="the CNN Wire Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Sandusky doesn&amp;apost;t testify; defense rests</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">Closing arguments are scheduled to begin at 9 a.m. Thursday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="17">Defense calls acquaintance of former grad assistant Mike McQueary.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="18">He says McQueary didn&amp;apost;t tell him he actually saw a sexual encounter, as he testified.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="24">At least 6 accusers spent the night in the Sandusky home, his wife testifies.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-18 14:06:18" annotation_time="69.41134">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">After the defense rested, the prosecution said it had no further rebuttal witnesses, and the judge scheduled closing arguments to begin at 9 a.m. Thursday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="2">On Wednesday, the defense called Dr. Jonathan Dranov, an acquaintance of former graduate assistant Mike McQueary, who testified that he saw Sandusky sexually assaulting a boy inside a university shower.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="3">Dranov told jurors that McQueary told him he heard &amp;quot;sexual sounds&amp;quot; and saw the boy in the shower when an arm reached around him, but that he told him he did not actually see a sexual encounter.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="4">On Tuesday, Sandusky&amp;apost;s wife told jurors that she could remember at least six of her husband&amp;apost;s accusers staying overnight at their house, and said she did not witness any sexual abuse.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The defense team for Jerry Sandusky rested on Wednesday without the former assistant football coach taking the stand.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Defense attorney Joe Amendola had told reporters earlier to &amp;quot;stay tuned&amp;quot; to see whether the former Penn State University defensive coordinator would testify.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>It was thought his testimony could provide the opening that prosecutors needed to introduce new evidence against the former coach.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Sandusky, 68, has pleaded not guilty to 51 counts related to accusations of child sex abuse against 10 boys over a 15-year period.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>After the defense rested, the prosecution said it had no further rebuttal witnesses, and the judge scheduled closing arguments to begin at 9 a.m. Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The prosecution had called its only rebuttal witness on Tuesday, to counter testimony that raised questions about Sandusky&amp;apost;s mental health.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Dr. Elliot Atkins testified that he diagnosed Sandusky with histrionic personality disorder, a class of conditions called dramatic personality disorders, which are marked by unstable emotions and distorted self-images.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>But a second psychologist, prosecution witness Dr. John O&amp;apost;Brien, disputed those findings, saying that the &amp;quot;personality profile Mr. Sandusky exhibited was within normal limits.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Following closing arguments on Thursday, the jury is expected to retire to begin deliberations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>At least one trial observer had said there was good reason for the defense to call the former coach to the stand.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Veteran criminal defense attorney Ron Kuby said Sandusky is facing a &amp;quot;tsunami of evidence against him,&amp;quot; and suggested that his taking the stand may be a way to help his case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Just maybe he can convince one juror to hold out,&amp;quot; Kuby told CNN before the defense rested.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;A hung jury, right now, is a lot better than life without parole.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>However, some court observers had said that if Sandusky were to testify, prosecutors could potentially submit as new evidence a TV interview the ex-coach had with NBC sportscaster Bob Costas.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>In a portion of the interview that was not part of the original November 2011 broadcast, Sandusky told Costas that he &amp;quot;didn&amp;apost;t go around seeking out every young person for sexual needs that I&amp;apost;ve helped.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>There are likely &amp;quot;many young people who would come forward and say that my methods and what I had done for them made a very positive impact on their life,&amp;quot; Sandusky said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>On Wednesday, the defense called Dr. Jonathan Dranov, an acquaintance of former graduate assistant Mike McQueary, who testified that he saw Sandusky sexually assaulting a boy inside a university shower.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Dranov told jurors that McQueary told him he heard &amp;quot;sexual sounds&amp;quot; and saw the boy in the shower when an arm reached around him, but that he told him he did not actually see a sexual encounter.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Sandusky then emerged from the shower area, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>That account is different from what McQueary testified.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The former graduate assistant said he witnessed Sandusky pressing against the boy in the shower, and that it seemed obvious that he had been raping him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Before Wednesday&amp;apost;s testimony, one juror was dismissed and replaced on account of illness.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Prosecutors wrapped up their case Monday after eight of the 10 alleged victims were called to the stand, among other witnesses.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>On Tuesday, Sandusky&amp;apost;s wife told jurors that she could remember at least six of her husband&amp;apost;s accusers staying overnight at their house, and said she did not witness any sexual abuse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Dottie Sandusky recalled that one of the accusers had once traveled with them to a bowl game in San Antonio, Texas, where she and her husband shared a hotel room with the boy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Many of the accusers testified that they knew Dottie Sandusky, who is not accused of having witnessed the alleged abuse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>She testified that children would often sleep at the Sanduskys&amp;apost; house and that &amp;quot;we would give them a choice of where they wanted to sleep.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Her husband also was the one to put the children to bed, typically, she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>She told jurors that &amp;quot;he would go downstairs and tell them good night.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The final prosecution witness testified Monday that her son seemed to suffer from stomach ailments during the times he was visiting Sandusky and sometimes did not want to visit the former Penn State assistant&amp;apost;s home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>But she said she didn&amp;apost;t ask him about any possible abuse and still does not know what happened to him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;I didn&amp;apost;t really want to hear,&amp;quot; she said, crying.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The defense then opened its case with a former Penn State coach who testified about Sandusky&amp;apost;s stellar reputation in the community.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Richard Anderson said it was not uncommon for coaches and youths to use the shower at the same time, and that he had never seen anything inappropriate between Sandusky and a child.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The defense called five other witnesses who supported the view of Sandusky&amp;apost;s good reputation in the community.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;A lot of people lied,&amp;quot; Amendola had said in his opening statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Over four days, several prosecution witnesses testified that Sandusky forced them to engage in sexual acts with him in various places, including showers in the Penn State coaches&amp;apost; locker room, hotel rooms and the basement of his home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>One told jurors that Sandusky -- whom he met, like many of the accusers, through the Second Mile nonprofit for disadvantaged youths that the ex-coach founded -- had threatened him if he told others about the abuse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Another said Sandusky warned he might send him home from a trip to Texas, where they&amp;apost;d gone to watch a Penn State bowl game.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The defense challenged the accusers&amp;apost; timetable, questioning whether Sandusky could have committed the crimes they claim he did when they say he did.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>On Monday, prosecutors dropped one of the 52 counts against Sandusky because the statute he was charged with wasn&amp;apost;t in effect on the date of the alleged incident.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>The accuser said the incident occurred in 1995 or 1996, but the unlawful contact with a minor statute didn&amp;apost;t apply until 1997.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>