<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="458" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/08/08/justice/warrantless-wiretap-lawsuit-dismissed/index.html" date_published="2012-08-08 07:11:17" category="justice" author="Bill Mears, CNN Supreme Court Producer" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Appeals court dismisses lawsuit over warrantless wiretap program</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">Al-Haramain said its overseas communications were illegally monitored.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="11">Court said Congress never waived immunity for government officials.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="16">Justice Department was sharply criticized by appeals court.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 18:11:56" annotation_time="13.4115">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">That spy program was unveiled in a 2005 New York Times article that said government officials were working with private telecom companies to secretly monitor telephone and e-mail traffic of targeted individuals and groups, both domestic and international.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="2">The appeals court said Congress had never waived immunity for government officials over alleged state eavesdropping, even if constitutional rights were violated as a result of improper government conduct.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="3">While ruling for the government, the appeals court sharply criticized Justice Department lawyers who had claimed in court papers the plaintiffs were engaged in &amp;quot;game-playing&amp;quot; by continuing their lawsuit for years.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A one-time American-based Islamic group cannot sue the government over claims it was targeted by the government&amp;apost;s once-secret Terrorist Surveillance Program, a federal court has ruled.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The San Francisco-based 9th Circuit U.S. Court of Appeals on Tuesday unanimously tossed out a lawsuit by the now-closed Al-Haramain Islamic Foundation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The federal government had listed the Ashland, Oregon, chapter as a supporter of terrorism in 2004.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The group sued, saying its private overseas communications were unconstitutionally being monitored under the Bush administration&amp;apost;s warrantless wiretap program.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>That spy program was unveiled in a 2005 New York Times article that said government officials were working with private telecom companies to secretly monitor telephone and e-mail traffic of targeted individuals and groups, both domestic and international.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Federal officials later publicly acknowledged the existence of the program, which was then officially authorized by Congress in 2008.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;This case effectively brings to an end the plaintiffs&amp;apost; ongoing attempts to hold the Executive Branch responsible for intercepting telephone conversations without judicial authorization,&amp;quot; said the appeals court.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The decision overturns a federal judge&amp;apost;s earlier award of more than $2.5 million to attorneys working for Al-Haramain.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>At issue was whether the federal government was liable from such suits.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The Bush administration in 2008 had separately granted the telecom companies &amp;quot;retroactive immunity&amp;quot; from any lawsuits.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The appeals court said Congress had never waived immunity for government officials over alleged state eavesdropping, even if constitutional rights were violated as a result of improper government conduct.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Al-Haramain can bring a suit for damages against the United States for use of the collected information, but cannot bring suit against the government for collection of the information itself,&amp;quot; the court concluded.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;Although such a structure may seem anomalous and even unfair, the policy judgment is one for Congress, not the courts.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The Islamic foundation said two of its U.S.-based lawyers had their telephone conversations with clients in Saudi Arabia secretly monitored, without a judge&amp;apost;s prior approval.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Lawyers for the group said they were in a Catch-22, unable to prove the government used the information from the wiretaps against Al-Haramain, after the government cited national security and state secrets.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>While ruling for the government, the appeals court sharply criticized Justice Department lawyers who had claimed in court papers the plaintiffs were engaged in &amp;quot;game-playing&amp;quot; by continuing their lawsuit for years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;In light of the complex, ever-evolving nature of this litigation, and considering the significant infringement on individual liberties that would occur if the Executive Branch were to disregard congressionally-mandated procedures for obtaining judicial authorization of international wiretaps, the charge of &amp;apost;game-playing&amp;apost; lobbed by the government is as careless as it is inaccurate,&amp;quot; said Judge Margaret McKeown, writing on behalf of her two colleagues.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The case is al-Haramain Islamic Foundation v. Obama (No. 11-15468).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
