<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="485" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/04/29/justice/connecticut-school-killing-charges/index.html" date_published="2014-04-29 22:16:57" category="justice" author="Ray Sanchez and Laura Ly, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Connecticut teen held in slashing death of classmate charged as adult</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Christopher Plaskon, 16, charged with murder as an adult in the slashing death of a classmate .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Maren Sanchez, 16, died Friday after being slashed in a school stairwell.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="8, 7">Police say the suspect allegedly confessed in the principal&amp;apost;s office: &amp;quot;I did it, Just arrest me.&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="12">Plaskon&amp;apost;s lawyer says his client &amp;quot;is in need of continued psychiatric care and medication&amp;quot;.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-11 17:15:09" annotation_time="39.105667" mapping_time_divergence="9.776417">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">A 16-year-old Connecticut high school student suspected in the slashing death of a classmate was charged with murder as an adult Tuesday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">The victim, Maren Sanchez, 16, who was described by her family as &amp;quot;a bright light full of hopes and dreams,&amp;quot; died Friday after being slashed in a school stairwell, authorities said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;I did it,&amp;quot; Plaskon allegedly told the officer, according to a probable cause statement filed with a Milford court Tuesday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;Just arrest me.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="4">Meehan said in a statement that Plaskon &amp;quot;is in need of continued psychiatric care and medication and should be housed in an age-appropriate correctional center when he is released from the emergency commitment.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A 16-year-old Connecticut high school student suspected in the slashing death of a classmate was charged with murder as an adult Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The victim, Maren Sanchez, 16, who was described by her family as &amp;quot;a bright light full of hopes and dreams,&amp;quot; died Friday after being slashed in a school stairwell, authorities said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>She was cut in her neck, chest and face.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Though the motive remains under investigation, police were looking into whether the boy was angry after Sanchez rejected him as a prom date.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The suspect, Christopher Plaskon, was taken into custody Friday by a school police officer in the principal&amp;apost;s office.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>His clothing and hands were bloodied.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;I did it,&amp;quot; Plaskon allegedly told the officer, according to a probable cause statement filed with a Milford court Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;Just arrest me.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The Jonathan Law High School student, who remains under emergency commitment at a medical facility, was ordered held on $3 million bond.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>During a special court session convened at the medical facility, Plaskon&amp;apost;s lawyer, Richard Meehan, Jr., said his client had been advised of his rights and told that he was being charged with murder as an adult.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>He faces 25 to 60 years in prison if convicted.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Meehan said in a statement that Plaskon &amp;quot;is in need of continued psychiatric care and medication and should be housed in an age-appropriate correctional center when he is released from the emergency commitment.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Plaskon is to be formally arraigned Friday, provided he is released from the emergency psychiatric hold.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>In a statement Tuesday, Plaskon&amp;apost;s family said words could not convey &amp;quot;the raw sadness we are left with by this unimaginable tragedy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Our hearts are forever broken.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The statement continued: &amp;quot;To the Sanchez family, our deepest sympathies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Please know that you are now, and forever, in our hearts, our thoughts and our prayers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>We join with the entire Milford community to celebrate the life and mourn the loss of this most vibrant and exceptional young woman.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>To our extended family, friends and neighbors and all who have reached out to us in our darkest hour with warmth, kindness, understanding and compassion, you cannot know how much it has meant to us.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Thank you.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The fatal slashing occurred about 7 a.m. Friday in a school stairwell.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>A witness saw Plaskon on top of the victim and tried unsuccessfully to pull him away, according to the probable cause statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Another witness allegedly saw him discarding a bloody knife in a school corridor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Sanchez, a junior, suffered &amp;quot;multiple lacerations,&amp;quot; police said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The state medical examiner&amp;apost;s office concluded Saturday that Sanchez had died from &amp;quot;stab wounds to the trunk and neck&amp;quot; and ruled the death a homicide.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>School staff members and emergency technicians attempted &amp;quot;life-saving measures,&amp;quot; according to Milford Police Chief Keith Mello, but Sanchez was pronounced dead at Bridgeport Hospital at 7:43 a.m.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The prom, which was scheduled for the night of the slaying, was postponed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>All students were sent home, and counseling services were made available throughout the weekend.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>On Friday, friends and classmates of Sanchez gathered and released balloons into the air.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The balloons were violet, her favorite color.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>On Instagram, classmates in prom attire posted images of themselves holding her green prom gown.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The slain girl&amp;apost;s cousin, Edward Kovac, read a statement from her family lamenting what they called an &amp;quot;unprovoked attack&amp;quot; that ended the life of a young woman who had &amp;quot;her future at her fingertips.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;Maren should be celebrating at her prom this evening, with her friends and classmates,&amp;quot; the family statement said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;Instead, we are mourning her death, and we are trying as a community to understand this senseless loss of life.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The family statement recalled other cases of school violence, saying &amp;quot;we can never forget the lessons ... from this&amp;quot; and other incidents.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>One of those incidents happened about 22 miles away in Newtown, where a lone gunman shot his mother to death, then went to Sandy Hook Elementary School and killed 26 people, including 20 children, before taking his own life in December 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;We need to ensure that more young children are protected from violent attacks at school,&amp;quot; the family said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>In their statement, the Plaskon family said, &amp;quot;In prayer we ask for comfort for the Sanchez family and all of us so deeply affected by this tragedy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>We pray for the wisdom to guide us as we desperately try to pull together the shattered pieces of our families.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>And finally, we pray that time may soften our wounds and reveal forgiveness in the hearts of all.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
