<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="542" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/04/justice/hot-car-death-ross-harris-grand-jury/index.html?hpt=hp_t3" date_published="2014-09-04 14:10:05" category="justice" author="Eliott C. McLaughlin, Greg Botelho and Devon M. Sayers, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Hot car death dad indicted on murder charges</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="12">NEW: District attorney will hold 3 p.m. news conference to discuss Thursday&amp;apost;s indictment.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Grand jury charges Justin Ross Harris with 8 counts, including murder, in hot car death.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="8">Charges allege Harris caused 22-month-old son, Cooper, &amp;quot;cruel, excessive physical pain&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="13">Harris, who is being held without bond, has pleaded not guilty to murder and child cruelty.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 13:39:00" annotation_time="149.43134">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2">Marietta, Georgia The Georgia dad whose toddler son died after being left all day in a hot car was indicted by a grand jury Thursday on eight counts, including malice murder and two counts of felony murder.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="3">By leaving Cooper in the car, Harris caused the boy &amp;quot;cruel and excessive physical pain,&amp;quot; the cruelty to children charges allege.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="1">County District Attorney Vic Reynolds will hold a news conference at 3 p.m. at the Cobb County Superior Courthouse to discuss details of the case.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="4">Harris pleaded not guilty to murder and child cruelty charges in June.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Marietta, Georgia The Georgia dad whose toddler son died after being left all day in a hot car was indicted by a grand jury Thursday on eight counts, including malice murder and two counts of felony murder.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The malice murder charge alleges that Justin Ross Harris, who has claimed his son&amp;apost;s death was an accident, premeditated the child&amp;apost;s killing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The other five charges are: first-degree cruelty to children, second-degree cruelty to children, criminal attempt to commit a felony (sexual exploitation of a minor) and two counts of dissemination of harmful material to minors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>According to the indictment, the grand jury found that on June 18, Harris &amp;quot;did unlawfully, and with malice aforethought, cause the death of Cooper Harris ... by placing said Cooper Harris into a child car seat and leaving him alone in a hot motor vehicle.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The two felony murder charges allege that Harris killed his 22-month-old son while committing the first- and second-degree felonies of cruelty to children.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>One count states he killed Cooper &amp;quot;maliciously,&amp;quot; while the other felony murder count says Harris killed him &amp;quot;with criminal negligence.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Harris faces a mandatory sentence of life in prison if convicted on any of the murder charges, while a guilty verdict for the malice murder count could make him eligible for the death penalty.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>By leaving Cooper in the car, Harris caused the boy &amp;quot;cruel and excessive physical pain,&amp;quot; the cruelty to children charges allege.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The criminal attempt to commit a felony and dissemination of harmful materials charges are not related directly to Cooper&amp;apost;s death.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>They involve allegations that Harris requested a nude photo of a minor&amp;apost;s genitalia and sent the same minor descriptions of &amp;quot;sexual excitement and sexual conduct,&amp;quot; according to the indictment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>A Cobb County detective testified at an earlier probable cause hearing that while Cooper was in the car at his father&amp;apost;s workplace, Harris was sexting with numerous women and sent one of them, who was underage, a photo of his erect penis.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>County District Attorney Vic Reynolds will hold a news conference at 3 p.m. at the Cobb County Superior Courthouse to discuss details of the case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Harris pleaded not guilty to murder and child cruelty charges in June.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Cobb County Chief Magistrate Frank Cox signed off on the charges, stating Harris would&amp;apost;ve had to notice that &amp;quot;the stench in the car was overwhelming&amp;quot; when he got in it as he left work and &amp;quot;drove it for some instance&amp;quot; before stopping to check on the boy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Charges filed in an indictment supersede the previous charges.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Harris has been held without bond since Cooper&amp;apost;s death this summer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Authorities have painted Harris as a terrible father who, after admittedly looking up online how hot a car needed to be to kill a child, purposely strapped his son into his sweltering SUV to die.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>His motivation?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The prosecutor has characterized Harris as an unfaithful husband who wanted a childless life.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Yet his attorney, H. Maddox Kilgore, has argued his client tragically forgot his child in the car.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Friends described Harris as a doting dad, not a malicious one, who loved to show off his blond, bright-eyed boy and talked about him incessantly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>It all started simply enough: Harris left home with Cooper in a rear-facing car seat in the back of his 2011 Hyundai Tucson, then headed to his job as a Web developer for Atlanta-based Home Depot after making a quick pit stop at a fast-food restaurant for breakfast.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>But he didn&amp;apost;t follow through on his routine of stopping to drop the boy off at daycare.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Instead, according to a criminal warrant, Harris drove to work and left Cooper strapped in his car seat.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>He went back to his SUV during lunch, put something in the car, then returned to work.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>All the while, the vehicle got increasingly hotter, with records showing the temperature topped 92 that day -- which can make the heat inside a closed vehicle soar past 100 degrees quickly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Sometime around 4:15 p.m., seven hours after he&amp;apost;d arrived at work, Harris got back into his Hyundai and left work.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Witnesses told police that, soon thereafter, they heard &amp;quot;squealing tires (as) the vehicle came to a stop&amp;quot; in a shopping center.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Cobb County Police Detective Phil Stoddard testified at the probable cause hearing that Harris got out of the car yelling, &amp;quot;Oh my God, what have I done?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>He then stood with a blank look, going to the other side of his SUV to make a phone call after someone told him that his son needed CPR, a witness told police, according to Stoddard.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Witness Leonard Madden testified that, upon leaving a restaurant, he noticed Harris was distraught and crying.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;He was hollering,&amp;quot; Madden testified, recounting the father saying, &amp;quot;Oh, my God!</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Oh, my God!</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>My son is dead!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Harris had to be physically restrained once it became clear Cooper wouldn&amp;apost;t make it -- at which time it was 88 degrees -- according to police.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Leaving his son alone in the car wasn&amp;apost;t the only thing Harris did that day, authorities say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>While at work, he messaged six women besides his wife and exchanged explicit texts with some of them -- including the lewd photo that he sent to an underage female, Stoddard testified.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Yet even after these allegations surfaced, his wife Leanna Harris stood by her man.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>She sat calmly through the probable cause hearing, and at Cooper&amp;apost;s funeral flatly insisted she was &amp;quot;absolutely not&amp;quot; angry with her husband.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;Ross is and was and will be, if we have more children, a wonderful father,&amp;quot; Leanna Harris said at the funeral in Tuscaloosa, Alabama, a gathering that her husband also addressed via phone from the Cobb County Jail.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;Ross is a wonderful daddy and leader for our household.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Cooper meant the world to him.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
