<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="687" link="http://www.cnn.com/2011/10/27/living/diy-halloween-decorating/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2011-10-27 18:40:03" category="living" author="Emanuella Grinberg, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Do-it-yourself Halloween decorating 101</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Pumpkins and wreaths with DIY touches can add whimsy, sophistication to holiday decor.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="10">Use doilies and coffee filters to make garlands that look old, beautiful and a little creepy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="9">Wrap a foam wreath base in yarn, embellish with flowers, for customized wreath.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="11">Bonus costume ideas for Mom and Baby: Chef and lobster, plane and aviator.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-20 09:50:26" annotation_time="85.32133">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">Pumpkins on the front porch and a wreath on the door with few special do-it-yourself touches can add visual interest, sophistication and whimsy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="3">Handmade yarn wreaths: Instead of hanging a fake-leaf wreath, tightly wrap a foam wreath base in yarn and embellished with a few felted flowers, all in autumn hues.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="2">Garland made from doilies and coffee filters: By using white and natural-colored filters, the florets look old and beautiful and still a little creepy ... a bit Miss Havisham.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="4">Bonus: Costume ideas for Mom and Baby: Mom can be the chef, and Baby can be the lobster in a pot.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>With Halloween on a Monday, there&amp;apost;s still the entire weekend to get into the holiday spirit.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Decorating the home is a great way to celebrate, especially if you have children or want to postpone the feeding frenzy until next week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>It doesn&amp;apost;t have to be the standard store-bought fare, and it doesn&amp;apost;t have to be a daylong undertaking, says crafter extraordinaire Emily Grosse of Assemble Gallery &amp;amp; Studio in Seattle.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Pumpkins on the front porch and a wreath on the door with few special do-it-yourself touches can add visual interest, sophistication and whimsy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Grosse took a few minutes from leading crafting workshops and children&amp;apost;s Halloween parties to share a few ideas from a variety of sources.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>For more home and style ideas, check out her blog, neatLOAF.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Pumpkins as candy corn: Instead of choosing the perfect round pumpkin, take oddly shaped ones and spray-paint the tops white and bottoms yellow.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Our pumpkin is now a candy corn.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Handmade yarn wreaths: Instead of hanging a fake-leaf wreath, tightly wrap a foam wreath base in yarn and embellished with a few felted flowers, all in autumn hues.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Garland made from doilies and coffee filters: By using white and natural-colored filters, the florets look old and beautiful and still a little creepy ... a bit Miss Havisham.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Bonus: Costume ideas for Mom and Baby: Mom can be the chef, and Baby can be the lobster in a pot.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Or, Mom can be the plane and Baby can be the pilot.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>How else would you pull that off?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Here are a few more ideas borrowed from Apartment Therapy and beyond:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Best Halloween party decorations: Budget-friendly ideas for dressing up furniture, lighting and the food table for your holiday bash.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Creepy botanical gardens: Creepy plants and flowers grow year-round that seem made for Halloween, from the eyeball plant to the bat-faced cuphea.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>But even just adding a few tiny tombstones to a small terrarium gives you a creepy graveyard scene that&amp;apost;s also pretty darn cute.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Make your own Halloween dinnerware: Cheaper and more fun than buying Halloween dinnerware, all it takes is some cheap plates, a porcelain pen and painters tape to make your own.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>DIY decor for the whole home: Novel takes on traditional themes, from candy jars and birdcages to garland and Spanish moss centerpieces.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
