<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="753" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/07/24/living/weiners-wife-should-huma-stand-by-her-man/index.html" date_published="2013-07-24 22:53:31" category="living" author="Kelly Wallace, CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Weiner&amp;apost;s wife: Should Huma stand by her man?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">Women have dramatically different reactions about Huma Abedin&amp;apost;s decision.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="10, 7">Some think Abedin is doing the right thing, others think she is making a bad mistake.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="25">One feminist argued that women should be focusing on Weiner, not Abedin.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="37">Women also debate the impact of Abedin&amp;apost;s background as a top Clinton adviser.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-04 19:06:45" annotation_time="89.02533" mapping_time_divergence="22.256332">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">But while women pretty unanimously feel for her, they have dramatically different reactions about whether she&amp;apost;s doing the right thing, judging from the responses of several women I interviewed from across the country Wednesday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;I think it&amp;apost;s great that she&amp;apost;s backing him.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="2">On the other side are women who think Abedin is making a terrible mistake, women like Andrea Kristina, a divorced mother with a teenage son who says she put up with &amp;quot;bad behavior&amp;quot; from her ex-husband for years.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;I would like to see feminist women focusing on the fact that his behavior is inappropriate and not on the fact that she&amp;apost;s being strong enough or being feminist enough by deciding to take her marriage vow seriously.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="37" ids_highlights="4">Abedin&amp;apost;s background as a top adviser to former Secretary of State Clinton also became a point of discussion among women.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Just about any woman who watched Huma Abedin publicly declare her decision to stick with her husband, embattled New York mayoral candidate Anthony Weiner, had to feel sympathy for her.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>How could you not?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>No wife, already facing her husband&amp;apost;s sexually explicit digital relationship with another woman (yet again!).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>, wants to face the prying eyes of the public, too.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>But while women pretty unanimously feel for her, they have dramatically different reactions about whether she&amp;apost;s doing the right thing, judging from the responses of several women I interviewed from across the country Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think she&amp;apost;s a good wife ... and she&amp;apost;s a loyal wife,&amp;quot; said Lydia Montgomery, a married mom with two grown sons in Chanute, Kansas.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think it&amp;apost;s great that she&amp;apost;s backing him.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;These days it has become too easy to just walk away when someone shows their character flaws or doesn&amp;apost;t live up to their end of the marriage contract,&amp;quot; said Dee, a married mom with one son who only wanted to use her first name.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think she&amp;apost;s decided that keeping her family intact and holding up her (end) of the marriage is worth the pain she&amp;apost;s facing right now.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>On the other side are women who think Abedin is making a terrible mistake, women like Andrea Kristina, a divorced mother with a teenage son who says she put up with &amp;quot;bad behavior&amp;quot; from her ex-husband for years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;Standing by your man when he repeatedly humiliates you by getting himself into trouble doesn&amp;apost;t make you a strong woman,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Leaving him and respecting yourself will.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Pam Selker Rak, a married public relations professional in Pittsburgh, said while she believes the decision to stay or leave is a personal one that only Abedin can make, she doesn&amp;apost;t think the former aide to Hillary Clinton should have backed Weiner publicly.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m not convinced she is projecting the best message by standing behind someone who hasn&amp;apost;t earned her confidence and loyalty,&amp;quot; Rak said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>In the middle of the &amp;quot;Is Abedin doing the right or wrong thing?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>debate are women who say we simply don&amp;apost;t know what is going on in their relationship, so who are we to judge?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have no idea what transpired,&amp;quot; said Rebecca, a single woman without children who asked to be identified by her first name.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;I know Huma is a smart woman and hasn&amp;apost;t made this decision lightly, especially with a child in the mix.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>All the criticism, especially from women who argue she is not standing up for herself and not asserting her power, really struck a chord with some women.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;ve seen people online call her a chump and call her desperate and (ask) what&amp;apost;s her problem,&amp;quot; said Jessica Dukes, a freelance writer in New York and mom of two young children.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;I don&amp;apost;t see the course that she&amp;apost;s taking as weak and capitulating.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>I see it as taking the harder path that requires even more strength.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;I understand from a political perspective that you should be looking at (Weiner&amp;apost;s) qualifications for a job, but I don&amp;apost;t feel that anybody should be judging a woman based on how she handles infidelity in her marriage,&amp;quot; said Meg Watt, a married mom with two teenage daughters in Stroudsburg, Pennsylvania.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Imani Gandy, a senior legal analyst with RH Reality Check, a reproductive and sexual health website, and editor of This Week in Blackness, thinks the focus -- for women -- should not be on Abedin, but on Weiner.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;I would like to see feminist women focusing on the fact that his behavior is inappropriate and not on the fact that she&amp;apost;s being strong enough or being feminist enough by deciding to take her marriage vow seriously.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>As women debated, online and off, about whether Abedin is making the right move, the conversation moved to &amp;quot;What would you do if you were in her shoes?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;I always think that if that were me, I could never stand by him, but when it came down to it, who knows?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>said Jennifer Merritt, a married digital editor in New York.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Women who know what Abedin is going through said no one can know how they would react.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>A woman who wanted to remain anonymous said she learned her boyfriend was sending naked pictures of himself to random women who were soliciting sex.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>She broke up with him, and after he sought professional therapy, gave him another chance, but ultimately the &amp;quot;trust was gone&amp;quot; and the relationship ended.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Opinion: Why does Abedin put up with Weiner?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;I will say that people are very quick to judge those women who choose to stay in relationships with men suffering from this disgusting habit, which clearly is the result of a deeper issue,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;I hope for Huma&amp;apost;s sake that Anthony has stopped his habit, but I do not think he deserves to be mayor.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Another woman, who also did not want to be identified, told CNN her sexting and infidelity nearly broke up her marriage: &amp;quot;I hurt my husband very badly.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>I can never undo it but I can stand by his side now and not screw it up again.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Abedin&amp;apost;s background as a top adviser to former Secretary of State Clinton also became a point of discussion among women.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Abedin certainly watched Clinton, her mentor, deal with sexual allegations against her husband, former President Clinton.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;I imagine she certainly has a lot of experience in navigating these sorts of situations regarding infidelity,&amp;quot; said Gandy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Montgomery said Abedin&amp;apost;s critics might speculate that she has political motives, but she disagrees.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;She&amp;apost;s got a family now and her career is on the back burner somewhat, and it&amp;apost;s all about her love and supporting her husband, and building and keeping that family,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Follow Kelly Wallace on Twitter and on Google+ and like CNN Living on Facebook.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
