<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="704" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/10/08/living/mnn-dog-bite/index.html" date_published="2012-10-08 15:05:23" category="living" author="Morieka Johnson, MNN.com" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>How to help a child get over a dog bite</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="8">Kids love to grab pets&amp;apost; ears, tails or simply rub them the wrong way.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="10">CDC: Nearly half of medically treated dog bites involve children.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="39">Training builds confidence for kids and for pets.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-08 07:04:06" annotation_time="20.288334">
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="1">They love to grab ears, pull tails and simply rub pets the wrong way.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="2">The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention estimates that nearly half of the 800,000 medically treated dog bites each year involve children, mostly between the ages of 5 and 9 years old.</sentence>
      <sentence id="39" ids_highlights="3">Try a training class: Avasthi and Collins recommend training to build confidence - for kids and pets.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>As a child, Ranjan Avasthi was once bitten by the family&amp;apost;s German shepherd.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>His parents responded quickly by separating the two, bandaging his wounds and gradually reintroducing healthy interaction with the dog.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Fast-forward a few decades.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Avasthi, now a doctor, has a wife, child and his very own German shepherd mix.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>His toddler may be a bit young for cautionary tales, but Avasthi fully understands the risks and rewards of kids and pets sharing a household.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>As a doctor who specializes in child and adolescent psychiatry, he has seen kids transform in the presence of pets.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>He also knows that kids will be kids.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>They love to grab ears, pull tails and simply rub pets the wrong way.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>While cats and dogs reside in roughly 84 million U.S. households without incident, accidents happen.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention estimates that nearly half of the 800,000 medically treated dog bites each year involve children, mostly between the ages of 5 and 9 years old.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Even with the most well-behaved fur kids, it&amp;apost;s best to avoid leaving children and pets unsupervised.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Kids naturally do things that upset cats and dogs - hugging, staring, petting on the head,&amp;quot; says animal behaviorist Kristen Collins of the American Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals (ASPCA.org).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;These can stress animals, and any stressed animal is more dangerous.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>MNN: Rescue dogs sniff out endangered species.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>We all know that kids and pets can peacefully coexist.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>But it also helps to have an action plan, just in case your child is bitten by a pet (yes, cats bite, too).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Take measures to help prevent emotional scars after a pet bites or scratches your child.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Collins and Avasthi offer expert advice:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Take swift action: Remove the pet immediately, then discuss why pets may have reacted negatively.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;A lot of it is talking about what happened and asking, &amp;apost;Why do you think this happened?&amp;apost;&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Avasthi says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;Allow children to discuss what can be done to prevent the situation from recurring.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Teach kids to read a pet&amp;apost;s body language: Collins strongly encourages parents to discuss body language while watching pets.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>ASPCA.org provides guidelines, photos and safety tips to help kids and parents recognize signs - such as flattened ears or wrinkled forehead - that indicate distress.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Reinforce healthy interaction: Help kids understand how to safely approach a cat or dog.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Start by asking human handlers if you can approach, then extend a closed hand for the cat or dog to smell.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s best if you let the pet come to you,&amp;quot; Collins says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;It can prevent a lot of bad situations.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>She also recommends that kids and parents practice the proper way to pet a cat or dog using stuffed animals.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Focus on areas where animals like to be petted, such as their chest or side.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;We sit with kids and talk about things dogs don&amp;apost;t like and cats don&amp;apost;t like,&amp;quot; Collins says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s equally important to explain what they do like.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>MNN: Why do cats purr?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Reintroduce pets slowly: Each situation differs, but psychiatrists often use exposure therapy to help patients deal with phobias, Avasthi says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The process resembles slow and deliberate steps that his parents took many years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Therapy may begin with kids seeing photos of puppies, then pint-sized pups and, eventually, larger dogs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>During subsequent sessions, kids watch videos of pets and gradually interact with an adult cat or dog.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>The goal is to help kids overcome a fearful response when they think about the pet.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Try a training class: Avasthi and Collins recommend training to build confidence - for kids and pets.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Many dog trainers encourage kids to participate in group classes, setting the foundation for safe interaction at an early age.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;Then the child is not afraid and doesn&amp;apost;t learn the wrong behaviors,&amp;quot; Avasthi says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Collins also encourages games such as fetch, along with obedience and teaching trick training.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>These activities help kids learn positive interaction, and dogs learn that kids are great treat dispensers, she says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Encourage a healthy respect for Mother Nature: &amp;quot;Educate kids that our house pets - even though domesticated and pets - they are animals,&amp;quot; Avasthi says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>&amp;quot;Sometimes they may not mean to hurt us; they may be playing, irritated or even frightened.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Respecting pets also means giving them space when they show signs of being distressed, overstimulated or tired.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Continue the conversation @Soulpup on Twitter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
