<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="749" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/04/09/living/tomboy-fashion/index.html" date_published="2013-04-09 11:52:10" category="living" author="Emanuella Grinberg, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Tomboy style no longer a passing fad</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7">Katherine McMillan wanted stylish shoes without the frills, so started making her own.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="11">She&amp;apost;s designing for women who blur the line between masculine and feminine.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="23">Tomboy style is no longer a passing fad, &amp;quot;Tomboy Style&amp;quot; blogger says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="37">Some say the term tomboy is outdated.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-11 10:19:17" annotation_time="221.72766" mapping_time_divergence="55.431915">
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">So when she couldn&amp;apost;t find a pair of shoes she liked, she decided to make her own.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="2">For Mrs. P. Hicks, McMillan is designing for women who blur the line between masculine and feminine, who gravitate toward styles traditionally associated with men: flat shoes with wide lasts, unembellished blouses and button-up shirts, unstructured sweaters and blazers, jeans and pants lacking unnecessary studs, embroidery or whiskering.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="3">As brands continue to adapt traditionally masculine styles for the female form, &amp;quot;the new statement on tomboy style is that it&amp;apost;s here to stay,&amp;quot; said Mettler, author of the 2012 book &amp;quot;Tomboy Style: Beyond the Boundaries of Fashion.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="37" ids_highlights="4">Not everybody is comfortable with the word &amp;quot;tomboy.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>All Katherine McMillan wanted in a shoe was style and comfort without the frilly bows or flowers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>She&amp;apost;s a working mother who tends to buy men&amp;apost;s shirts in small sizes and prefers the kinds of casual shoes made for men -- desert boots, moccasins, chukkas.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>She&amp;apost;ll take a pair of shoes or a jacket in olive green or navy blue over lavender or aqua any day.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think a lot of my friends would agree that we don&amp;apost;t want to look like an Easter egg when we go out,&amp;quot; said McMillan, who lives in Minneapolis, Minnesota.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m all for feeling like a girly-girl but there are ways to do it without being a French poodle.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Don&amp;apost;t get her wrong, she likes high heels and dresses, but not in pink.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>So when she couldn&amp;apost;t find a pair of shoes she liked, she decided to make her own.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Hers are desert boots, moccasins and chukkas made of leather and suede with a kelly green lining to distinguish them from what the guys wear.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>She launched her made-to-order collection in fall 2011 under the name Mrs. P. Hicks, a nod to Pierrepont Hicks, the successful menswear accessories brand she and her husband, Mark McMillan, created in 2009.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>He runs the business while she is the creative force behind Pierrepont Hicks&amp;apost; collection of neckties, pocket squares and bow ties, which has earned a devoted cult following among menswear bloggers and the people who read them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>For Mrs. P. Hicks, McMillan is designing for women who blur the line between masculine and feminine, who gravitate toward styles traditionally associated with men: flat shoes with wide lasts, unembellished blouses and button-up shirts, unstructured sweaters and blazers, jeans and pants lacking unnecessary studs, embroidery or whiskering.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s tomboy style, but that doesn&amp;apost;t mean it&amp;apost;s not feminine or sexy,&amp;quot; McMillan said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think you feel sexy and stylish when you&amp;apost;re wearing something you&amp;apost;re comfortable in.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>These looks have always been around, cycling in and out with the seasons, but the latest signs show they&amp;apost;re more than just a momentary fad.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Women are looking for shoes, shirts, even neckties that fit them better than their boyfriend&amp;apost;s clothes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Also, brands are popping up to meet those demands, from the artisanal approach of Mrs. P. Hicks to mass-market retailers like Madewell and J. Crew, which have been widely credited with giving &amp;quot;tomboy&amp;quot; fashion broad appeal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s easy to forget the time before J. Crew or &amp;quot;boyfriend shirts,&amp;quot; times when &amp;quot;nice girls&amp;quot; didn&amp;apost;t leave home in pants.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Katharine Hepburn and Diane Keaton were trailblazers, female fashion icons whose neckties and pants drew stares.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Modern style mavens Alexa Chung and Jenna Lyons show &amp;quot;tomboy chic&amp;quot; is more than a passing fashion, said Lizzie Garrett Mettler, creator of the popular &amp;quot;Tomboy Style&amp;quot; blog.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Just as modern American women have won the right to vote and compete for the same jobs as men, it&amp;apost;s nothing special for them to dress up in jeans or don a blazer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>A tomboy is more than a girl in boy&amp;apost;s clothing, Mettler says in her blog; it&amp;apost;s someone with an &amp;quot;inherent sense of confidence, rebelliousness and adventure.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s part style, part substance.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>As brands continue to adapt traditionally masculine styles for the female form, &amp;quot;the new statement on tomboy style is that it&amp;apost;s here to stay,&amp;quot; said Mettler, author of the 2012 book &amp;quot;Tomboy Style: Beyond the Boundaries of Fashion.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Designer Sadie Beaudet was also drawn to menswear, but she didn&amp;apost;t like the boxy fit on her body.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>She also didn&amp;apost;t like how women&amp;apost;s fashion was pulled from the racks one season and tossed a few months later, while menswear often had a timeless quality that never fell out of season.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>With her fiance, she started Tradlands, a line of tailored women&amp;apost;s shirts that incorporate masculine features, she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a small collection of eight button-up shirts with a higher collar that doesn&amp;apost;t necessarily lend itself to an exposed collarbone; the shirts have side gusset detail typically found in the workwear of the 1940s for reinforcement and brass snaps.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>All of their shirts are made in San Francisco, using denim and cotton sourced from the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re trying to walk that line with a dash of feminism in the fit but clearly masculine in the details,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Even the necktie is getting a feminine overhaul.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>What makes a lady tie?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The fabric and the width, naturally, said Nashville designer Otis James.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>His hand-stitched ties have earned him nods from publications like GQ and Garden and Gun.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>When the 29-year-old designer realized that many of his customers were women buying for their significant others, he decided to start creating products they might want for themselves.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m hoping maybe they&amp;apost;ll bring in more single women,&amp;quot; James said, mostly joking, in an interview in his Marathon Village studio last month.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think there&amp;apost;s definitely a market for them.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Not everybody is comfortable with the word &amp;quot;tomboy.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Some say the spirit of progressiveness has rendered the term archaic.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>When Carmela Spinelli hears the word &amp;quot;tomboy,&amp;quot; a particular look comes to mind: Strong, independent, rebellious.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>But the chairwoman of the fashion and accessories design department at the Savannah College of Art and Design said the description might need an update.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;To use a term that includes the word &amp;apost;boy&amp;apost; to describe a state of independence and free-thinking for women seems kind of backward,&amp;quot; Spinelli said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;The boundaries have changed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Women are strong and independent and have no sense of preciousness, so why would you use a term like tomboy to describe that?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Perhaps it&amp;apost;s because of the style&amp;apost;s close ties to menswear.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>McMillan&amp;apost;s Pierrepont Hicks is better-known, but Mrs. P. Hicks is her passion project.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>(Plus, she gets to keep the samples, she said.).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>From the start, McMillan and her husband decided to keep their products made in the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>That wasn&amp;apost;t hard to do with neckties and pocket square, but it proved much more difficult for women&amp;apost;s shoes, because so few manufacturers were equipped to do what she had dreamed up.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>McMillan ultimately partnered with Maine-based mens&amp;apost; shoe maker Rancourt and Co., one of few shoemakers in the United States who specialize in classic men&amp;apost;s styles similar to the ones she wanted.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>For her moccasins, she found another family-owned business in rural Minnesota.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>With Mrs. P. Hicks approaching the two-year mark, McMillan said she has finally hit a groove and found a market.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>&amp;quot;We even get orders from men now,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>&amp;quot;They say they like the green interior.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
