<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="690" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/26/living/earthships-new-mexico/index.html?hpt=hp_c4" date_published="2014-09-26 14:27:53" category="living" author="Meera Senthilingam, for CNN." highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Earthships, the sustainable homes made with old junk</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Earthships are self-sustainable buildings independent of all utilities.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="16, 5">The first Earthships were designed in New Mexico, in and near the city of Taos.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">Walls are made from recycled tires, tin cans and bottles.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="15">The price of each one ranges from $250,000 to $1.5 million.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-02 10:25:08" annotation_time="69.596" mapping_time_divergence="17.399">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;An Earthship is the name we have given a building or vessel that we use to live on this planet that is absolutely independent of all public and municipal utilities,&amp;quot; explains Michael Reynolds, founder of Earthship Biotecture, who developed the concept.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">In the mountains of New Mexico, USA, Reynolds has built 15 cliff-top homes which, as well as providing a view, were designed to prove that the Earthships could be built anywhere.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">At their core are walls made from old tires, bottles, and tin cans mixed with concrete, so your home leftovers are creating new homes.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="4">The Earthships range in price from $250,000 to $1.5 million.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="2">But remote deserts are not the only modus operandi, as Reynolds&amp;apost; company has also built 75 homes across the city of Taos, New Mexico and his designs have gone global.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The ability to live completely off the grid is now a reality courtesy of solar homes, known as Earthships.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The U-shaped buildings utilize local resources such as the sun and are made entirely of natural and recycled materials.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The future of city living may be to not need the city at all.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;An Earthship is the name we have given a building or vessel that we use to live on this planet that is absolutely independent of all public and municipal utilities,&amp;quot; explains Michael Reynolds, founder of Earthship Biotecture, who developed the concept.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>In the mountains of New Mexico, USA, Reynolds has built 15 cliff-top homes which, as well as providing a view, were designed to prove that the Earthships could be built anywhere.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>At their core are walls made from old tires, bottles, and tin cans mixed with concrete, so your home leftovers are creating new homes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Even sewage isn&amp;apost;t spared and is used in indoor and outdoor treatment cells for food production and landscaping.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Leftover &amp;apost;gray&amp;apost; water is also used to flush toilets.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;We were accused of running sewage through the living room,&amp;quot; says Reynolds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;That was scary to people but when you see the pictures of what it looks like, it&amp;apost;s no longer scary if you understand it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Most modern amenities such as plumbing, heating, power and even internet are provided in a self-sufficient way to change the face of remote living.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The use of a design known as the &amp;apost;stack effect&amp;apost; in their construction uses natural ventilation to regulate internal temperatures for comfort.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;A lot of people think off-the-grid living is like living in some kind of teepee or something,&amp;quot; says Reynolds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is a pretty damn nice house.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The Earthships range in price from $250,000 to $1.5 million.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>But remote deserts are not the only modus operandi, as Reynolds&amp;apost; company has also built 75 homes across the city of Taos, New Mexico and his designs have gone global.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Earthships have been built across the USA, entered Europe, and relief projects are being developed in Malawi, Guatemala, Haiti, India, Jamaica, Philippines, and New Zealand.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Fundraising is taking place for a self-sustaining music school on Easter Island, one of the most remote locations in the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>But the spread of these ships has not been plain sailing, as their radical design breaks most architectural rules.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Reynolds has battled with local governments about the Earthships meeting structural codes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>However, his fights are being won as hundreds of people now live, or use, these uniquely designed buildings around the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The company&amp;apost;s next goal is to expand from remote living to more self-sufficient cities which would be more affordable and sustainable to build -- an Earthship city.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;If some government or corporation was getting ready to do a city for ten thousand people, they&amp;apost;d spend ten years putting in infrastructure to support that city&amp;apost;s power and sewage,&amp;quot; concludes Reynolds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;We don&amp;apost;t need that: if I had a thousand acres somewhere, and funding, I could start building a city tomorrow.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
