<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="723" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/01/14/living/parents-happiness-child-free-studies" date_published="2014-01-14 16:07:27" category="living" author="Kelly Wallace, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>New studies: Are people without kids happier than parents?</title>
  <keywords>childfree,parent happiness,happiness study,are parents happier</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7">New study finds no difference in life satisfaction between parents and nonparents.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="23">Parents experienced more highs and lows than the child-free, study found.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="29">Another study found childless couples happier with their relationship than parents.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="47">Best takeaway for parents and childless: It&amp;apost;s the small things that matter, study found.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-22 15:56:47" annotation_time="147.662" mapping_time_divergence="73.831">
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">A report by Princeton University and Stony Brook University published in the Proceedings of the National Academy of Science found &amp;quot;very little difference&amp;quot; between the life satisfaction of parents and people without kids, once other factors -- such as income, education, religion and health -- were factored out, said Arthur Stone, one of the study &amp;apost;s co-authors.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="2">The Princeton-Stony Brook study -- which involved an examination of a survey of 1.8 million Americans, including parents between the ages of 34 and 46, conducted by Gallup from 2008 through 2012 -- did find one difference between parents and the childless: Parents tend to experience more highs and lows.</sentence>
      <sentence id="29" ids_highlights="3">In that study, which involved surveys of more than 5,000 people in England and in the United States, the authors found childless couples were happier with their relationships and their partners than parents were, and were doing more work on their relationships than parenting couples.</sentence>
      <sentence id="47" ids_highlights="4">&amp;quot;We need to think differently about what constitutes relationship work and we need to think about, if it&amp;apost;s those everyday small things that are important to people, then let&amp;apost;s think about what those small things might be and start to be more attuned to what&amp;apost;s going on in our own relationships,&amp;quot; said Gabb.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>When it comes to who is happier -- parents or child-free people -- most of the research up until now has concluded that it is the childless who are more satisfied with their overall lives.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>As a married mom of two, I always find myself reacting a bit defensively to that research.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m happy,&amp;quot; I say to myself.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>I may be stressed, sleep-deprived and sorely in need of &amp;quot;me&amp;quot; time, but I am very satisfied with my life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Isn&amp;apost;t it possible that I could be just as happy as someone without kids -- even if they have more time to sleep and take care of themselves?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>According to two new studies, the answer might be yes and no.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>A report by Princeton University and Stony Brook University published in the Proceedings of the National Academy of Science found &amp;quot;very little difference&amp;quot; between the life satisfaction of parents and people without kids, once other factors -- such as income, education, religion and health -- were factored out, said Arthur Stone, one of the study &amp;apost;s co-authors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>People with kids living at home tend to have more money and are more highly educated, more religious and in better health, said Stone, a professor of psychiatry and psychology at Stony Brook University.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;All of those are factors that go along with people having better life evaluations.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Once those factors were statistically removed, the study found no difference in how satisfied the two groups felt about their lives.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Stone said in an interview that similarities in reported happiness among parents and the child-free, especially in developed countries like the United States, can be chalked up to priorities, specifically whether a person chooses to have kids.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;I choose an orange because I like oranges.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>You choose an apple because you like apples.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>There&amp;apost;s no reason to think that your experiences should be any better than mine,&amp;quot; said Stone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;The orange is different than the apples.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Having kids is different than not having kids.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>It doesn&amp;apost;t mean that one is ... intrinsically better.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Sarah Maizes, author of the children&amp;apost;s book &amp;quot;On My Way to Bed&amp;quot; and a mom of three in Los Angeles, agrees.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s like asking who&amp;apost;s happier -- people who like pizza or people who like Chinese?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>she said on Facebook.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;Now what I&amp;apost;d like to know is who lives longer.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>... That you can measure!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The Princeton-Stony Brook study -- which involved an examination of a survey of 1.8 million Americans, including parents between the ages of 34 and 46, conducted by Gallup from 2008 through 2012 -- did find one difference between parents and the childless: Parents tend to experience more highs and lows.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;They have higher highs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>They have more joy in their lives, but also they have more stress and negative emotions as well,&amp;quot; said Stone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Adina McGinley, a mom of three who lives outside New York City, said watching children grow &amp;quot;is probably life&amp;apost;s greatest joy.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>At the same time, she said, &amp;quot;Stress over wanting your kids to have good lives can be tapped into at any time, sometimes to an awful degree and this adds endless strain to marriage.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>That strain can lead parents to feel less satisfied with their relationship, according to another study, this one by the Open University in England.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>In that study, which involved surveys of more than 5,000 people in England and in the United States, the authors found childless couples were happier with their relationships and their partners than parents were, and were doing more work on their relationships than parenting couples.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>When asked who was the most important person in their lives, mothers said their children and fathers said their partners, the study found.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;(It) may be during those mid-years when people are parenting that there is a shift away from the relationship for women as they focus more on children,&amp;quot; said Dr. Jacqui Gabb, one of the study&amp;apost;s co-authors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Gabb, who is a senior lecturer in social policy at the Open University, said this doesn&amp;apost;t mean the relationships are not working.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;It just means there is a difference in emphasis and probably partly due to the time pinch,&amp;quot; she added.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;There just isn&amp;apost;t as much time to devote to the relationship.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Jen Bosse, a mom of two who blogs at Defining My Happy, said on Facebook, &amp;quot;All too often when couples have kids, they begin to deprioritize one another.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s the problem, not the children.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Ironically, according to the Open University study, mothers were &amp;quot;significantly happier with life&amp;quot; than any other group including childless women -- a finding, Gabb says, which can be explained by how mothers said children were No. 1 in their lives.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;If they&amp;apost;re the happiest with life but the least content with the level of relationship satisfaction and least happy with partners and least happy with the amount of maintenance (of the relationship), but they&amp;apost;re happy with life, then there&amp;apost;s got to be something,&amp;quot; said Gabb.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>What&amp;apost;s a parent or a nonparent to make of this latest, somewhat conflicting research?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Perhaps the most actionable finding for our lives comes from the Open University study, aptly titled &amp;quot;Enduring Love?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Couple Relationships in the 21st Century.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>The authors found that when asked what makes people feel most valued in their relationship, research participants said small acts of kindness.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s as little as saying &amp;apost;I love you,&amp;apost;&amp;quot; said Gabb.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;Out of everything in life, (mothers) identified having a cup of tea brought to them in bed as significant.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>In the U.S., we might replace that cup of tea with a latte from Starbucks, but we all get the point.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Relationships benefit from those everyday gestures.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>&amp;quot;We need to think differently about what constitutes relationship work and we need to think about, if it&amp;apost;s those everyday small things that are important to people, then let&amp;apost;s think about what those small things might be and start to be more attuned to what&amp;apost;s going on in our own relationships,&amp;quot; said Gabb.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>I think I&amp;apost;ll be picking up a latte on my way home tonight!</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Follow Kelly Wallace on Twitter and like CNN Living on Facebook.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
