<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="742" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/09/11/living/high-cost-of-fashion/index.html" date_published="2012-09-11 17:50:58" category="living" author="Elizabeth Cline, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>The fashionista&amp;apost;s dilemma: Cheap clothes</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="25">Elizabeth Cline: Major fashion brands should reduce water and energy use, and waste.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="38">The average American consumer spends $1,700 a year on apparel.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="9">About 3% of apparel is produced in the United States.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-11 14:59:04" annotation_time="10.863667">
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="3">Few of those purchases are made here -- 3% of apparel is produced in the United States, down from about half in 1990.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="1">Major fashion brands also have an obligation to dramatically reduce the amount of water and energy used and waste emitted in making and selling their clothes, as well as to offer consumers more stylish products that are made out of recycled and eco-friendly materials.</sentence>
      <sentence id="38" ids_highlights="2">The average American consumer spends $1,700 a year on apparel.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>When was the last time you looked at the label on your clothes to check where they were made or what they are made of?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>A few years ago, I was living a paradox familiar to many Americans: eating local and organic food, carrying reusable bags to the grocery store and choosing eco-friendly products wherever I could.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>This mindfulness was in no way extended to my closet -- I owned more than 350 items of clothes, every single bit of it cheap, trendy, poorly made and assembled in low-wage factories in other countries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Fashion today has a here-today-gone-tomorrow mentality, where the latest look, lowest price or the hottest designer are paramount and quantity is valued over quality.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>For the first time in history, we are consuming clothes as a disposable good, buying a cheap dress for a date night and wearing it but once or twice.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>These changing attitudes prompted me to write my book, &amp;quot;Overdressed: The Shockingly High Cost of Cheap Fashion,&amp;quot; and what I learned about the fashion industry during the process compelled me to change.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Our consumption of clothing is growing at an alarming rate.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Most Americans have closets brimming, if not overflowing with clothes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Few of those purchases are made here -- 3% of apparel is produced in the United States, down from about half in 1990.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>While American factories sit empty, our thirst for cheap imported clothing has kept the cash registers at many stores humming throughout the recession.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Fashion&amp;apost;s environmental footprint has also mushroomed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>There are more than 80 billion garments produced around the world today, and according to a study by the UK&amp;apost;s Cambridge University, the industry is creating 70 million tons of waste water as of 2006 in the UK alone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>In China, the largest clothing manufacturer in the world, the textile industry is also a major polluter.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Last year, I traveled undercover to southern China and saw smog enshrouding a landscape of factories and, more shockingly, hundreds of factory workers wearing cheap, trendy clothes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>As China&amp;apost;s consumer class grows, already-scarce resources like water and petroleum may soon buckle under all of this shopping.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>In July, when it came out that the Olympic uniforms were made in China, Americans were outraged, making it clear that we&amp;apost;re growing weary of soulless consumption.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>I believe we&amp;apost;re ready for more meaningful wardrobes, and to support our amazing clothing heritage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>My mother recently gave me a dress that she wore in high school in the 1960s.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>It was made by Jonathan Logan, a juniors brand that was considered cheap for its day -- the dress is 100% wool, fully lined, finished with French seams and made in the USA.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>What&amp;apost;s so wonderful about locally made fashion is that it offers designers tight control over their product, has a lower environmental footprint and makes it easier to keep an eye on any labor problems.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>And according to a Cotton Incorporated Lifestyle Monitor survey, approximately 55% of consumers agree it is &amp;quot;very/somewhat important&amp;quot; that their clothing is made in the U.S.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>I was recently in Portland, Oregon, and met with the owners of Spooltown and the Portland Garment Factory, two small shops that have opened recently in a city that had very little existing garment industry infrastructure.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>They were able to build profitable manufacturing businesses from scratch.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Just imagine what other Americans cities could do with the right government and consumer support.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Major fashion brands also have an obligation to dramatically reduce the amount of water and energy used and waste emitted in making and selling their clothes, as well as to offer consumers more stylish products that are made out of recycled and eco-friendly materials.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Nike is creating athletic team uniforms out of recycled PET bottles and has recycled more than 28 million pairs of athletic shoes through their Reuse-a-Shoe program; Eileen Fisher has just released a beautiful line of bluesign-certified silk shirts dyed without hazardous chemicals; and H&amp;amp;M has agreed to stop using toxic and nonbiodegradable perfluorinated compounds, called PFCs, in their outerwear by 2013.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>These efforts need to be expanded.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Clothing designers also need to rethink the materials they&amp;apost;re using and how they&amp;apost;re sourced.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Fortunately, eco-friendly textiles have improved so much in recent years that luxurious eco-friendly fibers like Tencel, Modal and Cupro have far more in common with silk than a hemp sack.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Some emerging designers are eschewing new textiles altogether for upcycling, which means taking waste and reclaimed textile material and turning it into a product with higher value.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>I recently bought a lovely red tunic upcycled from a men&amp;apost;s dress shirt produced by a small Brooklyn designer called State.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>According to the Environmental Protection Agency, we are throwing away 68 pounds of textiles per person per year and donating such a staggering volume of clothes that a majority of our donations to charity have to be sold to textile recyclers who then sell more than half of our used clothes overseas, largely to Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Retailers like Eileen Fisher and Patagonia are accepting returns of their worn products -- Fisher resells them in her Green Eileen retail store, while Patagonia recycles theirs into new products.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Fast-fashion stores need to start these types of recycling programs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Consumers can also take more responsibility by repairing and caring for the clothes they own, trading their duds at clothing swaps and, for the particularly creative, refashioning last year&amp;apost;s styles into fresh looks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Now for the million-dollar question: How can you afford this?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>It all starts by taking an honest look at how you&amp;apost;re spending money on clothes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>The average American consumer spends $1,700 a year on apparel.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Most of us own more clothing than we know what to do with, so I encourage people to first of all buy less clothing and to try to limit trendy, throwaway purchases to only one or two a season.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Divert the rest of your clothing budget to clothes that you truly love and are going to wear for several seasons.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>If just a quarter of our purchases were put toward locally made or eco-friendly fashion and fashion companies with a commitment to sustainability, we could change the face of the industry.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>I also believe we&amp;apost;d be happier with our clothes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>See what a cotton T-shirt goes through before it gets to you.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Is your closet filled with cheap, disposable clothing?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Do you think it&amp;apost;s worth changing how you shop?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Share your thoughts in the comments section below.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
