<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="750" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/07/07/living/transgender-dmv-complaint-west-virginia/index.html" date_published="2014-07-08 02:10:57" category="living" author="Astead Herndon, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Transgender women complain of DMV mistreatment</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7">Transgender women report being called &amp;quot;it,&amp;quot; forced to take off makeup for photo.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="22">DMV chief: Wearing excessive makeup as male falls under attempting to conceal identity .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="41">Commissioner renounces any employees who treated women with disrespect .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-01 11:10:45" annotation_time="35.886665">
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;The manager referred to me as &amp;apost;it&amp;apost; and told me to take off my makeup, wig and fake eyelashes.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="2">Under West Virginia law, Dale said, a photo that deviates from gender listed on the license falls under an &amp;quot;attempt to conceal or alter your identity or appearance.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="41" ids_highlights="3">However, he stressed that if their internal review finds any customer service representative or manager treated the women with disrespect, his office would issue a swift apology.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>With its long lines and seemingly endless paperwork, a trip to the Department of Motor Vehicles can rarely be classified as fun.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But it could be worse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Two West Virginia transgender women claim their recent DMV visits were especially harrowing as they attempted to update their names and change their driver&amp;apost;s license photos.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>In separate incidents, both recount officials telling them their appearance looked too feminine for a driver&amp;apost;s license issued to a male and that they would have to dress down for their photos.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Now they&amp;apost;ve enlisted The Transgender Legal Defense &amp;amp; Education Fund to get their stories heard.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;(A manager) told me it was a DMV policy that people listed as male could not wear makeup,&amp;quot; said Kristen Skinner.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;The manager referred to me as &amp;apost;it&amp;apost; and told me to take off my makeup, wig and fake eyelashes.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Skinner, whose hair and eyelashes were her own and not fake, eventually took the license photo after removing all facial makeup.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The 45-year-old IT professional called the experience at the Charles Town office in Jefferson County on January 7 &amp;quot;humiliating.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;The way I was treated was unprofessional,&amp;quot; Skinner said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;Isn&amp;apost;t the point of a photo identification to identify how you look every day?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Trudy Kitzmiller said she had a similar experience many months later in neighboring Berkeley County.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>According to her, after showing all the legal paperwork to change her name on her driver&amp;apost;s license, DMV workers in Martinsburg demanded she remove all makeup, jewelry and long hair.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The 52-year-old says she was also called &amp;quot;it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;It doesn&amp;apost;t matter whether my license says M or F. I&amp;apost;m still a transgendered woman, and they shouldn&amp;apost;t tell me how to dress or appear,&amp;quot; Kitzmiller said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;I don&amp;apost;t know many transgender women in this state, but it (should have) never happened that way.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>I am a human being and should be treated as a human being.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Kitzmiller refused to change her physical appearance and left the DMV on May 10 without a new driver&amp;apost;s license.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>In an interview with CNN, Steve Dale, acting commissioner of West Virginia&amp;apost;s Department of Motor Vehicles, renounced any remarks that made individuals feel uncomfortable.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;I do not condone or approve any conduct which embarrassed an applicant or would single an applicant out,&amp;quot; he said, adding the department is investigating the women&amp;apost;s claims of verbal humiliation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>However, Dale emphasized he believes proper protocol was followed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Under West Virginia law, Dale said, a photo that deviates from gender listed on the license falls under an &amp;quot;attempt to conceal or alter your identity or appearance.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;It would be the same as if you wanted to take a driver&amp;apost;s license picture with a scarf over your face or if you we were wearing some type of garb that conceals your identity,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;And the decision is a subjective one that is handed down by the customer service representative, and then is subject to appeal by the manager and then it could come all the way up to me, the commissioner.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Dale recommends each woman receive a court-ordered statement that indicates they have transitioned genders.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Then, and only then, can their photo appearance &amp;quot;match&amp;quot; their listed driver&amp;apost;s license gender.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Kitzmiller and Skinner are listed as men on their licences.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;Normally, if a customer comes in with the court order designating a gender change, it is handled discreetly at the local office and the information is changed,&amp;quot; Dale said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;The customer leaves the office with what the circuit court judge has directed and the issue does not reach my desk.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>However, according to both women and the Transgender Legal Defense &amp;amp; Education Fund, a court-ordered gender change may not be that easy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>In most cases, the court requires medical action to issue the order, which some transgender people are uncomfortable with or simply cannot afford.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Skinner said cost is an issue for her.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Michael Silverman, the executive director of the Transgender Fund, elaborated on the cost issue.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;To get your gender changed under the West Virginia license, one must perform a certain surgery.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>And for many people, this is not possible,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;And whether that&amp;apost;s because of discriminatory insurance that does not recognize this or through other means should not matter.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Silverman disagreed with the DMV&amp;apost;s characterization that makeup, long hair and even eyelashes can equate to attempting to conceal an identity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;Trudy and Kristen have struggled to become who they are, and they are finally open and honest now in presenting the women they truly are,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is how their friends, family, co-workers and community know them, and the DMV cannot tell them they have to hide their true identities as transgender women.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Dale told CNN that he believes many other states have similar policies and that the West Virginia DMV has no plans to change its protocol.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>However, he stressed that if their internal review finds any customer service representative or manager treated the women with disrespect, his office would issue a swift apology.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;We want all our applicants to be treated with respect no matter their gender choices, race or creed.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Regardless of the outcome of the review, Kitzmiller says she is struggling to find steady work without a valid ID card.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>She has worked as a heavy-machine operator.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>&amp;quot;Employers will not hire me because my union card and everything else shows me as Trudy,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>&amp;quot;My union brothers and sisters treated me great.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>I was so surprised to see how I was treated by government employees.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
