<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="692" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/06/19/living/entrepreneur-barbie/index.html?hpt=ibu_c2" date_published="2014-06-19 21:32:59" category="living" author="Emanuella Grinberg, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Entrepreneur Barbie leans into a new career</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Mattel says it hopes to inspire female entrepreneurs with new Barbie.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">Entrepreneur Barbie partners with eight real-life female entrepreneurs.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="11">Some criticized Mattel for suiting up Entrepreneur Barbie in a pink dress and her usual proportions.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-26 15:31:20" annotation_time="18.758">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">Mattel says it hopes to inspire a generation of female entrepreneurs with Entrepreneur Barbie, which went on sale Thursday on Amazon.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">She also comes with a marketing back story in which Mattel partnered with eight real-life female entrepreneurs to serve as &amp;quot;chief inspiration officers.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="3">Entrepreneur Barbie comes wearing a fitted pink dress in her usual unrealistic proportions.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Barbie boasts an extensive resume of more than 150 careers, from fashion model to nurse, astronaut, veterinarian, firefighter, aerobics instructor and rapper.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Now, Barbie is leaning in with a 21st century gig as an entrepreneur.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Entrepreneur Barbie is available in four ethnicities and carries the essentials of start-up life: a tablet, smartphone and briefcase.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Mattel says it hopes to inspire a generation of female entrepreneurs with Entrepreneur Barbie, which went on sale Thursday on Amazon.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>She also comes with a marketing back story in which Mattel partnered with eight real-life female entrepreneurs to serve as &amp;quot;chief inspiration officers.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;Having positive role models for dolls that are inspiring young girls to be entrepreneurs is exactly what we need to inspire a generation of young women to start running businesses,&amp;quot; Reshma Saujani, founder of Girls Who Code, said in an interview with TechCrunch.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;You can&amp;apost;t be what you cannot see.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;To me, Barbie has always been a way to live out each and every one of my dreams and that young women today have Barbie as a role model, an icon in the form of an entrepreneur is so exciting and the best form of inspiration,&amp;quot; said Jennifer Fleiss, co-founder of Rent the Runway.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>In typical start-up style, Entrepreneur Barbie made her debut by hosting a Twitter #BarbieChat in which she invited her #CIOs to share stories of &amp;quot;breaking glass (and plastic) ceilings.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>While many participants in Wednesday&amp;apost;s Twitter chat praised Barbie&amp;apost;s latest career, Mattel faced familiar criticism for pink-washing the message.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Entrepreneur Barbie comes wearing a fitted pink dress in her usual unrealistic proportions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;If we&amp;apost;re talking representation, let&amp;apost;s take a step back.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>It is impossible to ever grow up and be Barbie.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>She&amp;apost;s anatomically impossible (unless you get tons of plastic surgery and survive on light and air),&amp;quot; writer Sarah Gray said in a Salon column.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;Entrepreneur Barbie is modern woman with her smartphone and her tablet stuck in a sexist, outdated, dangerous representation of femininity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>I take umbrage with the fact that, even though this doll is backed by an awesome group of diverse women - aimed at providing positive representation - Barbie still represents this problematic view of women.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The backlash is nothing new.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Barbie caused a stir in February when Mattel and Sports Illustrated revealed that she would appear in the 50th anniversary edition of its annual swimsuit edition.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The partnership included a promotional cover-wrap on 1,000 copies declaring Barbie &amp;quot;the doll that started it all,&amp;quot; a four-page advertising feature inside the magazine and video outtakes posted online.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The doll was also available for sale at Target.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Mattel stood by Barbie&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;unapologetic&amp;quot; stance, and continues to use the #unapologetic hashtag in its social media campaigns for Entrepreneur Barbie.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Do you think Entrepreneur Barbie is a suitable role model for children?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Share your take, and your favorite iteration of Barbie, in the comments section below.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
