<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="745" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/05/28/living/white-people-diversity-identity/index.html" date_published="2014-05-28 12:13:16" category="living" author="Susan Bodnar, Special to CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>The uncomfortable role white parents play in diversity</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="11">Susan Bodnar: &amp;quot;White is not the signifier of normal&amp;quot; .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="15">Author: Work, students and her kid&amp;apost;s schools altered her &amp;quot;white centric&amp;quot; perspective .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="41">Bodnar: I want to live in a society where dignified difference constitutes our common core.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="59">Raise children to accept their own stories so they can respect others, author says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-13 16:51:37" annotation_time="37.961502">
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="1">White is not the signifier of normal.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="2">Three influences have altered my white-centric perspective: my psychology students, the people with whom I work in my clinical practice and the diversity work of both my kids&amp;apost; New York City private schools.</sentence>
      <sentence id="41" ids_highlights="3">I now look at diversity as something that is in my interest: I want to live in a society where dignified difference constitutes our common core.</sentence>
      <sentence id="59" ids_highlights="4">When we raise children to accept and acknowledge their own story, they learn to listen to someone else&amp;apost;s, with respect.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>In my family, I&amp;apost;m always bringing up stories from the past, our family&amp;apost;s story, our diversity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>My daughter often rolls her eyes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;We don&amp;apost;t need to keep talking about this stuff.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>We get it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>My son admonishes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;We know!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>In truth, their schools have done of a good job trying to make their population more closely resemble our country and our world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>My kids have friends of all races, cultures and social classes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>However, as a female white mom married to a male white dad with two biologically conceived white children, I&amp;apost;m trying to make a different point.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>I want them to understand that light skin color is not the norm from which everyone differs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>White is not the signifier of normal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Many white kids take diversity for granted.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>They have worked hard to overcome stereotypes and bias and to accept other people as different.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The fact that they may be someone else&amp;apost;s diversity rarely occurs to them, let alone most white adults.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Three influences have altered my white-centric perspective: my psychology students, the people with whom I work in my clinical practice and the diversity work of both my kids&amp;apost; New York City private schools.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Some of my psychology students wanted to write a children&amp;apost;s book where every character had a different identity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Children&amp;apost;s books generally feature characters of one race or ethnicity, not multiple identities in interaction with one another.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>When we finished our first draft, we realized our characters had become very close friends.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>They each came from a different place but everyone had came from somewhere.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Skin color doesn&amp;apost;t define personhood, but since race is a marker of identity in our society, the experience of personhood includes having to deal with the meanings others attribute to racial identity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Protected by the privacy of a clinical relationship, beautiful black and brown women have shared how ugly they feel.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Gentle dark-skinned men convey the humiliation that overcomes them when white people mistake them for dangerous criminals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Since whiteness has become synonymous with a better life, it is easy for any lighter-skinned person to use skin color as a shield against hurtful stereotypes about social class, gender, sexuality, family history or even mental illness.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>When white people deny their own embarrassing identity markers, we perpetuate the hypocrisy that only people of color have these problems.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>As a psychologist -- no, as a person -- recognizing status and identity anxiety as a mutual experience lifts the veil that ordinarily separates us from each other.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>This year, the parents association at one of my kids&amp;apost; schools named me co-chair of the diversity committee.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>I felt so self-conscious.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Group leadership called forth a greater reckoning with my identity than simply participating in a committee.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>It also provided me the chance to experience being a minority member of a group.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Sometimes I sat as the only white person at the table feeling really insecure, worried that I would be seen as a white stereotype instead of as myself.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>How did growing up white with financial struggles intersect with racial diversity?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>When white people want to &amp;quot;help&amp;quot; people of color, it always reeks of privilege and entitlement as in, &amp;quot;let me help you with your problems.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a different sentiment than &amp;quot;let&amp;apost;s help each other with our problems.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Did people of color trust me?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Did they wonder what I was doing on the diversity committee?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Was it my job to speak for the concerns of underrepresented minorities?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Or did I contribute more by trying to put forth a more multifaceted approach to the question of identity?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>How can we sit with each other&amp;apost;s differences without feeling compelled to rank one way of being or looking as being better or worse than the other?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Our diversity committee ultimately worked through these questions in our conversations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Although we did not fully answer them, we found that by talking about them, we discovered the theme of our work and developed a friendship.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>I now look at diversity as something that is in my interest: I want to live in a society where dignified difference constitutes our common core.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Nuances in how we think, feel, work and love define what it means to be human.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Everyone is unusual and unique.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Racism is just another word for hating our realness.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Our commonality as a country derives from the fact that we all have an identity just beneath the surface of our skins.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>The variety of stories that inhabit the people who call this country home -- from the brutality of slavery to the flight from genocides to the call to some better god -- enable democracy&amp;apost;s creative synergy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>The hands that have built the instruments of modern America have been every color, every nationality and every religion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>I want to be part of a world that loves and embraces humanity as a diverse and interconnected organism.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>I want to be part of a world that accepts that every difference has a color, and every color has a unique meaning.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>How do I do this?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>I realized that it starts at home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Rather than teaching my kids that they are white, I want to impart to them that they are part of a kaleidoscope -- lots of continually shifting colors and shapes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>They don&amp;apost;t always want to hear their parents tell another story about grandpa&amp;apost;s poverty or the coal-mining relatives.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>But this history holds our family&amp;apost;s painful and joyous truths.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>Every family need only peel back the layers of a few generations to find their own story.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>Authentic family history exposes everyone&amp;apost;s diversity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>A society that embraces uniqueness loves the messiness of the human condition.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>Being loved despite or because of our messy truths creates empathy rather than sympathy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="37">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="59">
          <content>When we raise children to accept and acknowledge their own story, they learn to listen to someone else&amp;apost;s, with respect.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
