<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="726" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/06/19/living/women-cheerful-leaders/index.html" date_published="2013-06-19 21:20:11" category="living" author="Sylvia Ann Hewlett, Special to CNN " highlights_mapped="false" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Opinion: Are cheerful female bosses hurt in biz?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="15">A recent study suggests cheerfulness could hold back female leaders .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="15">This is the latest in several studies that look at women&amp;apost;s path to leadership.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="53">The author says as long as the stereotypical leader looks like a man, women will face trade-offs.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_time="24.413">
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="1, 2">A recent study suggests cheerfulness could hold back female leaders, which is just the latest in a body of research exploring the behavioral barriers women encounter on the road to the top.</sentence>
      <sentence id="53" ids_highlights="3">But the &amp;quot;damned if you do, doomed if you don&amp;apost;t&amp;quot; trade-off will continue to snag many potentially high-impact females for one fundamental reason: As long as the stereotypical leader looks like a man, women will find themselves up against the impossible expectation to be someone they are not.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Early in Dara&amp;apost;s career, she was told by a coach that &amp;quot;honey attracts more bees than vinegar,&amp;quot; so she took pains to rein in her natural candor and soften her opinions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But when she started her present job as vice president at a national retailer, her boss told her she was too nice.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;Where&amp;apost;s the balance?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Dara muses.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;Do they want me to be harder or softer?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>With men or with women?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>With my superiors or my subordinates?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s tricky to figure out.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Call it the Goldilocks Syndrome.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s the double bind women too often find themselves entangled in when they try to prove they have what it takes to be a leader.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>They&amp;apost;re called out for being either too this or too that: too feminine or too masculine, too self-deprecating or too self-aggrandizing, too frumpy or too provocative, too bossy (read: bitch) or too circumspect (read: cream puff).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>They&amp;apost;re never &amp;quot;just right.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>In short, smart women face tough choices.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Should they try to be perceived as competent or likeable?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>A recent study suggests cheerfulness could hold back female leaders, which is just the latest in a body of research exploring the behavioral barriers women encounter on the road to the top.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Research conducted in 2012 by the Center for Talent Innovation, the New York think tank where I serve as president, shows that across all three pillars of executive presence - gravitas, communication and appearance -- traits or behaviors thought to enhance a woman&amp;apost;s executive presence are just as often cited as likely to detract from it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Focus group participants told us, for example, that too much makeup undermines a woman&amp;apost;s credibility, but then faulted female leaders for looking too unpolished.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Forty-two percent of our survey respondents said that unkempt nails detract from a woman&amp;apost;s executive presence, yet nearly as many (37%) said that &amp;quot;overly done&amp;quot; nails were un-leader-like.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The issue of age, for women, is fraught with peril: Almost the same number of respondents (8% vs 11%) said &amp;quot;looking too young&amp;quot; was a liability as told us &amp;quot;looking too old&amp;quot; undermined a woman&amp;apost;s executive presence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>When we pressed managers to identify the &amp;quot;sweet spot&amp;quot; for women in terms of looking just the right age, we discovered the band of acceptability was somewhere between the ages of 39 and 42.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Older women are invisible, they explained, while younger women project &amp;quot;the wrong kind&amp;quot; of visibility.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Everyone I spoke to agreed that those awful days when women donned mannish suits and bow-ties are long gone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>But they also conceded that &amp;quot;getting it right&amp;quot; across all professions and environments was a tightrope act.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Suzi Digby, a British conductor, was particularly adamant that women not compromise their femininity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s counterproductive to look like a man,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;You give up a card.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>In her profession, however, this presents special difficulties.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Conducting demands she put her back to the audience, a pose that features her posterior.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Men can wear tails to downplay the distraction: &amp;quot;Women tend to have big bums, and that is bad: it has connotations,&amp;quot; she points out.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>So to downplay the distraction of presenting her backside, and to strike the right silhouette (tall, lean, clean-lined), Digby wears heels and &amp;quot;a well-cut trouser suit.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>She also ties back her long hair.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s important to get it right,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Then she sighs and adds, &amp;quot;I just don&amp;apost;t know any women who do.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Women seeking to command a room run up against a similarly narrow band of acceptability.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>If they speak confidently about their accomplishments, it will cost them: 29% of our survey respondents said &amp;quot;tooting your own horn&amp;quot; detracts from a woman&amp;apost;s executive presence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Yet 24% felt that &amp;quot;self-deprecating&amp;quot; behavior undermines it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Women, we learned, are deemed to be &amp;quot;too shrill&amp;quot; (which seems to be the universal code for describing overly emotional and/or egregiously feminine women) or not outspoken enough; too direct in their remarks (&amp;quot;ruthless&amp;quot; being a common descriptor) or &amp;quot;too nice,&amp;quot; meaning ineffectual.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>The too blunt/too nice bind also surfaced: 17% of respondents believe a &amp;quot;failure to convey empathy&amp;quot; detracts from a woman&amp;apost;s executive presence; a nearly equal number (15%) believe that being &amp;quot;too nice&amp;quot; also detracts from it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>The trickiest terrain a woman must navigate concerns her gravitas, where the effective-but-unlikeable chasm yawns the widest.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>A woman who is decisive, assertive and willing to hold her ground risks being perceived as shrill, aggressive, or uncooperative (&amp;quot;not a team player&amp;quot;).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>A man is viewed as a strong personality if he is arguing a point, whereas a woman arguing the same point is viewed as a bitch and &amp;quot;hard to get along with,&amp;quot; one focus group participant observed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Our survey results reflected her confusion perfectly: 31% of respondents said that being &amp;quot;too bossy&amp;quot; undermines a woman&amp;apost;s executive presence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Another 31% said being &amp;quot;too passive&amp;quot; undermines it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Go figure.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Nobody knows the Goldilocks Syndrome better than Hillary Clinton.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>For as long as she has occupied the national consciousness - as first lady, as senator, and as secretary of state - she has never been quite &amp;quot;right&amp;quot;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Too female to be taken seriously (remember that bit of cleavage she revealed on the Senate floor?).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>, she was also dubbed too aggressive for driving health care reform.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>She was perceived as too accomplished to appeal to the electorate, but too politically inexperienced to be elected president; too much Bill&amp;apost;s wife to assume the White House in his wake, but not enough of a mother to Chelsea to win the women&amp;apost;s vote.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>If only she&amp;apost;d baked more cookies!</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>Clinton eventually proved that a female leader could be both effective and endearing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>When she stepped down from her Cabinet position in 2012, she had approval ratings higher than President Obama&amp;apost;s.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>But the &amp;quot;damned if you do, doomed if you don&amp;apost;t&amp;quot; trade-off will continue to snag many potentially high-impact females for one fundamental reason: As long as the stereotypical leader looks like a man, women will find themselves up against the impossible expectation to be someone they are not.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
