<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="727" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/12/13/living/millennial-women-wage-parity-identity" date_published="2013-12-13 22:03:09" category="living" author="Shelby Knox, Special to CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Opinion: Millennial women see gains, and continue to fight wage gap</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">New Pew Research study shows millennial women face narrowest pay gap on record.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">Shelby Knox: Until women are paid the same as men, we will never be truly equal.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="13">75% of millennial women believe more change is needed to combat workplace inequality.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="2">Knox: Millennial women might be the generation to make workplaces equal.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-11 10:18:33" annotation_time="81.37967" mapping_time_divergence="20.344917">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">A new Pew Research Center study shows that millennial women are entering the workplace at near wage parity, with the narrowest pay gap on record.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="4">Millennial women like me are more likely to have graduated from college than their male counterparts.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">But until women are paid the same as men, we will never be truly equal.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="3">The Pew study found that an astounding 75% of millennial women believe more changes are needed to combat gender inequality in the workplace.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A new Pew Research Center study shows that millennial women are entering the workplace at near wage parity, with the narrowest pay gap on record.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Millennial women like me are more likely to have graduated from college than their male counterparts.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>We have role models like Marissa Mayer and new General Motors CEO Mary Barra.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Today, there&amp;apost;s a much more open conversation about sexism and how it manifests than there was 10 years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>And it&amp;apost;s no coincidence that a recent poll from Ms. magazine found that 73% of women voters under 30 identify as feminist.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>It would seem today&amp;apost;s young women are set for the post-feminist professional paradise dreamed up by our foremothers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>But until women are paid the same as men, we will never be truly equal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>In a capitalist society, money is the key indicator of worth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The wage gap has functioned across history to make women dependent on men as providers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>We can&amp;apost;t save as much for retirement, stash away cash to treat ourselves or even take care of our families in the way we want if we&amp;apost;re starting at a deficit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>This is an issue of financial security for a generation already facing much more instability than our parents or grandparents.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>READ: Millennial women are closing pay gap, but pessimistic about workplace equality.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The Pew study found that an astounding 75% of millennial women believe more changes are needed to combat gender inequality in the workplace.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>It makes sense, then, that these are the same young activists who have been working valiantly for the passage of the Paycheck Fairness Act and who see working-class heroine Lilly Ledbetter as a more imitable role model than Sheryl Sandberg.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Millennial women can get involved by letting their representatives know they want legislation that addresses wage parity for men and women.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Additionally, one of the most powerful things young women can do for their own negotiations is to organize with their peers before and after taking a job, so they can know compare notes and know if they are being underpaid.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Information makes a difference in knowing what to ask for.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The best news to come out of this study is that we strongly and rightly acknowledge that the old boy&amp;apost;s club is still in place.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Young women are far more likely than men their age to cite the continued existence of the wage gap and the reality -- supported by a glance at a recent study on the stagnant role of women on corporate boards -- that men have it easier when it comes to getting the top job.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>They are just as likely as older women to say that society is set still set up to serve men.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s notable and promising, since many women my age have been fed the myth that the feminist movement achieved its goals and sexism no longer exists.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>But I worry that we, as young women, while understanding sexism to be a systemic problem, still think of it as something we have to fix individually -- and therefore, we don&amp;apost;t want to see ourselves as victims of it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>In the Pew study, I was surprised to see that while women are highly aware of gender discrimination and the different forms it takes, very few reported experiencing it themselves.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>READ: The generation we love to dump on.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s much less scary to imagine sexism as something that happens to other women.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Once you&amp;apost;re forced to admit that you&amp;apost;ve experienced it, you have to either accept it or do something about it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Feminism is hearing your pain and your struggle in another woman&amp;apost;s voice and suddenly realizing there&amp;apost;s nothing wrong with you and nothing wrong with her, but something wrong with the world trying to make you think there is.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s easy to focus the conversation on specific examples of highly privileged women who&amp;apost;ve made it to the upper echelons of power.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>But feminism isn&amp;apost;t about making it possible for a few women to get power.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Instead, it&amp;apost;s about changing the system from the ground up so that all women have that opportunity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>In order to do that, women have to be on an equal playing field in terms of pay from the moment they accept their first job.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Some may take from this new study that millennial women, despite the narrowing wage gap, have a bleak view of their future.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>As a member of that group, I&amp;apost;d argue that we have a realistic view.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s that understanding -- that the fight is not over and there is still much more work to be done -- that might make us the generation that crafts workplaces and a world where sexism is truly a thing of the past.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
