<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="713" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/01/24/living/justin-bieber-arrest-talk-to-kids-parents/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-01-24 17:06:15" category="living" author="Kelly Wallace, CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Justin Bieber&amp;apost;s arrest: What do you tell the kids?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Justin Bieber&amp;apost;s arrest is a conversation starter, many parents say.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">Parents should do more listening than talking, one mom says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="11">Asking kids what defines &amp;quot;greatness&amp;quot; could be beneficial, former principal says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 20:19:42" annotation_time="19.545">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">But instead of fretting over what to say, many parents believe his arrest is a chance to continue the conversation about drinking, drug use and doing either while behind the wheel.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">Parents should try to do more listening than talking, and ask kids what they think about Bieber&amp;apost;s troubles, said Rachel Vail, a New York City mom of two and author of numerous books for kids and teens including her latest &amp;quot;Kiss Me Again.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="3">Asking kids what really defines &amp;quot;greatness&amp;quot; could be enormously beneficial to them, said Tish Howard, a mother, grandmother and former elementary school principal.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Here&amp;apost;s yet another time when I&amp;apost;m oh-so-thankful my kids are too young to a) be Justin Bieber fans and b) know anything about his arrest and Lamborghini joy ride allegedly under the influence of marijuana, alcohol and prescription drugs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Sadly, parents of tweens and teens, especially those who continue to adore the 19-year-old superstar (despite his ongoing public travails), are not quite so lucky.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>But instead of fretting over what to say, many parents believe his arrest is a chance to continue the conversation about drinking, drug use and doing either while behind the wheel.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;I have used these sorts of &amp;apost;public displays of difficulty,&amp;apost; as I like to call them, to sometimes segue into a conversation about what they would do if they had a friend who was in the same situation,&amp;quot; said Devra Gordon Renner, a mom of two in Northern Virginia and co-author of the book &amp;quot;Mommy Guilt.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;However, I don&amp;apost;t use these as teachable moments all of the time,&amp;quot; Gordon Renner, a clinical social worker, said in response to a request for comment on Facebook.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;Teens only listen for so long and too many &amp;apost;examples&amp;apost; feels like proselytizing to them.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Parents should try to do more listening than talking, and ask kids what they think about Bieber&amp;apost;s troubles, said Rachel Vail, a New York City mom of two and author of numerous books for kids and teens including her latest &amp;quot;Kiss Me Again.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;Scaffold their growing ability to think through complex issues like celebrity, entitlement, fame, substance abuse -- and really listen to their thoughts,&amp;quot; said Vail, also on Facebook.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;So often we think we have to have the correct answers and serve them up like so many inoculations to our kids.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Being present and asking questions is sometimes the wiser, more respectful, and ultimately more empowering route.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Asking kids what really defines &amp;quot;greatness&amp;quot; could be enormously beneficial to them, said Tish Howard, a mother, grandmother and former elementary school principal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;In conversations with my young students, I tried to steer the dialogue with them to a point where they were telling me the qualities they thought made someone worthy of being idolized,&amp;quot; said Howard, who continues to work with schools through her education consulting firm.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;Kids can come to an accepted belief that it&amp;apost;s not the talent that makes you great.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>It is what you do with it and your contribution to the whole that defines you,&amp;quot; said Howard.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is okay for kids to love (Bieber&amp;apost;s) voice but differentiate that from him being a model of behavior.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Parents can sometimes &amp;quot;go overboard&amp;quot; when it comes to worrying about who their teens idolize, said Gordon Renner, the clinical social worker.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;Who amongst us did not swoon for someone when we were teens?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>But in reality did any of us copy their lives and confuse it with reality?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>she added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Jenny Dean Schmidt, a mom of two and radio host of The Channelmom Show in Denver, says her 11-year-old would say she chose not to be a Bieber fan &amp;quot;on purpose.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;We make a point of steering our kids away from &amp;apost;idol worship,&amp;apost; reminding them that they are just as valuable as any celebrity,&amp;quot; Dean Schmidt said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;The fact that Mr. (Is he old enough for Mr.?).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Bieber was arrested helps us drive home that point.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Celebrities are just as fallible as anyone else, and there&amp;apost;s no need to worship them.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Evan Katz, a behavioral therapist and author of the book &amp;quot;Inside the Mind of an Angry Man,&amp;quot; believes Bieber is suffering from what therapists call &amp;quot;imposter syndrome.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s basically someone who really lives in fear of being revealed for who he or she believes they really are,&amp;quot; said Katz, who said he suffered from this himself and shared his own experiences in his book.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;I guarantee when they go home and look in the mirror after a huge concert and a huge night that they don&amp;apost;t see the person that everyone else is seeing,&amp;quot; Katz said of Bieber and other celebrities who might struggle with insecurities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;In fact, they are scared to death that people are going to see the person that they are seeing so ... the person will continue to implode and fall apart.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Katz&amp;apost;s advice to parents is to encourage kids to learn from the pop star instead of criticizing him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;The lesson is happiness is an inside job and that true validation has to come from looking in the mirror and liking who you see regardless of ... chaos going on around you,&amp;quot; Katz said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Justin Bieber &amp;quot;got lost somehow and had to give up himself and he was so overwhelmed with validation from outside himself that he was lost and you don&amp;apost;t want that to happen to you,&amp;quot; said Katz, describing a conversation parents could have with their kids.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>As for Bieber&amp;apost;s teenage fans, Dean Schmidt, the Denver radio personality, believes they shouldn&amp;apost;t stop liking him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;And I&amp;apost;ll go one step further and say they shouldn&amp;apost;t judge him,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;Every person needs love, so I&amp;apost;m not going to tell a child to stop loving a person (celebrity or not) just because they&amp;apost;ve made some bad decisions.&amp;quot;&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is important to remind our kids that our mistakes do not define us,&amp;quot; said Melissa Atkins Wardy, author of the new book &amp;quot;Redefining Girly: How Parents Can Fight the Stereotyping and Sexualizing of Girlhood, from Birth to Tween.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;Justin&amp;apost;s mistakes are a big deal, but they are not life altering,&amp;quot; Atkins Wardy said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;Thankfully, no one was killed while Justin was driving drunk and drag racing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Luckily, no one overdosed that night.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>That said, his troubles are also a cautionary tale of what fame can bring, she added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;An important thing to point out to our kids is just how many of these young stars have crashed and burned out like this.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Maybe,&amp;quot; she said, &amp;quot;being famous isn&amp;apost;t all it is cracked up to be.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Follow Kelly Wallace on Twitter and like CNN Living on Facebook.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
