<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="740" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/09/10/living/identity-opinion-yaba-blay-dreadlocks-brown-girl/index.html" date_published="2013-09-10 20:39:04" category="living" author="Yaba Blay, Special to CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Tell a brown girl she&amp;apost;s pretty, dreadlocks and all</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">An Oklahoma student was told wearing dreadlocks was against the school policy .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">This week, the elementary school changed the dress code policy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="17">Author Yaba Blay says people should affirm brown girls&amp;apost; beauty and value.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-31 10:48:09" annotation_time="60.053997">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">The school&amp;apost;s policy at the time said &amp;quot;hairstyles such as dreadlocks, afros, mohawks, and other faddish styles are unacceptable.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">The charter school&amp;apost;s board decided Monday night to change its dress code, but when I first learned about the story, and saw Tiana in tears, it reminded me of a time in my life when I yearned to have long, straight flowing hair.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="3">So I reached out to other women with dreadlocks -- more positively referred to as &amp;quot;locs&amp;quot; -- to create a care package, of sorts, to affirm a little girl&amp;apost;s beauty; a digital book of photos and messages from 111 women and girls from all over the country and all over the world, all of whom wear their hair in locs, all of whom want Tiana to know that she and her hair are perfect.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Late last month, school officials at Deborah Brown Community School in Tulsa, Oklahoma, sent 7-year-old straight-A student Tiana Parker home crying.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Her offense?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Wearing dreadlocks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The school&amp;apost;s policy at the time said &amp;quot;hairstyles such as dreadlocks, afros, mohawks, and other faddish styles are unacceptable.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Rather than change their daughter&amp;apost;s hair to adhere to the school&amp;apost;s policies, Tiana&amp;apost;s parents, Miranda and Terrance Parker, instead made the brave decision to remove their daughter from the school.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The charter school&amp;apost;s board decided Monday night to change its dress code, but when I first learned about the story, and saw Tiana in tears, it reminded me of a time in my life when I yearned to have long, straight flowing hair.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Hair that looked nothing like the hair that grew naturally out of my head.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Hair that my mother would have to pay someone else to create through chemical processing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Hair that, when it was &amp;quot;done,&amp;quot; still didn&amp;apost;t look &amp;quot;did&amp;quot; -- at least not like the tresses that garnished the heads of all the little girls that other children and adults named &amp;quot;pretty.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Hair that forever escaped me.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Hair that, in its absence, made me cry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Whereas I spent most of my youth chasing beauty, at only 7, Tiana and her parents are simply seeking affirmation for a beauty that is the child&amp;apost;s own; a beauty that would take me another 17 years to find.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Seeing that precious little brown girl break down and cry in front of news cameras, I became instantly focused on her.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>And her spirit.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>And her self-reflection.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>And I wanted to do something for her.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>So I reached out to other women with dreadlocks -- more positively referred to as &amp;quot;locs&amp;quot; -- to create a care package, of sorts, to affirm a little girl&amp;apost;s beauty; a digital book of photos and messages from 111 women and girls from all over the country and all over the world, all of whom wear their hair in locs, all of whom want Tiana to know that she and her hair are perfect.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>When a 7-year-old, straight-A student is removed from class and told that she cannot go to her school any longer simply because she wears her hair in a culturally specific hairstyle, there is a big chance that her reflection on herself, and perhaps even her culture, will be negatively impacted.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Rather than run the risk that little Tiana might look in the mirror and see something wrong, I wanted to manually, if not emotionally, insert a positive reflection for her, one that I myself didn&amp;apost;t get until I was well into my adult years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>It wasn&amp;apost;t until I was an adult that I learned about the politics of black beauty.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>We live in a society in which normative standards tend to reflect those ideals established by the dominant group.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>And in a racialized society such as our own, one in which the white ideal is constantly pedestaled as the ideal against which all other bodies are measured, black bodies are often regarded substandard -- &amp;quot;unacceptable&amp;quot; as is.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>For black women, our ability to be perceived as beautiful in this society depends upon our ability to emulate a white ideal for feminine beauty.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The closer our features are to white ones -- straight hair, light skin and aquiline features -- the more likely it is that we will be regarded as beautiful.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>So when compared to a white ideal, natural hair is not beautiful, especially not dreadlocks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>But the issue here isn&amp;apost;t just one of beauty.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Tiana was not asked to leave her school because her hair was judged &amp;quot;ugly.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>She was asked to leave because school officials opined that her hair was &amp;quot;faddish&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;unacceptable.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The problem lies in perspective: On what grounds and on whose terms do we determine what is &amp;quot;acceptable?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Dreadlocks are rooted in our cultural history and are as old as humanity itself.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Yet Tiana&amp;apost;s African-American led school, one chartered by Langston University, a historically black university, didn&amp;apost;t view her hairstyle in the truth of its own cultural significance.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>And therein lies the issue.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Tiana&amp;apost;s story is the one that made the news, but so many young girls question their beauty every single day.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Our girls need constant affirmation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Girls need to know they are beautiful, even though there are people in this world that would have us believe that natural hair is &amp;quot;ugly&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;nasty.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>If they can&amp;apost;t pick up a magazine in the checkout line of the grocery store, turn to any page, and see themselves reflected, then we as adults have to provide them that reflection.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>And affirmation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;A Care Package Full of Locs&amp;quot; is one such reflection -- my attempt to begin to ground Tiana and all the little Tianas in their own culture, and in their own norms, and in their own beauty, lest they be forced to compare themselves to others, lest they look in the mirror and find something wrong.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Plus, I just want them all to know that they have an army of sisters, cousins, aunties, mamas, grandmothers and elders all over the world who support them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>I sent the care package to Tiana and her family.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>When I spoke to them Sunday, they were extremely thankful for the outpouring of love and support.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>And when I asked Tiana how she was feeling, she responded, &amp;quot;Much better.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Thank you.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>A few hours later she sent me a text to tell me her message to little girls -- &amp;quot;Believe in yourself.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>As I did back in December, after CNN aired its documentary &amp;quot;Who is Black in America?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>and as I do often, I&amp;apost;m calling on everyone to join me in &amp;quot;singing a black girl&amp;apost;s song,&amp;quot; not only for Tiana, but for all the little girls who could benefit from the affirmation of their beauty and their value.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>An intimate weaving of past and present, memory and contemporary, their stories are our stories.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Perhaps if they know that we truly understand, they can be encouraged to see themselves through our eyes; perhaps they will soon be able to see themselves for what they are: Pretty brown girls.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>No matter her hair texture, length, color or style, please, in some way, tell a little black girl that she is beautiful today.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>And every day.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
