<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="708" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/05/11/living/kinsman-never-a-mother" date_published="2012-05-11 19:04:12" category="living" author="Kat Kinsman, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>I am nobody&amp;apost;s mother and never will be</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6">Kat Kinsman knew as a child that she didn&amp;apost;t want to have children.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8">&amp;quot;A married woman who chooses not to have children is highly suspect to some,&amp;quot; she writes.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="11">Still, friends (and their beloved children, for those who have them) enrich her life, she writes.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="61">In marriage, friendships, career and life, she&amp;apost;s content: &amp;quot;Everything I want is right here&amp;quot;.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-21 11:47:56" annotation_time="171.23">
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">I have known since I was a child myself that I didn&amp;apost;t want to have any of my own.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">A married woman who chooses not to have children is highly suspect to some, broken in some fundamental way.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="3">I have wept with joy, staring into the faces of their children for the first time -- seeing in them the undeniable imprint of their parents and loving them already and always, just for that.</sentence>
      <sentence id="61" ids_highlights="4">Everything I want is right here.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>On Mother&amp;apost;s Day, no one is going to send me flowers or a card.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>I will not be awakened by sweet, giggling toddlers bearing a tray of breakfast in their chubby hands or receive an awkward but heartfelt hug from a gangly teenage son or end a phone call with a teary, dorm-bound daughter saying, &amp;quot;I love you, Mom.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>I am no one&amp;apost;s mother, and I never will be.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>This is not by accident, a case of insurmountable physical challenges, an unwilling partner or prioritizing career over children.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>At age 39, the window of my fertility is sliding shut, but I feel no sense of dread, panic or regret.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>I have known since I was a child myself that I didn&amp;apost;t want to have any of my own.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s simply astonishing to me how frequently people -- strangers, especially -- have felt that I should answer to them for that.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>A married woman who chooses not to have children is highly suspect to some, broken in some fundamental way.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>My friends know that I am not and that I support their parenthood in any way I can.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>I have offered solace while they grieved over infertility and miscarriage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>I have wept with joy, staring into the faces of their children for the first time -- seeing in them the undeniable imprint of their parents and loving them already and always, just for that.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>I have taken my friends&amp;apost; sad and stumbling teens on long walks, under the auspices of their parents to whom they&amp;apost;d simply stopped talking.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>When my best friend of nearly two decades asked me to be present at the birth of her child, I simply said yes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>I did not know that it would entail kneeling aside a tub for hours, her head in one of my hands, and her knees locked into her husband&amp;apost;s and my elbows as she heaved and strained their son out into the world in a bloody, howling, miraculous mess.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>I watched her face as she held him to her chest and fell in lifelong love with him -- as her heart grew extra chambers, as she metamorphosed into a mother.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>I felt nothing but pure bliss for her budding family -- and nothing but contentment for myself having been lucky enough to witness this momentous thing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Not a pang, not an emptiness, not a tick or a twinge.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>One of the concerns often levied at intentionally childless people is that we&amp;apost;ll never truly know love until it is reflected back to us by our own flesh and blood.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>I suppose I should be grateful for that level of solicitousness, but it tends to smack of pity and disdain.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>So do the allegations of selfishness.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>I remember this as clear as day, being 10 years old and a friend telling me I&amp;apost;d be a bad mother.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The children from her parents&amp;apost; home day care had crawled up to the tip-top shelf where she&amp;apost;d stashed her social studies project and smashed it all to bits.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>She&amp;apost;d brought in the tattered remains to our unsympathetic teacher, who gave her a failing grade for the project.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>I was livid from the injustice of it all -- from the cranky, burned-out educator who no longer had any business molding young minds, to her parents who made her live in a home that stank of diapers and was never silent, to the pint-sized savages who had laid waste to her lovely work.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;How do you stand it?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>I asked.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;All of it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The noise, the diaper changing, not having anything ever be private?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>She hissed at me, wounded, &amp;quot;You&amp;apost;re going to be a horrible mother!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;No, I&amp;apost;m not,&amp;quot; I calmly replied.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m not going to be a mother at all.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Somehow I understood it in my bones, as deeply and simply as know I have hazel eyes and cannot sing: I was never going to carry a child inside my body, and I was completely at peace with that.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The need, want and drive are simply not there.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Nearly three decades later, that hasn&amp;apost;t wavered, though it has hardly gone unassailed by others who have felt compelled to critique or to pry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>My family has always understood this about me and was content with my sister and me finding fulfillment in other arenas.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>On both sides, there were some aunts or uncles who never married or reproduced, and it wasn&amp;apost;t seen as a metric for happiness.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>When my husband and I married, he was 40, it was his second time, and the next generation (and their children) were well under way.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>I gather that being spared familial pressure is a rare and tremendous thing, and I am grateful for it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>To friends and strangers who ask, I say I just don&amp;apost;t want to.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>If they push further, &amp;quot;You two would make such great parents!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>(Take THAT, childhood pal!).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>, I tout the role of the fabulous New York City aunt -- an Auntie Mame (minus the mansion) or Cousin Serena (minus the magical powers).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Often, that stops the interrogation, but on occasion (or online), it gets hostile.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>How dare I?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>What&amp;apost;s wrong with me?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>I toss aside the accusations of selfishness: Not having to care for children of our own makes my husband and me nimble with our assistance when it&amp;apost;s needed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>We&amp;apost;re quick with a listening ear and a chilled cocktail for friends in need of company, share cash and volunteer time we might not have otherwise had and are fluent in cranky, misfit teen.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>As we often tell our friends and family, we may not be especially comfortable cradling babies, but when your kid hits puberty and decides they &amp;quot;hate&amp;quot; you and the rest of humanity, hand &amp;apost;em over.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>We&amp;apost;ll let them know how lucky they are to have you as parents.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Less easy to shake off is the assertion that a female who does not bear a child is somehow not a real woman.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>I&amp;apost;m secure in my choice but deeply disappointed that one woman would wield that as a slur against another.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>I&amp;apost;ve no right to mandate what a mother should teach her daughter, but I hope, deep down in my nullipara heart, that some of the lessons would be about personal freedom, the beauty of difference and the possibility that a person could be content and complete all on her own.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>And I am not alone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>In the world I&amp;apost;ve made for myself, I have a career I adore and friends who fill my head, heart and waking hours.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>They are in various stages of couple and singlehood, childlessness and large-brooded, and each illuminates my world in a different way.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>They make my heart larger, stronger and better.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>At home, there is my family: the husband who I tell on a daily basis that he is my favorite person on Earth (I made sure on our second date that he didn&amp;apost;t want kids either; otherwise, there would not have been a third), a rabbit and our two dogs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>They are not our children, as they are for some people, but they are our charges, and we fuss and spoil accordingly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="59">
          <content>On Mother&amp;apost;s Day, I&amp;apost;ll come downstairs, rub the sleep out of my eyes, pour some coffee and cuddle in with my odd little pack on the couch.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="60">
          <content>There might not be a greeting card for that, but I don&amp;apost;t need one.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="61">
          <content>Everything I want is right here.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
