<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="674" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/02/14/living/barbie-sports-illustrated-swimsuit-edition-parents/index.html" date_published="2014-02-14 21:28:46" category="living" author="Emanuella Grinberg, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Barbie to appear in Sports Illustrated swimsuit edition</title>
  <keywords>sports illustrated,barbie,swimsuit edition,sports illustrated swimsuit,kate upton</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Barbie&amp;apost;s appearance in Sports Illustrated swimsuit issue is causing a stir.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">Barbie featured in magazine is also for sale at Target .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="14">Mattel says campaign&amp;apost;s goal is to empower fans to celebrate what makes them unique.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="39">Critics say &amp;quot;unapologetic&amp;quot; campaign blurs lines between real women, inanimate objects.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-20 09:49:37" annotation_time="58.638">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">Barbie caused a stir when Mattel and Sports Illustrated revealed last week that she would appear in the 50th anniversary edition of its annual swimsuit edition, which hit stands Tuesday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">The doll is also for sale at Target.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="3">The goal of the campaign is to empower fans to engage and celebrate all that makes them who they are,&amp;quot; a Mattel spokeswoman said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="39" ids_highlights="4">Others took issue with blurring the line between women as objects and actual plastic objects.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>When Barbie burst onto scene in a black and white swimsuit in 1959, she was considered a rebel who embodied both &amp;quot;the sensuality of Marilyn Monroe and the innocence of Debbie Reynolds.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Now, she&amp;apost;s returning to her &amp;quot;fashion model&amp;quot; roots in an updated version of her iconic zebra swimsuit, and not everyone&amp;apost;s pleased.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Barbie caused a stir when Mattel and Sports Illustrated revealed last week that she would appear in the 50th anniversary edition of its annual swimsuit edition, which hit stands Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The partnership includes a promotional cover-wrap that will appear on 1,000 copies declaring Barbie &amp;quot;the doll that started it all,&amp;quot; a four-page advertising feature inside the magazine and video outtakes posted online.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The doll is also for sale at Target.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The official Barbie Twitter account tweeted about the campaign February 10.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Responses to the tweet foretold the ensuing controversy, with one person calling &amp;quot;unapologetic&amp;quot; an &amp;quot;ill-advised hashtag.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Another person asked if &amp;quot;unapologetic&amp;quot; really meant #sorrynotsorry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>A post on &amp;quot;Mommyish&amp;quot; blog, &amp;quot;The Sport&amp;apost;s Illustrated Swimsuit Issue Will Feature Barbie, So Your Daughter Can Feel Bad Too,&amp;quot; underscored criticism of the partnership for using a children&amp;apost;s toy to promote sexualized images intended for adults.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>It further complicates Barbie&amp;apost;s legacy for parents unsure of whether to view her as a positive or negative role model.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Mattel, however, stands by Barbie&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;unapologetic stance.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is not a program targeted towards girls.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>As a brand that is always a part of the cultural conversation, Barbie, for the first time, has an active voice in the debate with her #unapologetic stance.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The goal of the campaign is to empower fans to engage and celebrate all that makes them who they are,&amp;quot; a Mattel spokeswoman said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The 2014 swimsuit issues celebrates &amp;quot;legends,&amp;quot; and Mattel said Barbie is a fitting example.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;As a legend herself, Barbie has always been a lightning rod for controversy and opinions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Posing in SI gives Barbie and her fellow legends an opportunity to own who they are and celebrate what they have accomplished.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>For some, it works.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>As one person said in response to a question posed on Twitter, &amp;quot;no little girl reads Sports Illustrated.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s literally a doll in a bathing suit, calm down society.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>For others, the issue was not so cut and dry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;When you look at the history of Barbie and how she&amp;apost;s &amp;apost;grown&amp;apost; in career choices I believe she&amp;apost;s a positive example ... and quite frankly, a more positive image than the SI models,&amp;quot; Utah grandmother Holly Albrecht said on Twitter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;Children KNOW Barbie is a toy but the &amp;apost;skinny&amp;apost; models tell society ... that a woman must be skinny to be accepted as beautiful; a far more negative example than Barbie,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;Parents need to remember THEY should to be the positive role in their child&amp;apost;s life, not toys or Hollywood or athletes.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>But a growing body of research suggests that children are influenced not only by what they see in the media, but by the toys with which they play.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;People who say it is just a doll obviously don&amp;apost;t realize how it shapes thinking while playing house,&amp;quot; nonprofit executive Alia Salem said on Twitter.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;If the image of what (you&amp;apost;re) imagining yourself as is never attainable and is billed as what to strive for, you&amp;apost;ll always be disappointed.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Her comments echo why many of the campaign&amp;apost;s critics saw something especially &amp;quot;creepy&amp;quot; -- or tone deaf -- in placing a toy intended for children in the pages of a magazine targeting adults.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am #unapologetic for being grossed out by Mattel&amp;apost;s desperation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Pairing up with Sports Illustrated to put Barbie on a cover mag?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>#yuck,&amp;quot; digital strategist Jessica Lee said on Twitter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Barbie and the Sports Illustrated swimsuit edition have both been accused of promoting idealized beauty in their own ways.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>For many, the campaign was problematic because they say the swimsuit edition objectifies women and promotes a homogenous view of beauty.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s actually kind of perfect,&amp;quot; said Occidental College professor Lisa Wade, a feminist and media critic.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;Barbie is the perfect model for the SI swimsuit issue.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s always been about celebrating conventional definitions of attractiveness for women, and Barbie is an icon of idealized femininity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;Both Barbie and the swimsuit issue have been making women and girls feel inadequate for decades.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a perfect partnership.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Others took issue with blurring the line between women as objects and actual plastic objects.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;Yes, the swimsuit edition is made up entirely of hypersexualized images of women, but this pairing blurs a new line.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Barbie is not a woman, she&amp;apost;s an inanimate object.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Juxtaposing her alongside real women as though the two are indistinguishable is dehumanizing, and in a literal sense, objectifying,&amp;quot; said Nicole Rodgers, editor-in-chief of RoleReboot.org, an online magazine that focuses on culture and gender roles.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>It also comes at a time when many are demanding representations of women without airbrushing or Photoshop, she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;Featuring a plastic doll as an object of admiration and desire feels like a slap in the face,&amp;quot; Rodgers said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Throughout the controversy, Mattel has remained &amp;quot;unapologetic,&amp;quot; citing Barbie&amp;apost;s 150 careers, her turns in 26 animated movies and partnerships with renowned fashion designers as evidence that you can be &amp;quot;capable and captivating.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>But nobody is thinking about Barbie&amp;apost;s career trajectory or its positive examples when she&amp;apost;s wearing a one-piece in Sports Illustrated&amp;apost;s swimsuit edition, said California State University-Long Beach professor Shira Tarrant, author of &amp;quot;Men Speak Out: Views on Gender, Sex, and Power.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>&amp;quot;I would never want to deny anyone love for Barbie,&amp;quot; she said, &amp;quot;but my concern is when we use her to present this hyper-sexualized model of beauty.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>After all, CEO Barbie and Dr. Barbie weren&amp;apost;t the dolls appearing in SI.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>&amp;quot;When you look at how the lives of women have changed since the doll originally launched, the choice strikes me as particularly tone deaf in 2014,&amp;quot; said Rodgers, of RoleReboot.org.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>The fact that &amp;quot;the version they want to focus their marketing blitz on is a sexy bikini Barbie tells us something.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>What do you think of Barbie&amp;apost;s appearance in the Sports Illustrated swimsuit edition?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Have your say in the comments, on Twitter @CNNLiving or on CNN Living&amp;apost;s Facebook page!</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>