<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="738" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/09/17/living/parents-dc-moms-talking-to-kids-tragedy/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2013-09-17 15:17:37" category="living" author="Kelly Wallace, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Talking to kids about the tragedy</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="45, 21">Parents nationwide must decide whether to talk to children about mass tragedies.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="29">Reassurance is one of the most important things a parent can provide, experts say.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="44">Parents of middle and high schoolers should ask children what they&amp;apost;ve heard.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-11 10:39:14" annotation_time="273.10767" mapping_time_divergence="91.03589">
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="1">But there will come a day when her boys are older, when sadly, another tragedy strikes and when she&amp;apost;ll definitely have to talk with them about it.</sentence>
      <sentence id="29" ids_highlights="2">Reassurance is one of the most important things parents can provide children during a time of tragedy, when they fear it could happen to them, said Dr. Glenn Saxe, chairman of the Department of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry at NYU&amp;apost;s Langone Medical Center.</sentence>
      <sentence id="44" ids_highlights="3">He said parents should take into account whether they think their kids will have heard about an event, but -- especially for middle and high schoolers -- parents should bring the subject up.</sentence>
      <sentence id="45" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;I think the most important thing is that the parent communicates a willingness to talk about this, an openness about it, that parents are really attuned to where their children are in this, even just asking a general question, &amp;apost;Have you heard about this?&amp;apost;.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Not again.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s what I and parents across the country say on social media following any large-scale assault on a group of innocent people, especially one involving children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Aurora.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Sandy Hook.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Fort Hood.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Boston.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Washington, D.C. Murrysville, Pennsylvania.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>And now near Portland, Oregon, where a gunman opened fire at Reynolds High School, killing one student, injuring a teacher and sending others running for their lives.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The suspected shooter is also dead.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Every tragedy filled with incomprehensible injury sparks nonstop news coverage and a major question for parents: What do we tell our kids?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Last year, that question was even more difficult for parents in the Washington area since their children -- from elementary school age on up -- were likely to hear about the Washington Navy Yard attacks that unfolded in their backyard and left 12 people dead, as well as the gunman.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>After that shooting, Jessica McFadden, a mom of three who lives just outside Washington, said she&amp;apost;d be taking her cues from her children about what to say and when.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>At the same time, she said she would try to ensure that she and her husband were the first sources of information for their eldest, a 9-year-old son.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;He&amp;apost;s going to hear about it, and I don&amp;apost;t want him to be scared or to feel as if his world is insecure if he hears about it from kids on the bus,&amp;quot; said McFadden, who founded the blog A Parent in Silver Spring.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;So we will be talking about it with him; we will talk about how his school has great safety procedures, how my husband&amp;apost;s office has good safety procedures, how our neighborhood is safe, that this isolated incident shouldn&amp;apost;t make us more fearful in our day to day,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Sadly, McFadden knows this from experience.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>A few years ago, McFadden&amp;apost;s husband worked inside the Maryland headquarters for Discovery Communications, where a man armed with a gun took three people hostage before police shot him to death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;We had to talk about it because other adults that came into our family&amp;apost;s sphere were talking about it, and so we wanted to make sure that we were the sources for the children&amp;apost;s information so that they weren&amp;apost;t overly scared hearing about it kind of second hand,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Stephanie Dulli, who lives in Washington with her two boys, ages 2 and 5, initially said she didn&amp;apost;t have any plans to tell them what unfolded during the deadly rampage at the Navy Yard.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;It would accomplish nothing but creating anxiety, especially for my eldest,&amp;quot; said the host of the blog Stephanie Says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>But there will come a day when her boys are older, when sadly, another tragedy strikes and when she&amp;apost;ll definitely have to talk with them about it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s not an easy conversation for any parent, but for Dulli, it will be exponentially harder.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Her father was murdered when she was around the same age as her 2-year-old.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;I guess I can only try to do what my mother did.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>No matter how terrified or scared she was, she never let it affect me,&amp;quot; Dulli said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;I will try to do the same.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>To explain what happened as clearly as I can, reassure and then show by example that we just have to keep going.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>I may be terrified to let my child go on the overnight trip, but he will never know that.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Reassurance is one of the most important things parents can provide children during a time of tragedy, when they fear it could happen to them, said Dr. Glenn Saxe, chairman of the Department of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry at NYU&amp;apost;s Langone Medical Center.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;The first kind of thought and feeling is, &amp;apost;Am I safe?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Are people close to me safe?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Will something happen?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Will people I depend on protect me?&amp;apost; &amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>said Saxe, who is also director of the NYU Child Study Center.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;You want to be assuring to your child, you want to communicate that you&amp;apost;re ... doing everything you can do to keep them safe,&amp;quot; Saxe said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;You also want to not give false assurances, too.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>And this is also depending on the age of the child.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>You have to be real about it as well.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Sarah Grosjean, who lives in Leesburg, Virginia, about 45 minutes from the Washington tragedy, hoped to arm her 5-year-old daughter with information when she talked to her.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;I want to be able to make sure my daughter knows, in the event she&amp;apost;s ever in something like this ... how would she react?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Would she know what to do?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>said Grosjean, founder of the blog Capitally Frugal, who said she&amp;apost;ll be emphasizing how her daughter should listen to the police or teachers in case of an emergency when her mom isn&amp;apost;t around.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Saxe said there are &amp;quot;no hard and fast rules&amp;quot; on the right age to talk to kids about tragedies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>He said parents should take into account whether they think their kids will have heard about an event, but -- especially for middle and high schoolers -- parents should bring the subject up.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think the most important thing is that the parent communicates a willingness to talk about this, an openness about it, that parents are really attuned to where their children are in this, even just asking a general question, &amp;apost;Have you heard about this?&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>and see where your kid goes with that,&amp;quot; Saxe said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Parents should also be mindful of what images their children are seeing on the news and make sure even older ones, who may be watching the nonstop coverage, aren&amp;apost;t &amp;quot;flooded with images ... without any attempt to help make meaning for them or bring perspective to it because that could be very difficult,&amp;quot; Saxe said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>McFadden said she kept the television off immediately after the Navy Yard shootings, but followed the latest developments via social media on her laptop.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>She knew she would be only so prepared when she ultimately had the conversation with her kids.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>&amp;quot;One of the biggest questions children ask is why,&amp;quot; she said, &amp;quot;and that&amp;apost;s something that we can&amp;apost;t answer.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>Follow Kelly Wallace on Twitter and like CNN Living on Facebook.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
