<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="725" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/09/30/living/aj-irpt-vintage-vinyl/index.html" date_published="2013-09-30 12:40:14" category="living" author="Alisha Ebrahimji and Emanuella Grinberg, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Old records get second life as journals</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="8">Through Vintage Vinyl Journals, Katie Pietrak transforms old records into notebooks.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">Pietrak launched her business after losing her job in the pharmaceutical industry.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="34">To get business off the ground, she moved to scale back on living expenses.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-19 10:16:35" annotation_time="68.17034" mapping_time_divergence="22.723448">
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">It took losing her job in 2010 for her to change her tune and launch a business doing something she enjoyed.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="1">Since 2011, Pietrak has been combining her enthusiasm for vintage records and bookbinding through her small business, Vintage Vinyl Journals.</sentence>
      <sentence id="34" ids_highlights="3">After being in business for six months, she realized she would have to scale back living expenses to get the business off the ground.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>On paper, Katie Pietrak was a success story throughout her 20s.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>She had her own home, a new car, a large, beloved collection of vinyl records and a six-figure salary from her job in the pharmaceutical industry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>But she didn&amp;apost;t love what she was doing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;I bought my first house when I was 21 but I wasn&amp;apost;t happy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>I kind of knew that all along but I did it because of financial stability,&amp;quot; Pietrak said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;I was afraid to think outside of the box because of money.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>It took losing her job in 2010 for her to change her tune and launch a business doing something she enjoyed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Since 2011, Pietrak has been combining her enthusiasm for vintage records and bookbinding through her small business, Vintage Vinyl Journals.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>She finds old records, repurposes them into book covers and makes them into journals for music lovers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;Everyone knows I was always making trinkets,&amp;quot; Pietrak says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;It wasn&amp;apost;t too hard of a transition for me since I had both the craft and business side.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>To make it happen, she had to leave corporate America behind and downsize from her three-bedroom home to a one-bedroom apartment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Now, she lives in a barn on her parents&amp;apost; property in a small town in Pennsylvania, dividing her time between raising an infant and building a business.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s worth the sacrifice to have control over her work and her life, said Pietrak, 34.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Besides, now she has an entire studio where she gives old records a second life.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m such a different person now,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Pietrak always has been interested in vintage items and antiques.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>As a teen, when her friends were buying CDs and cassettes, she was sifting through boxes of 15-cent records at yard sales and flea markets.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>When she left her parents&amp;apost; home, she took her large collection with her.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>She pursued a bachelor&amp;apost;s degree from La Salle University in Philadelphia and later earned her MBA from St. Joseph&amp;apost;s University in Philadelphia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>She continued to collect vinyl as her career took off.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>When the records became too scratched for listening, she didn&amp;apost;t want to get rid of them, but how could she use them?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>While she was looking for a journal to jot down ideas, &amp;quot;something clicked&amp;quot; and she was inspired to find a way to incorporate her languishing records into a notebook.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;I got in my car, drove to Barnes and Noble and sat in the aisle reading almost everything I found about bookbinding,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>She began crafting journals for friends and family and giving them as gifts to loved ones.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>After Pietrak was laid off, she decided to turn her journal-making hobby into a career.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>To fund start-up costs, she did temporary contract work and drew from her savings so she could eventually devote all her efforts to Vintage Vinyl Journals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>She crops the album covers herself and contracts out the laser-cutting of the vinyl.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>She sews the journal pages together and attaches them to the cover using an acid-free adhesive.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The average price of one of Pietrak&amp;apost;s journals is $35, depending on the price of the vinyl.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Custom designs requiring records that are hard to obtain cost a bit more.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>She used to think of them as simply journals, but over time she&amp;apost;s seen people use them for a variety of purposes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;People use them for wedding guest sign-in books, scrapbooks, drawing, books to store concert ticket stubs and photos -- stuff I never thought of,&amp;quot; Pietrak says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>After being in business for six months, she realized she would have to scale back living expenses to get the business off the ground.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>She and her boyfriend (now her husband) moved into an apartment and she sold many of her belongings.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>After two years in the apartment, they moved into her parents&amp;apost; barn to accommodate their growing family.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Her life is much simpler now than when she was a &amp;quot;corporate, hungry, heel-wearing person,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>She can work and focus on her daughter while tending to new passions, like gardening and beekeeping.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Running her business is a full-time job, even if it doesn&amp;apost;t provide enough income to support her family; her husband has an outside job.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>There have been the typical ups and downs of being a small-business owner and entrepreneur, especially in learning how to market her products, she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>But &amp;quot;not a day goes by&amp;quot; when she regrets her decision.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Her vinyl journals are sold in stores across the United States and Canada.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>She used to attend craft shows to sell her product and find retailers, but as sales have grown through her website, she has been able to travel less.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Her success has led her to pursue new business ventures, too, including an apparel line, Lucky Penny, named for her daughter, that will launch next month.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Her dream now is to see her product on the shelves of larger retailers, like Urban Outfitters and Anthropologie.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>&amp;quot;Either way,&amp;quot; she says, &amp;quot;it&amp;apost;s exciting finally having my own business.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
