<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="731" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/10/15/living/parents-honors-student-punished-drunk-driving/index.html" date_published="2013-10-15 18:49:34" category="living" author="Kelly Wallace, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>School punishes teen who helped drunk friend</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">Erin Cox went to a party to pick up a friend who was too drunk to drive, according to reports .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">Cox&amp;apost;s school charged she violated its zero-tolerance policy against drug and alcohol use.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="9">Cox was demoted as captain of the volleyball team and suspended for five games.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="14">Reaction online has been fierce, with most expressing outrage at school&amp;apost;s decision .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-27 10:54:36" annotation_time="52.879665">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">Two weeks ago, Erin Cox, an honors high school student who lives near Boston, got a call from a friend at a party who was too drunk to drive.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">Even though Cox wasn&amp;apost;t drinking and a police officer vouched for her sobriety in a written statement, according to the Herald, her school, North Andover High, charged that she violated its zero-tolerance policy when it comes to alcohol and drug use.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="3">She was demoted from her position as captain of her volleyball team and told she would be suspended for five games.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="4">wrote Stevie Street, one of the thousands of commenters on CNN&amp;apost;s Facebook page expressing outrage and disappointment at the school&amp;apost;s decision.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>When I hear about an outrageous story involving kids -- and we know there is another crazy one just about every day -- I often try to put myself in the shoes of the parents at the center of the controversy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>How would I have acted?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>What would I have wanted my daughters to do?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>In the case of a teen recently punished by her school for trying to drive a drunk friend home, I find myself firmly siding with the girl and her parents -- and wondering what on Earth the school administrators were thinking.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Two weeks ago, Erin Cox, an honors high school student who lives near Boston, got a call from a friend at a party who was too drunk to drive.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Cox went to the party to get her friend, and shortly after she got there, police arrived and arrested a dozen kids for underage drinking, warning 15 others, including Cox, they would get a summons for drinking, according to the Boston Herald.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Even though Cox wasn&amp;apost;t drinking and a police officer vouched for her sobriety in a written statement, according to the Herald, her school, North Andover High, charged that she violated its zero-tolerance policy when it comes to alcohol and drug use.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Her punishment?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>She was demoted from her position as captain of her volleyball team and told she would be suspended for five games.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>All because she did the right thing, as far as this reporter mom is concerned.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>I would hope my girls, now in elementary school, would do what Cox did if they ever found themselves in a similar situation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;She did what we teach our kids to do!!</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Friends don&amp;apost;t let friends drive drunk!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>wrote Stevie Street, one of the thousands of commenters on CNN&amp;apost;s Facebook page expressing outrage and disappointment at the school&amp;apost;s decision.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>For some, the issue is very personal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;My daughter was killed at age 17 riding in a car with a drunk driver.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>How I wish she would have called us or asked a sober friend to drive her home.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The girl should be rewarded, not punished, for potentially saving a life,&amp;quot; Karen Donahue Moses said, also on Facebook.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;I know someone ... who was raped at a party after passing out drunk.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Her friends had left without her,&amp;quot; a commenter named David wrote in an e-mail.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;Looking out for your friends, making sure they get home safe, that&amp;apost;s the responsible thing to do.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>If that student had just left her friend there, she could have been assaulted, she could have driven drunk or ridden with a drunk driver.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Cox&amp;apost;s family filed a lawsuit to force the school to reverse its decision, but a judge ruled that the court did not have jurisdiction over the school&amp;apost;s decision, according to reports.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Now, she and her family plan to file formal legal action against the school district &amp;quot;in the hope that officials there will think twice before imposing sanctions on any student whose only offense involves trying to prevent yet another drunk-driving tragedy,&amp;quot; Wendy Murphy, Cox&amp;apost;s attorney, said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;(Erin) wants to really raise awareness of the issue to the point where people understand it&amp;apost;s much better to encourage kids to help each other and that by pursing additional legal action, she hopes that her school and other schools will understand why it&amp;apost;s so important for young people to watch out for each other,&amp;quot; Murphy said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Repeated calls and e-mails to the school, the school district and the school&amp;apost;s lawyer have not been returned.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>In a comment to the Herald, Geoffrey Bok, who represented the high school in court, said the school had basically no choice once the police got involved.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;The school is really trying to take a very serious and principled stand regarding alcohol,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;And we all get that.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Teen drinking is a serious problem.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Kendra Vinson Sales, in an e-mail and on her blog, said that Cox should be &amp;quot;the example of what to do when you need a ride home from a party.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;Instead, now students at this school are filled with mixed signals and contradictory messages,&amp;quot; wrote Vinson Sales.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;From now on, students will think twice about calling a friend for help or worse, they may not reach out to help a friend in a similar situation.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Although 95% of the comments we&amp;apost;ve received via e-mail or on Facebook were wildly critical of the school for its decision, there were a few voices of support online.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;While I am not a fan of zero tolerance policies, zero means zero.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>If you are going to put the policy in place, you must enforce it,&amp;quot; Jill Worden Benjamin wrote on CNN&amp;apost;s Facebook page.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;She wasn&amp;apost;t punished for driving a friend home.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Why do people keep saying that?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>She was actually punished for being in a place (where) alcohol was served,&amp;quot; Nancy Taylor said, also on Facebook.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m sure she is well aware of the school&amp;apost;s policy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>She chose to violate that policy.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;Just because she was an honors student and the captain of the volleyball team shouldn&amp;apost;t give her a free pass to disregard the school&amp;apost;s known zero tolerance policy,&amp;quot; Elyse Bruce said on CNN Living&amp;apost;s Facebook page.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>&amp;quot;To let her off the hook is to discriminate against those who are not honors students or captains of sports teams who take the school police seriously and abide by it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is the second time in a week CNN has gauged levels of national outrage over a ridiculous K-12 school policy applied in a ridiculous manner,&amp;quot; Adam of Alexandria, Virginia, wrote in an e-mail.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>He was referring to last week&amp;apost;s story, which we covered on CNN Parents, about a school banning the use of most balls during recess and even requiring supervision of rough games of tag while the schoolyard space is restricted due to a construction project.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Adam said these stories reflect a failure of common sense in education.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>&amp;quot;Let&amp;apost;s hope North Andover High&amp;apost;s administrators pick humility over hubris, amend their anti-alcohol policy to prevent such unintended consequences, pardon the student caught up in their mistake, publicly apologize and move on,&amp;quot; he added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>&amp;quot;Then let&amp;apost;s hope the school district responsible for next week&amp;apost;s episode of &amp;apost;(Administrators) Gone Wild&amp;apost; does the same.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>What do you think of the school&amp;apost;s decision?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Tell us below in the comments.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>Follow Kelly Wallace on Twitter and like CNN Living on Facebook.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
