<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="722" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/12/17/living/relate-loss-at-the-holidays/index.html" date_published="2013-12-17 14:56:10" category="living" author="Sarah LeTrent, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Navigating the holidays without a loved one</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="9">Grief-stricken can have a hard time balancing the merry with the mourning, psychologist says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="13">Guilt during moments of holiday cheer is a common emotion for those grieving, he says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="24">Expert advises people to manage social obligations wisely as grief takes a toll.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-27 10:43:34" annotation_time="548.028">
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="1">While popular culture proclaims the holiday season as a time of happiness, grief-stricken people can have an especially hard time balancing the merry with the mourning, says clinical psychologist Joshua Klapow.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="2">Klapow, an associate professor of public health at the University of Alabama at Birmingham, says guilt is often a common and unexpected emotion for those who have experienced loss near the holidays.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="3">Klapow says the process of grief takes an emotional and physical toll, so it&amp;apost;s important to manage the plethora of social obligations wisely during the holidays.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Tasha Dimling always looked forward to sharing a prized bottle of wine on Christmas Day with her father from his cellar.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Last Christmas, Dimling had to decant the bottle of 1975 Château Grand-Puy Ducasse at her dad&amp;apost;s grave site in Findlay, Ohio.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;I knew I needed to connect just with Dad that day before going off and celebrating Christmas with the rest of my family,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Her father, James Dimling, died from a heart attack two days after Thanksgiving in 2012; he was 74.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;He was the only person who understood me,&amp;quot; says the self-described &amp;quot;Daddy&amp;apost;s little girl.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>This year, she will once again pack up her car with the Waterford glasses from her parents&amp;apost; wedding, a picnic blanket and a bottle of 1970 Château Canon Saint-Emilion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s her way of breathing life into a holiday tradition cut short.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Words such as jolly, cheery and bright infiltrate the season between Thanksgiving and New Year&amp;apost;s, but those who have lost a dear friend or family member during this time are left with the antitheses of good tidings, comfort and joy -- an annual reminder that their holiday celebration is missing a very important person.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>While popular culture proclaims the holiday season as a time of happiness, grief-stricken people can have an especially hard time balancing the merry with the mourning, says clinical psychologist Joshua Klapow.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Even the brightest holiday lights can&amp;apost;t dull the grief of losing a loved one.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;If you&amp;apost;re grieving, your natural, healthy and necessary emotional process runs contrary to what&amp;apost;s around you,&amp;quot; Klapow says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;And that can make your grief more noticeable to you and to others.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Klapow, an associate professor of public health at the University of Alabama at Birmingham, says guilt is often a common and unexpected emotion for those who have experienced loss near the holidays.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;People don&amp;apost;t understand just because you&amp;apost;re going through grief doesn&amp;apost;t mean that you must be, or will be, sad every single day throughout the holidays,&amp;quot; Klapow says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Kristine Brite McCormick of Indianapolis has always experienced a tinge of somberness around the holidays; her grandfather passed away on Christmas Day before she was born.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;My mother didn&amp;apost;t directly talk about it, but loss has always been a part of the holidays for me,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>On December 6, 2009, that seasonal melancholy reached critical mass when her newborn daughter, Cora, died in her arms of a congenital heart defect at only 5 days old.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Cora was the first and only child for McCormick and her husband.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>They had already bought a &amp;quot;Baby&amp;apost;s First Christmas&amp;quot; ornament.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Instead, it hung at her funeral on a pink Christmas tree they chose to display.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Klapow says the most vital piece of advice for those in a similar situation is to give yourself permission to grieve.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;(Grief) is this amazing process of our ability to handle tragedy,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;If you think about it that way, I&amp;apost;m not saying it&amp;apost;s going to make you feel happy, it just doesn&amp;apost;t make grief so foreign, mysterious and negative.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Klapow says the process of grief takes an emotional and physical toll, so it&amp;apost;s important to manage the plethora of social obligations wisely during the holidays.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>If you don&amp;apost;t want to come out of your room for a day or two, that&amp;apost;s acceptable, he says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>But, after two weeks, if you&amp;apost;re not able to muster up the strength to do basic tasks, it might be useful to talk to a professional.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;You don&amp;apost;t have to go to every party.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Recognize you may feel tired, you may feel spent -- it&amp;apost;s important that you take care of yourself physically,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>He also says not to be afraid of the wave of powerful emotions; do not continually push away feelings of sadness.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;One of the best things you can do is, if you need a cry, you cry,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;You will not be crying for days on end.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Klapow says, unfortunately, every holiday may trigger traumatic memories.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>For the families of Newtown, Connecticut, there is never going to be a December where they magically forget that tragic day at Sandy Hook Elementary School.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s important to redefine the holiday period as a memorial, he says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>In McCormick&amp;apost;s case, she lights five flameless candles for those five days she was able to have with her daughter, and she puts out the pink Christmas tree from her funeral.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>McCormick has since become an advocate for newborn screenings; Cora&amp;apost;s Law passed in February 2011 in Indiana, requiring newborns to undergo a pulse oximetry screening, a test that determines the amount of oxygen in the blood and pulse rate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>This year, Cora&amp;apost;s handmade stocking hangs once more on the mantel with care.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;When we have the family time, it&amp;apost;s less of we have to get together and more of we get to get together.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>I just don&amp;apost;t take people for granted,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>