<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="729" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/03/15/living/same-sex-wedding-photography/index.html" date_published="2013-03-15 13:56:15" category="living" author="Emanuella Grinberg, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Photographing same-sex weddings presents unique challenges</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7">Traditional wedding photo poses don&amp;apost;t always work for same-sex couples, photographer says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12">New photo book aims to help photographers, same-sex couples tweak old standards.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="15">Like with hetero couples, the best images tells a story beyond the frame, authors say.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-10 20:08:17" annotation_time="39.958">
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">Just as the traditional canon of wedding poses does not fit all heterosexual couples, there&amp;apost;s a lot of variety in same-sex weddings that photographers need to plan for, Dodd said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">Together, they came up with &amp;quot;Capturing Love: The Art of Lesbian &amp;amp; Gay Photography,&amp;quot; a book to help photographers and couples understand the art and mechanics of shooting same-sex couples.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="3">The best images capture a moment that tells a story beyond the frame, she said, like a shot of the feet of two grooms in their dress shoes, one standing on his tiptoes.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Anyone who&amp;apost;s ever scanned a wedding album or set of engagement photos knows the standard poses: The dip.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The kiss.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Back to chest, prom-style.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Forehead to forehead, anyone?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Most of those poses have been around for a long time and are based on the idea that there&amp;apost;s a man and a woman involved, wedding photographer Thea Dodd said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The placement of a hand or positioning of the groom contains assumptions about physicality and gender roles that often don&amp;apost;t apply to same-sex couples or even nontraditional straight couples.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Just as the traditional canon of wedding poses does not fit all heterosexual couples, there&amp;apost;s a lot of variety in same-sex weddings that photographers need to plan for, Dodd said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;There are more similarities than differences between gay and straight weddings, but the subtle differences can be very impactful on how the photography is going to look,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;I see this as an opportunity and challenge for wedding photographers to do better.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>But, as a straight person, she didn&amp;apost;t feel like she had the authority to rewrite the rules on her own.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>She approached Kathryn Hamm, president of GayWeddings.com, the first site to cater to same-sex couples, for advice.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Together, they came up with &amp;quot;Capturing Love: The Art of Lesbian &amp;amp; Gay Photography,&amp;quot; a book to help photographers and couples understand the art and mechanics of shooting same-sex couples.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The pair scoured thousands of images before whittling the book down to a selection of 65 images taken by 38 photographers of 46 couples from the United States, the United Kingdom, Canada and Italy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;We began looking for examples of couples that struck as very authentic and believable in a moment that captured some bit of intimacy,&amp;quot; Hamm said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The best images capture a moment that tells a story beyond the frame, she said, like a shot of the feet of two grooms in their dress shoes, one standing on his tiptoes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Having spent time with the couple, photographer Jeremy Fraser knew that one was shorter than the other and had to stand on his toes to kiss his husband.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;We thought it would be a really cute way to capture something that occurs on a regular basis in an artistic fashion,&amp;quot; Fraser says in the book.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>As with any couple, the goal is to make them comfortable with the photographer so the poses come organically, Dodd said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The devil is in the details, but most issues can be addressed in a pre-shoot planning session.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Attire is the most common wild card in same-sex weddings, so it&amp;apost;s important to find out what they&amp;apost;re wearing, she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Creating contrast between two white dresses can be difficult, so consider a sash or belt to break up the washed-out palette.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The same goes for distinguishing two tuxedos or suits: Use accessories to make the look less matchy-matchy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Be mindful of boutonnieres traditionally worn on the left lapel, she cautioned, especially in shoulder-to-shoulder shots of two grooms.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>One is likely to be squashed or hidden.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>When it comes to gender expression, don&amp;apost;t assume that the person wearing the pants at the wedding plays a dominant role in the relationship, she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Get to know the couple, and see how they naturally position themselves.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>When it comes to layering couples, however, the longstanding technique of placing the taller of the two in the back tends to hold true for basic principles of composition.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>With same-sex weddings becoming more commonplace, the timing was right, said Hamm, whose company has been providing information and vendor services to same-sex couples for more than a decade.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;Capturing Love&amp;quot; is primarily designed to help wedding photographers think about what to ask couples in the planning phase, but couples can also draw inspiration from the poses regardless of their sexual orientation, she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;By taking a look at these questions and asking how you can better serve same-sex couples, you open up a better skill set to serve all couples,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
