<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="718" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/07/31/living/florida-mom-arrested-son-park/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-07-31 21:23:10" category="living" author="Caitlin Schmidt, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Mom arrested for letting 7-year-old walk to the park</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Florida mom was arrested after letting her 7-year-old walk to the park alone.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="24">Her attorney believes the charges will be dropped.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="21">State&amp;apost;s Attorney hasn&amp;apost;t assigned a prosecutor to the case.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="37">State law doesn&amp;apost;t specify an age at which a child can be left alone.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-19 09:50:33" annotation_time="40.127">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">After letting her 7-year-old son walk from their home to a park to play, a Florida mother faces up to five years in jail for child neglect.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="3">A representative from the Florida State Attorney told CNN that the case hadn&amp;apost;t been assigned to a prosecutor yet.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="2">On Wednesday, Gainey met with an employee from the Florida Department of Children and Families who told her the charges would likely be dropped, according to Whitehead.</sentence>
      <sentence id="37" ids_highlights="4">Many states do not specify an age at which a child can be legally left at home or allowed to go places alone.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>After letting her 7-year-old son walk from their home to a park to play, a Florida mother faces up to five years in jail for child neglect.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Nicole Gainey, 34, was arrested on July 26 after her son, Dominic, was found by police alone in a park less than a half-mile from her Port St. Lucie home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>On Saturday afternoon, Gainey had given Dominic permission to walk to Sportsman&amp;apost;s Park, a route he&amp;apost;s familiar with since he uses it to ride his bike to school, her lawyer said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>On the way, he passed a public pool, and someone asked him where his mother was.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;They asked me a couple questions, and I got scared, so I ran off to the park and they called the cops,&amp;quot; Dominic Guerrisi told CNN affiliate WPTV.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>An officer arrived at the park where Dominic was playing a short time later.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;Dominic checked in with his mom a few minutes before the police came and was getting ready to go home for dinner,&amp;quot; said Gainey&amp;apost;s attorney, John Whitehead, founder of the Virginia-based civil liberties group the Rutherford Institute.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>He always has a cell phone with him and was wearing it in a case around his neck that his mother had made.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>According to Whitehead, the phone had fallen out of his pocket recently and she didn&amp;apost;t want him to lose it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>When the officer asked Dominic whether his mother knew where he was, the child told him that she did and he&amp;apost;d just spoken to her on the phone, according to the police report.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Dominic told the police his name, address and mother&amp;apost;s name but wasn&amp;apost;t able to answer when asked for his date of birth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>He was then driven home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;When I saw the police cars pull up in my driveway, and the officers started asking me about Dominic, I was frantic to know whether he was OK,&amp;quot; Gainey told CNN in an e-mail.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>According to the report, Gainey told the officer that she let her son go to the park alone once or twice a week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The arresting officer said that Gainey had failed to provide her son with care and supervision by allowing him to cross the street and go to the park alone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>According to the report, he told her that there had been recent criminal activity in and around the park and a number of sex offenders lived nearby.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Gainey was arrested on a felony child neglect charge and taken to jail, leaving Dominic and her 17-year-old daughter at the house with her boyfriend.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>She was released seven hours later on $3,750 bond.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The Port St. Lucie Police Department has not responded to requests for comment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>As of Thursday afternoon, Gainey&amp;apost;s attorney still hadn&amp;apost;t received notice of a preliminary hearing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>A representative from the Florida State Attorney told CNN that the case hadn&amp;apost;t been assigned to a prosecutor yet.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is a small town and a safe area,&amp;quot; Whitehead said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;Nicole knows she&amp;apost;s not guilty of anything, and she&amp;apost;ll plead that way if it comes to it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>On Wednesday, Gainey met with an employee from the Florida Department of Children and Families who told her the charges would likely be dropped, according to Whitehead.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m really sad about how this has already impacted our family,&amp;quot; Gainey wrote in an e-mail to CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;My son is worried that I&amp;apost;ll get in trouble if he goes outside.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>I&amp;apost;m even worried about getting in trouble if I let him walk down my driveway alone.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>A number of child neglect arrests are gaining attention nationwide, with some onlookers arguing local authorities are overstepping bounds in arresting parents for childrearing decisions that wouldn&amp;apost;t have merited notice a generation ago or which plunge families close to the poverty line into even more dire situations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;Something has shifted and now we&amp;apost;re in the middle of a dangerous societal trend of arresting parents for noncriminal activities,&amp;quot; Whitehead said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>In early July, Debra Harrell of South Carolina made national news after being arrested after letting her 9-year-old daughter play unattended in a nearby park while she worked.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>She lost her job at McDonald&amp;apost;s but has since gotten it back and regained custody of her child, according to her attorney, Robert Verner Phillips.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>She&amp;apost;s awaiting trial, and the Department of Social Services case against her is still open.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>In March, Shanesha Taylor was arrested in Scottsdale, Arizona, on two counts of felony child abuse after leaving her two children in her Dodge Durango for about an hour while she interviewed for a job.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>On July 18, she reached a settlement with the Maricopa County Attorney&amp;apost;s Office dismissing her case if she completes a diversion program.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Along with parenting and substance-abuse classes, Taylor is required to establish education and child-care trusts for each of her three children, two of which are still in state custody.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Florida&amp;apost;s child neglect statute has no age written into the law.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Many states do not specify an age at which a child can be legally left at home or allowed to go places alone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>This leaves some parents unsure of when it&amp;apost;s appropriate or even legal to leave a child unsupervised.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>The Florida Department of Children and Families said in a statement that people who believe they&amp;apost;ve witnessed a case of neglect can call a hotline to report it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;The hotline can be called when a child of any age is without adult supervision or arrangements appropriate for the child&amp;apost;s age or mental or physical condition, so that the child is unable to care for the child&amp;apost;s own needs or another&amp;apost;s basic needs or is unable to exercise good judgment in responding to any kind of physical or emotional crisis,&amp;quot; according to the statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>But the resource is little help to parents who are trying to figure out at what age they can legally allow their children to go out into the world alone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;Parents I talk to are nervous about doing anything, thinking they could get charged for something without knowing what they&amp;apost;re doing wrong,&amp;quot; Whitehead said.Do you think authorities are simply doing their job by arresting parents who let young children go places alone, or are they overreacting?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Share your opinion in the comments section below.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
