<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="906" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/06/05/opinion/navarrette-rubio-immigration/index.html" date_published="2013-06-05 11:13:06" category="opinion" author="Ruben Navarrette, CNN Contributor" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Opinion: Rubio&amp;apost;s wild immigration ride</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Ruben Navarrette: Immigration reform is not for the faint of heart or the thin-skinned .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="29">Navarrette: Marco Rubio has the thankless job of ginning up support among Republicans.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">He says most lawmakers prefer not to go near it; for those who do, it can be frustrating .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="32">Navarrette: Why can&amp;apost;t the GOP be confident and come up with policies that appeal to them?.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 14:44:01" annotation_time="130.33899" mapping_time_divergence="32.584747">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">Simpson knows that the endeavor is not for the faint of heart, or the thin-skinned or the easily disillusioned.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">It is no wonder that most lawmakers won&amp;apost;t go anywhere near the immigration issue.</sentence>
      <sentence id="29" ids_highlights="2">Here you have a rising star in the GOP tasked with the thankless job of ginning up support among Republicans for a bill that many of them think would create millions of new Democratic voters, albeit, 13 years down the road, which is the amount of time that the legislation requires illegal immigrants to wait before becoming citizens and getting the right to vote.</sentence>
      <sentence id="32" ids_highlights="4">Or that Republicans have so little confidence in their own party, message and ability to win over these voters in those same 13 years by coming up with policies that appeal to them.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>San Diego Former Wyoming Sen. Al Simpson knows a thing or two about passing landmark immigration reform.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>My friend and former graduate school professor did it in 1986 with the Immigration Reform and Control Act, which he co-authored with former Rep. Romano Mazzoli.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Simpson knows that the endeavor is not for the faint of heart, or the thin-skinned or the easily disillusioned.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>It means navigating one of the wackiest and wickedest debates in our public discourse.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The immigration debate, he likes to say, is filled with &amp;quot;emotion, fear, guilt and racism.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>It is no wonder that most lawmakers won&amp;apost;t go anywhere near the immigration issue.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>For those who grab the bull by the horns and wrestle it to the ground, things can get frustrating.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>So began the education of Marco Rubio.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The Florida senator is the de-facto leader of the Gang of Eight, the bipartisan group of senators pushing for immigration reform.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Rubio has become the face of immigration reform.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>He is the most articulate advocate and the game&amp;apost;s most valuable player in large part because he is charged with rounding up Republican votes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Meanwhile, if Rubio were to withdraw support for the bill, it wouldn&amp;apost;t just be a game changer.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>It would be game over.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>He recently worried allies by characterizing the bill as not strong enough and said that more border security measures have to be added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>While Rubio courts Republicans, the Democratic members of the gang (Charles Schumer of New York, Dick Durbin of Illinois or Bob Menendez of New Jersey) need to arm-twist Democrats to make sure they&amp;apost;re on board.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Many of the Senate&amp;apost;s Democrats don&amp;apost;t seem enthusiastic about a path to citizenship for 11 million illegal immigrants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>On my scorecard, I count at least 10 Democrats, from both red states and union-friendly rust belt states, who either outright oppose the legislation or whose support is shaky.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Schumer predicted Sunday on NBC&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;Meet the Press&amp;quot; that a bill could pass by the Fourth of July and that he is shooting for 70 votes, which he thought he could get, including a majority of Republicans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Don&amp;apost;t believe it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>I&amp;apost;ve followed Schumer&amp;apost;s approach to the immigration issue for many years, and most of what he says on the subject is a falsehood, a fraud or a fairy tale.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>A couple of weeks ago, Menendez went on Univision&amp;apost;s Sunday show, &amp;quot;Al Punto,&amp;quot; and candidly told host Jorge Ramos that the Gang of Eight didn&amp;apost;t have 60 votes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>And now suddenly they have 70?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>This is Schumer&amp;apost;s game: Set expectations high and put the burden of meeting them squarely on Republicans.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Leave Democrats off the hook.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Talk about how most Republicans will support the bill.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>So when the vote comes and it turns out -- surprise!</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>-- a majority of Republicans vote against the thing, the GOP will catch all the blame.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s all part of Mr. Rubio&amp;apost;s wild ride.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Here you have a rising star in the GOP tasked with the thankless job of ginning up support among Republicans for a bill that many of them think would create millions of new Democratic voters, albeit, 13 years down the road, which is the amount of time that the legislation requires illegal immigrants to wait before becoming citizens and getting the right to vote.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>I can&amp;apost;t decide which is more pathetic.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>That Republicans have such a guilty conscience -- for the hamhanded way in which they&amp;apost;ve handled immigration, and the acrimony they&amp;apost;ve stirred up against Latinos -- that they think legalized immigrants are going to hold a grudge for 13 years before finally getting even.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Or that Republicans have so little confidence in their own party, message and ability to win over these voters in those same 13 years by coming up with policies that appeal to them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>From the sounds of the debate, Rubio isn&amp;apost;t making as many converts as he is making enemies in his own party.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>There are even some conservatives, in the conspiracy corner of the GOP, who suggest that this was the secret plan of Democrats all along: Rope Rubio into supporting immigration reform.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Put him front and center.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Ruin his reputation with conservatives.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>And effectively remove him from the top-tier of 2016 GOP presidential hopefuls.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>That is a little far-fetched.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Besides, Rubio could emerge from all this with enough new supporters on the left to make up for whatever support he could be losing on the right.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Either way, he seems intent on fighting one battle at a time and, assuming he has White House ambitions, letting the next presidential race take care of itself.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>As for the senator wavering on the immigration bill, I don&amp;apost;t see it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Rubio supports the main principles, and he&amp;apost;s simply thinking about the best way to pass it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>He said during a television interview on Tuesday that he doesn&amp;apost;t think the bill has the 60 votes needed to break a possible filibuster and that &amp;quot;even the Democrats would concede that.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>And he is worried that &amp;quot;horse trading&amp;quot; could water down the border security provisions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>But he still backs the final product.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Credit mom.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>In an interview with Time a few months ago, Rubio, whose middle name is Antonio, said that his mother, Oriales Garcia Rubio, left him a voice mail in December.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>She urged him to do right by illegal immigrants, whom she called &amp;quot;los pobrecitos&amp;quot; (the poor ones).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>The message went: &amp;quot;Tony, some loving advice from the person who cares for you most in the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Don&amp;apost;t mess with the immigrants, my son.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>Please, don&amp;apost;t mess with them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>They&amp;apost;re human beings just like us, and they came for the same reasons we came.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>To work.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>To improve their lives.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>So please, don&amp;apost;t mess with them.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>Rubio has said that his mother&amp;apost;s plea reminded him that immigration has a &amp;quot;human element.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>Now everything I see and hear, including the senator appearing on a gauntlet of conservative radio shows to defend the bill, tells me that Rubio will keep the faith.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s not easy to do when, I have it on good authority, your Senate office is getting hate mail comically telling the Cuban-American lawmaker to &amp;quot;Go back to Mexico!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="59">
          <content>Normally, that sort of thing might seem strange.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="60">
          <content>But in the immigration debate, it&amp;apost;s madness as usual.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="61">
          <content>Follow us on Twitter @CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="62">
          <content>Join us on Facebook/CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
