<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="807" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/01/10/opinion/opinion-poirier-french-comedian/index.html?iref=allsearch" date_published="2014-01-10 16:31:46" category="opinion" author="Agnès Poirier, political analyst, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>French comic banned: Victory for French values?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="18">The interior ministry adviced to ban a controversial comedian from performing if they deemed public order at risk.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="25">France may not have a First Amendment, but censorship is not considered lightly, Poirier writes.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="31">The government is walking a fine line between censorship and the respect of republican values, she says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-01 11:03:50" annotation_time="25.049667">
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="1">However, what has divided France is the interior ministry&amp;apost;s advice to the country&amp;apost;s prefects to ban the comedian from performing if they deemed public order at risk.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="2">France may not have a First Amendment, but censorship is not considered lightly.</sentence>
      <sentence id="31" ids_highlights="3">The French government is walking a fine line between censorship and the respect of republican values; it looks however as if it has won the first round against racism.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>It has been some rather strange three weeks in France.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Since footballer Nicolas Anelka dedicated a goal to his friend, the controversial French comedian Dieudonné, by doing the comedian&amp;apost;s infamous trademark salute, the &amp;quot;quenelle,&amp;quot; what some believe is a reverse Nazi salute, during a match for West Bromwich Albion, France has been talking about little else.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>It is as if the entire public debate has been hijacked by a comedian who, over the last 15 years, has steadily drifted towards more and more extreme behavior and inflammatory speech.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Anelka&amp;apost;s gesture suddenly shone the light on a phenomenon that had so far been little known outside France.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Now, the world knows that there is more to the &amp;quot;quenelle&amp;quot; than the exquisite dish, a creamy mixture of fish and egg, originated from Lyon, France&amp;apost;s gastronomic capital.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Dieudonné, 48, started his career as a comedian in the 1990s, in a duo with Jewish Franco-Moroccan Elie Semoun.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>They separated in 1997 when Semoun developed a career in cinema.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Dieudonné struggled to exist solo and was said to be bitter about his ex-partner&amp;apost;s success and fame.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>He then entered the realm of French politics, first of all fighting against the extreme right National Front before slowly getting closer to Marine Le Pen&amp;apost;s xenophobic party, alongside extremist Islamists.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>His shows started focusing almost exclusively on his hatred of Israel and Jews.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Condemned many times by the French courts for incitement to hatred, Dieudonné publically defended Iran&amp;apost;s and the Hezbollah&amp;apost;s anti-Semitic rhetoric.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Dieudonne himself, who no longer gives interviews to the mainstream media, denies that his act, or la quenelle, is anti-Semitic.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>He claims through his legal team to be nothing more than a comedian and the victim of unjustified attacks because he stands up for those who are excluded from French society.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Each time that the manager of a theater in France has refused to let him use their premises for one of his controversial shows, Dieudonné has threatened legal action.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Anelka&amp;apost;s public gesture has had the merit to prompt French Interior Minister Manuel Valls to action and to look into other aspects of the comedian&amp;apost;s personality.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>It was revealed that Dieudonné has been quietly investigated for money laundering and tax fraud for more than a year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Valls, interviewed on French radio Europe 1, stated that Dieudonné was trying to declare himself bankrupt in order to avoid paying taxes and fines and that a possible case of money laundering between France and Cameroon was being closely looked at.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>However, what has divided France is the interior ministry&amp;apost;s advice to the country&amp;apost;s prefects to ban the comedian from performing if they deemed public order at risk.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Dieudonné, at the beginning of a national tour, thus received his first ban on Thursday morning ahead of a planned performance in Nantes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>His lawyer immediately appealed and an administrative court overturned the ban.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The interior minister then appealed to France&amp;apost;s highest jurisdiction which decided to uphold the ban on Thursday evening.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>A similar legal wrangling is expected to take place in every town where Dieudonné is supposed to perform.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>French President Francois Hollande weighed in the debate, giving all his support to his Interior minister.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>So far, France&amp;apost;s public opinion and the media have been split over the issue of the ban.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>France may not have a First Amendment, but censorship is not considered lightly.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>There may be an understanding that freedom of speech stops where incitement to hatred begins and the French, in their majority, think that Dieudonné has gone much too far.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>However, is the ban in danger of giving publicity to Dieudonné?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>His shows are now selling fast.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Others, such as French philosopher Bernard Henry Levy, argue that Dieudonné ceased long ago to be an artist and that his virulent anti-Semitism shouldn&amp;apost;t be seen as artistic license: &amp;quot;This is not humor anymore, this is political,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>And why should Dieudonné be indeed treated differently than Marine Le Pen?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The French government is walking a fine line between censorship and the respect of republican values; it looks however as if it has won the first round against racism.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>