<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="888" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/08/29/opinion/citron-revenge-porn" date_published="2013-08-29 10:57:30" category="opinion" author="Danielle Keats Citron, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="false" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Opinion: Make &amp;apost;revenge porn&amp;apost; a crime in U.S.</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7, 6, 5">Danielle Citron: &amp;quot;Jane&amp;apost;s&amp;quot; ex posted nude photo on revenge porn site with contact info.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8, 23, 18">Citron: Women harassed, lose jobs, stalked as photos posted without permission go viral.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="13">Citron: Nonconsensual disclosure of naked images needs to be criminalized.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_time="15.643001">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">For example, in the United States, &amp;quot;Jane&amp;quot; allowed her ex-boyfriend to take her naked photograph because, he assured her, it would be for his eyes only.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">After their breakup, the man betrayed her trust.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">On the revenge porn site UGotPosted, he uploaded her naked photo and contact information.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">Jane received calls, e-mails, and Facebook friend requests from hundreds of strangers, many of whom wanted sex.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="3">Many states prohibit the nonconsensual taking of sexually explicit images -- the disclosure of someone&amp;apost;s naked images should be criminalized as well.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="2">Jane, who is a nurse, did not go to work for days.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="2">Because searches of victims&amp;apost; names display their naked images, they lose their jobs.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A new law in Israel makes it a sex crime to post sexual pictures or videos to the internet without the consent of the person featured in them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>We need to follow that example.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Revenge porn can ruin a person&amp;apost;s life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>A single post can go viral.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>For example, in the United States, &amp;quot;Jane&amp;quot; allowed her ex-boyfriend to take her naked photograph because, he assured her, it would be for his eyes only.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>After their breakup, the man betrayed her trust.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>On the revenge porn site UGotPosted, he uploaded her naked photo and contact information.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Jane received calls, e-mails, and Facebook friend requests from hundreds of strangers, many of whom wanted sex.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>After the site refused to take down the post and the anonymous calls and e-mails intensified, she turned to law enforcement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>According to the officers, nothing could be done because her ex had not engaged in a harassing &amp;quot;course of conduct,&amp;quot; as required by criminal harassment law, and because he had not explicitly solicited others to stalk her.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Criminal law should have a role in deterring and punishing revenge porn.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s not new that certain types of privacy invasions are crimes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Many states prohibit the nonconsensual taking of sexually explicit images -- the disclosure of someone&amp;apost;s naked images should be criminalized as well.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Only California and New Jersey have laws against turning people into objects of pornography without their permission -- although a huge loophole in California allows the posting of &amp;quot;selfie&amp;quot; images and only applies to photos posted by the photographer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Revenge porn and its ilk raise the risk of offline stalking and physical attack.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Fear can be profound.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Victims don&amp;apost;t feel safe leaving their homes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Jane, who is a nurse, did not go to work for days.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>As many victims have told me, they struggle especially with anxiety, and some suffer panic attacks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Revenge porn victims withdraw from online engagement, shutting down their social media profiles and blogs to prevent strangers from finding them online.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>They cannot participate fully in our networked age.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The professional costs of revenge porn are steep.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Because searches of victims&amp;apost; names display their naked images, they lose their jobs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Schools have fired teachers whose naked photos appeared on revenge porn sites.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>A government agency terminated a woman&amp;apost;s employment after a co-worker circulated her nude photograph to colleagues.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Victims may be unable to find work at all.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>According to a 2009 Microsoft study, more than 80% of employers rely on candidates&amp;apost; online reputations as an employment screen.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Common reasons for not interviewing and hiring applicants include concerns about their &amp;quot;lifestyle,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;inappropriate&amp;quot; online comments, and &amp;quot;unsuitable&amp;quot; photographs, videos, and information about them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Recruiters don&amp;apost;t contact victims to see if they posted nude photos of themselves or if someone else did in violation of their trust.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The simple but regrettable truth is that after consulting search results, employers don&amp;apost;t call revenge porn victims to schedule an interview or to extend offers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s just seen as good business to avoid hiring people whose search results would reflect poorly on them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Revenge porn is a harmful form of bigotry and sexual harassment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>It exposes victims&amp;apost; sexuality in humiliating ways.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Their naked photos appear on slut shaming sites.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Once their naked images are exposed, anonymous strangers send e-mail messages that threaten rape.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Some have said: &amp;quot;First I will rape you, then I&amp;apost;ll kill you.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Victims internalize these frightening and demeaning messages.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>New Jersey is the only state to make it a felony to disclose a person&amp;apost;s nude or partially nude images without that person&amp;apost;s consent.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>In California, it&amp;apost;s a misdemeanor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The New Jersey statute is a helpful model for states that are considering proposals to criminalize revenge porn.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Congress should amend the federal cyberstalking law, 18 U.S.C. 2261A, to cover the use of any interactive computer service to produce or disclose a sexually graphic visual depiction of an individual without that individual&amp;apost;s consent.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>What about First Amendment objections to legislative proposals to criminalize revenge porn?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>A narrowly crafted criminal statute like New Jersey&amp;apost;s can be reconciled with our commitment to free speech.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>First Amendment protections are less rigorous for purely private matters because the threat of liability would not risk chilling the meaningful exchange of ideas.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Listeners and speakers have no legitimate interest in nude photos or sex tapes published without the subjects&amp;apost; permission.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>That online users can claim a prurient interest in viewing sexual images does not transform them into a matter of legitimate public concern.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Nonconsensual pornography lacks First Amendment value as a historical matter, and could be understood as categorically unprotected as obscenity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Although the Court&amp;apost;s obscenity doctrine has developed along different lines with distinct justifications, nonconsensual pornography can be seen as part of obscenity&amp;apost;s long tradition of proscription.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Criminalizing revenge porn is a crucial step in protecting victims from real and profound harms to their physical, emotional, and financial health and safety.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>It would deter damaging privacy invasions and send the powerful message that posting someone&amp;apost;s most private moments, most often in a breach of their trust and without their permission, is unacceptable.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>That lesson needs to be repeated early and often before online users, especially young people, think that shaming and terrorizing individuals is an acceptable practice.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>We need a &amp;quot;cyber civil rights&amp;quot; agenda to combat bigoted online abuse.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>The criminalization of nonconsensual disclosure of someone&amp;apost;s naked images is an important part of that agenda.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>Follow us on Twitter @CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>Join us on Facebook/CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
