<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="853" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/03/14/opinion/keen-kony-2012/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2012-03-14 15:18:01" category="opinion" author="Andrew Keen, CNN contributor" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Opinion: After Kony, should kids decide our morals?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Keen: Tens of millions of innocent kids have found a new Jerusalem to liberate.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">Keen: All it takes to join the crusade is a click of a mouse and $15.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="16, 5">Millions have watched the &amp;quot;Kony2012&amp;quot; movie spotlighting the horrors of Joseph Kony.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="46">Keen: Should we trust children to make moral decisions with minimal world experience?.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-25 09:15:47" annotation_time="57.112335" mapping_time_divergence="14.278084">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">Today, in what we might dub the Children&amp;apost;s Crusade 2.0, tens of millions of innocent kids have found a new Jerusalem to liberate.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">It&amp;apost;s called Africa and their liberation vehicle is the &amp;quot;Kony2012&amp;quot; viral video commodifying innocence that has been watched 80 million times since its release last week.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">All it takes is a click of a mouse and $15 to liberate the world from an infidel who catches, disfigures and eats children.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="3">We can do that, it promises, by creating a network of millions of kids who will catch Joseph Kony, the Ugandan warlord described by Gavin, the deliciously blonde, four-year-old star of the movie, as a &amp;quot;big bad guy.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="46" ids_highlights="4">But should we really be empowering children to make moral decisions about a world in which they have little experience?</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>In June 1212, some 30,000 people, most of them children, massed in the center of France.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>This mob of Christian kids - remembered by historians as The Children&amp;apost;s Crusade - was on its way to Jerusalem to liberate it from an infidel who, it was rumored, ate children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Eight hundred years later, the connected children in today&amp;apost;s Facebook world have it much easier.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Today, in what we might dub the Children&amp;apost;s Crusade 2.0, tens of millions of innocent kids have found a new Jerusalem to liberate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s called Africa and their liberation vehicle is the &amp;quot;Kony2012&amp;quot; viral video commodifying innocence that has been watched 80 million times since its release last week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>This time though, the kids don&amp;apost;t even need to leave home to go on their crusade.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>All it takes is a click of a mouse and $15 to liberate the world from an infidel who catches, disfigures and eats children.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>And this time, they might even get a bracelet and an &amp;quot;action kit&amp;quot; to memorialize their participation in this struggle against almighty evil.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Yes, Africa -- and specifically Uganda -- has been reduced to a meme.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>An online meme spread like a rash by hyper-connected kids on global networks like Facebook, YouTube and Twitter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s no coincidence that &amp;quot;Kony2012,&amp;quot; part &amp;quot;Chitty Chitty Bang Bang&amp;quot; and part &amp;quot;Star Wars,&amp;quot; begins with the video of a birth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Our Facebook world changes everything, the movie promises its audience of children.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>We are told that &amp;quot;the game has new rules.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The world has been turned upside down by social media, the eschatological video explains, and now &amp;quot;a bunch of littles can make difference.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;We can change the course of human history,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Kony2012&amp;quot; promises its audience of littles.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>We can do that, it promises, by creating a network of millions of kids who will catch Joseph Kony, the Ugandan warlord described by Gavin, the deliciously blonde, four-year-old star of the movie, as a &amp;quot;big bad guy.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;Kony abducts kids just like Gavin,&amp;quot; the movie&amp;apost;s narrator, Jason Russell -- who just happens to be Gavin&amp;apost;s dad --- tells us.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Joseph Kony forces kids to kill their own parents and mutilate people&amp;apost;s faces.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>He is the personification of evil, the antichrist of Christian eschatology, the sort of monster who, 800 years ago, inspired 30,000 kids to leave home and set sail to Jerusalem.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;Kony2012&amp;quot; may be in poor taste, but it&amp;apost;s rich in irony.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>And it&amp;apost;s particularly ironic that the most viral YouTube video of all time was made by a non-profit group called &amp;quot;Invisible Children&amp;quot;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Children are many things these days, but they certainly aren&amp;apost;t invisible -- especially on the Internet, where it is the kids, these adolescent messengers, who are becoming the McLuhanite message of our networked age.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The glossily seductive &amp;quot;Kony2012&amp;quot; was explicitly designed for kids.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In defense of his movie, Jason Russell said on CNN that he thinks of &amp;quot;Kony2012&amp;quot; as being owned by children because &amp;quot;the youth of the world&amp;quot; has funded it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Invisible Children&amp;apost;s CEO, Ben Keesey, even acknowledged to the Wall Street Journal that the movie was made to appeal to children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;How do we make this translate to a 14-year-old who has just walked out of algebra class?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Keesey said of Invisible Children&amp;apost;s thinking behind the movie.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>And the kids of the world, those millions of innocent 14-year-olds who walked from their algebra class to the nearest screen, have repaid Invisible Children by turning &amp;quot;Kony2012&amp;quot; into one of the most viral products in history.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Yes, outraged celebrities like Angelina Jolie and Rihanna, who unselfishly showed off her breasts for Invisible Children, helped spread the word.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>But it&amp;apost;s the children who have transformed the big mustachioed Joseph Kony from a has-been Ugandan warlord into the second-coming of Adolf Hitler (whose little mustachioed face is, of course, also featured in the video).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Even the most informed bloggers on the Internet, like GigaOm&amp;apost;s Mathew Ingram, A-list blogger Jeff Jarvis and Columbia University&amp;apost;s Emily Bell all discovered &amp;quot;Kony2012&amp;quot; through their kids.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am watching https://twitter.com/ &amp;apost; my 11 yr old:&amp;apost;oh I&amp;apost;ve seen that: I&amp;apost;ve already emailed it to my grade&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>This is the new news cycle,&amp;quot; Bell, who heads up Columbia University&amp;apost;s Tow Center for Digital Journalism, tweeted last week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>In a way then, all the messianic promise of &amp;quot;Kony 2012&amp;quot; is eerily prescient.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The world has been turned on its head and the game does, indeed, have new rules.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>In our radically democratic age, it&amp;apost;s the kids rather than the grown-ups who are curating the news, identifying the bad guys, perhaps even architecting the moral thrust of U.S. foreign policy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Writing in the New York Times at the weekend, the cultural critic Douglas Coupland observed: &amp;quot;In the past decade that we appear to have entered an aura-free universe in which all eras coexist at once -- a state of possibly permanent atemporality given to us courtesy of the Internet.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>No particular era now dominates.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>We live in a post-era era without forms of its own powerful enough to brand the times.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Coupland is right.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>But in what he calls &amp;quot;our new world of flattened time and space,&amp;quot; I wonder if we are also seeing, alongside the radical democratization of time and space, the flattening of age.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>In a post-era era world of &amp;quot;Kony2012,&amp;quot; with its harrypotterfication of reality and its transformation of Africa from a complex, infinitely nuanced society into a manichaean Madison Avenue fantasy of good and evil, are we all now becoming teenagers?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>I hope not.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>800 years ago, back in 1212, the Children&amp;apost;s Crusade ended in shipwreck and enslavement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Today&amp;apost;s digital version of that innocent crusade, led by the pied-pipers from Invisible Children, probably won&amp;apost;t end so tragically.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>But should we really be empowering children to make moral decisions about a world in which they have little experience?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Should we entrust the innocent, that &amp;quot;bunch of littles&amp;quot; who have made &amp;quot;Kony2012&amp;quot; such an instant hit, to architect our brave new connected world?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
