<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="867" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/01/21/opinion/brennan-sexual-abuse/index.html" date_published="2014-01-21 12:54:48" category="opinion" author="Allison Brennan" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Opinion: Don&amp;apost;t stay silent on sexual abuse</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="20">Allison Brennan: I was sexually abused when I was a child; it&amp;apost;s not easy to reveal this.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="17">Brennan: To heal, victims need to be able to talk about what happened to them .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">She says many victims are afraid to speak out because they feel ashamed or scared .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="19">Brennan: Talking about it sends a message to society to pay more attention to this issue .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-16 16:44:23" annotation_time="64.5925">
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">As a society, I&amp;apost;m well aware that many people -- victims like me -- are afraid to speak out because they feel ashamed or scared.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="2">But in order to heal, victims need to be able to talk about what happened to them, to acknowledge the horror of it, to condemn it and to demand punishment.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="4">By talking about sexual abuse, we send a message to society to pay more attention to this problem.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="1">It&amp;apost;s not easy for me to disclose this part of my life.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>I was 5 years old when the person who took my innocence touched me inappropriately.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>What he did to me went on for a period of time, though I don&amp;apost;t remember how long exactly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>He was a teenage babysitter.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>His sister also participated in the abuse.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>She taught me things that no child should know about sex.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>To this day I don&amp;apost;t understand why they did what they did.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>I&amp;apost;m not sure I care why they did it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>What matters to me now is talking about it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>As a victim, I want to start a conversation about sexual abuse.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>As a society, I&amp;apost;m well aware that many people -- victims like me -- are afraid to speak out because they feel ashamed or scared.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>But by remaining silent, victims like me feel like we&amp;apost;re taking responsibility for a crime committed against us that we know is wrong.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>I wanted nothing to do with the abuse.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>I didn&amp;apost;t want it to be a part of me, so I ignored it for almost 25 years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>During that time, the memories haunted me and I developed unhealthy coping mechanisms to compensate for the negative way I saw myself.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>I tried to be outwardly perfect.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>I withdrew and became defensive when I faced criticism.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>But in order to heal, victims need to be able to talk about what happened to them, to acknowledge the horror of it, to condemn it and to demand punishment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>For example, if we pretend that armed robberies don&amp;apost;t happen because they are bad, we would probably have Bonnies and Clydes running around everywhere.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>By talking about sexual abuse, we send a message to society to pay more attention to this problem.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s not easy for me to disclose this part of my life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>But with the love of my family and friends, I have begun to address the problem.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Part of that includes seeking the help of a therapist to understand the impact of the abuse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>And then something happened the other day.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>When Woody Allen received a lifetime achievement award and got a standing ovation at the Golden Globes on Sunday night, his ex-wife Mia Farrow and her son Ronan Farrow sent out tweets that alluded to alleged sexual abuse of Mia Farrow&amp;apost;s adopted daughter Dylan, who was 7 when Allen and Farrow were married.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Allen denied the allegation and was never charged, but Mia and Ronan believe otherwise.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Their tweets made me think of my own past.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>I remember reading an article a few months ago about the allegation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>When I read about Dylan and the Farrows trying to put forward her voice and her story, I wondered what was holding me back in telling my story.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Now, I&amp;apost;m revealing to the public something so personal I&amp;apost;m not sure what&amp;apost;s going to happen as a result.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>I am not sure how people will treat me.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>I don&amp;apost;t know if people will think I am damaged.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>I hope not.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>I&amp;apost;ve been told I am brave for talking about it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>But I wish I never had to be brave.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>I wish it had never happened.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a punishment to me every day knowing that the people who abused me -- who impacted my life in such a harmful way -- escaped justice.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>As much as I want to bring my case to justice, it is difficult to do so because it happened more than two decades ago in a foreign country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>At the time, I didn&amp;apost;t understand what was happening to me.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>I was 5, and I wasn&amp;apost;t going to take anyone to court.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>I am not entirely sure that going public with my story is a good idea.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>I do know that the alternative - denial and silence - is no way to live.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>I felt ashamed of something I didn&amp;apost;t do.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>But as I have begun to talk about the abuse, I have discovered that I have no reason to feel ashamed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>There are many adults who may feel ashamed about sexual abuse in their own life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>They may be confused about what to do.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>They may think -- &amp;quot;what if I am wrong and I accuse this person and create a mess&amp;quot; -- and they balk at action.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>They should take action -- when they are ready.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Whether that means taking their perpetrator to court, speaking out about how to help victims, discussing with their communities about ways of prevention, or advocating for more resources to help those who are being sexually abused or were sexually abused.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>The therapy I have been lucky enough to have access to has changed my life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>An important part of overcoming sexual abuse is addressing the stigma of seeking the help of a therapist, because some people may think you&amp;apost;re crazy or unstable.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>I am not.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>But I was wounded.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>Therapy has helped me begin to heal that wound.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>According to National Center for Victims of Crime, one in five girls and one in twenty boys are victims of sexual abuse.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>Such abuse causes children to &amp;quot;develop low self-esteem, a feeling of worthlessness and an abnormal or distorted view of sex.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>And when they grow up, they can become withdrawn and suicidal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>As a journalist, every day when I show up for work, I ask other people to tell their stories from staring down the Navy Yard shooter to surviving the Moore, Oklahoma tornado.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>I ask these people to be fearless in telling the world about their stories.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="59">
          <content>But when it came to my own story, I haven&amp;apost;t done it...until now.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="60">
          <content>I believe in telling the truth -- and I believe telling the truth can set you free, however trite that is.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="61">
          <content>If you can find your words, you should use them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="62">
          <content>I hope it helps.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="63">
          <content>Follow us on Twitter @CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="64">
          <content>Join us on Facebook/CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
