<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="923" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/05/08/opinion/ghitis-nigeria-powerful-women/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-05-08 11:25:37" category="opinion" author="Frida Ghitis" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Opinion: Women of Nigeria stand up to terror</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="8">Frida Ghitis: Women of Nigeria got the world to pay attention to mass kidnapping of girls.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="51">Ghitis: Women endure the brunt of the worst aspects of repression and exploitation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">But women in many repressive countries are fighting back against injustice, she says .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="19">Ghitis: Pushback from women&amp;apost;s groups combined with social media gets results.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-28 05:12:54" annotation_time="41536.62">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">Women in many countries are vulnerable and victimized, but they are fighting back in unexpected places with the built-up fury of long held frustration.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="1">Let there be no doubt: The reason the United States is sending help, Nigeria is accepting it and the entire world is paying attention is that the women of Nigeria demanded it.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="4">And the response shows a phenomenon of both spontaneous and organized pushback from women&amp;apost;s groups, from the millions of men who join them, and from the forces that social media can unleash across cyberspace.</sentence>
      <sentence id="51" ids_highlights="2">Women endure the brunt of the worst aspects of repression and exploitation.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Women are not powerless.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Look at Nigeria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s impossible not to be outraged by the capture of hundreds of Nigerian schoolgirls by a terrorist group, and by the inexcusable delay in pursuing the armed men who took them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>For women, in particular, the continuing drama has ignited a particularly powerful response.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Women in many countries are vulnerable and victimized, but they are fighting back in unexpected places with the built-up fury of long held frustration.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>And they are getting results.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Women are no longer powerless.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Let there be no doubt: The reason the United States is sending help, Nigeria is accepting it and the entire world is paying attention is that the women of Nigeria demanded it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Nigerian women from the town of Chibok in the northeastern Borno state, the mothers, sisters, relatives and friends of the schoolgirls, launched their protests and set off the #BringBackOurGirls campaign that swept away weeks of international apathy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>At a rally in Abuja, one woman held up a sign that read &amp;quot;Can Anyone Hear Me?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The long-delayed answer was a most emphatic &amp;quot;Yes,&amp;quot; which resonated across the oceans and echoed in the Nigerian presidential palace.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Sure, the decisions are mostly up to male politicians, but in Washington, all the women members of the Senate, 20 of them, signed a letter to the president of the United States demanding a firm response.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>They did it without hesitation and without regard to political affiliation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The tragedy of the Nigerian girls was grotesquely highlighted in a video by a laughing Abubakr Shekau, the leader of Boko Haram.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>He declared &amp;quot;Allah says I should sell.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>He commands me to sell.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>I will sell women.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The revolting message encapsulated the distilled essence of women&amp;apost;s plight in many corners of the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>And the response shows a phenomenon of both spontaneous and organized pushback from women&amp;apost;s groups, from the millions of men who join them, and from the forces that social media can unleash across cyberspace.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>It is a movement that begins with the grassroots, moves into cyberspace and powers its way into the halls of power.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Women have had enough.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>There is a reason that Malala Yousefzai has become a major international figure, a hero especially to women.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>It is, of course, about her bravery.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Gunmen belonging to the Pakistani Taliban boarded the bus that was bringing the 14-year-old champion of girls&amp;apost; education and her friends from school.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>They shot her in the face.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The Taliban oppose girls&amp;apost; education with that obsessive fervor displayed by the most radical Islamist groups, who want to take all Muslims back to the 7th century.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>They could not kill her and they could no silence her.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Instead, they made her stronger, and they made her voice louder.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>In Afghanistan, when the Taliban came to power, one of its first acts was to shut down women&amp;apost;s schools and ban women from universities.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>They did it under the guise of enforcing Islamic rules.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Religious pretexts are common.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>But they are nothing more than an excuse.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Like the Taliban, Boko Haram finds it particularly offensive that girls should receive an education.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Shenkau appears on the latest video holding his AK-47, offering his considered advice.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;Girls should go and get married,&amp;quot; he said, adding he would give them in marriage &amp;quot;at the age of 9&amp;quot;...at the age of 12, &amp;quot;because they are our slaves.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s no wonder frustration is boiling over.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Consider the recent news from Indonesia&amp;apost;s Aceh province, where a woman was raped by eight men as punishment for having an affair.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Now an official Shariah court has sentenced her to a humiliating public caning.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Women are fed up.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>And it&amp;apost;s not all about the work of Muslim extremists.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>In late 2012, emotions boiled over in India after the horrific gang rape of a student riding a city bus in Mumbai.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>The woman came to be known as Nirbhaya, which means &amp;quot;the fearless one,&amp;quot; in Hindi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Nirbhaya, who had left home to study physiotherapy, had plans to show the Indian people that a woman could realize her dreams.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>She was planning to give free health care to the poor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Instead, she died at 23, when six men on the bus she took with her boyfriend attacked her with such brutality that she died from internal injuries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Nirbhaya shook India&amp;apost;s women.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>She jolted the country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>In massive demonstrations Indian women joined by thousands of men demanded the government take action to stop the epidemic of rape.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>The world was horrified.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>The government vowed to act, but there is much left to be done in a country dominated by men on all spheres of society.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>Women endure the brunt of the worst aspects of repression and exploitation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>As many as 30 million people are slaves today.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>Most of them are sex slaves working in brothels and enduring other forms of captivity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>And 98% of the sex slaves are women and girls.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>Cases like the Nigerian girls, still unaccounted for, and millions sold into bondage are the most urgent, the most dramatic.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>But they are only a part of the problem.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>They are so outrageous, so offensive, that they leave no room for moral equivocation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>Just a few days ago, the world was barely paying attention to Nigeria&amp;apost;s abducted schoolgirls.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="59">
          <content>Today, the whole world is watching, help is on the way.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="60">
          <content>That is what the women of Nigeria have accomplished -- not quite what Boko Haram had in mind.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="61">
          <content>Follow us on Twitter @CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="62">
          <content>Join us on Facebook/CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
