<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="810" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/11/24/opinion/china-foreign-policy/index.html" date_published="2013-11-25 03:36:25" category="opinion" author="Stephanie Kleine-Ahlbrandt, special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>From Japan to the U.S., China embarks on a bolder foreign policy</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">China is busy designing and implementing a bolder foreign policy .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Move comes in light of an anticipated U.S. decline.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="40">Xi Jinping effectively ending the traditional Chinese policy of non-intervention.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="35">Likely to see an even more self-confident foreign policy as Xi continues his decade of rule.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-13 16:53:38" annotation_time="28.6765">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1, 2">Many expected Xi Jinping to focus on internal politics in his first year in office and not make major external moves, but in fact China is busy designing and implementing a bolder foreign policy in light of an anticipated U.S. decline.</sentence>
      <sentence id="35" ids_highlights="4">And we are likely to see an even more self-confident Chinese foreign policy as he continues his decade of rule.</sentence>
      <sentence id="40" ids_highlights="3">Xi is likely to make efforts to deliver, and in so doing will effectively end the traditional Chinese policy of non-intervention.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Many expected Xi Jinping to focus on internal politics in his first year in office and not make major external moves, but in fact China is busy designing and implementing a bolder foreign policy in light of an anticipated U.S. decline.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>This strategy was made clear this weekend as Beijing mapped out airspace over a disputed island chain in the East China Sea and released rules that it says must be followed by all aircraft entering the zone -- under penalty of intervention by China&amp;apost;s military.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Unlike his predecessors, Xi is making foreign policy with the mindset of a great power, increasingly probing U.S. commitments to its allies in the region and exploiting opportunities to change the status quo.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>China&amp;apost;s recent rhetoric and actions show a move from a defensive, reactive, and image-conscious policy to a proactive approach designed to further China&amp;apost;s vital interests.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Officials in China have begun using new diplomatic language, with decades-old terms sloughed off to allow more room to maneuver.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Traditional mantras like &amp;quot;non-interference&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;hide our capacities and bide our time&amp;quot; are no more under Xi, whose new slogan is the &amp;quot;Chinese dream,&amp;quot; a vision for the national rejuvenation of the Chinese people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>And in the U.S.-China relationship, U.S. diplomats used to frame the debate with terms such as &amp;quot;responsible stakeholder&amp;quot; in the global system.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>But China has now put forth its own catch phrase: a &amp;quot;new type of great power relations,&amp;quot; in which the U.S. recognizes China&amp;apost;s core interests and respects it as an equal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>China&amp;apost;s actions also demonstrate a more activist external strategy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Regionally, maritime security interests have taken precedence in China&amp;apost;s strategic rationale.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Even before officially taking power, Xi was made head of the maritime small group that presided over Beijing&amp;apost;s swift and decisive response to Japan&amp;apost;s September 2012 purchase of three disputed islands in the East China Sea from their private owner.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>By declaring territorial baselines around the islands, increasing the number and length of its law enforcement patrols, and introducing military forces in the vicinity, China has challenged Japan&amp;apost;s de facto control of the area and moved to solidify its own claims.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>China&amp;apost;s demarcation of a new &amp;quot;Air Defense Identification Zone&amp;quot;, which includes the disputed islands - known as the Diaoyu in China and Senkaku in Japan - underscores these goals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>In the South China Sea, China has played a double game, calling for the peaceful settlement of disputes through bilateral negotiations and engaging in a wide-ranging charm offensive, while simultaneously trying to gain control of disputed territories.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The cancellation of President Obama&amp;apost;s October trip to the region, forced by the U.S. government shutdown, greatly assisted Xi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>It left him as the star attraction at regional gatherings where U.S.-China rivalry features strongly, and Xi made the most of the attention by announcing a slew of new deals across Southeast Asia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>China initially left the Philippines out of its largesse to punish it for submitting their maritime dispute to international arbitration and to warn other Association of South East Asian Nations (ASEAN) countries against doing the same.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Central Asia and the Middle East.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Xi has also acted strongly to protect other interests.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>He swept through Central Asia in September to forge closer trade ties at a time when the U.S. is disengaging from Afghanistan and the region.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>China has recently splashed cash there to secure access to petroleum resources beyond the reach of the U.S. navy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>And China and Russia continue to engage in joint multi-polarity to keep the U.S. in check while furthering their energy relationship.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>In the Middle East, where traditionally China has been content to have the U.S. play the decisive political role, Xi has made moves calibrated to establish a presence without becoming mired in the region&amp;apost;s disputes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>With China expected to become even more dependent on oil from the region, Beijing realizes that instability there could jeopardize supply.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>In May, Xi received both Mahmoud Abbas and Benjamin Netanyahu, issued a &amp;apost;four point peace plan,&amp;apost; and offered to host an Israeli-Palestinian peace summit.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>While the components of the plan are not new and the offer has not been accepted, the initiative showed that as its power and interests grow, China will act when affected by issues outside its neighborhood.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>North Korea.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Closer to home, Xi has sharply distinguished himself from his predecessor in dealing with North Korea.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Where Hu was indulgent , Xi has laid down some &amp;quot;house rules,&amp;quot; signing up to sanctions and employing bolder rhetoric against the wayward neighbor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>But when North Korea walked back its provocations, Xi angered the U.S. and South Korea by dispatching Vice-President Li Yuanchao to Pyongyang to attend a military parade marking the 60th anniversary of the end of the Korean War.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>His presence was a potent symbol, showing that China&amp;apost;s pique over North Korea&amp;apost;s earlier actions didn&amp;apost;t preclude Beijing from trying to repair relations there.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>American preferences on North Korea are less and less central to China&amp;apost;s decision-making; unless the U.S. takes measures on the Peninsula that China sees as undermining its regional security.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Xi has also doubled down on involvement in Myanmar, which plays an increasingly important role in China&amp;apost;s energy security and where China fears that American engagement efforts are part of a U.S. strategic encirclement of China.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Taken together, Xi&amp;apost;s decisions and words illustrate a more active strategy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>And we are likely to see an even more self-confident Chinese foreign policy as he continues his decade of rule.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Because Xi&amp;apost;s domestic agenda and China&amp;apost;s external agenda are intertwined.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Xi&amp;apost;s crafting of the &amp;quot;Chinese Dream&amp;quot; as a vessel for party legitimacy also more closely yokes the party&amp;apost;s fortunes to its performance as a defender of national interests and ambitions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>And in his pronouncements on ideology, and by establishing a new national security council, Xi has made clear that he sees a link between ideological menaces to one-party rule and strategic threats abroad, especially from the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Nationalists, especially online, continue to demand that the government use its new-found international heft to more actively and directly defend China&amp;apost;s global interests.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Xi is likely to make efforts to deliver, and in so doing will effectively end the traditional Chinese policy of non-intervention.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
