<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="822" link="http://cnn.com/2014/03/05/opinion/russia-ukraine-austria/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-03-05 15:25:16" category="opinion" author="Timothy Snyder, historian, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>If Russia swallows Ukraine, the European system is finished</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Ukraine crisis is making Europeans think again about &amp;apost;30s and origins of World War II, says Timothy Snyder.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="15">Snyder: As with Putin today in Ukraine, Hitler in 1938 in Austria based claim on need to protect fellow ethnics.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="32">Once Austria had gone, European leaders easily betrayed Czechoslovakia, which truly deserved support, he adds.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="46">Seizure of Crimea was meant as challenge to EU, to prove European values cannot defend themselves - Snyder.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-13 17:22:24" annotation_time="116.486336">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Vienna, Austria As Russia continues its military occupation of the Crimean district of Ukraine, as Putin enunciates a doctrine of military intervention in support of ethnic brethren, and the West ponders what might be done, Europeans begin to think again about the 1930s and the origins of World War II.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="2">As with Putin today in Ukraine, Hitler in 1938 in Austria based his claim on the need to protect fellow ethnics.</sentence>
      <sentence id="32" ids_highlights="3">Once Austria had been abandoned, European leaders had little trouble betraying a country that truly deserved their support, democratic Czechoslovakia.</sentence>
      <sentence id="46" ids_highlights="4">The seizure of Crimea was meant as a challenge to the European Union.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Vienna, Austria As Russia continues its military occupation of the Crimean district of Ukraine, as Putin enunciates a doctrine of military intervention in support of ethnic brethren, and the West ponders what might be done, Europeans begin to think again about the 1930s and the origins of World War II.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The Russian historian Andrei Zubov, for example, has published a sophisticated comparison between Putin&amp;apost;s seizure of Crimea and Adolf Hitler&amp;apost;s annexation of Austria, seeing both as the beginning of a chain of events with fatal consequences not just for the subjects of the aggression but for the aggressors themselves.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>In Vienna, where I live, one also hears constant mentions of 1938.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Austrians and other citizens of European Union countries are beginning to consider what the end of Ukraine might mean for their own European system.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The point is not that Putin is like Hitler; the point is that the removal of a state from Europe has consequences for the continent.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>When we consider any state in isolation from the system, it can seem fragile, new, perhaps unnecessary.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Ukraine today, like Austria in the 1930s, is a creation of a dramatic change in the world order.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Austria as an independent republic owed its existence to World War I, just as Ukraine as an independent republic owes its existence to the unexpected collapse of the Soviet Union.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Independent Austria lasted for two decades; independent Ukraine has existed for only slightly longer.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>For some, an artificial creation that had no right to exist; for others home to a people indistinguishable from Germans, Austria had few friends in 1938.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Ukraine finds itself in much the same position today.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Just as most European leaders were happy to accept the German idea that Austria had no right to exist, many people around the West seem ready to forget about Ukraine or to believe the Kremlin&amp;apost;s propaganda that half of the country is Russian.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Yet the reasons why states are supposed to exist are general, transcending their particular histories.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The principles of international law are not subject to particular claims about identities.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>As with Putin today in Ukraine, Hitler in 1938 in Austria based his claim on the need to protect fellow ethnics.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>It is easy to criticize Putin&amp;apost;s arguments in some important details.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>He claims to be defending Russian citizens.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>But since dual citizenship in Ukraine is illegal, the most visible of Russian citizens in Ukraine are (1) the Russian soldiers and sailors based in Sevastopol, (2) the Russian soldiers who have just invaded southern Ukraine and (3) Ukrainian riot police who are being given Russian citizenship at the Russian consulate in Simferopol to reward them for beating Ukrainian protesters.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Putin claims to be defending &amp;quot;compatriots,&amp;quot; but that is a category that has no meaning.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The suggestion is that anyone who speaks Russian needs a Russian invasion; that would mean that since I am writing in English I need an English invasion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>But the real problem goes much deeper.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>In both cases the claim of a right of protection of ethnic brethren was only one element of a larger worldview.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Hitler in fact cared little for ethnic Germans in Austria or for Austria itself.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Its destruction of Austria was meant to show, as it did, that all standards of the European system were subject to corruption if a single man took a single risk.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>What Europeans decide to see in the Ukrainian revolution might in the end define Europe.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The interwar European system was based on the principle of state sovereignty.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>No doubt this was an imperfect and incomplete moral and legal basis for international relations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>And yet its violation meant the end of the system itself.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>When Europe&amp;apost;s leaders abandoned Austria in 1938, they were conceding to Hitler the right to define the new rules of the new order.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The immediate consequences were clear enough.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Without the protection of a state, Austria&amp;apost;s Jewish minority was subject to anti-Semitic violence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Once Austria had been abandoned, European leaders had little trouble betraying a country that truly deserved their support, democratic Czechoslovakia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Its dismemberment began later that same year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Once Europeans had the experience of allowing states to die they could do so again.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>By the time the great powers came to their senses in 1939 it was too late.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>The European system of today is based on the principle of state sovereignty, combined with the robust international cooperation of the European Union, and legitimated by a historically new attention to human rights.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>The European Union is based on the premise of learning from history.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>National Socialism and Stalinism are seen as experiences from which Europeans have learned and extremes to which European politics must be restrained.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>This system, like the interwar system, is vulnerable to challenge.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Russia has now proposed an alternative, in which Russian culture is historically unique and demanding of protection, European fascism and Stalinism are a trove of constructive ideas, and human rights are nothing more than a facade for western imperialism.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Russian propaganda assigns a particular importance to sexual minorities, with many prominent commentators claiming for example that many in the EU are part of an international gay conspiracy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>The Russian invasion of southern Ukraine is a threat above all to the citizens of Ukraine.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>As Professor Zubov has argued, it has threatening implications also for Russians.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>This was a courageous argument for him to make -- he says he was immediately fired from his position.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Europeans who face fewer risks can continue the argument.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>The seizure of Crimea was meant as a challenge to the European Union.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>It is meant to prove that European values cannot defend themselves.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Can they?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
