<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="828" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/01/23/opinion/ukraine-unrest-dictatorship-lutsevych/index.html" date_published="2014-01-23 13:29:50" category="opinion" author="Orysia Lutsevych, analyst at Chatham House, special for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Is Ukraine becoming a dictatorship?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Clashes escalate between protesters and police after controversial new laws adopted.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">Lutsevych: Action could seriously undermine chances for free and fair presidential elections.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">Protests against President Viktor Yanukovych&amp;apost;s policy U-turn away from EU integration.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="22">Lutsevych: &amp;quot;What can be seen in Ukraine is an attempt to create dictatorial rule, preserve power of Yanukovych&amp;quot;.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 20:22:14" annotation_time="45.43133">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">London The past few days in Ukraine have been marked by an escalation of street protests and ongoing clashes with riot police in the center of Kiev, as Ukrainians respond to new repressive laws adopted last week.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">In short they could seriously undermine the chances for free and fair presidential elections when they are held.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">The protests erupted two months ago against pro-Russian President Viktor Yanukovych&amp;apost;s foreign policy U-turn away from EU integration.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="4">What can be seen in Ukraine is an attempt to create a criminal dictatorial rule in order to preserve the power of Yanukovych, as the chances of his political survival or a victory in free and fair elections in 2015 are slipping away.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>London The past few days in Ukraine have been marked by an escalation of street protests and ongoing clashes with riot police in the center of Kiev, as Ukrainians respond to new repressive laws adopted last week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The legislation seriously undermines the freedom of assembly, media, privacy and civil society.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>These laws constitute a crackdown on major democratic freedoms and offer a path to dictatorship.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>They criminalize defamation, introduce a label of &amp;quot;foreign agents&amp;quot; for foreign funded NGOs, enact jail terms for wearing masks and hard hats during the protest, and restrict the work of non-registered news agencies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>In short they could seriously undermine the chances for free and fair presidential elections when they are held.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The protests erupted two months ago against pro-Russian President Viktor Yanukovych&amp;apost;s foreign policy U-turn away from EU integration.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Since then, his strategy has been to suppress and intimidate the media and political activists.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>In December, prominent journalist Tatiana Chornovol was attacked and badly beaten.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The Ukrainian president&amp;apost;s office condemned the attack and ordered an investigation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Since then, four protesters have died amid ongoing clashes with police and dozens have been arrested -- and a Ukrainian Catholic Church spokesman told the National Catholic Reporter that the church&amp;apost;s website had been compromised by cyber attacks via neighboring Russia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Instead of dialogue and compromise, President Yanukovych has chosen the hard line towards establishing dictatorial rule.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>His ruling Party of Regions, in cooperation with the Communist Party, passed the repressive laws, and the Ministry of Interior issued a decree allowing riot police to use force and weapons against the protesters.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The Kiev court prohibited any demonstrations until March 8.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Statements about the &amp;quot;foreign instigated&amp;quot; nature of the protests and the language of an &amp;quot;external enemy&amp;quot; have started to appear in the ruling party rhetoric.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Yanukovych has also fired his long-standing head of presidential administration, Serhiy Liovochkin, who is believed to take a moderate position in proposing dialogue with the opposition and protesters.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>As of today his post is vacant.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The expectations are that it could be filled by a hardliner.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Groups of thugs and aggressive young men who support the government have further destabilized the situation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>On Tuesday more than 500 of them were roaming the streets of Kiev.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Any attempts by citizens to call in police forces to address this security issues were ignored.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Such further escalations could be the plan of the elites to introduce marshal law and forbid any demonstrations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>What can be seen in Ukraine is an attempt to create a criminal dictatorial rule in order to preserve the power of Yanukovych, as the chances of his political survival or a victory in free and fair elections in 2015 are slipping away.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>It is a dangerous strategy, which will be futile for three main reasons.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>First, the civic protest is strong and is spreading to the east and south of Ukraine.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Each aggressive move on the side of the regime sparks more and more people on the streets.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Independent opinion polls show that 50% of the population support the protest and 25% cent are ready to participate in it actively.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Second, the charisma of Yanukovych is hardly matching the profile of the dictator.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>His recent addresses to the nation and pre-recorded closed meetings with Ukrainian media show his lack of confidence and evasion of talking about political crisis.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Much less is he ready to face any open rally of his supporters.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>His popularity levels are at a record low.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Even before the start of the protest they were only 14%, compared to 42% in 2010.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Finally, Ukraine&amp;apost;s economic model is not viable to support a dictatorship.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The macroeconomic situation remains very fragile and the investment climate had deteriorated even before the political crisis.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The coffers of the state are drained as illegal raids pushed businesses into a shadow economy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The $15 billion infusion from Russia will only help so much and these disbursements will be tied to conditionality, such as state asset sales.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Earlier this month the World Bank pointed to endemic corruption, weak governance, limited access to finance and a lack of competition as serious obstacles to growth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>All this dooms Yanukovych&amp;apost;s aspirations for a dictatorial rule.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>He should face the reality of irreversible change and prevent a further escalation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>The alternative is an unpredictable collapse of his rule, as the nation will reject a tight grip on freedom and democracy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>READ: Clashes turn deadly for first time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>READ: Ukraine unrest explained.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
