<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="952" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2011/10/20/opinion/gergen-gadhafi-obama/index.html" date_published="2011-10-20 22:10:21" category="opinion" author="David Gergen and Michael Zuckerman" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Will the end of Gadhafi sway U.S. politics?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">President Obama said Gadhafi&amp;apost;s death made it a &amp;quot;momentous day in the history of Libya&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="15">Authors say the demise of Gadhafi won&amp;apost;t greatly boost Obama&amp;apost;s re-election chances.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">They say Americans are focused on domestic, not foreign policy, concerns.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="19">Authors: Obama can argue that he wields force more prudently and surgically than Bush.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-19 10:26:31" annotation_time="927.4253" mapping_time_divergence="125.0">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">President Obama appeared Thursday afternoon in the White House Rose Garden to celebrate this &amp;quot;momentous day in the history of Libya&amp;quot; and to declare that &amp;quot;one of the world&amp;apost;s longest dictators is no more.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">It is a much-discussed irony that a president elected largely around domestic concerns has gone on to amass some sterling foreign policy bona fides, while his approval on matters stateside sinks deeper and deeper.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="2">Critics may likewise downplay how much credit the president deserves for Gadhafi&amp;apost;s demise -- after all, there&amp;apost;s no indication American forces took him out, the way they got al-Awlaki and, unforgettably, bin Laden.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="4">His approach (later redubbed by the publication that first reported it, &amp;quot;leading from behind the scenes&amp;quot;) will also bolster a campaign argument that may resonate not only with his base, but also with swing voters increasingly wary of foreign engagements: that Obama wields force much more prudently and surgically than the reckless GOP -- that he has wound down Iraq and helped win back international respect, all while delivering strong results.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Cambridge, Massachusetts With Libyan dictator Moammar Gadhafi&amp;apost;s dramatic demise this Thursday morning, the world is rid of a tyrant, and a free Libya has jumped a mile forward to stability (though, as CNN&amp;apost;s Ben Wedeman reports, there are still many more miles to go).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Yet in America, we are speeding toward the 2012 presidential elections, and talk quickly turns to the political considerations here.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>President Obama appeared Thursday afternoon in the White House Rose Garden to celebrate this &amp;quot;momentous day in the history of Libya&amp;quot; and to declare that &amp;quot;one of the world&amp;apost;s longest dictators is no more.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>As Obama pledged his support to Libya&amp;apost;s future, many in the crowd and watching at home surely began to wonder about the president&amp;apost;s own future.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>It is a much-discussed irony that a president elected largely around domestic concerns has gone on to amass some sterling foreign policy bona fides, while his approval on matters stateside sinks deeper and deeper.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>But what impact, if any, will his string of overseas successes have on his standing -- and re-election prospects -- here at home?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The first, most obvious answer is: not much.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>While you might expect a president who has bagged Osama bin Laden, Anwar al-Awlaki, and now Moammar Gadhafi in just under six months to be riding high in the public&amp;apost;s estimation, foreign policy concerns simply don&amp;apost;t register much on the public&amp;apost;s radar these days.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>With the economy sputtering -- and veering dangerously toward the edge of another downturn -- voters are homed in there.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>An October Gallup poll found 32% mentioning &amp;quot;unemployment/jobs&amp;quot; as the most important issue facing the nation, with another 31% mentioning &amp;quot;the economy in general.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Where did &amp;quot;wars/fear of war&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;terrorism&amp;quot; stack up?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Two percent each.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Nor does it help that Libya was never a particularly popular war in the first place.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>A March Gallup poll taken just one day after our Air Force began helping enforce the no-fly zone over Libya showed Americans approving of our involvement, 47% to 37% -- a majority, yes, but lower than every other foreign military action since Vietnam (including Grenada and Kosovo).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Critics may likewise downplay how much credit the president deserves for Gadhafi&amp;apost;s demise -- after all, there&amp;apost;s no indication American forces took him out, the way they got al-Awlaki and, unforgettably, bin Laden.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Nevertheless, there may be some political benefits in this string of successes for Obama: Even if they don&amp;apost;t lift his approval up to dazzling heights, they fortify him against criticism on the foreign policy flank and give courage to his remaining supporters.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The victories may also help firm up the president&amp;apost;s standing as a decisive leader, a contrast that may prove helpful if he faces former Massachusetts Gov. Mitt Romney -- whom rivals on both sides of the aisle like to portray as changing with the wind -- in the general election.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Defense Secretary Bob Gates said in September that Obama&amp;apost;s decision to go after bin Laden with Navy SEALs was one of the most courageous ever made by any of the eight presidents he has served -- and Obama&amp;apost;s gamble on Libya (derided by critics quoting the characterization of &amp;quot;leading from behind&amp;quot;) certainly seems to be paying off as well.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>His approach (later redubbed by the publication that first reported it, &amp;quot;leading from behind the scenes&amp;quot;) will also bolster a campaign argument that may resonate not only with his base, but also with swing voters increasingly wary of foreign engagements: that Obama wields force much more prudently and surgically than the reckless GOP -- that he has wound down Iraq and helped win back international respect, all while delivering strong results.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Still, domestic issues reign supreme, and so it&amp;apost;s hard to say that the credit Obama will get for these successes abroad will be enough to turn back the tide of his sinking poll numbers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>An August NBC/Wall Street Journal poll found Obama&amp;apost;s approval on foreign policy a positive 50% to 45%, but the same poll gave him horrendous 37% to 59% marks on the economy and a 44% to 51% disapproval overall.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Since then, he&amp;apost;s only slipped, with the latest Gallup tracking poll putting his total approval at 39% to 54%.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Obama may yet get a bump from the Gadhafi news, but it&amp;apost;s hard to imagine it overshadowing the bin Laden spike, which itself proved extraordinarily fleeting.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In the meantime, if he wants to bring the numbers back up for the long haul, the president will have to find a way to transfer some of that daring success of his War Room into his domestic Cabinet.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>In their second terms, presidents often find themselves drifting into more and more foreign policy initiatives, both as a way to bolster their legacies and because they find that, with their domestic political capital usually spent, it&amp;apost;s the only arena left where they can make a big impact.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Obama has gone through that cycle a bit quicker than most, and it leaves one questioning what his second term would look like.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Whether or not that comes to pass, he will at the very least be able to console himself that even if the voters aren&amp;apost;t rushing to record these international victories, the history books one day will.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
