<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="918" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/03/05/opinion/shumlin-governors-minimum-wage/index.html" date_published="2014-03-05 11:59:46" category="opinion" author="Gov. Peter Shumlin and Gov. Dan Malloy " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Opinion: Three reasons why a $10.10 minimum wage is good for America</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="14">Democratic Govs. Shumlin and Malloy support raising the federal minimum wage to $10.10.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12">They argue it hasn&amp;apost;t increased in real dollars since 1968.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="24, 23">Republican governors, they say, have stood in the way of or tried to roll back the minimum wage.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 16:58:51" annotation_time="86.355995" mapping_time_divergence="57.570663">
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">Adjusted for inflation, that&amp;apost;s lower than it was in 1968.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="1">In fact, recent studies conclude that raising the minimum wage makes workers more productive and therefore helps businesses retain profitability -- a conclusion affirmed by Gap Inc.&amp;apost;s recent decision to raise the minimum wage for its employees to $10.10 an hour.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="3">Republican governors across the country have also stood in the way of progress.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="3">Some have pandered to stereotype, suggesting that a raise in the minimum wage should be rejected because it would only help young workers rather than acknowledging that 88% of workers who would be affected by moving the minimum wage to $10.10 an hour are over the age of 20, and more are over the age of 55 than are teenagers.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Democratic governors are working every day to grow and strengthen a middle class that&amp;apost;s been under assault from global economic forces and failed, trickle-down policies for decades.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>In furtherance of that mission, we will be proud to stand with President Barack Obama, Massachusetts Gov. Deval Patrick and Rhode Island Gov. Lincoln Chafee at Central Connecticut State University this afternoon to announce actions we&amp;apost;re taking to raise the minimum wage in our states to $10.10 an hour by 2017.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>House Republicans continue to block progress on this critical issue for middle class families.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>But that doesn&amp;apost;t mean this common-sense idea, like so many others before it, needs to die a Washington-inflicted death.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>With a paralyzed Congress, Democratic governors will act.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>We&amp;apost;ll do so with the benefit of having the American people on our side.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Democrats, Republicans and independents alike overwhelmingly support raising the minimum wage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>A recent Wall Street Journal/NBC poll shows 63% of Americans support it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Here&amp;apost;s why:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>One, it makes good economic sense.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The federal minimum wage is currently $7.25 an hour.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Adjusted for inflation, that&amp;apost;s lower than it was in 1968.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Raising the minimum wage to $10.10 an hour nationally will provide 28 million Americans with more money to spend and to invest, increasing economic activity and growth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>In fact, recent studies conclude that raising the minimum wage makes workers more productive and therefore helps businesses retain profitability -- a conclusion affirmed by Gap Inc.&amp;apost;s recent decision to raise the minimum wage for its employees to $10.10 an hour.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Two, it&amp;apost;s good for women.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Women account for roughly two-thirds of workers whose incomes would rise by increasing the minimum wage to $10.10 an hour.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>These women currently work 40 hours a week to make just $14,500 a year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>These women are our daughters, sisters and mothers who are often the only breadwinners in their families.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Our country is in a stronger position when women are in a stronger economic position.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>We need to make that a reality.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Three, it&amp;apost;s the right thing to do.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>No American working 40 hours or more a week deserves to live in poverty.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Republican governors across the country have also stood in the way of progress.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Some have pandered to stereotype, suggesting that a raise in the minimum wage should be rejected because it would only help young workers rather than acknowledging that 88% of workers who would be affected by moving the minimum wage to $10.10 an hour are over the age of 20, and more are over the age of 55 than are teenagers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>New Jersey Gov. Chris Christie and New Mexico Gov. Susana Martinez went so far as to veto minimum wage hikes in their states.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Wisconsin Gov. Scott Walker mocked the idea, while Florida Gov. Rick Scott described how the proposal makes him &amp;quot;cringe.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Michigan Gov. Rick Snyder, Pennsylvania Gov. Tom Corbett and Maine Gov. Paul LePage all oppose this common-sense change.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>And of course there is billionaire Bruce Rauner, running in Illinois, who went so far as to suggest slashing minimum wage workers&amp;apost; salaries by a dollar an hour in order to keep the state &amp;quot;competitive.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>They just don&amp;apost;t get it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Just look at Bobby Jindal, former Republican Governors Association chair and current governor of Louisiana, who recently said -- in a widely-criticized partisan outburst outside the White House -- that raising the minimum wage was equivalent to &amp;quot;waving the white flag of surrender&amp;quot; on the economy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s patently absurd.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>But it&amp;apost;s what the tea party wants to hear.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>A fair minimum wage was once an issue upon which Republican and Democratic leaders could agree.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>But now, the Republican Congress and Republican governors have embraced partisanship and right-wing ideology rather than economic growth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>And that&amp;apost;s why we are standing with President Obama today to make clear we won&amp;apost;t wait for Republicans to come around -- we&amp;apost;re going to give hard-working Americans a raise and we are going to start today.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
