<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="940" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/07/03/opinion/maguire-anderson-cooper/index.html?hpt=op_t1" date_published="2012-07-03 12:23:04" category="opinion" author="Gregory Maguire, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="false" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Thank you, Anderson</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6, 3">Gregory Maguire: Most people knew Anderson Cooper was gay; he came out Monday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8">He likes that Cooper insists that he still deserves privacy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="8">He says like Cooper, he knows that being gay is one part of the many qualities that define him.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="31">Maguire: Emerson said &amp;quot;character is centrality;&amp;quot; maybe Cooper believes this, too.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_time="20.465666">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">I am a great fan of Anderson Cooper, especially of his hair, but I still want to be honest about what I think of the message he recently sent to Andrew Sullivan, on whose blog he came out on Monday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">I mean, there may yet be a population of creatures on the planet surprised that Anderson Cooper is gay, but I suspect they eat plankton.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2, 3">What I like better than Cooper&amp;apost;s admission, or the good reasons he summarizes for making such an admission, is his insistence that even under these circumstances he has a right to a private life, and he intends to invoke those rights.</sentence>
      <sentence id="31" ids_highlights="4">He wrote &amp;quot;Character is centrality, the impossibility of being displaced or overset.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>I feel like a short-order cook flipping a pancake, looking at it in the air from side to side, to see how well done it is, to see if it is ready.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>There are plusses and minuses to every statement made by a celebrity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>I am a great fan of Anderson Cooper, especially of his hair, but I still want to be honest about what I think of the message he recently sent to Andrew Sullivan, on whose blog he came out on Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a pancake with two sides, and it&amp;apost;s still up in the air.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>On one side, Anderson Cooper joins a long troupe of people like Ellen DeGeneres, Elton John, Liberace and on back down the line, for which the Great Announcement has got to be seen as made, perhaps, for the sea whelks and the Easter Island statues who don&amp;apost;t get CNN at home and don&amp;apost;t notice sexuality and its cues.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>I mean, there may yet be a population of creatures on the planet surprised that Anderson Cooper is gay, but I suspect they eat plankton.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>On the other side, honesty still takes courage, and one of the things that a bright cunning professional with good hair does when he or she comes out is to encourage other gay or lesbian people with good hair to let it down, too.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>What I like better than Cooper&amp;apost;s admission, or the good reasons he summarizes for making such an admission, is his insistence that even under these circumstances he has a right to a private life, and he intends to invoke those rights.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>I have generally resisted being identified as a gay spokesperson, even though I am gay and I do speak.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>And have political opinions, and I use them in my writing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>(I haven&amp;apost;t got the hair to be a gay spokesperson, though.).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Less facetiously, the truth is that I could not stomach being a professional gay spokesperson because I have never been a professional homosexual.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>I am only a professional writer, and as such -- just as Cooper attests, too, about himself -- my sexuality is a real but a limited part of my character.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>It is something that has helped define me as an artist in that it taught me how to stand on the margins and scrutinize the center.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Incidentally, so, too, has being a Roman Catholic in this dark season of Catholic instability, hysteria and political game-playing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>So, too, has being married to a man with whom I have adopted three brown-skinned kids.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>So, too, is believing that the physicality of books matters.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Also, believing in not being a one-issue voter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>All these aspects of my self marginalize me, but they don&amp;apost;t make me a Catholic writer, a gay writer, a blended-family writer, a nut-job.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>They make me a better writer, because they round me out.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>They fill me with contradictory and complicating sympathies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>They make me work harder at being myself.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>So, the pancake is still in the air.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Will Anderson Cooper be a better professional journalist for having been honest in this aspect of his life?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>I don&amp;apost;t know that anyone can be sure of this, him least of all.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>But that is why, in the end, the pancake flips onto a plate ready for serving in a pool of warm maple syrup, and it looks just right.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>He is willing to take the chance that he might be marginalized for this.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>He thinks it is important enough to risk being belittled, even by an admirer, like me.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Maybe Anderson Cooper holds close to his heart a maxim that I do.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s by Emerson, one of my own local heroes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>He wrote &amp;quot;Character is centrality, the impossibility of being displaced or overset.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>When I was about 17, I stitched those words into some invisible vest pocket of my psychic armor and said to myself: &amp;quot;You don&amp;apost;t have to tell all the truth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>You just have to be sure not to lie.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Do not do anything that will cause you to be displaced or overset.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Be central upon the limited, unorthodox, marginalized square upon which, through no doing of your own, you find that you stand.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Here&amp;apost;s your pancake.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>And look.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>It has a face in it!</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>A holy miracle.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>It isn&amp;apost;t the face of Anderson Cooper and it isn&amp;apost;t even the face of Jesus (who also has great hair).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s Ralph Waldo Emerson.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Eat your pancake.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s good for you.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Thank you, Anderson.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Follow @CNNOpinion on Twitter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Join us at Facebook/CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
