<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="914" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/05/13/opinion/simmons-girls-proms/index.html" date_published="2013-05-13 11:40:29" category="opinion" author="Rachel Simmons, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Opinion: The damaging messages of proms</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Rachel Simmons: The most coveted rite of passage for many teenage girls is the prom.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">Simmons: Prom is an event where girls internalize damaging cultural messages.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="24">She says prom teaches girls to value money and conventional beauty and wait to be asked out.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="22">Simmons: The good news is that girls are pushing back against the pressure to just wait .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 20:31:59" annotation_time="31.352">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Spring may be graduation season, but the most coveted rite of passage for many teenage girls is the prom.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">Sure, but it&amp;apost;s also an event where girls internalize damaging cultural messages.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="4">Prom drops girls squarely into the beauty spending pipeline.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="3">She learns that the most valued girls must wait to be asked.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Spring may be graduation season, but the most coveted rite of passage for many teenage girls is the prom.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>From the latest craze of &amp;quot;promposals&amp;quot; to the minute-by-minute social media broadcast of it all, the rituals of prom form a throwback cultural primer called &amp;quot;How to be a young woman.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Teen girls are competing relentlessly to be queen.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The queens of prom are the conventionally beautiful, the wealthy and the heterosexual -- always passively waiting to be asked.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Isn&amp;apost;t prom just a fun dance that hardworking students deserve?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Sure, but it&amp;apost;s also an event where girls internalize damaging cultural messages.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Those who are exalted on this &amp;quot;once in a lifetime&amp;quot; night offer an object lesson in how modern girls are expected to look and act.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Prom is a cultural report card of sorts on how well, or not, young women are doing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Here&amp;apost;s what a bright 17-year-old girl learns as her lace gown drags behind her into the school gymnasium:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>She learns that she must have money to attend the prom.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Prom was modeled after the debutante ball of the old days, where elite girls formally announced they were ready to date, while a hand-picked bevy of suitors watched.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Today, prom is still a rich girl&amp;apost;s party.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>In 2013, prom spending will rise on the shoulders of a more robust economy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Families who plan to spend money on the big night are expected to drop an average of $1,139.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>All that cash might be good for business, but it disadvantages the poor and working class girls who can&amp;apost;t keep up.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Meanwhile, boys can get away with renting a tux for less than $100.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>She learns that conventional beauty is valued above all else.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Girls will spend lavishly on expensive dresses and shoes, along with professional tanning, hair and makeup.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The final look is a far cry from Molly Ringwald&amp;apost;s original, homespun vibe in the &amp;apost;80s teen classic &amp;quot;Pretty in Pink.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Instead, girls are angling for the Hollywood red carpet look.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Oscar gown knockoffs, such as a copy of Jennifer Lawrence&amp;apost;s pink Dior dress, are among the most sought after this season.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Prom drops girls squarely into the beauty spending pipeline.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>It prepares them to shell out a disproportionate amount of money on their appearance as adult women, when they will spend $7 billion annually on makeup alone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>She learns that the most valued girls must wait to be asked.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Asking season can begin during the winter, consigning girls looking for a date to months of anxious waiting.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Nor is it enough just to be invited; now, the truly successful prom girls get elaborate public promposals, with suitors spelling out &amp;quot;Prom?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>in cupcakes or smoke, as was the case with the boy who hired a skywriter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>By contrast, the brave girls who do the inviting often endure a scrim of embarrassment for breaking the unwritten rules.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The message?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Assertiveness makes you less attractive, a lesson girls are likely to draw on as women, when they avoid asking for raises and are seen as less likeable when they do.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>She learns to broadcast every minute of it to get &amp;apost;likes&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Prom culture is now painstakingly documented on sites such as Instagram and Facebook, exacerbating the angst of the uninvited.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The near constant posting of photos -- of having one&amp;apost;s hair done, doing makeup, riding in the limo -- becomes a strategic social press conference, announcing to anyone with a social media account that you are playing the game.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The online photo albums are anxiously monitored as barometers of popularity, telling girls who is &amp;quot;in&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;out,&amp;quot; as many girls learn to equate their worth with the number of &amp;quot;likes&amp;quot; each photo receives.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The underside of this constant self-promotion is comparing oneself endlessly to others.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>The prom beauty contest in girlhood is a final dress rehearsal for modern womanhood when, in one study, 80% of women said they competed with peers over appearance.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>She learns that straight is better.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Who you bring to the prom is under as much scrutiny as the hem of your dress.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>In all but the most progressive communities, prom glorifies heterosexuality, leaving gay youths facing disapproval at best, outright rejection at worst.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>In its 2011 School Climate report, the Gay Lesbian and Straight Education Network found that same-sex couples were frequently not allowed to attend school dances together or were penalized for doing so, such as being ineligible for &amp;quot;couple discounts&amp;quot; on tickets.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>The good news is that the rules of prom are starting to change.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Girls are pushing back against the pressure to wait for an invitation and are asking boys first.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Lindsay, 17, a senior from San Antonio, engineered her own promposal with a poem, a special T-shirt and poster.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Meanwhile, same-sex couples are growing more visible.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Dates are being replaced by whole groups of friends attending together.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>This spring, girls in Georgia used social media to end their town&amp;apost;s racially segregated proms with national support.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>When I went to prom in the early 1990s, I seesawed between my wish to get asked by the right guy and ride in the cool kids&amp;apost; limousine with the burgeoning realization that I was gay.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>I had a fun night, but I was far from my authentic, assertive self that night.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Prom felt mostly like a job I had to do to maintain my position in the social hierarchy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Three decades after Title IX, our culture has yet to decide how powerful it wants its girls to be.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>As we figure out the answer, prom becomes an even more important cultural touchstone for who we want our girls to become.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Follow us on Twitter @CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>Join us on Facebook/CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
