<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="825" link="http://cnn.com/2013/03/04/opinion/brazil-world-cup-and-olympics-opinion/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2013-03-04 19:35:06" category="opinion" author="Parag Khanna, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Is Brazil ready to take sporting center stage?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">Brazil continues preparations to host next year&amp;apost;s World Cup and 2016 Summer Olympics.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">It&amp;apost;s crunch time for the South American giant, says Parag Khanna.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="21">An economic boost is essential, says Khanna.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="7">Politicians are yet to live up to their continental scale ambitions, he says .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-11 10:20:06" annotation_time="99.937325" mapping_time_divergence="24.984331">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1, 2">It&amp;apost;s crunch time for the South American giant as it prepares to host next year&amp;apost;s football World Cup and 2016 Summer Olympics.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="4">Hosting these mega-events was seen as an essential spark to get Brazil to overhaul its dilapidated infrastructure, but despite the advance notice, politicians aren&amp;apost;t yet living up to their continental scale ambitions.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="3">Airports, roads and railways have been slated for privatization, hundreds of new airports are planned to link the vast interior, the country&amp;apost;s development bank has pledged an immediate $10 billion in related spending, private banks are planning greater lending in the infrastructure space, a Sao Paulo to Rio bullet train has been announced for completion by 2020, and $26 billion has been allocated to modernize the country&amp;apost;s 34 ports which are responsible for more than 90% of the country&amp;apost;s annual $482 billion in trade.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The upcoming World Cup and Olympics guarantee that Brazil&amp;apost;s international visibility will continue its rapid ascent.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The country just has to ensure there are seats for all of the guests.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Brazil may be emerging from its reputation as the permanent &amp;quot;land of tomorrow,&amp;quot; but Parag Khanna suspects it will likely get there only at the last minute.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>As Brazil&amp;apost;s annual Carnival hangover fades, a more serious road lies ahead.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s crunch time for the South American giant as it prepares to host next year&amp;apost;s football World Cup and 2016 Summer Olympics.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The country definitely needs an economic boost given the recent downgraded forecast of barely over 1% growth for 2013.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Hosting these mega-events was seen as an essential spark to get Brazil to overhaul its dilapidated infrastructure, but despite the advance notice, politicians aren&amp;apost;t yet living up to their continental scale ambitions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Brazilians excel at throwing massive parties, but so much is at stake beyond the Games.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Can Brazil really become the &amp;quot;America of South America,&amp;quot; unchallenged and indispensable to all its neighbors?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Brazil wants to be the first superpower from the global south, yet with the equator just crossing a sliver of the country&amp;apost;s north, it has quite a long climb still to join the league of the wealthy, not just the large.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Brasilia&amp;apost;s technocrats have been aggressive, even creative, in recent years, using pro-poor policies and monetary intervention to deliver growth and stability.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Yet lower interest rate policy has failed to drive stronger investment, and business confidence is down due to government intrusions large and small in banks, car companies, and other sectors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Even the major offshore oil discoveries haven&amp;apost;t yet borne fruit for energy major Petrobras due to local content requirements that favor less sophisticated domestic suppliers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>While its currency control policy has effectively been blessed by the IMF, the still massively overvalued Real currency has undercut exports in what has been an increasingly diversified economy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Latin America in general, and Brazil in particular, has been the most urbanized region long before cities became the dominant meme of global socio-economic studies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Sao Paulo very much feels like the second-largest city in the world, but unlike even larger Tokyo, its airport feels third world and public transportation can scarcely cope with demand.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>It ranks alongside New Delhi, Moscow, Beijing and Mexico City in IBM&amp;apost;s aptly named Commuter Pain Index.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>And with close to 1,000 new cars joining the traffic jams each day, it&amp;apost;s no surprise that the rich take to the air: Paulistas have the highest rate of private helicopter usage in the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Overall, the World Economic Forum&amp;apost;s most recent Global Competitiveness Report ranks Brazil a measly 107 (out of 144) for quality of infrastructure.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Since taking office just over two years ago, President Dilma Rousseff has regularly announced massive infrastructure investment schemes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Airports, roads and railways have been slated for privatization, hundreds of new airports are planned to link the vast interior, the country&amp;apost;s development bank has pledged an immediate $10 billion in related spending, private banks are planning greater lending in the infrastructure space, a Sao Paulo to Rio bullet train has been announced for completion by 2020, and $26 billion has been allocated to modernize the country&amp;apost;s 34 ports which are responsible for more than 90% of the country&amp;apost;s annual $482 billion in trade.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Taken together, the government promises $100 billion in infrastructure spending over the next decade, while raising $65 billion in privatization and auctions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Discuss these numbers with any Brazilian, however, and they are apt to stare blankly and demand, &amp;quot;But where is all the money going?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>As popular a figure as former president Lula was -- and deservedly so for his innovative and transformative policies such as the targeted cash transfer program &amp;quot;Bolsa Familia&amp;quot; -- corruption allegations still dog his still-dominant Workers Party (PT).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>O Estado de Sao Paulo, the leading daily newspaper, recently added a &amp;quot;corruption library&amp;quot; to its website to track the steady tide of suspicious contracts and spending.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>With the opposition parties fragmented and scattered, however, the PT may well be in power long enough to be held accountable to its plans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>As Brazil focuses on its overhauling its cities, it must remember that urbanization itself won&amp;apost;t drive meaningful growth, but rather empowering the tens of millions in the urban underclass.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Cities like Sao Paulo are designed for an industrial age while the urban economy has become 85% related to services.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The key question then is how to humanize such mega-cities, the theme of the upcoming New Cities Foundation summit that Sao Paulo is hosting in June.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>(Full disclosure: I serve on the NCF board of trustees.).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The reinvention of Sao Paulo will begin right at its center with projects such as the URBEM Foundation&amp;apost;s Casa Paulista.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Multiple mixed used social and commercial developments designed to be affordable and professional could help to reintegrate a population that has grown accustomed to gated communities.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>In such neighborhoods, Brazilians should find apprenticeships, vocational training, and more public libraries that promote literacy, social inclusion, and citizenship, all topics debated by world-famous architects and experts and locals together in a new series called Arq.Futuro being held around the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>There is an opportunity to conduct this urban regeneration in a way that embodies Brazil&amp;apost;s amazing cultural depth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Like China, the more modern it gets, the more Brazilian it gets; its identity is enhanced rather than diluted.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>There is no higher symbol of this than fabled architect Oscar Niemeyer&amp;apost;s buildings, which manage to be both angular yet still in harmony with nature.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>But there are also efforts to restore the lifestyle of Carnival in Rio, a tradition of street culture and music, rather than just an annual bonanza, and connecting Rio&amp;apost;s favelas closer to its beaches through cable cars.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>In Sao Paulo, soccer pitches are being hastily laid in the outskirts to remind the nation that its best players have come from conditions of socio-economic adversity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>The message is clear: Brazilians should resist overly consumerist temptations; when they become too showy, they (especially their soccer stars) get distracted and under-perform.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>In the coming years, Brazil&amp;apost;s image will also be shaped by a new set of stars and issues.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Banks like Itau Unibanco have a healthy balance sheet and appetite to expand across Latin America and beyond.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Secondary regions like Bahia are now rivaling Rio for visitors reveling in Carnival culture, while Pernambuco&amp;apost;s capital Recife is attracting innovative industries to relocate.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Given that Brazil holds approximately one-third of the world&amp;apost;s biodiversity and 20% of its fresh water in the Amazon rainforest, it is also becoming a leader in fields ranging from combating deforestation (which has dropped by 80% since 2004) to plant genetics.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>And Brazil has become a leading and positive investor in Africa, as the country&amp;apost;s eloquent foreign minister Antonio Patriota reminded participants at the recent Munich Security Conference.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>The upcoming World Cup and Olympics guarantee that Brazil&amp;apost;s international visibility will continue its rapid ascent.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>The country just has to ensure there are enough seats for all of the guests.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Brazil may finally be emerging from its reputation as the permanent &amp;quot;land of tomorrow,&amp;quot; but it will likely get there at the last minute.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
