<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="872" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/04/03/opinion/syria-refugees-tisdall/?hpt=bosread" date_published="2014-04-03 12:00:54" category="opinion" author="Simon Tisdall, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Opinion: Forget Ukraine, Syria is now the world&amp;apost;s biggest threat</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Russia&amp;apost;s annexation of Crimea, and feared threat to invade Ukraine, has grabbed attention .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8">Simon Tisdall says Syria, not Crimea, directly affects western security in more basic ways.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="21">Much of northern Syria under control of jihadi groups, united in opposition to West - Tisdall.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="22">Syria is in the process of becoming a bridgehead to Europe for al Qaida, he adds.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-26 06:25:46" annotation_time="25.51">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Russia&amp;apost;s annexation of Crimea, and what many fear is its apparent threat to invade Ukraine, has riveted international attention since the crisis erupted with February&amp;apost;s revolution in Kiev.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">Syria, not Crimea, directly affects western security in very basic ways.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="3">Large areas of northern Syria are now under the control of jihadi groups and militias who, whatever else they may disagree about, are united in their opposition to western values and interests.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="4">Syria is in the process of becoming a bridgehead to Europe for al Qaida and like-minded fanatics.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Russia&amp;apost;s annexation of Crimea, and what many fear is its apparent threat to invade Ukraine, has riveted international attention since the crisis erupted with February&amp;apost;s revolution in Kiev.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Excitable talk has proliferated as fast as North Korean missiles.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Pundits obsess about a new Cold War, a showdown with &amp;quot;mad bad Vlad&amp;quot; Putin, and the resulting need to boost military spending (always a Pentagon favorite).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The talk is all Ukraine, Ukraine.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Politicians and diplomats have put everything else on hold.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Including Syria, which is a big mistake.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Far more than an argument over an obscure shard of territory on the edge of Nowhere-on-Don, the catastrophe now taking place in and around Syria ranks as a fundamental challenge and threat to the current world order.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Syria, not Crimea, directly affects western security in very basic ways.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>What&amp;apost;s happening there is changing the power balance in the Middle East.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>And unlike in Ukraine or the Baltic republics or other post-Soviet lands, a vast human catastrophe is unravelling, apparently without end.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>In Syria&amp;apost;s real, not phoney, war, more than 100,000 people have died so far.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The total number of Syrian refugees in Lebanon, for example, has now passed the 1 million mark, according to the U.N.&amp;apost;s refugee agency -- and that does not include the tens of thousands who have not registered with the agency.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>About 12,000 are fleeing Syria for Lebanon each week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The refugee outflow is also affecting Jordan, Turkey, Egypt and Iraq.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>As the war enters its fourth year, the overall refugee total is around 2.5 million.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>A further 6.5 million Syrians are internally displaced, and 9.3 million are in need of humanitarian assistance, according to the U.N.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The suffering concealed behind these bald figures is appalling, as any visitor to the refugee camps will testify.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Children are particularly badly affected.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Yet even if they are not swayed by the human cost of a conflict that has become depressingly familiar, basic considerations of self-interested realpolitik suggest governments, politicians and diplomats should be paying more attention to Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>One obvious reason is the way the war has been exploited to facilitate the spread of Islamist fundamentalism.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Large areas of northern Syria are now under the control of jihadi groups and militias who, whatever else they may disagree about, are united in their opposition to western values and interests.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Syria is in the process of becoming a bridgehead to Europe for al Qaida and like-minded fanatics.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>It is already a magnet for young European Muslim men who want a piece of the global jihad.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>They then bring their new &amp;quot;skills&amp;quot; home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>A second reason to take a second look at Syria is the way instability there is steadily spreading outwards to affect neighboring countries.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Turkey&amp;apost;s neo-Islamist government, having initially tried to broker a peace deal, now regards itself as virtually at war with Bashar al-Assad&amp;apost;s regime.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Last week the Turks very deliberately shot down a Syrian warplane they said had violated their airspace.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The threat of a Syria-Turkey conflict aside, the impact on Turkey&amp;apost;s politics and people has been considerable.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The increasingly authoritarian behaviour of Recep Tayyip Erdogan, Turkey&amp;apost;s prime minister, to some degree reflects the pressure the country is under.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Kurdish militants trying to make common cause with their divided Syrian counterparts is one concern.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Another is that border areas inundated with refugees are becoming less governable.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Growing instability and consequent political uncertainty are also affecting pro-western Lebanon and Jordan, while apparently reviving Shia-Sunni conflict in Iraq is being fed by the Syrian flames.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Recent reports suggest many Iraqi Shia fighters are now inside Syria, determined (like the Hezbollah fighters from Lebanon) to bolster the Assad regime against its mostly Sunni foes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>In geopolitical terms, the Syrian collapse has provided Iran with an opportunity to extend its influence into the heart of the Arab world, opening up a new front in its proxy war with the Sunni monarchies of the Gulf led by Saudi Arabia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>No doubt to Iran&amp;apost;s delight, Riyadh&amp;apost;s displeasure at the Obama administration&amp;apost;s refusal to get directly involved in Syria has caused a rift between the two long-time allies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Given the current state of western relations with Tehran, handing Iran a free boost in this way is a serious diplomatic own goal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>The ongoing failure to address and resolve the Syrian conflict has numerous other far-reaching consequences.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>What goes for Iran goes for Russia, too.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Its obstinate and unprincipled support for Assad has come cost-free as the U.S. and Europe dither and the Geneva &amp;quot;peace process&amp;quot; leads precisely nowhere.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Perceived American weakness over Syria may even have encouraged Vladimir Putin in his Crimean misdemeanors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Al-Assad&amp;apost;s continued survival as Syria&amp;apost;s head of state is an egregious affront to the U.N. Security Council and its various related Syria resolutions, to the U.N. charter, to international law, and specifically to international war crimes legislation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Al-Assad stands accused of war crimes and crimes against humanity, not least over the use by his forces of chemical weapons against civilian populations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>But once again, nothing much is done, and the credibility of such institutions and laws suffers as a result.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>The moral example set by such dereliction is shocking.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>A lot has been made of the bad precedent Russia set by annexing the territory of an independent sovereign state.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>And it is fair to say such behavior is unacceptable and illegal, and should not be emulated by others.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>But in the overall scheme of things, the Crimea problem fades into insignificance when set alongside the dreaded ramifications and implications, short and long term, of the international community&amp;apost;s plain inability or its lamentable lack of will to halt the Syrian war.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
