<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="777" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/07/23/opinion/zelizer-capitalism/index.html" date_published="2012-07-23 14:48:29" category="opinion" author="Julian Zelizer, CNN Contributor" highlights_mapped="false" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Campaign 2012: The phony war of markets vs. government</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Pundits are painting President Obama as the anti-capitalist candidate, says Julian Zelizer.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">But this election is not a choice between government and markets, Zelizer says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="13">Liberals have been firm supporters of capitalism, he says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="23">Zelizer: Conservatives have accepted that government is an inevitable part of American life.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_time="17.148666">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Brooks wrote that President Obama, who he said is feeling defensive about the failure of his policies to revitalize economic growth, has launched an all-out assault on capitalism by depicting Mitt Romney as the embodiment of corrupt and vicious economic practices.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">This election is not a choice between government and markets.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="3">Indeed, since Franklin Roosevelt, American liberals have been firm supporters of American capitalism.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="4">Despite their rhetoric, conservatives have accepted that government is an inevitable part of American life.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>In a recent column for The New York Times, David Brooks argued that the nation has now entered into a &amp;quot;capitalism debate.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Brooks wrote that President Obama, who he said is feeling defensive about the failure of his policies to revitalize economic growth, has launched an all-out assault on capitalism by depicting Mitt Romney as the embodiment of corrupt and vicious economic practices.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The president&amp;apost;s decision to focus on Romney&amp;apost;s work at Bain Capital, Brooks argues, has shifted the &amp;quot;focus of the race from being about big government, which Obama represents, to being about capitalism, which Romney represents.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Romney responded in kind, &amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m convinced he wants Americans to be ashamed of success.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>If this shift continues, the campaigns will spend the next four months presenting voters with a false impression about the the real contest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>While both parties have a strong incentive to ramp up the rhetoric to mobilize voters to turn out, this kind of campaign features a debate that has little to do with the governing that will actually take place after the election.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>This election is not a choice between government and markets.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The reality is that we will continue to have a system that mixes government and markets, with the political battles centering on the particular priorities that the nation emphasizes within that mix.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Obama, as Brooks points out, has not really been a critic of free-market capitalism.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>His policies have done little to challenge the forces of globalization, and he has worked closely with economic leaders in his efforts to fix the economy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>His financial regulation did little to curb the freedom of Wall Street investors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Obama is not some kind of exception among American liberals.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Indeed, since Franklin Roosevelt, American liberals have been firm supporters of American capitalism.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Their goals have been to tame the excesses of this economic system and to make capitalism fairer for all Americans.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Many of FDR&amp;apost;s economic policies, such as the National Recovery Act, depended on voluntary cooperation from big business.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>FDR backed away from any proposals that entailed the federal government obtaining strong control over managerial decisions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The point of legitimating unions, which happened through the Wagner Act (1935), was to provide workers with some kind of countervailing power to business owners within the capitalism system.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Other Democrats, such as Harry Truman, followed in this market-friendly liberal tradition.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Lyndon Johnson offered economic assistance to the poor and educational assistance to all students, so that more people could participate and enjoy the fruits that the capitalist system produced.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>With his support of deregulation and deficit reduction, Jimmy Carter moved market-based Democrats even further to the center.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Bill Clinton embraced globalization and believed that nurturing free markets could offer the best opportunities to those struggling at home and abroad.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>While liberalism has always been a political system that sought to use government to strengthen the market-based economy, conservatives have usually been comfortable with government.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Despite their rhetoric, conservatives have accepted that government is an inevitable part of American life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Romney has been no exception.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>As governor, he was not some kind of radical slasher of government services.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The centerpiece of his term was a bold health care initiative that expanded that role of government in ensuring access to health care.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Romney cut services, but he also increased all kinds of government fees.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>During his current campaign, Romney is not talking about eliminating the big-ticket programs like Social Security, and he has firmly defended robust levels of national security spending.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Like Obama, Romney reflects his own political tradition.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Libertarianism has long been dead among conservatives.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>During the Cold War, conservatives like Sen. Barry Goldwater and author James Burnham pushed for the government to spend more on the fight against communism.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>During the 1970s, historian Gareth Davies recounted, many conservatives came to accept federal programs such as education as an inevitable part of domestic life.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>President Ronald Reagan, the iconic conservative, quickly backed off proposals like an initiative to reduce certain Social Security benefits when they stimulated a strong political backlash, and he left many other kinds of domestic spending, like Medicare or agricultural subsidies, intact.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>George H.W. Bush brought the federal government into new areas of domestic life, providing, for example, protections for people with disabilities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Congressional conservatives like Newt Gingrich proved that they were not much different, as they too were aware that Americans in red states often depended on the government they lambasted.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>George W. Bush and the Republican Congress grew government in the early part of this century.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Bush pushed several significant domestic initiatives such as No Child Left Behind and a costly prescription drug benefit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Like all Republicans, he did little to take out the massive welfare state of tax exemptions and deductions upon which many industries depend.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>In 2008, he saved financial markets through government with TARP, not through deregulation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>His homeland security program involved an aggressive expansion of government power, and he launched two wars abroad.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Like it or not, liberals have always accepted capitalism, and conservatives have proved more than willing to live with, and even to use, the federal government for certain purposes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>The debate today is not between big government and free market capitalism but rather about how we should structure our mixture of these two systems.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>The more we have these kinds of overblown debates, the less voters get a sense of what politicians are actually about and what they&amp;apost;ll do once in power.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>A more realistic debate would be about which portion of the public will have tax cuts extended.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Rather than an all or nothing debate, we should hear which specific parts of the budget will be trimmed and where will each candidate try to find more efficiency in government.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>In terms of the economy, where and how will they use government to stimulate economic investment and to curb the deficit, how else will candidates try to raise revenue.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>This current rhetoric is not only unrealistic, it fuels public frustration with government by generating false expectations and providing campaign discussions that have little to do with real life in Washington.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Follow @CNNOpinion on Twitter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Join us at Facebook/CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
