<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="893" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/06/02/opinion/brazile-climate-change-rules/index.html" date_published="2014-06-02 17:32:07" category="opinion" author="Donna Brazile" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Opinion: New climate rules are a breath of fresh air</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="11">Donna Brazile argues that new EPA rules protect families and communities of color.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">The regulations place tough limits on emissions from coal-fired power plants.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="46">Air pollution, she says, is one of the prime causes of climate change and extreme weather .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 20:24:47" annotation_time="35.608334">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">The administration&amp;apost;s new pollution standards -- new Environmental Protection Agency regulations that place tough limits on emissions from coal-fired power plants -- are an answered prayer for working families.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="1">They showed the world who suffers the most from the impacts of extreme weather: low-income families and communities of color.</sentence>
      <sentence id="46" ids_highlights="3">We can be thankful President Barack Obama is taking aim at one of the prime causes of climate change and extreme weather: air pollution.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The debate on climate change is over.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Scientists are now as certain that climate change is a real, man-made threat as they are that cigarettes kill.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>But cleaning up our air has much more to it than combating shifts in Earth&amp;apost;s temperatures and environment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The administration&amp;apost;s new pollution standards -- new Environmental Protection Agency regulations that place tough limits on emissions from coal-fired power plants -- are an answered prayer for working families.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>I&amp;apost;m talking about those many families who endured damaged homes or lost work hours from our more frequent, and more severe, extreme weather.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Dialing down air pollution is a gust of relief for a retiree without the luxury of air conditioning, who battles climbing temperatures and brutal heat waves.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a breath of fresh air for every child playing in the shadow of a power plant, at risk from an asthma attack just by being outdoors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Placing limits on carbon pollution from power plants is about ensuring that we have clean air to breathe and communities that are safe to live in.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Carbon pollution limits are about defending families who have borne the heaviest burden of the main pollutant that is driving climate change.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Events like Hurricane Katrina and Superstorm Sandy were unlike any weather disasters before.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>They showed the world who suffers the most from the impacts of extreme weather: low-income families and communities of color.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>These family communities lack the resources to insulate and protect themselves from the severity of this emerging crisis.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Even worse, it is the weeks and months after -- before people go back to work and businesses reopen -- that leave working families especially vulnerable.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>As we enter hurricane season again, we know that extreme weather events come and go.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>But before they arrive, it is lower-income families and people of color -- forced by housing market dynamics and land costs -- who live the very closest to carbon pollution sources, such as highways, factories and power plants.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>In addition to that, they are already predisposed to health risks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The American Lung Association says that in excess of 20.2 million low-income people live in areas with at least one failing grade for its air.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>There are 4.5 million people breathing air that fails all three of the association&amp;apost;s air pollution tests.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Sixty-eight percent of African-Americans have homes within 30 miles of a coal plant.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Considering that one in six African-American kids has asthma, compared with one in 10 children overall, that is a dangerous fact.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>An African-American child is 3.6 times more likely to visit the emergency room for asthma, as compared with white children, according to the Department of Health and Human Services&amp;apost; Office of Minority Health.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Let me tell you a personal story.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>On the last Sunday of summer in 2005, my niece called me from New Orleans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re leaving,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;Where are you going?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>I asked brightly.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;On vacation?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Her answer, and the landfall of Hurricane Katrina the next day, became one of the most humbling periods of my life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Humility and anger turned into my dominate emotions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>I was angry for not knowing whether family members caught there without transportation had made it out safely.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Or if they hadn&amp;apost;t, whether they had survived.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>I was angry when federal officials told me that I had to wait weeks to find my sister, trapped by rising waters in an assisted-living facility.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>I was angry that my 92-year-old uncle, stranded on his roof, was flown to Roswell, Georgia, only to suffer a heart attack when he landed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Hurricane Katrina was the storm of the 21st century.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>It devastated an area the size of Great Britain.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>More than 1,800 Americans died.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Three hundred thousand homes were destroyed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>There was $96 billion in property damage.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>I served on the Louisiana Recovery Authority.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>I saw Congress write one big check and then skip town.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>I respected President George W. Bush, who personally visited the Gulf 17 times.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Laura Bush visited 24 times.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>She made certain books were donated to schools whose libraries were washed away.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Katrina was not a single disaster but three, a storm that wiped away miles of the Gulf Coast, a flood caused by breaches in the New Orleans levees and an outbreak of violence and lawlessness in the city.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>We can be thankful it wasn&amp;apost;t worse.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>We can be thankful President Barack Obama is taking aim at one of the prime causes of climate change and extreme weather: air pollution.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>The EPA&amp;apost;s carbon pollution standards are the most significant step forward our country has ever taken to protect our health by addressing climate change.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>They secure the hope that someday soon, power plants will no longer be free to dump unlimited amounts of carbon pollution into our air.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Despite what critics are saying, this is no &amp;quot;war on coal.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a battle for every American&amp;apost;s right to breathe clean air.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
