<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="930" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/08/20/opinion/perry-pope-wasnt-calling-for-crusade/index.html?hpt=hp_t5" date_published="2014-08-20 17:46:24" category="opinion" author="David M. Perry" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Pope Francis didn&amp;apost;t call for a crusade (Opinion)</title>
  <keywords>Pope Francis,Iraq,ISIS,Crusades</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="9, 4">Asked about bombing in Iraq, Pope Francis says it is &amp;quot;licit to stop the unjust aggressor&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="13">David Perry says those remarks aren&amp;apost;t a call for a new crusade, as some have suggested.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="52">He adds that the Pope is trying to balance lessons of the ancient and modern.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-02 10:26:11" annotation_time="61.554337" mapping_time_divergence="41.036224">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">With what seemed careful deliberation, Pope Francis said: &amp;quot;In these cases where there is an unjust aggression, I can only say this: It is licit to stop the unjust aggressor.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="1">To stop the unjust aggressor is licit.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="2">Certainly, much of the media response quickly fixated on what seemed to be approval for a military campaign and how a Pope -- the leader of the Catholic Church -- was seemingly sanctioning war against an Islamic caliphate.</sentence>
      <sentence id="52" ids_highlights="3">But when there is great suffering in the world, as is being inflicted on religious and ethnic minorities in areas controlled by ISIS, then Francis says one must act, while also drawing on both the ancient idea of justified war and the modern concept of international cooperation.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Pope Francis&amp;apost; trip to South Korea memorialized the atrocities of the last century.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>On the way home, the Pope became embroiled in controversy about a conflict raging in the current one.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>During a lengthy discussion, Francis remarked on the spread of cruelty and torture before being asked about violence against religious minorities in Iraq, and whether he approved of the U.S. bombing campaign aimed at stopping the Islamic State of Iraq and Syria, or ISIS.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>With what seemed careful deliberation, Pope Francis said: &amp;quot;In these cases where there is an unjust aggression, I can only say this: It is licit to stop the unjust aggressor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>I underline the verb: stop.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>I do not say bomb, make war, I say stop by some means.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>With what means can they be stopped?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>These have to be evaluated.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>To stop the unjust aggressor is licit.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>This response -- and the reaction to it -- says much about the complexity of running an organization that is at once modern and ancient, religious and political, international and parochial.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>But what exactly did he mean?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Was he, as a few excitable writers suggested, calling for a new crusade?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Certainly, much of the media response quickly fixated on what seemed to be approval for a military campaign and how a Pope -- the leader of the Catholic Church -- was seemingly sanctioning war against an Islamic caliphate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Actually, he wasn&amp;apost;t.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Crusading, as defined by most historians, generally involved taking religious vows to head east and assist in military expeditions against Islamic powers in exchange for spiritual rewards (redemption from sin).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Historians have identified major campaigns as the First, Second, Third, etc.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Crusades.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>In response to these conquests, the local Islamic powers leveraged the idea of jihad to rally disparate Muslim groups together.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Yet although the Crusades featured not just plenty of violence but also peaceful cross-cultural exchange, they aren&amp;apost;t an example Francis wants to invoke.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>In fact, he isn&amp;apost;t saying that anyone should take vows and go off to fight.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Instead, Francis is making the point that taking action to stop evil is just.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>This idea of justified violence, even from Catholics, chiefly emerged from the writing of St. Augustine (354-430).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>As Matthew Gabriele, associate professor of medieval studies at Virginia Tech, writes: &amp;quot;Augustine argued that war was never desirable but was sometimes necessary.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>We must protect those who suffer from unjust aggression.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>If that could be accomplished without war, so much the better, but force could be used by legitimate authorities as a last resort.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The end goal, however, was always -- and simply -- lasting peace.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s the context for understanding the ancient part of Francis&amp;apost; response.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The modern context emerged in how he concluded his answer.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;One nation alone cannot judge how to stop an unjust aggressor,&amp;quot; Francis said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;After the Second World War there was the idea of the United Nations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>It is there that this should be discussed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Is there an unjust aggressor?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>It would seem there is.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>How do we stop him?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Only that, nothing more.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Such pursuit of multiple perspectives to ward off bias is also Augustinian.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>In &amp;quot;On Christian Doctrine,&amp;quot; St. Augustine argued that reading the Bible required special training because though the book contains all the truths of the universe, humans (flawed creatures that we are) are far too likely to assume that whatever we think is good is also what God thinks is good.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>To counteract this, St. Augustine prescribed a strict intellectual diet of the best liberal arts and science education the late Roman world could provide.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Multiple perspectives help us discern what is truly just from what might just be convenient.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>In a way, that&amp;apost;s what Francis is doing with his words, too.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s concerned that any individual leader or nation is far too likely to assume that someone with whom they disagree is unjust, and thus the principles of stopping unjust action instead becomes a tool for warmongering.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Instead, he argues, we should try to find consensus before acting, collectively, to put an end to atrocity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>&amp;quot;We must also have memory,&amp;quot; Francis said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;How many times under this excuse of stopping an unjust aggressor the powers (that intervened) have taken control of peoples, and have made a true war of conquest.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>History teaches us all about the dangers of mission creep.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>And it also makes clear that when two sides engage in the rhetoric of religious war, things can deteriorate rapidly.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Osama bin Laden and Saddam Hussein, for example, both routinely railed against the West as &amp;quot;crusaders,&amp;quot; an accusation that gained traction in the Islamic world after President George W. Bush called for &amp;quot;this crusade, this war on terrorism&amp;quot; after 9/11.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Francis doesn&amp;apost;t want to make a similar mistake.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Indeed, while he named himself after a medieval saint who lived during the era of the Crusades, that St. Francis didn&amp;apost;t actually go to war.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Instead he went on mission, seeking (at least as we remember it today) dialogue and understanding.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>And that&amp;apost;s certainly been Pope Francis&amp;apost; path so far.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>But when there is great suffering in the world, as is being inflicted on religious and ethnic minorities in areas controlled by ISIS, then Francis says one must act, while also drawing on both the ancient idea of justified war and the modern concept of international cooperation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>The question, of course, is whether in a digital age -- when misinformation and misunderstanding spreads so fast -- Pope Francis can somehow find true harmony between old and new.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>His ability to do so will determine the lessons his papacy ultimately hands down for posterity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>Read CNNOpinion&amp;apost;s new Flipboard magazine.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
