<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="790" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/03/03/opinion/casey-bullying-legislation/index.html" date_published="2013-03-03 14:13:22" category="opinion" author="Robert Casey, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Congress, help fight bullying</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Robert Casey: All children have a right to an education free from being bullied.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="14">Casey: I reintroduced bipartisan legislation to help prevent bullying and harassment .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">He says lawmakers have a responsibility to ensure that our schools are safe.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="21">Casey: I urge my colleagues in Congress to pass the Safe Schools Improvement Act .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-30 12:53:46" annotation_time="33.219666">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">Lawmakers have a responsibility to ensure that our schools are safe, which is why I have made addressing this problem a priority in the United States Senate.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">I firmly believe that all children have a right to an education free from fear of being bullied.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="2">Recently, I reintroduced bipartisan legislation to help prevent bullying and harassment -- the Safe Schools Improvement Act.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="4">I applaud those who are already working to make schools a place where all children can achieve their full potential without fear of being bullied, and I urge my colleagues in Congress to work with me in passing the Safe Schools Improvement Act.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>CNN and the Cartoon Network&amp;apost;s presentation of the AC360° special feature, &amp;quot;The Bully Effect,&amp;quot; spotlight a serious issue affecting children across our nation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The film underscores the damaging consequences of bullying and the need to prevent and respond to it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Lawmakers have a responsibility to ensure that our schools are safe, which is why I have made addressing this problem a priority in the United States Senate.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>I firmly believe that all children have a right to an education free from fear of being bullied.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The denial of this basic right is a betrayal of children who simply want to learn.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The impact of bullying for students and for our nation are severe.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>In an era when a quality education matters greatly in a competitive global economy, students must be able to focus on their studies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Bullying distracts students who worry more about surviving the day unscathed than about the grades on their report card.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Research has indicated that bullying causes increased absenteeism, dropout rates and academic underachievement, all of which undermine a child&amp;apost;s ability to succeed in the classroom and beyond.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>I am particularly disturbed by stories of bullied youth who feel powerless to change their situation and who choose not to seek help from adults.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>A recent report from a newspaper in my home state of Pennsylvania told the story of a 12-year-old boy who regularly asks his parents not to report when he has been bullied because he fears possible retaliation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Rather than speak up about the threatening environment at school, he felt that his only option was to keep quiet or risk making things worse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Putting an end to bullying will require a consistent message from adults, including lawmakers, that young people can make a real difference in their lives and the lives of others when they speak up about bullying and harassment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Recently, I reintroduced bipartisan legislation to help prevent bullying and harassment -- the Safe Schools Improvement Act.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>My bill, which I&amp;apost;m proposing with co-sponsor Sen. Mark Kirk, R-Illinois, will require school districts that receive federal funding to develop codes of conduct that specifically ban bullying and harassment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>This includes cyberbullying and bullying based on a student&amp;apost;s actual or perceived race, color, national origin, sex, disability, sexual orientation, gender identity or religion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>At the end of the 112th Congress, 41 senators had joined Senator Kirk and me in supporting this important, commonsense legislation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>A new study found that the psychological side effects of bullying can extend up to a decade after the harassment has ended.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Moreover, this elevated risk of mental health effects occurs not only with victims of bullying but also with the bullies themselves.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Faced with the possibility of such far reaching consequences, it is more important than ever that we put a stop to the intimidation of our youth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>I applaud those who are already working to make schools a place where all children can achieve their full potential without fear of being bullied, and I urge my colleagues in Congress to work with me in passing the Safe Schools Improvement Act.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Watch the AC360 special documentary, &amp;quot;The Bully Effect,&amp;quot; on March 3 and March 9 at 8 p.m. ET on CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Follow us on Twitter @CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Join us on Facebook/CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>