<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="780" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/08/22/opinion/the-moment-of-truth-for-the-gulf-cooperation-council-approaches/index.html?hpt=hp_mid" date_published="2014-08-22 17:12:28" category="opinion" author="David B Roberts, special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Can Qatar, Saudi Arabia ease tensions at Gulf Cooperation Council?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">The leaders from the six-member Arab alliance prepare to meet in Jeddah.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">David B Roberts: Qatar will not do as it&amp;apost;s told by Saudi Arabia and the UAE.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">Tensions between Saudi Arabia and Qatar are nothing new, he writes.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="10">Main concern is Qatar&amp;apost;s support for groups linked with the Muslim Brotherhood, he says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 13:46:38" annotation_time="44.944668">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">It&amp;apost;s the gravest diplomatic crisis the Gulf Cooperation Council has ever faced -- but as leaders from the six-member Arab alliance prepare to meet in Jeddah, are things about to get even worse?</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">Qatar simply will not do as it&amp;apost;s told by Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates, who have spent months trying to force the energy-rich nation to fundamentally alter its foreign policy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">Of course, tensions between Saudi Arabia and Qatar are nothing new.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="4">Among a variety of modern-day issues, the central concern animating this round of difficulties is Qatar&amp;apost;s support for various groups associated with the Muslim Brotherhood -- the long-suppressed pan-regional Islamist movement that swept to power in the Egyptian elections of 2012 before being deposed by the military a year later.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s the gravest diplomatic crisis the Gulf Cooperation Council has ever faced -- but as leaders from the six-member Arab alliance prepare to meet in Jeddah, are things about to get even worse?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The root of the current problem?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Qatar simply will not do as it&amp;apost;s told by Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates, who have spent months trying to force the energy-rich nation to fundamentally alter its foreign policy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Bahrain, the UAE and the Saudis withdrew their ambassadors from Qatar in March, and have kept up the pressure ever since.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Of course, tensions between Saudi Arabia and Qatar are nothing new.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Qatar has striven since the late 1980s to escape the Saudi political orbit by vigorously pursuing its own independent foreign policy -- regardless of the displeasure it caused in Riyadh.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The Saudis, for their part, have never liked this rejection of its leadership from an uppity small country like Qatar that it sees as barely more than an appendage of its own state.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>But for all the pressure Saudi Arabia exerted on Qatar -- including withdrawing its ambassador from Doha from 2002-2008 -- it could not put the Qatari genie back in the bottle.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>A modus vivendi was reached in 2008, but the current crisis seems to mark another attempt to put Qatar in its place.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Among a variety of modern-day issues, the central concern animating this round of difficulties is Qatar&amp;apost;s support for various groups associated with the Muslim Brotherhood -- the long-suppressed pan-regional Islamist movement that swept to power in the Egyptian elections of 2012 before being deposed by the military a year later.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The Saudis are deeply troubled by the practical and rhetorical threats the group poses in the region.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>And although a Brotherhood-inspired revolution seems deeply unlikely in the UAE, this is what its authorities fear and the reason they have sentenced to jail dozens of people in the last 18 months.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>In March 2014 both states banned the group and labelled it a terrorist organization.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Qatar has made some concessions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>In mid-August, reports emerged that Qatar has considered ending the naturalization of nationals from other GCC countries -- Saudi Arabia, the UAE, Bahrain, Oman and Kuwait -- in answer to their criticism of the practice.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>And it beggars belief to think that Qatar has not made other concessions in private, given the seriousness of the break in regional relations between the countries.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Yet still Saudi Arabia and the UAE continue to try to force Qatar to accept and conform to their particular world-view.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Up to this point, this current disagreement has had a negligible impact on the GCC -- and the fact that the Council cannot provide a united front on the Gaza or ISIS crises is nothing new for the argumentative and perennially-divided group.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Demoting Qatar somehow from the GCC, one of the potential punishments for the recalcitrant state, would merely codify the ineffectiveness of the GCC, not create it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Furthermore, punishing Doha would adversely affect on-going efforts to promote &amp;quot;jointness&amp;quot; among the GCC militaries in areas like ballistic missile defence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>And if Qataris were to need new visas to enter other GCC countries, this would foster a logistical nightmare and increase the already bitter intra-GCC tensions felt by people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>If things got worse at the GCC, Qatar would double-down on its relations with the likes of Turkey, Iran, and the remaining Muslim Brotherhood affiliates in the region, and it would reinforce its relations to its closest international allies: the US, the UK, France, Japan, and South Korea.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>So what could the Saudis do to try to bring Doha into line?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Any closure of the Qatari-Saudi border would be deeply harmful for Qatar given the importance of the route for trade.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Around 80% of dairy imports, 30% of stone and cement imports, and 92% of aluminium imports come across the land border, according to the Ministry of Development Planning &amp;amp; Statistics in Qatar.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>If the Qatari Government were to react to this (even though they have taken the moral high ground by doing nothing so far), they could curtail its gas supply to the UAE (and Oman), which is crucial given the surging demand for natural gas in the Emirates.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>While closing the border would generally be seen as an overreaction by Saudi Arabia, so too was removing its ambassador from Qatar, not to mention its rejection of the U.N. Security Council seat it won in October 2013 after years of lobbying and training for the role.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Some kind of escalation looks likely, barring a last minute reprieve.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Saudi Arabia and the UAE appear to want a public sign of contrition from Qatar -- something that the new Emir of Qatar cannot give.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Not only can the Emir not overturn decades of Qatari policy that has sporadically supported groups like the Brotherhood, but barely a year into his leadership, he cannot capitulate to such naked regional pressure.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Vociferous and patriotic public pressure in Qatar alone precludes that.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>And as the on-going Iranian-American nuclear talks have lowered tensions in the region, so too have the talks diminished the only real factor -- the threat of a nuclear Iran -- forcing any kind of cohesion from the GCC.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The GCC does face a serious political crisis, but though this may concern the countries involved, the tiff will likely pass mostly unnoticed by the rest of the region -- and the oil, the gas, the investment, the imports, and the money going to a wide variety of groups around the Middle East will continue to flow from all states.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
