<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="771" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/10/01/opinion/gonzalez-white-house-freedom/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-10-01 15:08:42" category="opinion" author="Mike Gonzalez" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Another freedom group abandoned by U.S. (Opinion)</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">White House has shunned people protesting for freedom, argues Mike Gonzalez.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="22">Tyrants will do what they want to do, whether we support protesters or not, Gonzalez says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="23">What foreign liberty-seekers want from us is moral validation of their cause, he writes.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="31">Support for freedom overseas has been America&amp;apost;s official policy since Truman, he says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 07:56:04" annotation_time="26.156">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">Indeed, time and again, this White House has shown itself to be allergic to those peacefully seeking backing for their freedom causes.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="2">But this ignores the fact that tyrants will do what they want to do, whether we support protesters or not -- the bloodily suppressed Iranian protests back in 2009 underscore this point.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="3">What foreign liberty-seekers want from us is often not &amp;quot;boots on the ground,&amp;quot; much less &amp;quot;nation-building.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="31" ids_highlights="4">Support for freedom overseas has been America&amp;apost;s official policy at least since Truman announced his doctrine to Congress, saying that, with Britain exhausted and its empire fading, we had to step up.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Hong Kong&amp;apost;s pro-democracy demonstrators are but the latest freedom group to be abandoned by the Obama administration.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The pattern was set in President Barack Obama&amp;apost;s first year in office, when he committed his initial major foreign policy error by refusing to support pro-democracy demonstrators in Iran.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>And, although we didn&amp;apost;t know it at the time, it was to be the administration&amp;apost;s original sin, an early predictor of things to come.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Indeed, time and again, this White House has shown itself to be allergic to those peacefully seeking backing for their freedom causes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Whether Cuban, Chinese, Iranian or Venezuelan, dissidents who regularly make the rounds of the halls of power in Washington privately complain that even when the White House and the State Department receive them, the official is of low stature and the support is tepid.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>And so when tens of thousands of demonstrators took to the streets of Hong Kong last weekend, the administration ran true to form.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Our consulate there expressed support for general rights such as freedom of expression, religion and association, but was signally quiet on democracy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>In fact, the consulate seemed to go out of its way to wash its hands of the demonstrations, saying: &amp;quot;We do not take sides in the discussion of Hong Kong&amp;apost;s political development, nor do we support any particular individuals or groups involved in it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>... We encourage all sides to refrain from actions that would further escalate tensions, to exercise restraint and to express views on (Hong Kong&amp;apost;s) political development in a peaceful manner.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The protesters&amp;apost; official Twitter feed was quick to express bitter disappointment: &amp;quot;Once again, democratic govs are not speaking up for democracy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Here is US consulate&amp;apost;s mealy-mouthed statement.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Why has the Obama administration been so slow to embrace freedom-seeking protesters?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Three main reasons spring to mind:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>We&amp;apost;re not Bush: President Obama&amp;apost;s aversion to his predecessor&amp;apost;s policies is clear not just in his snide condescension, but also in his actions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>President George W. Bush&amp;apost;s embrace of what he called &amp;quot;the freedom agenda&amp;quot; appears to be enough to damn the whole project and for Obama to want to do the opposite.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Pretensions to realism: Despite the fact that failures are piling up, the Obama administration apparently sees itself as really good at international relations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>As such, it appears to be under the impression that it is pursuing cold-eyed national security interests and, as the &amp;quot;only adults in the room,&amp;quot; has no time for idealism.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Liberty is not the progressives&amp;apost; thing: Though it receives little attention, progressivism&amp;apost;s well-known preference for centralized control over what it sees as &amp;quot;unplanned chaos&amp;quot; must play a role.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Progressives mock &amp;quot;liberty&amp;quot; here at home, so why would they take to it overseas?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>It is no coincidence that, very early on in her role as secretary of state, Hillary Clinton elevated climate change and gender issues over freedom in her dealings with foreign officials.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Some of the White House&amp;apost;s most thoughtful defenders point out that it is counterproductive to support pro-democracy groups, whether in Tehran or Hong Kong.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>But this ignores the fact that tyrants will do what they want to do, whether we support protesters or not -- the bloodily suppressed Iranian protests back in 2009 underscore this point.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>What foreign liberty-seekers want from us is often not &amp;quot;boots on the ground,&amp;quot; much less &amp;quot;nation-building.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>They desire moral validation of their cause, the knowledge that an outside power -- the world&amp;apost;s only superpower, no less -- stands by them and believes in their cause.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The Soviet dissident Natan Sharansky, for example, has written vividly of what it meant to those in the Gulag to hear that President Ronald Reagan had called the Soviet Union evil:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;This was the moment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>It was the brightest, most glorious day.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Finally a spade had been called a spade.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Finally, Orwell&amp;apost;s Newspeak was dead.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>... It was one of the most important, freedom-affirming declarations, and we all instantly knew it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Support for freedom overseas has been America&amp;apost;s official policy at least since Truman announced his doctrine to Congress, saying that, with Britain exhausted and its empire fading, we had to step up.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;One of the primary objectives of the foreign policy of the United States,&amp;quot; Truman said, &amp;quot;is the creation of conditions in which we and other nations will be able to work out a way of life free from coercion.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>But it goes back much earlier, and the founders understood we were to hold the torch of freedom for the rest of the world to see.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>When we don&amp;apost;t, it creates not just disappointment in places like Hong Kong, but dissonance here at home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>