<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="899" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/09/22/opinion/fateh-pakistan-islam-protests/index.html" date_published="2012-09-22 07:33:07" category="opinion" author="Aazadi Fateh Muhammad, special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Opinion: Pakistanis can debunk myths about Islam peacefully</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">There is little public debate in Pakistan, Fateh Muhammad writes.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="13">She says Islamic scholar seeking modest approach should be more visible.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="13">Less coverage should be given to hard-line political parties, figures, she adds.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="17">The biggest problem in the world today is misunderstanding, Fateh Muhammad says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-20 14:23:29" annotation_time="68.82533">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">The country&amp;apost;s big problem is that it suffers from natural disasters, terrorism, crime, poor living conditions and corrupt sociopolitical systems -- but there is little public debate.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="2, 3">Islamic scholars seeking a modest approach should be brought forward on the popular media to calm people&amp;apost;s resentment, while less coverage should be given to more hard-line political parties and public figures.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="4">The biggest problem in the world today, religiously and culturally, is misunderstanding.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content> Most Pakistanis have rejected the defamatory attacks on the profile of Prophet of Islam Muhammad (Peace be Upon Him) in the movie &amp;quot;Innocence of Muslims,&amp;quot; which has triggered intensive protests and anger in Pakistan along with Egypt, Libya and Yemen.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The government in Pakistan was the first to announce a public holiday and banned YouTube as a mark of protest.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>But this failed to calm the violent demonstrations and resulting violent mob actions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The country&amp;apost;s big problem is that it suffers from natural disasters, terrorism, crime, poor living conditions and corrupt sociopolitical systems -- but there is little public debate.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Erfan Aziz, an academician from Karachi, observed that &amp;quot;the public in Pakistan has remained much oppressed in the past.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Even the genuine issues of society were not allowed to be discussed in public.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Notifications such as &amp;apost;avoid political conversations&amp;apost; still may be seen in some public areas.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Many in Pakistan are seeking to convey a message to the international community by promoting mutual respect for each other&amp;apost;s faiths.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Kulsoom Shah, a Fulbright student, for example says young people must come up with creative ideas to register the hurt feelings that the movie provoked -- but peacefully.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Shah said she applauded French students who distributed copies of the Quran in non-Muslim communities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>In this way, productive ways to register feelings can help in debunking myths about Islam and promote it as a religion of peace.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The present situation is sensitive indeed and cannot be dealt with in isolation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Islamic scholars seeking a modest approach should be brought forward on the popular media to calm people&amp;apost;s resentment, while less coverage should be given to more hard-line political parties and public figures.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Lindsey Boyle, from Ohio University, condemns the movie&amp;apost;s offense and its overgeneralized tone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>For one, the film does not represent popular U.S. opinion; second, the U.S. government has condemned the movie, so burning the American flag is not necessarily a reasonable reaction.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Furthermore, she believes there are many similarities between Christianity&amp;apost;s Jesus and Islam&amp;apost;s Mohammed: They were both open-minded, helped the weak, overcame personal struggles and far more besides.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The biggest problem in the world today, religiously and culturally, is misunderstanding.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>People on both sides of this situation simply need to take time to learn about one another.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>That becomes almost impossible when one side is making an over-generalized, demeaning movie, and the other side is violently protesting it in an overgeneralized way.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>We need to work to promote positive messages and understanding, above all else.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The question about the nature of protest remains a sensitive one, and it&amp;apost;s far more difficult to motivate people to follow that in practical ways.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Pakistani youth must realize the differences of mass media usage in U.S. society and protest in creative, constructive ways to get the desired results, as aggressive protests not only generate more violence and conflict but also make it easy to lose the true spirit of their cause.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>In the present world, human diversity and pluralism must be understood to promote peace and prosperity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>We need peace and harmony, and to do this we must show tolerance and give space to each other&amp;apost;s differences, be they color, race, creed, religion or nationality in order to promote a friendlier lifestyle around us.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>