<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="897" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/03/28/opinion/navarrette-school-discipline-white-house/index.html" date_published="2014-03-28 12:42:59" category="opinion" author="Ruben Navarrette" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Opinion: Obama&amp;apost;s school discipline plan is overkill</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Ruben Navarrette: Obama administration has targeted &amp;quot;zero tolerance policies&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="29">He says there is evidence that school discipline is meted out in discriminatory way.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="32">Putting two Cabinet departments on the issue is overkill, Navarrette says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="31">Navarrette: Micromanaging our schools is a risk and could erode authority of teachers .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-08 22:16:42" annotation_time="80.69967">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">The Obama administration has unleashed two Cabinet departments to get tough on teachers and other school personnel who -- through so-called &amp;quot;zero tolerance&amp;quot; policies -- often refer disciplinary cases to police.</sentence>
      <sentence id="29" ids_highlights="2">This isn&amp;apost;t to say that there isn&amp;apost;t any discrimination in the doling out of school discipline, or that this isn&amp;apost;t a subject worthy of more study.</sentence>
      <sentence id="31" ids_highlights="4">Yet, this initiative could also backfire on the administration by micromanaging our schools, undermining the authority of teachers and teaching African-American and Latino students to see themselves as victims.</sentence>
      <sentence id="32" ids_highlights="3">Besides, throwing two Cabinet departments at the problem is a serious case of overkill.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>San Diego When the worlds of federal bureaucracies and public schools collide, what results is often a teaching moment for all involved.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The Obama administration has unleashed two Cabinet departments to get tough on teachers and other school personnel who -- through so-called &amp;quot;zero tolerance&amp;quot; policies -- often refer disciplinary cases to police.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>What concerns folks at the Justice and Education departments is that African-American and Latino students might be singled out for suspension and other forms of discipline, in ways that could amount to outright racial and ethnic discrimination.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Their proposed solution is called the Supportive School Discipline Initiative, which seeks to limit student suspensions and expulsions and provide &amp;quot;alternative best practices such as restorative justice, peer mediation and positive behavioral supports.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The initiative was unveiled in 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>But last week, the administration went so far as to lay out specific guidelines for states and even individual school districts.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The administration will propose $50 million in grants to more than 1,000 schools to train teachers and staff in strategies aimed at improving student behavior and improving the climate of schools.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Upon hearing all this, memory takes me back to a junior high school in a small, largely Mexican and Mexican-American farming town in Central California, where I found myself, in the years after college, trying to support my writing habit by working as a substitute teacher.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>I had a long-term assignment, about three months, teaching a &amp;quot;special education&amp;quot; course that was being misused as a dumping ground for rowdy and disruptive kids with behavioral problems.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Almost all the kids in the class were Hispanic.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The regular teacher, a 60-something woman with a kind disposition and white hair, was in poor health and on a prolonged absence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>One day, I was looking for a lesson plan in the teacher&amp;apost;s desk and ran across some diary-like notes that the teacher had written -- probably in case she needed them someday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Her problem kid was an angry 13-year-old Hispanic young man named &amp;quot;Martin.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>They apparently had a running conflict, and, one day, the teacher had scribbled down in her notes: &amp;quot;Martin called me a white @#$%&amp;amp;, and said he was going to hurt me.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Welcome to the real world of public schools in America, which bears no resemblance to what they teach you at schools of education or university-run teacher credentialing programs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>When students such as Martin act up or get out of line, they have to be disciplined.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>They have to get in trouble, pay a price and be taught that they simply can&amp;apost;t go through life disrupting their environment and threatening authority figures.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>We can debate what the punishment should be, but there have to be consequences.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>No &amp;quot;if&amp;apost;s,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;and&amp;apost;s&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;but&amp;apost;s.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s for his own good.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Let&amp;apost;s say you give him a pass.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>What&amp;apost;s going to happen the first time he&amp;apost;s on the street and mouths off to a cop?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Also, note the part about how Martin allegedly called this nice, elderly woman &amp;quot;a white @#$%&amp;amp;.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>From my experience, that&amp;apost;s also very common.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>We&amp;apost;ll hear advocates for students talk about how teachers sometimes harbor prejudices against students, and there is no doubt that this is true.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>But we don&amp;apost;t hear much about what happens when the shoe is on the other foot.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Go into any inner-city high school in America, and you&amp;apost;ll hear African-American and Hispanic students using racial slurs when talking about teachers and administrators.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>It goes with the territory.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>This isn&amp;apost;t to say that there isn&amp;apost;t any discrimination in the doling out of school discipline, or that this isn&amp;apost;t a subject worthy of more study.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>They might well be, and it certainly is.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Yet, this initiative could also backfire on the administration by micromanaging our schools, undermining the authority of teachers and teaching African-American and Latino students to see themselves as victims.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Besides, throwing two Cabinet departments at the problem is a serious case of overkill.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>How is this for a new approach?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>If we really want to help students who get in trouble, why don&amp;apost;t we stop meddling in the schools and start dealing with those societal factors -- such as poverty, despair and broken homes -- that help these young people get into trouble in the first place?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Follow us on Twitter @CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Join us on Facebook/CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
