<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="871" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/06/11/opinion/opinion-afghan-women/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-06-11 16:38:42" category="opinion" author="Martha Roby, Niki Tsongas, Renee Ellmers, Susan Davis and Cheri Bustos" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Opinion: For women of Afghanistan, life is better</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="30">A bipartisan coalition of women in Congress visited women in Afghanistan.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">The improvement in the quality of life for Afghan women is unmistakable, they say.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="30">Still, long-term success will be in the preservation of the gains made by Afghan women.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-01 11:15:36" annotation_time="76.02567">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">More than a decade after American and allied forces toppled the Taliban regime, the improvement in the quality of life for Afghan women is unmistakable.</sentence>
      <sentence id="30" ids_highlights="1, 3">An important bellwether for the success or failure of America&amp;apost;s efforts in Afghanistan will be the preservation of the gains made by Afghan women.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>We awoke one morning in Kabul to the sound of not-too-distant explosions, marking the start to the fighting season.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But bombs were not the foremost takeaway from our Mother&amp;apost;s Day trip to Afghanistan -- the women fighting to stop the bombs left a more lasting impression.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>More than a decade after American and allied forces toppled the Taliban regime, the improvement in the quality of life for Afghan women is unmistakable.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Women are now participants -- and in many cases, leaders -- in a society that once systematically subjugated them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>There are female government officials at almost every level, young girls going to school, young women in college, and new opportunities cropping up around the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>On a sixth annual trip, our congressional delegation of women legislators spent several days in Afghanistan in May meeting with many of the women who have helped begin to reverse centuries of repression.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>We spoke with female public officials, women journalists, and heads of organizations focused on advancing the role of women.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>And we had the privilege to spend time with a special group of people who, although they are not from Afghanistan, have a unique appreciation for what Afghan women are fighting for.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>On Mother&amp;apost;s Day we met our &amp;quot;military moms&amp;quot; -- women soldiers from the United States who have children back home.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>We delivered Mother&amp;apost;s Day cards made by American school children, hosted a luncheon and listened to their stories of heroism and sacrifice.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>It became clear that all these women -- Afghan, American or otherwise -- are determined to preserve and grow the progress made by Afghan women and girls.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The most striking example came when we met with women members of the Afghan parliament.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>At a roundtable, we discussed the opportunities that have been made available to Afghan women and girls over the past decade; the important role they must play in the country&amp;apost;s society, security and economy in order to see future success; and the critical need to protect these gains from backsliding.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;We can bring democracy to Afghanistan,&amp;quot; one of the Parliamentarians said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>For emphasis, another added: &amp;quot;We can deliver.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>By engaging with the Afghan people directly, we experienced firsthand the growing sense of cautious optimism that seems to have taken root here, due in large part to women&amp;apost;s gains and to the recent national elections.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>There is no mistaking that the situation in Afghanistan is still fragile and highly complicated.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Yes, the elections in April saw relative success with high voter turnout, a higher than expected turnout among women, and relatively small amounts of violence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>But runoff elections set for June 14 are another important test of the coalition-trained Afghan security forces and voter retention.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>A bilateral security agreement needs to be signed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Both remaining presidential candidates have signaled their willingness to participate in such an agreement, but details are yet to be finalized.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>A clear plan to maintain Afghan women&amp;apost;s gains must be included.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Our delegation urged for more focus to be placed on recruiting women to the Afghan National Security Forces.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The Afghan Ministry of Defense currently has 700 women in the security forces, but that number needs to be increased significantly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Last week, President Barack Obama announced that 9,800 American troops will remain in Afghanistan after the end of 2014, with that number stepping down in subsequent years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>No one wants our troops to stay in Afghanistan one moment longer than necessary, and the transition from a combat role to one of training and advisory must be done carefully and responsibly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Afghanistan must take the reins of their country&amp;apost;s future, and America must play an important role in ensuring a lasting peace.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>A secure Afghanistan ultimately impacts America&amp;apost;s national security.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>And strong signals of U.S. support contribute to the confidence of the Afghan people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>An important bellwether for the success or failure of America&amp;apost;s efforts in Afghanistan will be the preservation of the gains made by Afghan women.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>If the bombs we heard that morning in Kabul reminded us of the challenges that remain here, the women we met in Afghanistan personified how far this country has come, and the potential for where it goes next.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
