<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="852" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/04/04/opinion/afghanistan-comment-hammond/index.html?hpt=hp_c5" date_published="2014-04-04 17:02:28" category="opinion" author="Andrew Hammond, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Opinion: After Karzai, Afghanistan at perilous crossroads</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Afghanistan heads to polls Saturday, but concerns voiced about likely electoral irregularities.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">Ballot is nonetheless a watershed moment in the country&amp;apost;s history, Andrew Hammond writes.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="25">New government must keep Washington on side, while not torpedoing peace talks with Taliban - Hammond.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="40">If U.S.-led forces withdraw completely in 2014, collapse of government becomes probability, he adds.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-08 07:13:16" annotation_time="64.60134">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">London With Afghanistan heading to the polls on Saturday, concerns have been voiced about likely electoral irregularities.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">Despite these concerns, and the prospect of Taliban attacks at polling stations, the ballot is nonetheless a watershed moment in the country&amp;apost;s history.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="3">All of these are points where the new government will walk a tightrope between keeping Washington on side, while not torpedoing the peace dialogue with the Taliban.</sentence>
      <sentence id="40" ids_highlights="4">But if international forces withdraw completely in 2014, the eventual collapse of the government becomes a real possibility.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>London With Afghanistan heading to the polls on Saturday, concerns have been voiced about likely electoral irregularities.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Abdullah Abdullah, a former foreign minister and leading presidential candidate, has warned the ballot will be marred by &amp;quot;industrial scale fraud&amp;quot; to rival the 1 million votes that were disqualified in the 2009 elections.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Despite these concerns, and the prospect of Taliban attacks at polling stations, the ballot is nonetheless a watershed moment in the country&amp;apost;s history.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>It heralds the first democratic transfer of power, and also the end of the post-9/11 Karzai era.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Some 13 years after the fall of the Taliban regime, President Hamid Karzai is bequeathing a mixed legacy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>To be sure, there are grounds for optimism.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Since 2001, for instance, the economy has grown rapidly, and women have more opportunities in much of the country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>And as the election underlines, a nascent, albeit dysfunctional, democracy may be taking root after years of Taliban oppression.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>But the most likely prospect is greater economic, political and security instability.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>And, this is despite the blood and treasure expended by U.S. and Western militaries since 2001 -- about 3,500 international coalition forces lives lost, and almost $700 billion spent by the U.S. military alone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Whether Afghanistan prospers, or implodes, will be determined in part by the new president&amp;apost;s success in dealing with a complex set of inter-related issues including: trying to forge a security deal with Washington and its NATO partners beyond 2014; pursuing the reconciliation agenda and a possible peace agreement with the Taliban; and preventing an economic downturn as foreign aid is reduced.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Of the original 27 candidates approved by the Electoral Commission, only eight remain.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Yet the ballot outcome is uncertain, partly because of electoral fraud.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>As well as Abdullah Abdullah, who finished second in the 2009 presidential election, the two other leading candidates are widely seen to be Ashraf Ghani, an economist and former World Bank executive, and Zalmai Rassoul, a former foreign minister.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Given the absence of an obvious front-runner, it appears likely no one will secure 50% of the vote to win outright.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Thus, a run-off ballot would be required, delaying the outcome several more weeks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Once elected, the priority for the new president will be bolstering domestic security, and Abdullah, Ghani and Rassoul have endorsed the need for a long-term deal with U.S. and NATO forces.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>However, to create the &amp;quot;political space&amp;quot; for what would be a controversial agreement with some of the populace, the new president will need to secure concessions from Washington.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>This could mean protracted negotiations which will frustrate the Obama administration.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>While it is likely than a deal will be reached, there is a possibility that U.S. and NATO forces may pull out completely in 2014.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>This could prove catastrophic for the new government, potentially leading to its eventual collapse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>This is widely recognized internationally, but the military presence in Afghanistan is unpopular in many Western countries.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Moreover, delays in signing a deal (Washington hoped to reach agreement last year with Karzai) means logistical and personnel complications of extending the international troop presence are growing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Key issues to be resolved between the new president and Washington include: any continuing U.S. mandate to perform counter-terrorism mission in Afghanistan; extending immunity for U.S. military personnel; and the fate of Taliban prisoners.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>All of these are points where the new government will walk a tightrope between keeping Washington on side, while not torpedoing the peace dialogue with the Taliban.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Should a security deal be secured, a residual U.S. and NATO force of 8,000-12,000 troops is most likely.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Importantly, this agreement would also ensure funding and training for Afghan security forces which may otherwise disintegrate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>However, Afghanistan still faces the prospect of instability from a Taliban counter-offensive.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Hence, the reason why another priority for the new president will be advancing reconciliation with the Taliban toward a potential final settlement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Pakistan&amp;apost;s influence could be key in facilitating any deal.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>While doubts remain about that country&amp;apost;s ability and willingness to facilitate such an agreement, last week Pakistani government representatives entered into formal peace talks with the Taliban in North Waziristan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Turning to the economic front, the new president will come into office at a difficult moment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Since 2001, the economy has become more dependent on foreign aid.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Economic risks would be intense in the event of a withdrawal of international troops.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>This could see aid cut back, partly because agencies would no longer be able to operate under an international security umbrella.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Another problem the new government faces is that there has been only limited success in economic diversification since 2001, with the extractives sector the only exception.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>The clear danger is that, as aid is reduced, the economy becomes more dependent upon illegal drug exports such as opium and heroin.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Taken overall, Afghanistan is therefore at a major inflexion point.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>A successful, decisive transfer of power combined with an eventual reconciliation deal with the Taliban could consolidate power and legitimacy of the new president, helping preserve some of the fragile gains since 2001.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>But if international forces withdraw completely in 2014, the eventual collapse of the government becomes a real possibility.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>READ: Amanpour&amp;apost;s Afghan presidential interviews.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>READ: NATO Commander: Troops will stay in Afghanistan post-2014.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
