<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="901" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/07/07/opinion/schlumpf-pope-apology-sex-abuse/index.html" date_published="2014-07-07 18:23:31" category="opinion" author="Heidi Schlumpf" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Opinion: Pope&amp;apost;s apology on abuse still doesn&amp;apost;t cut it</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Heidi Schlumpf: Pope Francis met with victims of clergy sexual abuse, begged forgiveness.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="23">She says apology good, but he must do more to make amends with victims, all Catholics.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="15">She says Vatican steps positive; Pope should remove Kansas City bishop who covered up.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="22">Schlumpf: Victims&amp;apost; groups want more action; if they can forgive, they are ones to be commended.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-08 22:50:39" annotation_time="334.836">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">After meeting Monday with six victims of sexual abuse by clergy members, Pope Francis apologized for the crimes committed against them and begged forgiveness &amp;quot;for the sins of omission on the part of church leaders who did not respond adequately to reports of abuse.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="3">But there is much more to be done, starting with the removal of Kansas City-St.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="4">Barbara Blaine, president of the Survivors Network of those Abused by Priests, applauded the courage of the victims who met with Francis on Monday but complained about the need for more decisive action.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;The Pope says the church should &amp;apost;make reparations&amp;apost; to victims.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>After meeting Monday with six victims of sexual abuse by clergy members, Pope Francis apologized for the crimes committed against them and begged forgiveness &amp;quot;for the sins of omission on the part of church leaders who did not respond adequately to reports of abuse.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Apologies are all well and good, but this one brings to mind two trite but true sayings: &amp;quot;Too little, too late&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Actions speak louder than words.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Unfortunately, Francis has more to do so that future popes won&amp;apost;t have to keep saying &amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m sorry&amp;quot; for these crimes and the Catholic Church&amp;apost;s cover-up.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>This is not to downplay the important symbolism of public apologies from the church&amp;apost;s top leader.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Indeed, Francis seems sincere and acknowledges the complicity of the institutional church in the cover-up, not just the actions of individual men.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>But Francis is not the first pope to meet with sex abuse victims or even the first to offer an official apology for what has to be one of the gravest evils in the church.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>His predecessor, Pope Benedict XVI, met on several occasions with victims, including during a trip to the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>After one such meeting, he also issued a formal apology, saying he was &amp;quot;deeply sorry for the pain and suffering the victims have endured.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>In comparison, Francis&amp;apost; apology, given during a lengthy homily, was more extensive, emphasizing the psychological and spiritual pain victims have endured and noting that these &amp;quot;despicable actions&amp;quot; had been &amp;quot;camouflaged with a complicity that cannot be explained.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>It also was better than his, &amp;quot;Yes, but ...&amp;quot; apology earlier this year, when he mentioned that abusers were &amp;quot;quite a few in number, though not compared to the total number&amp;quot; of priests, after earlier complaining about how the church had been unfairly singled out for the problem of sexual abuse of minors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Given the enormity of this problem facing the Catholic Church, however, victims&amp;apost; rights groups are correct in expressing disappointment with how long it took for the new Pope to meet with them (16 months into his pontificate).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>In March, editors of the National Catholic Reporter, which has been covering sex abuse by clergy for nearly three decades, implored the Pope in an open letter to make meeting with victims a priority.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>As someone who clearly understands the significance of his actions -- everything from his choice of attire to whose feet he washes on Holy Thursday -- Francis should have met with victims much sooner than this.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Still, Monday&amp;apost;s apology seems to be part of more significant movements in the Vatican, including the naming of a victim to a new panel to address sex abuse and the recent defrocking of a Polish archbishop and papal ambassador accused of paying for sex with minors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>But there is much more to be done, starting with the removal of Kansas City-St.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Joseph Bishop Robert Finn, who has been found guilty of failing to report suspicions of child abuse to police or state child welfare authorities.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The diocese has recently been ordered to pay $1.1 million for violating terms of an earlier contract of reparations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Of course, a good apology includes not only acknowledgment of personal and/or corporate responsibility for the victim&amp;apost;s pain, but also a promise to fix things, or at least to not continue to inflict that pain.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The church is finally, after decades of denying or minimizing victims&amp;apost; pain, accepting responsibility.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>But we&amp;apost;re not yet there on fixing things.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s why victims&amp;apost; rights groups are understandably frustrated by the molasses-like pace of the church on this issue.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Barbara Blaine, president of the Survivors Network of those Abused by Priests, applauded the courage of the victims who met with Francis on Monday but complained about the need for more decisive action.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Pope says the church should &amp;apost;make reparations&amp;apost; to victims.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s secondary.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Stopping abuse and protecting children comes first.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>And sadly, no child on earth is safer today because of this meeting,&amp;quot; she wrote in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Here&amp;apost;s another saying: &amp;quot;To err is human; to forgive, divine.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>If that&amp;apost;s true, it will be the victims who will be the real saints, not the apologizers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
