<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="859" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/07/18/opinion/navarrette-mexico-cartel-arrest/index.html" date_published="2013-07-18 11:37:46" category="opinion" author="Ruben Navarrette Jr., CNN Contributor" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Opinion: Cartel leader&amp;apost;s arrest won&amp;apost;t stop the horror</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Mexico arrested Miguel Trevino Morales, leader of the brutal drug cartel The Zetas .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">Ruben Navarrette: The arrest is a major coup for new Mexican President Enrique Peña Nieto.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="32">He says Trevino Morales is behind bars, but his brother will take over the cartel.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="36">Navarrette: High-profile arrests put the cartels on notice that they&amp;apost;re in the cross hairs.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-11 10:20:48" annotation_time="57.845" mapping_time_divergence="14.46125">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">It&amp;apost;s probably close to how our southern neighbors feel now that they have in custody Miguel Angel Trevino Morales, leader of the brutal paramilitary drug cartel known as The Zetas.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">The takedown is a major coup for Mexican President Enrique Peña Nieto, who came to office just seven months ago and returned the Institutional Revolutionary Party to power.</sentence>
      <sentence id="32" ids_highlights="3">His brother is in line to succeed him.</sentence>
      <sentence id="36" ids_highlights="4">They put the cartels on notice that they&amp;apost;re in the cross hairs, and make it clear that the Mexican government won&amp;apost;t negotiate with narco-terrorists.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>San Diego, California Mexican authorities are having an Eliot Ness moment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Imagine what it felt like for the famed U.S. federal agent to arrest legendary gangster Al Capone in 1929.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s probably close to how our southern neighbors feel now that they have in custody Miguel Angel Trevino Morales, leader of the brutal paramilitary drug cartel known as The Zetas.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The takedown is a major coup for Mexican President Enrique Peña Nieto, who came to office just seven months ago and returned the Institutional Revolutionary Party to power.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>I had the chance to meet with Peña Nieto in Mexico City in November a few weeks before he was sworn in, as part of a group of other Americans.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>It was clear from what we heard that he intended to implement a different strategy against the cartels than the one deployed by former President Felipe Calderon, who hailed from the rival National Action Party.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>His predecessor took the fight to the cartels, and the result was more than 70,000 deaths with some estimates reaching as high as 120,000.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Even before he was elected, Peña Nieto had signaled to Mexico&amp;apost;s voters that surrender wasn&amp;apost;t an option, that legalizing drugs wasn&amp;apost;t on the table, and that the fight against the cartels would continue -- with different methods and objectives.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The new plan was to continue to confiscate the traffickers&amp;apost; money and drugs while not driving up the body count.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Peña Nieto was supposed to focus less on capturing drug lords and more on curtailing violence and protecting the Mexican people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>I wanted to understand this terrain better.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>And so, before I left Mexico City, I met up with an old friend who also happens to be one of the best reporters in the business and certainly one of the most knowledgable about Mexico.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Alfredo Corchado is the Mexico City bureau chief for the Dallas Morning News and author of the acclaimed new book, &amp;quot;Midnight in Mexico: A Reporter&amp;apost;s Journey Through a Country&amp;apost;s Descent into Darkness.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>I asked him if Americans should be concerned now that there is a new sheriff in town.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>What is to stop Peña Nieto from giving up on this war?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;I don&amp;apost;t think they can afford to give up on it,&amp;quot; Corchado said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;That would be like conceding the country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>And yet, I also think the strategy of going after the cartels, confronting them head-on, is only going to generate more and more violence.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>This is supposed to be a new kind of drug war, although it bears a striking resemblance to the old war.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>As critics have pointed out, the number of casualties in first six months of Peña Nieto&amp;apost;s administration are almost identical to the number in the last six months of Calderon&amp;apost;s tenure in office.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Some Mexicans are wondering if, politics aside, the two major political parties in Mexico will turn out to be more or less the same in the war on drug trafficking.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>For a frame of reference from this side of the border, think about how -- in fighting the war on terror -- President Obama has borrowed liberally from President George W. Bush&amp;apost;s strategies for securing the U.S. homeland.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>And from the looks of it, Mexico&amp;apost;s enemy is just as determined as ours to wreak havoc and create nightmares.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In the last 10 years, the drug trade in Mexico has become much more brutal.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>A big reason for that is the arrival on the scene of The Zetas, and dangerous individuals like Trevino Morales who had a $5 million bounty on his head courtesy of the U.S. government.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The cartel is a relative newcomer in Mexico&amp;apost;s bloody drug trade.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Its origins date back to 1999, when elite commandos of the Mexican army decided that they would rather work for the drug traffickers than shoot it out with them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>So they deserted and became the muscle of the powerful and well-established Gulf Cartel.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>In 2010, Los Zetas went into business for themselves.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Three things set them apart: They have diversified their illicit activities beyond drug trafficking to include extortion, kidnapping, prostitution and other crimes; they&amp;apost;re more sophisticated and tech savvy than their rivals, according to U.S. authorities; and they are much more violent and apt to brutally terrorize the population -- with beheadings, torture, mass killings, grenades tossed into crowds, bodies hanging in the town square like pinatas at the mercado, and more.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Even with Trevino Morales behind bars, the horror is likely to continue.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>His brother is in line to succeed him.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The metaphor you hear from the cynics in Mexico is that when authorities cut off the head of the serpent, another head grows in its place.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Perhaps.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>But high-profile arrests like these do serve a purpose.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>They put the cartels on notice that they&amp;apost;re in the cross hairs, and make it clear that the Mexican government won&amp;apost;t negotiate with narco-terrorists.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>That chapter of the story is new, at least when you think about how cozy these parties were a few decades ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;For 50 or 60 years, we looked the other way,&amp;quot; said Corchado.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s like you don&amp;apost;t want to let the evil spirit out of the bottle.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s what we did in Mexico for too long, and now that it&amp;apost;s out, you&amp;apost;re going to have to face a monster.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Now that our neighbors are no longer looking the other way and they&amp;apost;re confronting their monster, Americans must continue to back them up so they don&amp;apost;t have to do it alone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Follow @CNNOpinion on Twitter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Join us at Facebook/CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
