<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="876" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/05/09/opinion/lemmon-education-nigeria/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-05-09 11:57:32" category="opinion" author="Gayle Tzemach Lemmon" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Opinion: Get girls&amp;apost; education out of the cross hairs</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2, 1">Gayle Tzemach Lemmon: Kidnapping girls during wartime is not new; the outrage is .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="20">Lemmon: Education creates stability and elevates girls, which is why terrorists hate it.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="46">Two-thirds of the world&amp;apost;s 800 million illiterate citizens are women, she says .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="18">She says more than ever, we can effectively support children&amp;apost;s education globally.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-08 22:42:28" annotation_time="35.199">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">The kidnapping of schoolgirls amid the horror of war is not new.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">The outrage is.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="4">More than 70 million children who should be receiving an education do not attend elementary school.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="2">Education is the foundation for prosperity, stability and security.</sentence>
      <sentence id="46" ids_highlights="3">A focus on ecosystems surrounding education is also critical given that a stunning two-thirds of the world&amp;apost;s 800 million illiterate citizens are women.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The kidnapping of schoolgirls amid the horror of war is not new.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The outrage is.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>And now the question is what is the world willing to do about it?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>For the issue is not only the future of schoolgirls abducted in the night at gunpoint and robbed of their lives, their education and their families.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>It is about the future of all of us in a world where seeking an education means risking your life.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The extremist movement Boko Haram has long laid plunder to schools.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>And it is not girls alone who sit in the cross hairs: For months, boys have died in their beds in Nigeria as the world went about its business.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>In February, Boko Haram fighters reportedly abducted 25 girls as they killed their way through the town of Konduga.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>One line of hell in a story of savagery and murder.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>But the kidnapping of up to 300 girls from the Chibok Government Girls Secondary School three weeks ago finally may have shoved the world out of its apathy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>A story that the media initially ignored has become a cause for citizens, activists and protesters in Nigeria and around the world, all determined to shake the world out of its indifference.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Reading the words of a mother whose daughter was set on becoming a doctor and is now missing somewhere in the hands of Boko Haram, it is hard to remain unmoved.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am so very sad because the government of Nigeria did not take care of our children and does not now care about our children.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>... She is my first-born, the best.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>... What am I to do as a mother?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Education has long been in the cross hairs of extremists.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>But the world has rarely acted to stop its suffocation, despite the fact that, as U.S. Education Secretary Arne Duncan has noted, &amp;quot;low educational attainment is one of the few statistically significant predictors of violence.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>More than 70 million children who should be receiving an education do not attend elementary school.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>More than half of them live in countries scarred by conflict.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Education is the foundation for prosperity, stability and security.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>And for too long, the world has watched as the right to go to school has been rolled back in exactly the places that most need the progress it brings.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Few knew of Malala Yousafzai&amp;apost;s valiant campaign to simply keep girls in school before Pakistani Taliban dared to try to kill her at close range.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>In Afghanistan under the Taliban, girls&amp;apost; schools closed immediately and a whole generation of future teachers and doctors saw their hopes extinguished.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Nearly three years ago, Khan Mohammad, head of the Porak girls&amp;apost; school in Afghanistan&amp;apost;s Logar province, fought hard to keep his institution for girls operating despite Taliban threats.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>As a reward for his valiant act of defiance, he received a bullet in the head in front of his home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Nor is this the first or only time this has happened in Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Joseph Kony, leader of the so-called Lord&amp;apost;s Resistance Army, stole children to use as soldiers and sex slaves.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>When she was just a girl studying at the St. Charles School for Girls in Uganda, &amp;quot;Margaret&amp;quot; and her fellow students were abducted by Kony to grow his clan and add babies to his ranks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The LRA leader picked five of the girls himself, including Margaret.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>As she tells it in a wrenching interview, the &amp;quot;girls were distributed among the soldiers.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>And if you tried to escape, &amp;quot;they would kill you right away.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>By the time government soldiers rescued Margaret from a Kony camp years later, she could no longer afford school fees and had little chance for earning the money she needed to support her baby boy fathered by Kony.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Her chance to have the future she dreamed of was dead.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>A loss that was not just hers, but ours, given the shared dividends created by investing in girls.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The numbers tell the story: Education is among the most potent anti-poverty vaccines.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>For girls, the numbers are startling: A World Bank study found that boosting girls&amp;apost; levels of education could lead to a gain in their lifetime earnings &amp;quot;equivalent to up to 68% of annual gross domestic product.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Every year of schooling that went beyond the average boosted growth by 0.6% each year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>And the gains came from even small advances.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Even a small gain in the amount of secondary education girls received raised annual incomes by .3% per capita.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>For a long time, the world has remained stunningly indifferent to the fate of girls and boys in pockets of the world it thought it would never have to face, even when those corners were found in poor, rural corners of the very same country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>But if the spread of globalization has taught us anything, it is that a cold in one room can lead to an outbreak of full-blown flu in another.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>The world&amp;apost;s future health depends more than ever on the education its youngest citizens receive.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Every one of us can make a difference in supporting children&amp;apost;s education all around the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>A quick online donation of time and funds can support NGOs such as Room to Read and larger organizations such as CARE and PLAN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Many NGOs focus on education, including initiatives such as Gordon Brown&amp;apost;s Education Without Borders, which is working to get refugee children into classrooms.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>A focus on ecosystems surrounding education is also critical given that a stunning two-thirds of the world&amp;apost;s 800 million illiterate citizens are women.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Recent work from NGO GiveDirectly as well as a pilot program from the government in Bangladesh showed that the power of small amounts of cash -- either with or without strings attached -- can help put more power in the hands of girls and make it easier for them to stay in school.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Letters and calls to Congress can keep the pressure on members to keep this issue at the fore.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>And pressure on Congress can also keep foreign aid funded and support for programs such as conditional cash transfers to keep girls in school front and center.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>A better-educated world is a healthier, wealthier and safer one for everyone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>It is in our interest to see girls in school and out of the cross hairs of extremist fighters seeking to delete modernity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Their battle is our battle.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>You have only to care about your own children&amp;apost;s future to have a stake in the fight ahead.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>Follow us on Twitter @CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>Join us on Facebook/CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
