<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="878" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/06/24/opinion/begala-hillary-clinton/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-06-24 12:37:36" category="opinion" author="Paul Begala" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Opinion: Hillary Clinton is no Mitt Romney</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="11">Paul Begala: Democrats have tradition of electing aristocratic populists like Kennedy, FDR.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="17">Why is Hillary Clinton taking heat for relative wealth? Voters know what&amp;apost;s in her heart, he says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="21, 20">He says Democrats like FDR long seen as champions of working people; same with Clinton.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="22">Begala: Clinton is no Romney; she&amp;apost;s long been tireless advocate for middle class.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-21 12:02:17" annotation_time="109.993">
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="1">Democrats have a tradition of electing aristocratic populists.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="2">Voters want to know what&amp;apost;s in her heart and what&amp;apost;s on her mind, not what&amp;apost;s in her wallet.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="3">FDR, JFK, Jay Rockefeller and all the other wealthy Democrats were seen as champions of working people.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="3">Same with Clinton.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="4">All her life, she has been a tireless advocate for the middle class and those struggling to get into the middle class.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>There&amp;apost;s a great story about Democratic icon Ted Kennedy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>When he was first running to succeed his brother John in the Senate, he was attacked for being a child of privilege.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>It was true.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Kennedy had nannies and nursemaids and private schools.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>He&amp;apost;d hobnobbed with ambassadors and princes and popes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>So the story -- perhaps not even true, but what the heck -- is that young Teddy was campaigning outside a factory in the predawn chill.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>As he shook hands with the working men, one stopped him and said, &amp;quot;So you&amp;apost;re young Kennedy?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>They say you haven&amp;apost;t worked a day in your life.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>To which Kennedy shrugged and answered, &amp;quot;I suppose that&amp;apost;s true.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>And the man replied, &amp;quot;You ain&amp;apost;t missed a thing.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Democrats have a tradition of electing aristocratic populists.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Franklin Roosevelt and John F. Kennedy were patricians.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>And one of the senior Democrats in the Senate today is as rich as a Rockefeller.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>His name is Jay Rockefeller.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Since 1977, first as governor of West Virginia, then senator, he has been elected and re-elected by the coal miners and farm families of West Virginia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>So the current hyperventilation over Hillary Clinton&amp;apost;s comments about her relative wealth and her lucrative book and speaking deals misses the point.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Voters want to know what&amp;apost;s in her heart and what&amp;apost;s on her mind, not what&amp;apost;s in her wallet.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Clinton was already wealthy when she ran for president in 2008.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Yet in the primary in Pennsylvania -- a bastion of blue-collar voters -- she bested Barack Obama by 12 points among voters earning between $30,000 and $50,000 a year, according to CNN exit polls.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>FDR, JFK, Jay Rockefeller and all the other wealthy Democrats were seen as champions of working people.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Same with Clinton.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>All her life, she has been a tireless advocate for the middle class and those struggling to get into the middle class.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>From her days at the Children&amp;apost;s Defense Fund to her advocacy for the rights of women and girls around the world, Clinton has a consistent record of fighting for middle-class economics and middle-class values.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>As an adviser to the super PAC that hammered Mitt Romney&amp;apost;s business record, let me explain why Clinton&amp;apost;s case is different.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The issue was never how much money Romney had; it was how he made that money.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>When you amass a megafortune in part by taking over companies, loading them with debt, plunging them into bankruptcy while paying yourself millions -- well, folks don&amp;apost;t like that.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>And when Romney combined that Gordon Gekko image with an agenda that included cutting taxes for the rich and making Medicare a voucher program, voters got the sense that he was not on their side.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>There is a dichotomy of elitism.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Republicans&amp;apost; downfall is economic elitism.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>For generations they&amp;apost;ve been seen as the party of the rich.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Democrats don&amp;apost;t have that problem.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Their Achilles&amp;apost; heel is cultural elitism: the sense that they value highfalutin&amp;apost; Ivy League degrees more than practical experience; that they look down their noses at folks who go to church, hunt and fish, and salute the flag.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Both are caricatures, to be sure.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>But as a Democratic strategist I am always more worried about cultural elitism than a Democrat&amp;apost;s wealth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>And remember: George W. Bush had degrees from both Harvard and Yale but was seen as a down-home guy you could have a beer with.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>There&amp;apost;s no doubt that this is a populist moment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Americans worry about the collapse of the American Dream and the shrinking of the middle class.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>If Clinton runs on an agenda of empowering working people -- with an increase in the minimum wage, equal pay for women, student debt relief, increased availability of child care, prekindergarten, and an end to tax breaks for corporations that ship jobs overseas -- few voters will care how fat her bank account is.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Read CNNOpinion&amp;apost;s new Flipboard magazine.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>