<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="884" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/07/02/opinion/ww1-no-end-furedi/index.html" date_published="2014-07-02 15:43:25" category="opinion" author="Frank Furedi, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Opinion: ISIS caliphate shows still no end to WW1</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">The period 1914-1945 was once described as a modern version of the Thirty Years War.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">This second Thirty Years War gave way to four decades-long Cold War, says Frank Furedi.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="21">Furedi: Origins of &amp;quot;Culture Wars&amp;quot; can be situated at some time around August 1914.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="32">Young Muslims embrace a call to arms for a war of cultures, he adds.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-21 22:45:35" annotation_time="63.282337">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">That is why many observers at the time described the period 1914-1945 as a modern version of the Thirty Years War.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">Yet this second Thirty Years War soon gave way to the four decades-long Cold War.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="3">That is why the origins of what is currently described as the Culture Wars can be situated at some time around August 1914.</sentence>
      <sentence id="32" ids_highlights="4">Young Western Muslims self-consciously reject the values of the communities where they grew up and embrace a call to arms for a war of cultures.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>It is widely recognized that the signing of the Armistice in 1918 did not put an end to the drama that began in 1914.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Traditional geopolitical rivalries continued but now overlapped with competing ideologies of fascism and Stalinism to foster a climate of permanent war.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>That is why many observers at the time described the period 1914-1945 as a modern version of the Thirty Years War.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Yet this second Thirty Years War soon gave way to the four decades-long Cold War.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>For a very brief moment the demise of the Cold War appeared to bring to an end the conflicts unleashed on the battlefields in 1914.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>But this &amp;quot;End of History&amp;quot; moment was brief.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Today we are in the midst of a conflict originally designated as a &amp;quot;War on Terror&amp;quot; but which has been rebranded by the American government as the &amp;quot;Long War&amp;quot; and more recently as &amp;quot;Overseas Contingency Operation.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The conflicts unleashed in 1914 were not confined to the military sphere.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>They were also a battle of ideas and a clash of cultures.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The story that began in 1914 was influenced by a crisis of meaning that afflicted the political and cultural elites of western societies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>A powerful mood of estrangement and disorientation dominated cultural life.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>In this moment of confusion even artists and intellectual sought meaning through fighting for a cause -- even a military one.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Some of the most enthusiastic supporters of the war were motivated by a disposition to react against what they took to be the soulless world of capitalist modernity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Stefan Zweig, the renowned Austrian novelist, playwright and well-known pacifist lived to see two world wars.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>When the Great War broke out in 1914, he along with almost all European intellectuals, supported his nation&amp;apost;s war effort.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Later, with a hint of embarrassment he recalled the sense of excitement and celebration that the news of the impending conflict provoked among people.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;And to be truthful, I must acknowledge that there was a majestic, rapturous, and even seductive something in this first outbreak of the people from which one could escape only with difficulty,&amp;quot; he recalled.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>World War I would be the last time that a significant body of intellectuals and artists would seek existential meaning on the battlefield.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>But conflicts over norms and values, which were crystallized through their quest for meaning continues to this day.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Indeed on hindsight it is evident that the Great War was a catalyst for eroding the prevailing system of meaning and helped intensify a clash of values.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>That is why the origins of what is currently described as the Culture Wars can be situated at some time around August 1914.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Culture became politicized and geopolitical ambitions were framed through appeals to a &amp;quot;way of life.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Today, very few respectable intellectuals would be caught waving the flag.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Instead of the flag, competing groups flaunt their identity and instead of celebrating their way of life they acclaim their lifestyle.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>With the demise of old ideologies the politicization of culture has acquired an increasingly unrestrained character.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>It is worth noting that most of the high-profile divisive issues -- family life, gay marriage, abortion, assisted suicide, multiculturalism -- express conflicts over cultural values.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>These symbolic struggles over the constitution of legitimate lifestyles continually exacerbate the fragmentation of social life.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>What&amp;apost;s more disturbing is that such struggles increasingly extend into global affairs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The current conflict between Russia and its Western opponents is almost entirely conducted through the medium of culture.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The denunciation of Putin as an authoritarian homophobe is self-consciously countered by the claim that Russia stands firm as the bastion of traditional values.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Like Putin, many Muslims also take their stand on hallow grounds of tradition.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Young Western Muslims self-consciously reject the values of the communities where they grew up and embrace a call to arms for a war of cultures.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Jihadist videos often communicate a simple message -- which is that the Jihad provides quest for meaning.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>As I write, the war drums are again beating.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Abu Bakr al Baghdadi, the head of ISIS, has declared the establishment of a new caliphate in the Middle East.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>His object is to abolish one legacy of World War I, the border between Syria and Iraq.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>There is still no end in sight to the Great War.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
