<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="855" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/08/15/opinion/opinion-smoking-packaging/index.html " date_published="2012-08-15 17:18:07" category="opinion" author="Stephen Cheliotis, special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Opinion: Australian tobacco packaging laws misguided</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="9">Brands are major drivers of economic growth, says Stephen Cheliotis.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="20">By making packaging a doddle to copy it gives rise to counterfeit cigarettes, he says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="27">Cheliotis: &amp;quot;Removing the ability to identify one product from another is a state gone too far&amp;quot;.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-13 17:30:23" annotation_time="16.520666">
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="1">Brands are major drivers of economic growth, and without them a company&amp;apost;s incentive to innovate is removed.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="2">By making packaging a doddle to copy it gives rise to counterfeit cigarettes, even more dangerous and cheaper than genuine brands, making it easier in the process for young people to start and continue their habit.</sentence>
      <sentence id="27" ids_highlights="3">By all means ban smoking in public places and create slow cultural change, but removing the ability to identify one product from another and trashing intellectual property rights is a state gone too far.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>London I&amp;apost;ve never profited from branding cigarettes, but the decision by the Australian government to pass a law removing brand colors and logos from packaging concerns me.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Good intentions almost always lead to unintended consequences; banned songs enjoy a boost as consumers clamor to rebel or see what the fuss is about, and what about prohibition?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Will the lack of a red triangle really be less glamorous to the young than packaging shouting: &amp;quot;&amp;apost;This product is scandalous!&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>to &amp;apost;authorities?&amp;apost;&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>And where does it end?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>What about alcohol, fatty foods, sugary drinks, and sweets?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Should they all be sold in plain packaging or unbranded?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a slippery slope to a nanny state, where consumer choice is curtailed and businesses restricted.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Brands are major drivers of economic growth, and without them a company&amp;apost;s incentive to innovate is removed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Why have the best or safest product if no one can distinguish you from the rest?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Equally, why spend on corporate social responsibility (CSR)?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Brands empower and enable consumers to select those companies they approve of.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The environmental policy of a company or how they treat their employees influences my decision to buy a given branded product.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Without the brand, however, that power is removed and, by default, the business&amp;apost;s interest in CSR.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The business&amp;apost;s fear factor and liability is reduced substantially.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Furthermore, trust is important to brands and they have to be careful not to breach that trust or consumers will vote accordingly, with their wallets, as they decide the source of a given product is no longer reliable or safe.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Obviously tobacco kills, but at least known brands have to uphold certain standards (for example the amount of nicotine contained in each cigarette) so consumers&amp;apost; trust can be retained.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>According to the BBC in January, counterfeit cigarettes being sold in Sussex contained abnormally high levels of cancer-causing chemicals.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>There are many similar stories, including the UK&amp;apost;s City of Stoke County Council highlighting that &amp;quot;people should be aware that fake tobacco is even more hazardous than the real thing.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>By making packaging a doddle to copy it gives rise to counterfeit cigarettes, even more dangerous and cheaper than genuine brands, making it easier in the process for young people to start and continue their habit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>We can assume that smokers in Australia generally understand the health consequences of smoking, so they are making an informed choice.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Why not allow them to choose which manufacturers they buy from too, rather than potentially opening the floodgates to criminal products and non-liable sellers?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Cigarette companies in Australia and elsewhere are restricted in their marketing, so are building hardly any new brand value and awareness.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>I cannot imagine building a new brand or reaching new audiences without undertaking marketing, so these brands are simply identifiers and guarantors of, at the very least, a certain standard of cigarette or tobacco.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Those with any real brand value have so principally amongst older smokers, who remember the past marketing; do younger audiences recall the Marlboro man and pick that brand because of that campaign?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Not likely.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>By all means ban smoking in public places and create slow cultural change, but removing the ability to identify one product from another and trashing intellectual property rights is a state gone too far.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Cigarettes are damaging, but restricting a legal business and consumer&amp;apost;s freedom and choice of legal products is a dangerous precedent.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>If they are that bad make them illegal!</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Otherwise, if this law is upheld, expect debates about other legal categories and products in due course and a future of identikit products, in identikit packaging from less accountable businesses (or in many cases illegal ones).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
