<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="937" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/09/14/opinion/york-libya-youtube/index.html" date_published="2012-09-14 20:12:51" category="opinion" author="Jillian C. York, Special to CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Should Google censor an anti-Islam video?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">An anti-Islam video sparked protests in Libya and Egypt; in Libya, violence erupted.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Jillian York: YouTube decided to block access to the video in the two countries.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="11">She says it is not in Google&amp;apost;s best interest to be arbiter of what&amp;apost;s acceptable .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="31">York: Google will have to explain why it censors videos in some cases but not others.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-08 23:25:45" annotation_time="987.434" mapping_time_divergence="125.0">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1, 2">Just hours after the U.S. consulate came under attack in Libya, resulting in the death of the U.S. ambassador and three of his colleagues, YouTube blocked access to an anti-Islam video that sparked protests in Egypt and Libya.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="3">Although restricting the video in the two countries might seem tempting in the wake of the horrific violence that occurred in Libya, it is in the best interest of neither the company nor, arguably, the citizens of those countries for Google to be the arbiter of acceptability.</sentence>
      <sentence id="31" ids_highlights="4">Instead, by placing itself in the role of arbiter, Google is now vulnerable to demands from a variety of parties and will have to explain why it sees censorship as the right solution in some cases but not in others.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Just hours after the U.S. consulate came under attack in Libya, resulting in the death of the U.S. ambassador and three of his colleagues, YouTube blocked access to an anti-Islam video that sparked protests in Egypt and Libya.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The video, which was made in America and crudely characterized the Prophet Mohammed, understandably offended many Muslims.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>It would appear that the decision by Google -- which owns YouTube -- was based not on an order by either government but on its own concerns.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;We work hard to create a community everyone can enjoy and which also enables people to express different opinions,&amp;quot; YouTube said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;This can be a challenge because what&amp;apost;s OK in one country can be offensive elsewhere.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>This video - which is widely available on the web - is clearly within our guidelines and so will stay on YouTube.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>However, given the very difficult situation in Libya and Egypt we have temporarily restricted access in both countries.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Our hearts are with the families of the people murdered in yesterday&amp;apost;s attack in Libya.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Although the video remains accessible for the rest of the world, users in Egypt and Libya will, upon attempting to access it, encounter a message that it is not available in their jurisdiction.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>This is the same mechanism used when a copyright holder restricts content to a certain country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Although restricting the video in the two countries might seem tempting in the wake of the horrific violence that occurred in Libya, it is in the best interest of neither the company nor, arguably, the citizens of those countries for Google to be the arbiter of acceptability.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>When it comes to copyrighted content, YouTube is required to abide by the law, specifically the Digital Millenium Copyright Act, which allows a copyright holder to report content posted by other users as belonging to them (it also allows for a rebuttal).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>YouTube has also taken down content under informal pressure from governments, such as in 2010, when it removed clips reportedly linked to al Qaeda after a speech in which British Security Minister Baroness Pauline Neville-Jones stated that such videos &amp;quot;incite cold-blooded murder and as such are contrary to the public good.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>When it comes to that type of content or the content in the video in question, the fact of the matter is that there are few regulations by which YouTube must abide.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>In the United States, the content of the video would be deemed protected under the First Amendment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>As an American company, YouTube itself also has a right to speech, which includes the right to make its own policies regarding what types of speech it deems appropriate to host.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Those policies have come under fire before.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>In 2007, a Turkish court ordered YouTube to be blocked in the country after the company refused to take down videos deemed insulting to the country&amp;apost;s founder; the ban was reversed two years later.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>YouTube faced a similar ban in Pakistan in 2010 after refusing to take down cartoons depicting the Prophet Mohammed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>But while some governments think YouTube is too lax, some of its users have felt it is too restrictive.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Egyptian human rights activist Wael Abbas found his account deactivated in 2007 after posting violent content depicting police brutality in his country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Eventually, his account was restored and YouTube shifted its policies in response to his and other users&amp;apost; complaints, allowing content containing violence to be posted under an exception for videos that are &amp;quot;educational&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;documentary&amp;quot; in nature.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>This policy later enabled activists in Egypt, Tunisia, Syria and elsewhere to post documentation of regime violence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In the current case, YouTube has stated that the video does not violate its terms of service.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>So if the video does not violate the company&amp;apost;s rules and YouTube didn&amp;apost;t receive an order from the two countries&amp;apost; governments (as far as we know), then the only explanation is that YouTube is determining on its own what serves the best interest of Libyans and Egyptians.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>This is, indeed, a rare move from the company and may eventually backfire.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Take another case from this year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>When Pakistan blocked Twitter after the company refused to take down offensive content, citizens were outraged, fearing it as a precursor to censorship during the election period.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Had Twitter simply taken down the content, the story would have slipped by without notice; instead, the outrage of citizens forced the government to reverse its decision in less than a day.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Google should take the lead from Twitter, a smaller and younger company that, when faced with similar concerns, has stood strong, issuing a policy stating that content would be &amp;quot;withheld&amp;quot; in a certain country only in the face of a valid legal order and that the ban would be communicated transparently to all users.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Instead, by placing itself in the role of arbiter, Google is now vulnerable to demands from a variety of parties and will have to explain why it sees censorship as the right solution in some cases but not in others.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Follow us on Twitter @CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Join us on Facebook/CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
