<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="894" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/06/28/opinion/mcpherson-aaron-hernandez/index.html" date_published="2013-06-28 22:10:51" category="opinion" author="Donald McPherson, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Opinion: NFL doesn&amp;apost;t have answers on Hernandez</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Don McPherson: Many are shocked that Aaron Hernandez was charged with murder.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">McPherson: When players commit heinous crimes, the NFL doesn&amp;apost;t have answers .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="26">He says there is little the league can do to influence the behavior of its players off field.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="36">McPherson: NFL players are products of our collective society.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-26 08:03:45" annotation_time="63.529">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Many were shocked this week when New England Patriots player Aaron Hernandez was arrested and charged with first-degree murder and linked to an unsolved double-homicide case from 2012.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">When players commit crimes such as murder, looking to the league for answers is not the solution.</sentence>
      <sentence id="26" ids_highlights="3">The problem for the NFL is that there is little the league can do to influence the behavior of its current players.</sentence>
      <sentence id="36" ids_highlights="4">NFL players are products of our collective society and they take center stage in one of the most successful enterprises of our society.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Many were shocked this week when New England Patriots player Aaron Hernandez was arrested and charged with first-degree murder and linked to an unsolved double-homicide case from 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The tone in the sports community has been muted because this is occurring during the off-season and the impact on the &amp;quot;game&amp;quot; is minimal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>There are many unanswered questions about the Hernandez case.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>What does it tell us about the intersection of sports and the violent and sometimes criminal behavior of athletes off the field?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>With a few exceptions, the National Football League&amp;apost;s governance of players&amp;apost; lives is restricted to behaviors that impact the game and the business of the league.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Players who violate the law and the rights of others are subject to the much broader laws that govern every citizen.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>When players commit crimes such as murder, looking to the league for answers is not the solution.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The Patriots have quickly cut ties with Hernandez but are faced with a &amp;quot;dead money&amp;quot; issue (the ironic name for money tied to a player no longer with the team, that counts against a team&amp;apost;s salary cap).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>On the field, they are left with a more uncertain hole at the tight end position.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>There&amp;apost;s a sentiment that on-field performance is all that we should be concerned with when it comes to sports and athletes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>No more was that on display than this past Super Bowl where the most popular player on the field was Ray Lewis, who 13 years ago was in a similar position as Aaron Hernandez is today.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Lewis was in jail charged with murder.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>While he was later exonerated, Ray Lewis has been, in part, redeemed by football.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>As incidents of violence increase in volume and severity it is becoming more difficult to ignore the social transgressions of athletes simply because they entertain us.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The bigger question is: What is the tipping point?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The dissonance regarding sports in our society is palpable.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The NFL is the most successful and powerful sports entity in the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>For many, it symbolizes the greatest elements of the meritocracy of sports and business.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Success is built on sound principle, discipline and character.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The NFL&amp;apost;s success is not simply due to the popularity of the game itself, but the business of monetizing the game.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The players are merely widgets in that business.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>However, as the NFL continues to grow in revenue and appeal, the off-field behavior of some of the players threaten to tarnish the pristine veneer of the brand.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The sport has an esteemed place in our culture by helping to build communities, teaching young people leadership and discipline, and promoting team spirit.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>But why is it that so many successful athletes -- those who have reached the pinnacle of their game -- seem to lack discipline in their lives away from the game?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Why is there such a glaring discrepancy?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The problem for the NFL is that there is little the league can do to influence the behavior of its current players.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The NFL is not the nurturer of men; it is not responsible for the attitudes and behaviors of the men its teams employ.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>As the great former UCLA basketball coach John Wooden once said, &amp;quot;sports don&amp;apost;t build character.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>They reveal it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>While the players on the field are stars of the business, they are not stars because of their depth of character or values and judgment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Their individual moral compass is their own, even if the sport has some influence over their perception of the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Their stardom lies in the volume of exposure the business affords them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>And, like the mega-salaries that make headlines, the business is such that the individual doesn&amp;apost;t matter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>What matters is that the individual can get the job done in the context of the business.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>And, in this case, character and discipline off the field have no relevance to success on the field.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>NFL players are products of our collective society and they take center stage in one of the most successful enterprises of our society.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>When we hear about Hernandez or Javon Belcher, we shouldn&amp;apost;t assume that it&amp;apost;s solely an NFL problem.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a larger societal issue.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>No child is born to be an NFL player.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The young men who grow up and are recognized for their talents need to be more than warriors on the field.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>The positive influences outside of their athletic lives need to be stronger and at every stage of their lives.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>The pursuit of excellence can exist in all aspects of a young athlete&amp;apost;s life and it should begin with civility before any games are played.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Follow us on Twitter @CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Join us on Facebook/CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
