<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="936" link="http://www.cnn.com/2011/10/29/opinion/martin-sex-education/index.html" date_published="2011-10-29 04:11:56" category="opinion" author="Roland Martin, CNN Contributor" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Sex education should be mandatory in all schools</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">NYC should be commended for mandating sex education, Roland Martin says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">Safe sex and abstinence must be dealt with in an educational setting, he says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="19">Martin: While abstinence is definitely safest, we have to accept reality.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 09:41:42" annotation_time="42889.992">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">The city of New York should be commended for not bowing to the blowhards and confronting the reality of sex in America by mandating a sex education curriculum beginning in 2012.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">Whether it&amp;apost;s safe sex practices or even abstinence, all of these issues must be dealt with in an educational setting, because when we look at the teen pregnancy rates, sexually transmitted diseases, including HIV/AIDS, it only makes sense to have as much education as possible.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="3">Abstinence is definitely the safest of all safe sex measures, but there is also a point when we have to accept reality.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>There are few things more annoying than listening to ignorant, whiny parents complain about a school district teaching their children about sex.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>How in the world do we say it&amp;apost;s OK for schools to teach our children about math, science, history, and numerous other subjects, yet then get high and mighty with righteous indignation when biology is taken a step further to focus on sex?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Too many parents live in denial about their children having sex, and somehow saying you&amp;apost;ll handle the tough stuff is living in fantasy land.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The city of New York should be commended for not bowing to the blowhards and confronting the reality of sex in America by mandating a sex education curriculum beginning in 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Whether it&amp;apost;s safe sex practices or even abstinence, all of these issues must be dealt with in an educational setting, because when we look at the teen pregnancy rates, sexually transmitted diseases, including HIV/AIDS, it only makes sense to have as much education as possible.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Taxes and death are considered two undeniably realities of life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>I would say that sex is right behind those two.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>I recall as an elementary student, as well as in middle school and high school, taking classes that dealt with sex.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Yes, elementary school.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>It was done properly and smartly, and was needed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Did it prevent children from getting pregnant too soon?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>I can&amp;apost;t say for sure.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>But I can definitely say knowing more about a topic than less is crucial.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Now let&amp;apost;s deal with the abstinence-only nuts who act as if anything else shouldn&amp;apost;t be taught.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Yes, I&amp;apost;m talking directly to The NYC Parents&amp;apost; Choice Coalition.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>They are upset with videos demonstrating how to put on a condom, as well as other aspects of the sex education curriculum.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Folks, y&amp;apost;all are flat out crazy if you want to encourage parents to opt out of sex education by making it more about abstinence and nothing else.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Why can&amp;apost;t both take place?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Abstinence is definitely the safest of all safe sex measures, but there is also a point when we have to accept reality.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Talk to school teachers and administrators and they will tell you that students as young as middle school are engaging in oral sex, and there is the belief that that really doesn&amp;apost;t count as sex.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Yet anyone with half a brain knows that to be the case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>If kids are out there having oral sex, they sure as heck need to know that doing so without protection can be life-altering.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>But such parents groups prefer to stick their heads in the sand.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>They find such talk unseemly and think such frankness should be left between child and parent.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Not me.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>As a Jesus lovin&amp;apost; Christian, I&amp;apost;m about real talk, and if that means dealing with sex directly, let&amp;apost;s go for it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Educators and city officials in New York should fully brace themselves for the onslaught.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Right-thinking folks are tired of seeing young folks coming back HIV-positive or dealing with a pregnancy at 16.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>I have nine nieces and four nephews, and I would be fully supportive of them being taught about sex education in school.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Forget shying from a tough subject.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>If we are going to equip our children for tomorrow, then sex needs to be dealt with in a smart, productive and educational setting by professionals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s clear that parents aren&amp;apost;t as dependable on some matters as they like to delude themselves into believing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
