<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="812" link="http://cnn.com/2013/05/27/opinion/opinion-ansari-iran-election" date_published="2013-05-27 14:48:30" category="opinion" author="Ali Ansari, Special for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Has Iranian regime learned nothing from 2009 election fiasco?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Iranian regime is keen to encourage the public to put the past behind them, Ali Ansari writes.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">He points out the consolidation of power around Supreme Leader Ayatollah Ali Khamenei.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="12">Ansari: Khamenei has been able to blame divisions on Ahmadinejad and his &amp;quot;deviant current&amp;quot;.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-14 17:01:43" annotation_time="83.1745">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">It reinforces a trend towards the consolidation of power around Supreme Leader Ayatollah Ali Khamenei and his acolytes, which has been taking place for the better part of a decade, and perhaps the real surprise is the fact is that there remain members of the elite who did not think this remorseless process would ultimately apply to them.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">Ever since the political catastrophe of 2009, when millions pored onto the streets to protest what was widely considered to be a highly fraudulent election process, the regime has been keen to encourage the public to put the past behind them and to look forward to these elections as a cathartic exercise during which political blemishes could be washed away.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="3">To date Khamenei has been able to blame divisions on Ahmadinejad and his &amp;quot;deviant current&amp;quot; on the one hand, and the foreign inspired sedition of Mir-Hussein Musavi and Mehdi Karrubi (still under house arrest) on the other.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Former President Ali Akbar Hashemi Rafsanjani&amp;apost;s abrupt fall from grace has taken many in political circles in Iran by surprise, further widening the gap between an increasingly insular and narrow hard-line elite and the rest of the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>It reinforces a trend towards the consolidation of power around Supreme Leader Ayatollah Ali Khamenei and his acolytes, which has been taking place for the better part of a decade, and perhaps the real surprise is the fact is that there remain members of the elite who did not think this remorseless process would ultimately apply to them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Ever since the political catastrophe of 2009, when millions pored onto the streets to protest what was widely considered to be a highly fraudulent election process, the regime has been keen to encourage the public to put the past behind them and to look forward to these elections as a cathartic exercise during which political blemishes could be washed away.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Rafsanjani&amp;apost;s dramatic last-minute entrance into the race, was seen by many as proof that some lessons had indeed been learnt.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>But if Rafsanjani was to galvanize the public, then his platform had to be radical and his boast that he had come to &amp;quot;save the nation&amp;quot; and effectively &amp;quot;reboot&amp;quot; the Islamic Republic, was certainly bold.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>However, the fact that he claimed that he had to ask permission to run, was indicative of how far the political realities of Iran had changed since he had last been president (1989-1997).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>No sooner had he registered than the bitter personal attacks came from the hard-liners; while others questioned just what the nature of the agreement with Khamenei had been, if any.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>But perhaps most galling was that for all the hype and excitement generated by his supporters, the public appeared unmoved.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Popular momentum might have developed, though the task would have been considerably harder than 2009 given the absence of a political infrastructure of street activists, (largely dismantled since 2009), and above all the sheer cynicism of the voting public.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Public apathy combined with the conceit of the new ruling class, to deliver a particularly brutal humiliation to Rafsanjani, barred apparently not for his political views, but for the rather less dignified reason that the members of the Guardian Council thought Rafsanjani too old to be able to bear the burden of office.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Rafsanjani&amp;apost;s dramatic entrance and precipitous fall has shone a light on the growing fractures within elite politics in Iran.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>To date Khamenei has been able to blame divisions on Ahmadinejad and his &amp;quot;deviant current&amp;quot; on the one hand, and the foreign inspired sedition of Mir-Hussein Musavi and Mehdi Karrubi (still under house arrest) on the other.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Few expected Ahmadinejad&amp;apost;s protégé, Esfandyar Rahim Mashaie, to survive the vetting process -- other that is, than Ahmadinejad, for whom being on the &amp;quot;outside&amp;quot; must be an uncomfortable experience.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Similarly, if slightly more realistically, few of Rafsanjani&amp;apost;s supporters considered him vulnerable.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>He remained after all a pillar of the establishment, even if two of his children had been hounded into jail and he had effectively been ostracized over the past four years for his tentative support of the Green Movement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>It says much of the &amp;quot;wishful thinking&amp;quot; that remains prevalent, that they thought this a political virtue.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Firm in the belief that the Islamic Republic faced an existential threat, they had retained their faith in the integrity of a system that has long since transformed beyond recognition into a sacred autocracy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Indeed the unpredictability of the Iranian political system is not a reflection of its inherent &amp;apost;democracy&amp;apost;, but of the absence of the rule of law and the growing identification of power in the person of Khamenei.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Both the Guardian Council&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;rulings&amp;quot; (which it should be stressed are neither published nor explained) and the fact they can be overturned on the whims of the Supreme Leader, are indicative of this harsh reality.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>What we are left with is a tightly controlled &amp;quot;election&amp;quot; with a dry and uninteresting field.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Of the eight ratified candidates, one is a nonentity, (Mohammad Gharazi); two are ostensible &amp;quot;moderates&amp;quot; lacking in charisma and therefore non-threatening, (Hassan Rouhani and Mohammad Reza Aref); one is an independent Principle-ist (Mohsen Rezaei) who likes to speak his mind but on past performance is unlikely to garner votes (real or imagined); while the remaining four are self proclaimed acolytes of the Leader.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Of these four, two have been highlighted as the probable annointees: Saeed Jalili, the current head of the National Security Council, and Mohammad Ghalibaf, the mayor of Tehran.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Jalili is widely assumed to be the favorite and his web presence is suitably polished and indicative of considerable preparation, though quite who the audience for this is, given the current restrictions on internet access in the run-up to the election, remains unclear.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Jalili is perhaps closest ideologically to the Supreme Leader.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>For this particular puritan, the crisis Iran faces is not existential, it is an opportunity to be seized and a trial to be welcomed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Ghalibaf, who once fancied himself as Iran&amp;apost;s answer to Tom Cruise, has had his popular credibility bruised by the sudden release of a recording of a speech he allegedly gave to members of the Basij militia bragging about how much he enjoyed getting on his motorbike and thumping students.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Ghalibaf has vigorously dismissed the recording as a malicious smear, but it says much about current politics that there are many who find it credible.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The real question of course is the source of the leak; and herein perhaps lies the real significance of recent developments.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>In 2009, the regime lost the people; it now appears to be in the process of divesting itself of its traditional elite.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>How the newly disenfranchised react will be interesting to watch.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>This may be the real legacy of the &amp;quot;election&amp;quot; of 2013.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
