<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="791" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/12/13/opinion/opinion-africa-survey-mandela-ogunlesi/index.html" date_published="2013-12-13 11:54:37" category="opinion" author="Tolu Ogunlesi, a blogger and newspaper columnist" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Corruption is Africa&amp;apost;s biggest challenge</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">The choice of mobile as a medium for CNN&amp;apost;s survey shows how things have changed, says Ogunlesi.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12">A semblance of democracy has taken root in many places that were once a byword for anarchy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="24">The fact that 37 percent think corruption is Africa&amp;apost;s biggest challenge is more telling that general optimism.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="29">Mandela will remain a towering icon of moral strength, but for economic freedom, the battle continues.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-14 15:36:06" annotation_time="35.747">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">The choice of mobile as the medium for CNN&amp;apost;s Africa-wide survey of Mandela-related opinion shows how much has changed across the continent in the two decades between Mandela&amp;apost;s presidency, and his death.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">A semblance of democracy has taken root in most of those places that were once a byword for anarchy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="3">The predictability of the responses -- 37 percent of respondents think corruption is Africa&amp;apost;s biggest challenge, 23 percent think its rising inequality, 16 percent think its poverty -- paints, in my opinion, a truer picture than the confident optimism about the future.</sentence>
      <sentence id="29" ids_highlights="4">He will of course continue to be a towering icon of moral strength, the face of one of the most outstanding feats of political freedom in recent human history.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The choice of mobile as the medium for CNN&amp;apost;s Africa-wide survey of Mandela-related opinion shows how much has changed across the continent in the two decades between Mandela&amp;apost;s presidency, and his death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Imagine attempting to do a phone survey in 1994, when a country like Nigeria -- Africa&amp;apost;s most populous -- had fewer than half-a-million landlines for its more than 100 million people, and mobile phones were mostly unheard of.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>(At this time of course land-lines were a staple across the developed world.).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The dire state of technology was of course a reflection of wider -- political -- dysfunction.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>While multi-party democracy was taking root in South Africa, only about five of Africa&amp;apost;s 54 countries were not being ruled by dictators, most of whom did little more than loot the treasury and kill everyone perceived to be an enemy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Indeed the circumstances of most African countries shared nothing in common with the peace and reconciliation and prospects of prosperity that the election of Nelson Mandela symbolized in 1994.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>1994 was the year that Robert Kaplan&amp;apost;s dystopian essay, &amp;quot;The Coming Anarchy,&amp;quot; appeared in the Atlantic Monthly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>In it Kaplan wrote: &amp;apost;&amp;quot;West Africa is reverting to the Africa of the Victorian Atlas.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>It consists now of a series of coastal trading posts, such as Freetown and Conakry, and an interior that, owing to violence, volatility and disease, is again becoming, as Graham Greene once observed, &amp;apost;blank&amp;apost; and &amp;apost;unexplored&amp;apost;.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>1994 was also the year that Rwanda fell apart -- almost a million people hacked to death in a matter of months.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Fast forward to 2013, and a lot has changed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>A semblance of democracy has taken root in most of those places that were once a byword for anarchy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Many of those wars have ended, and the same continent in which negative economic growth was a badge of honor now boasts of more countries on the list of fastest-growing economies in the world than any other.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Where once the continent was defined by its AK-47s -- the Economist&amp;apost;s famous Hopeless Continent cover in 2000 featured a child soldier clutching a rifle -- it is now more likely to be defined by those mobile phones that have made this survey possible.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Perhaps it is then easy to see why the majority of respondents in the survey -- 64 percent -- are more optimistic about the future than they were when Mandela became President in 1994.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Then again it&amp;apost;s important to note that only a tenth of the surveyed population is older than 30.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Which means that most were not even teenagers yet when Mandela became President.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>And you should know that across the world, the Millennial generation (as those born post-1980 are known), armed with their mobile phones and social networking, seem to be an unshakably optimistic lot.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Why that is so, is up for debate -- there are any number of articles on the Internet asking the question: &amp;quot;Why are Millennials so optimistic?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>A 2013 Gallup poll found that only a quarter of American 18 to 29 year olds believe their standard of living is declining.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>In the CNN-Jana poll, even fewer -- 15 percent -- failed to succumb to optimism.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Overwhelming as it is, however, that optimism fails to mask the depth of Africa&amp;apost;s subsisting problems: The facts of jobless growth and rising inequality; that democracy is still largely a theoretical principle and government accountability mostly a mirage.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a good thing the poll asks what respondents think is the biggest challenge their country is dealing with.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The predictability of the responses -- 37 percent of respondents think corruption is Africa&amp;apost;s biggest challenge, 23 percent think its rising inequality, 16 percent think its poverty -- paints, in my opinion, a truer picture than the confident optimism about the future.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Not much has happened in the last few years to inspire much confidence that there will be a marked improvement in the coming years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Youth unemployment in Mandela&amp;apost;s South Africa is one of the highest in the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>And it&amp;apost;s a similar story across the continent: Fantastic economic growth jostling with technological revolutions everywhere you turn, but very little benefit trickling down to the lives of ordinary people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>In truth Mandela being alive or dead will mean very little to the daily realities of most people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>He will of course continue to be a towering icon of moral strength, the face of one of the most outstanding feats of political freedom in recent human history.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>But for economic freedom, the battle continues, in South Africa and elsewhere, and the end is nowhere in sight.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Which is perhaps why citizens will be needing all the optimism they can lay their minds on.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
