<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="836" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/03/28/opinion/kennedy-cesar-chavez-new-york/index.html?hpt=hp_bn7" date_published="2014-03-28 11:57:52" category="opinion" author="Kerry Kennedy, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Kerry Kennedy: How New York could benefit from their own Cesar Chavez</title>
  <keywords>kerry kennedy,cesar chavez,farm workers,agricultural labor relations act,robert kennedy</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Farm workers suffer from laws California addressed nearly half a century ago.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">Kennedy: You should see how farm workers are treated.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="16">Passing new bill is first step to addressing human rights violations.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="26">All of us have the opportunity to join the struggle today.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-15 09:38:25" annotation_time="28.631">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">And so today -- in the state where my father served as senator and where I now live -- our farm workers suffer from the leftover Jim Crow laws that California addressed nearly half a century ago.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">If you think what farms do to the geese is bad, you should see how they treat the farm workers.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="3">The Farmworkers Fair Labor Practices Act, passed by the State Assembly last year and languishing in the State Senate, is the first step to addressing some of these egregious violations of international human rights New York farm workers still face.</sentence>
      <sentence id="26" ids_highlights="4">All of us still have the opportunity to join the struggle today.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Forty-six years ago this month, my father joined Cesar Chavez in Delano, California, to share the Eucharist and end Chavez&amp;apost;s 1968 fast for farm workers&amp;apost; rights.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>It took another nine years, but the state of California would go on to answer Chavez&amp;apost;s call for justice and pass its groundbreaking Agricultural Labor Relations Act.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>That law surged California forward in the global labor movement, but New York never had a Cesar Chavez.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>And so today -- in the state where my father served as senator and where I now live -- our farm workers suffer from the leftover Jim Crow laws that California addressed nearly half a century ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>As a resident of New York State, I wanted to see the conditions for myself.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>So I drove a few hours north of my home to Liberty, New York, and visited the largest producer of fois gras east of the Mississippi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>If you think what farms do to the geese is bad, you should see how they treat the farm workers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>I met a man who worked 12 hours a day, seven days a week for 10 years without a single day off.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>He was paid minimum wage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>And though he earned it, he could not claim overtime pay -- overtime that would be paid to any deli worker in New York City.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>If he tried to form a union, he could be fired.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>I walked through one-room shacks that housed entire families and past queues that led to filthy bathrooms -- one toilet for every 20 workers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>I met women sexually assaulted in the fields by supervisors in return for employment, and children doing backbreaking labor for $3.20 an hour.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The legacy of Jim Crow is alive today in New York, resulting in inexcusable conditions for people who plant our vegetables, pick our fruit and milk our cows.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>All this is legal in New York, the remnants of a bargain struck nationally with the Dixiecrats to exclude minority workers from New Deal federal fair labor laws.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The Farmworkers Fair Labor Practices Act, passed by the State Assembly last year and languishing in the State Senate, is the first step to addressing some of these egregious violations of international human rights New York farm workers still face.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The bill is far from radical; it merely extends to farm workers the same labor protections nearly every other industry in America has enjoyed since the industrial era.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>But it would be revolutionary for the roughly 100,000 men, women, and children who give New York its daily bread.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The State Assembly has passed the bill several times; where it stalls is in the Senate, a body that has the votes to pass the bill into law, but where special interests have prevented it from coming to the floor for a vote.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>We cannot allow partisan politics to condemn New York&amp;apost;s farm workers to another year of misery and abuse.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>New York&amp;apost;s legislature must bring the FFLPA to a vote in 2014.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>And when it does, I hope the members of our State Senate will think of that day in 1968, when in front of a crowd of 6,000 farm workers, Robert Kennedy said:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;When your children and grandchildren take their place in America -- going to high school, and college and taking good jobs at good pay -- when you look at them, you will say, &amp;apost;I did this.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>I was there at the point of difficulty and danger.&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;And though you may be old and bent from many years of labor, no man will stand taller than you when you say, &amp;apost;I marched with Cesar.&amp;apost;&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>All of us still have the opportunity to join the struggle today.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>And if we do, one day when we are old and bent, we will to turn to our children and grandchildren and say, &amp;quot;I was there at the point of difficulty and danger.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>I marched with the New York Farmworkers.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Si se puede!</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Follow us on Twitter @CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Join us on Facebook/CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
