<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="775" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/13/opinion/eddie-izzard-no-to-scottish-independence/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-09-13 06:18:19" category="opinion" author="Eddie Izzard, comedian and opponent of Scottish independence, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Beautiful relationship will end if Scotland leaves UK</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="8">Voters in Scotland to decide on country&amp;apost;s independence on September 18.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12">Comedian Eddie Izzard supports &amp;quot;Let&amp;apost;s Stay Together&amp;quot; campaign.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">Referendum &amp;quot;will have a resounding impact on all of us -- how we see ourselves&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="22">By staying in the union, &amp;quot;Scotland can have the best of both worlds,&amp;quot; says Izzard.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-19 09:53:44" annotation_time="47.687">
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="1">With just days to go, on September 18, Scotland will vote on whether it wants to stay in the United Kingdom family or leave to form a separate country.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">Whatever the result of the referendum, it will have a resounding impact on all of us -- how we see ourselves, our culture and our future.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">That&amp;apost;s why I am happy to support the &amp;quot;Let&amp;apost;s Stay Together&amp;quot; campaign to say to everyone in Scotland just how much we do appreciate them being part of the UK family.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="4">To my thinking, Scotland can have the best of both worlds: It can have its own parliament, its own strong voice and its own cultural identity.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>I am proud to be English.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>I am also proud to be British.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>In fact I define myself as a British European.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>This means I am happy to support England in football matches, support Team GB at the Olympic Games and support Europe in the Ryder Cup golf tournament.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>When you write this all down, it looks a little complicated, but in practice millions of people do this every year in the UK with no problem -- some supporting in the way I do, some supporting Scotland, others Wales, and so on.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>I love the vibrant, tolerant, diverse, confident, nation that the UK now is.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>In so many places I travel to in the world, people are struggling to find a way of working together, but we&amp;apost;ve developed this character and human skill over three centuries in our United Kingdom: It is a precious thing and worth standing up for.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>With just days to go, on September 18, Scotland will vote on whether it wants to stay in the United Kingdom family or leave to form a separate country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a huge decision, especially for those in Scotland but also for everyone in the rest of the UK.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Whatever the result of the referendum, it will have a resounding impact on all of us -- how we see ourselves, our culture and our future.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>I feel it would be for more positive for Scotland to remain an important and integral part of the UK and I wanted to say so publicly.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s why I am happy to support the &amp;quot;Let&amp;apost;s Stay Together&amp;quot; campaign to say to everyone in Scotland just how much we do appreciate them being part of the UK family.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The campaign brings together a wide and diverse group of people from all walks of life -- both famous and not -- to show Scotland just how much we do care.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The UK would feel a deep sense of loss if Scotland left Great Britain.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>You could ask, why should an English person have any views on this?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Well as a member of the United Kingdom, I feel I have the viewpoint of a fellow UK family member.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Also, I have performed in most major towns and cities across Scotland and I ran eight marathons through Scotland holding the Saltire, the flag of Scotland.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>And it&amp;apost;s not just me.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>There are millions of people in the United Kingdom who feel like this, who care about Scotland and want it to remain within the union, but whose voices haven&amp;apost;t been heard.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Of course, I fundamentally believe in the right of those in Scotland to determine their own future and will fully respect the decision, whichever way the vote goes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>But it&amp;apost;s also true that everyone else in the UK will also find big changes in their lives, and I think it&amp;apost;s important that we think about our combined goals and future.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>To my thinking, Scotland can have the best of both worlds: It can have its own parliament, its own strong voice and its own cultural identity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>And at the same time it can also have the strength, the security and the stability of being within the UK.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>At the 2012 Olympics, the whole of the Great Britain team was fighting so hard to win medals and had such a positive spirit.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>It was beautiful.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>If Scotland leaves, we&amp;apost;ll never have that again.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>There are very strong economic reasons for staying together, but there is something even deeper that binds England and Scotland.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s like a beautiful and long-lasting relationship.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>We&amp;apost;ve overcome a lot to get where we are, we do care about each other despite our tiffs, and I believe the future is much better with us working together.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>We do amazing things when we&amp;apost;re together and I ask anyone who feels the same to visit letsstaytogether.org.uk.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>WATCH: Brian Cox and Rory Stewart debate independenceREAD MORE: Actor Brian Cox on why Scots should vote &amp;apost;Yes&amp;apost;READ MORE: Scottish independence - what you need to know.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
