<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="861" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/06/15/opinion/africa-manufacturing-hub/index.html" date_published="2012-06-15 10:25:06" category="opinion" author="Hinh T. Dinh, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Opinion: Could Africa be world&amp;apost;s next manufacturing hub?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Low labor costs and abundant resources are some of Africa&amp;apost;s manufacturing advantages.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">Rising costs of land and labor in China have begun to erode Beijing&amp;apost;s cost advantage.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="34">African countries can benefit from taking timely measures to develop manufacturing goods.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="32">Manufacturing can help Africa industrialize and create jobs for millions.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-14 17:31:39" annotation_time="32.5815">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">Besides low labor costs and abundant resources, these include duty-free and quota-free access to U.S. and EU markets for light manufactures under the Africa Growth and Opportunity Act and the Cotonou Agreement.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">But steeply rising costs of land, regulatory compliance, and especially labor in China&amp;apost;s coastal export manufacturing centers have begun to erode the latter&amp;apost;s cost advantage, a trend likely to accelerate in the coming years.</sentence>
      <sentence id="32" ids_highlights="4">Manufacturing can be an unprecedented opportunity for Africa to industrialize and provide productive jobs to millions of Africans, especially young people who make up as much as 36% of the total working-age population; three in five of Africa&amp;apost;s unemployed are under the age of 25.</sentence>
      <sentence id="34" ids_highlights="3">Due to widely varying country conditions, some African economies can take advantage of favorable wages and natural resources and benefit from taking timely measures to develop and export manufacturing goods.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington D.C. With domestic labor costs rising, many Asian manufacturing producers are now looking to relocate their factories in other regions of the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Could Africa replace Asia and/or China as the world&amp;apost;s next manufacturing hub?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>To be sure, Africa has a number of manufacturing advantages that it has yet to realize.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Besides low labor costs and abundant resources, these include duty-free and quota-free access to U.S. and EU markets for light manufactures under the Africa Growth and Opportunity Act and the Cotonou Agreement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Is this enough to offset Sub-Saharan Africa&amp;apost;s generally low labor productivity relative to that of its Asian competitors?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Yes, if Africa can implement appropriate supportive policies to leverage its opportunities soon.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>This is the finding from a recent book by a team of World Bank economists.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>China dominates the global export market in light manufacturing, and its competitive edge far exceeds that of low income exporters that recently entered the global market.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>But steeply rising costs of land, regulatory compliance, and especially labor in China&amp;apost;s coastal export manufacturing centers have begun to erode the latter&amp;apost;s cost advantage, a trend likely to accelerate in the coming years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The ongoing redistribution of cost advantages in labor-intensive manufacturing presents an opportunity for Sub-Saharan Africa to start producing many light manufactures, enhance private investment and create millions of jobs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>According to new evidence, feasible, low-cost, sharply focused policy initiatives aimed at enhancing private investment could launch the region on a path to becoming competitive in light manufacturing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>These initiatives would complement progress on broader investment reforms and could foster industrialization and raise the market share of domestically produced goods in rapidly growing local markets for light manufacturers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>And as local producers scale up, product will improve, and experience with technology, management and marketing will accumulate, allowing them to seize emerging export opportunities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>In Sub-Saharan Africa, as in China and Vietnam, policies that encourage foreign direct investment can speed up industrial development and export expansion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Isolated successes can be multiplied, as with Ethiopia&amp;apost;s recent foray into selling cut flowers in EU markets: a single pioneering firm opened the door to an industry that now employs 50,000 workers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Previous studies identified long lists of constraints, including corruption, red tape, inadequate utilities, poor transport and skills, inadequate access to finance, and so on.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>In contrast, the book proposes smaller, more specific, and sometimes newly identified constraints.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Narrowing the analysis can make the reform agenda more manageable within the financial and human resource constraints of most African countries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Take the leather industry in Ethiopia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>This sector employs about 8,000 workers and exported about $8 million in 2010, a fraction of similar countries in Asia such as Vietnam.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Ethiopia&amp;apost;s labor costs are lower than Asia&amp;apost;s and the country has Africa&amp;apost;s second largest cattle population, next to Sudan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Furthermore, climatic conditions mean Ethiopian animal skin is among the best in the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Yet the most binding constraint is the shortage of quality processed leather due to poor disease control, lack of quality processing of raw hides and restrictive trade policies on processed leather.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Once the problems are identified, the proposed solutions are straightforward.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Treat ectoparasites (the skin disease that causes blemishes) at modest cost; allow imports and exports of raw hides and processed leather to help alleviate this constraint; and provide technical assistance.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Some of these measures require changing existing policies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Others require provision of public goods such as industrial parks that could be inexpensive.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Ethiopia&amp;apost;s comparative advantage in wages, productivity, and natural resources has led the Huajian Group, a Chinese shoe maker, to build a factory in Ethiopia in three months, with two production lines starting in January 2012, exporting 20,000 pairs of shoes a month and creating some 550 jobs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>So the opportunities and the preconditions are certainly there, provided African policy makers speedily seize them, as the book notes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>But will Africa be the world&amp;apost;s next manufacturing hub?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Not likely.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Manufacturing can be an unprecedented opportunity for Africa to industrialize and provide productive jobs to millions of Africans, especially young people who make up as much as 36% of the total working-age population; three in five of Africa&amp;apost;s unemployed are under the age of 25.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>But the emergence of China as a powerhouse producing a variety of manufacturing goods at very cheap prices thanks to the large scale and skilful exploitation of the supply chain means that not all manufacturing jobs will be transferred from China to Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Due to widely varying country conditions, some African economies can take advantage of favorable wages and natural resources and benefit from taking timely measures to develop and export manufacturing goods.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>But large-scale production requirements also mean that some jobs will be transferred to countries such as India, Bangladesh, Cambodia and Vietnam while others will move to China&amp;apost;s interior.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>In short, the invisible hand of globalization will work to ensure a redistribution of cost advantages to the benefit of the ultimate consumers around the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
