<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="773" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/07/25/opinion/bennett-aurora-three/index.html" date_published="2012-07-25 20:50:29" category="opinion" author="William Bennett, CNN Contributor" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Aurora heroes: Three who gave their lives</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">William Bennett says three men in Colorado shooting died while shielding girlfriends.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12, 9, 6, 3">He says actions of Jon Blunk, Alex Teves, Matt McQuinn leave us wondering at their sacrifice.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="19, 17">Bennett: It was more than chivalry; it was a code of honor, an instinct to protect, not run .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="30, 22">Bennett: The three had their struggles, showed themselves as good men, real-life heroes.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-11 17:41:53" annotation_time="385.32364">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Great evil often brings out the best in good men, men like Todd Beamer on Flight 93, Medal of Honor recipient Michael Murphy in Afghanistan and now the Aurora three -- the three young men, each in different parts of theater nine, who gave their lives to protect their girlfriends.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">Blunk instinctively pushed his girlfriend to the ground and threw his body on top of hers.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">Twenty-four-year-old Alex Teves dived on top of his girlfriend, Amanda Lindgren, when the gunfire erupted.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">Matt McQuinn, 27 years old, threw his body in front of his girlfriend, Samantha Yowler, as the shooting continued.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">Their incredible sacrifice leaves us asking: Why?</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="3">They believed, to put it simply, in a code of honor.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="3">Their instincts were to protect, not run away.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="4">Like all men, they had their own struggles.</sentence>
      <sentence id="30" ids_highlights="4">They need heroes like the Aurora three.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Great evil often brings out the best in good men, men like Todd Beamer on Flight 93, Medal of Honor recipient Michael Murphy in Afghanistan and now the Aurora three -- the three young men, each in different parts of theater nine, who gave their lives to protect their girlfriends.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Twenty-five-year-old Jon Blunk was sitting next to his girlfriend, Jansen Young, at the midnight premiere of &amp;quot;The Dark Knight Rises&amp;quot; when the gunman (who shall remain nameless) opened fire in the dark theater.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Blunk instinctively pushed his girlfriend to the ground and threw his body on top of hers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Blunk, a security guard, served five years in the Navy and was in the process of re-enlisting in hopes of becoming a Navy SEAL, family and friends said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>He was killed in the gunfire; his girlfriend survived.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Twenty-four-year-old Alex Teves dived on top of his girlfriend, Amanda Lindgren, when the gunfire erupted.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Covering her body, he took the bullets so they did not harm her.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>She survived the massacre; he did not.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Matt McQuinn, 27 years old, threw his body in front of his girlfriend, Samantha Yowler, as the shooting continued.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Yowler survived with a gunshot wound to the knee; McQuinn&amp;apost;s body absorbed the fatal shots.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>These men were three of the 12 innocent people killed early that morning.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Their incredible sacrifice leaves us asking: Why?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Why would a young man with his entire life ahead of him risk everything for a woman he has no legal, financial or marital obligations to?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>As Hanna Rosin so eloquently pointed out in a recent article, calling it chivalry would be a tremendous understatement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>By all appearances, these men believed that a man has a responsibility to protect a woman, even to the point of death.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>They believed that there are things in life worth dying for and the innocent woman sitting next to them was one.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>They believed, to put it simply, in a code of honor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>They put the lives of the women before their own, an old fashioned notion to be sure, but certainly an honorable one (if you have any doubt, ask the survivors).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Their instincts were to protect, not run away.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>From all accounts, these young men were average, working men in their 20s.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>(We know a little about Jon Blunk, but not much, and we know even less about the others.).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Like all men, they had their own struggles.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>After his death we learned that Blunk had an ex-wife and two children living in Nevada.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>He was scheduled to visit them to resolve marital issues.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>This isn&amp;apost;t to take anything away from Blunk or the other two heroes, but to illustrate that, in spite of shortcomings, men can still recognize what it means to be a good man and act like one.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>This is especially important given the state of many men today.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Record numbers of men aren&amp;apost;t working or even looking for work.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Record numbers aren&amp;apost;t marrying or even acting as fathers to their children.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>These men need heroes to imitate whom they can relate to in everyday life, not just make-believe superheroes who catch their imagination for an hour or two.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>They need heroes like the Aurora three.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>While much of the media obsesses over the psychology and motivations of this deranged killer, we should hold the Aurora three high.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>It is only by telling their story that this code of honor will survive for future generations of men.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;The world is forwarded by having its attention fixed on the best things,&amp;quot; Matthew Arnold wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>In an age when traditional manhood has been increasingly relegated to fiction -- capes, masks and green screens -- these three men stand as real-life heroes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Their actions remind us that good triumphs over evil, not just in movies, but also in reality.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Are you a friend or family member of one of the victims?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Share your tributes here.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Follow us on Twitter @CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Join us on Facebook/CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
