<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="953" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/01/16/opinion/murad-alazzany-yemen-oped/index.html" date_published="2012-01-16 11:06:56" category="opinion" author="Murad Alazzany, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Yemen youth march &amp;apost;shows true spirit of revolution&amp;apost;</title>
  <keywords>Life March yemen</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Thousands of young people took part in inspirational march over 250 km in five days .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="22">March &amp;quot;broke cliches of Yemen as a country of bombs and terrorists,&amp;quot; says Murad Alazzany.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="24">Youth have broken the shackles of oppression and submission, he adds.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-10 13:11:26" annotation_time="16.212">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Thousands of youths walked for almost five days, covering more than 250 kilometers by foot.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="2">The march broke the typical cliches of Yemen as a country of bombs and terrorists and, if covered, could have shown the whole world that Yemen is an army of liberation -- demonstrating hope for all those who seek freedom but lack the means to achieve it.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="3">The area is witnessing a birth of a new generation that has broken the shackles of oppression and submission.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Like many other Yemenis, I was overwhelmed by the news of the Life March which was set off from Freedom Square in Taiz late December 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Thousands of youths walked for almost five days, covering more than 250 kilometers by foot.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The youth used the term Life March to denote a continuation of their revolutionary protest and a rejection of the immunity given to President Ali Abdullah Saleh.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>They wanted the whole international community to notice that what is happening in Yemen is in fact a revolution, not just a political crisis.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>In this spirit, they wanted the world to seriously consider their demands to topple Saleh&amp;apost;s regime completely and start building the civil and democratic country they all aspire to have.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>When the youth started their march, they knew that it might involve many risks and dangers that may have threatened their lives.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>It was not unrealistic that thugs and snipers loyal to Saleh could inflict heavy casualties on the marchers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>However, the marchers slowly shed these concerns as they climbed the mountainous roads along the cities of Ibb and Dhamar on their way to Sana&amp;apost;a.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Their march surprisingly grew in size as youth from cities joined in.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>However, they were received at the entrance of the capital of Sana&amp;apost;a and some of its streets with a fierce attack by Saleh&amp;apost;s loyalists and thugs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Early reports stated that at least 13 protesters died and dozens more were injured as troops opened fire on the Gandhi-style mass peaceful protest.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>That was the way Saleh and his associates decided to show their hospitality to the exhausted and fatigued marchers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Yet the revolutionary youth of Change Square in Sana&amp;apost;a rushed to defend them against Saleh&amp;apost;s forces and to lead them to the square which was set as their final destination.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>That was where they gave them a warm welcome and later celebrated them as heroes of the nation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>As the marchers overcame the risks and troubles they faced, the march&amp;apost;s meaning evolved and came to represent a new turn in the course of Yemen&amp;apost;s revolution.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>From one perspective, the march revealed the true depth to which the Arab youth have contributed to the success of the revolutionary protests.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>What surprised the world the most about the Arab Spring was not the unpredictability of events, but the level of civility utilized to achieve success.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The Life March is just one example of the youth&amp;apost;s determination to shape the arc of Yemen&amp;apost;s future without guns, violence or bloodshed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Despite the bravery shown by the marchers, and their commitment to non-violence, the media has largely remained silent on the first march from one city to another.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The media simply circumvented the march by tabbing it is a &amp;quot;peaceful rally&amp;quot; falling drastically short of what it really was.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>It is difficult to understand why the event did not receive the coverage it deserved.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The march broke the typical cliches of Yemen as a country of bombs and terrorists and, if covered, could have shown the whole world that Yemen is an army of liberation -- demonstrating hope for all those who seek freedom but lack the means to achieve it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The march was a symbol for the historical new trajectory of the Arab world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The area is witnessing a birth of a new generation that has broken the shackles of oppression and submission.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>By realizing the universal rights of a life of dignity and freedom of choice, this new generation is eager to shape its future and build a country of its own volition.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The autocracy of oppression that has permeated the Arab world will never find its way into the history of the Arabs as long as youth exist.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Youth have sacrificed their lives for the success of the revolution, and now should not be the time to undermine them and the role they will play in shaping Yemen&amp;apost;s future.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Youth have always been at the heart of the uprisings: they were the first out on the streets to demonstrate, the least likely to be intimidated, most likely to raise their voice against authorities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>They have received enough criticism.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>It is now time to join them in their marches and celebrate them as the heroes our country needs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
