<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="796" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/16/opinion/omara-daniele-watts-case/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-09-16 20:52:09" category="opinion" author="Mark O&amp;apost;Mara" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Daniele Watts was out of line (Opinion)</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Actress Daniele Watts claimed racism after being detained by a police officer .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="27">Mark O&amp;apost;Mara: In this case, officer was doing his job, and it&amp;apost;s Watts who was out of line.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">He says many incidents do give black people reason to be distrustful of cops .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="23">O&amp;apost;Mara: In general, law enforcement can do better in addressing racial bias.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-19 21:16:32" annotation_time="40.338">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1"> I&amp;apost;m frustrated by the story of &amp;quot;Django Unchained&amp;quot; actress Daniele Watts&amp;apost; claim of racism after being detained by a police officer.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">It&amp;apost;s the kind of action that gives black people reason to be distrustful of cops.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="4">I have analyzed and critiqued cops&amp;apost; behavior lately, and I think law enforcement everywhere in this country has to do better, especially when it comes to addressing bias in their police work.</sentence>
      <sentence id="27" ids_highlights="2">In Watts&amp;apost; case, the officer was doing his job, and it was Watts who was out of line.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>I&amp;apost;m frustrated by the story of &amp;quot;Django Unchained&amp;quot; actress Daniele Watts&amp;apost; claim of racism after being detained by a police officer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>I think it is true that police officers, in general, are more likely to be suspicious of black people than white people in specific circumstances, and I know the phenomenon of &amp;quot;driving while black&amp;quot; happens.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>I have clients who have been pulled over, questioned and detained without any obvious probable cause.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>It reminds me of an incident a few weeks ago in which Hollywood producer Charles Belk was detained by police officers for six hours until cops realized they had the wrong &amp;quot;tall, bald-headed black male.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Such an event is demoralizing and humiliating, and it is evidence of how ingrained cultural biases affect law-abiding citizens.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s the kind of action that gives black people reason to be distrustful of cops.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>What happened to Belk is the kind of incident that can help white people understand how racial bias impacts other people&amp;apost;s lives.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>White people, like it or not, receive the benefit of racial bias, although it&amp;apost;s hardly ever very apparent when it happens.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>When I quickly catch a cab in Manhattan, I don&amp;apost;t think, &amp;quot;that was easy because I was white.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>When I&amp;apost;m pulled over by police, I never think, &amp;quot;I bet this would go better if I was black.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s an unnatural thought process, but it&amp;apost;s a thought process that keeps many whites from understanding an experience shared by many blacks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>When such an incident happens to a high-profile personality -- such as a Hollywood producer or actress -- it provides an opportunity for people from both sides of the racial divide to connect and identify with the story.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>In a situation like Belk&amp;apost;s, it has the potential to foster a broader understanding of our inherent cultural biases.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s a good thing; it&amp;apost;s a conversation about race that has the potential to bring us closer together.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>But the details in the Watts&amp;apost; case could produce the opposite effects.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Police responded to a very specific call: a white man and a black woman in a Mercedes involved in a sex act outside the CBS Studio.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The officer explained why he had probable cause to ask for her identification.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Her continued refusal to comply resulted in her being temporarily placed in handcuffs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>When her boyfriend persuaded her to produce her ID, she was finally released.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Here are some basic legal procedures: Police are allowed to ask you for your identification when they are investigating a particular event that may be a crime; it&amp;apost;s part of their job.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>If they have probable cause to believe an actual crime occurred, they are allowed to arrest you.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Asking for your ID is a polite first step to establish whether further investigation is appropriate and whether an arrest is warranted.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>I have analyzed and critiqued cops&amp;apost; behavior lately, and I think law enforcement everywhere in this country has to do better, especially when it comes to addressing bias in their police work.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>However, there are some basic rules to follow when interacting with law enforcement: respect them and their authority -- indeed, their obligation -- to investigate circumstances.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>If a cop acts inappropriate, file that complaint later, not during the interaction on the street.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>That is a battle you simply will not win.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>In Watts&amp;apost; case, the officer was doing his job, and it was Watts who was out of line.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>I think many people -- especially many white people -- are going to look at the Watts situation and come to the conclusion that she overreacted.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>In the best-case scenario, it detracts from the significance of cases like the Belk case, in which outrage is justified.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>In the worst-case scenario, Watts&amp;apost; reaction re-entrenches prejudices held by some that black suspects contribute disproportionately to the contentious relationship between cops and the black community.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Either way, Watts&amp;apost; behavior and her accusations in this case are not conducive to advancing thoughtful discussions about race.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>If we want a constructive conversation, we need to engage in a way that brings us together, not pushes us further apart.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>