<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="809" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/05/06/opinion/royal-navy-way-of-leadership/index.html" date_published="2013-05-06 06:32:56" category="opinion" author="Andrew St George, Special for CNN" highlights_mapped="false" mapping_error="false">
  <title>From James Bond to the boardroom: What the Royal Navy teach leaders</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7">Royal Navy runs on soft skills more than shouted orders.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12">Soft skills are easy to understand but hard to learn .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="15">Half of Royal Navy may be working in an office at any one time.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="11">Leaders and managers could learn much from navy&amp;apost;s way of operating.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_time="14.931">
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">Here&amp;apost;s the surprising thing: the Royal Navy runs on &amp;quot;soft skills&amp;quot; (and never on shouted orders).</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="4">And where two groups attempt the same thing, the successful group will be the one whose leaders understand how to use those soft skills in motivating their people and maintaining their effort.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">The soft skills are pretty easy to identify and pretty hard to learn.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="3">And remember that half the Royal Navy at any one time might be working in an office (even at sea or on land deployment), so their workplace is much more like yours or mine than you think.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>&amp;quot;The name&amp;apost;s Bond, Commander Bond.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Words uttered by the world&amp;apost;s most famous secret agent who is adored by his country, feared by the bad guys and trained by Britain&amp;apost;s Royal Navy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>I have just spent three years with the Royal Navy and written the &amp;quot;Royal Navy Way of Leadership&amp;quot; commissioned by the Commander in Chief of the Royal Navy and issued to 15,000 personnel.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>I spent long spells at sea on all types of vessel; I followed officer training with the Surface Fleet and with the Royal Marines.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Never have I found a more cheerful, consistent and yet flexible and innovative working environment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The Royal Navy is expert at planning, measuring and executing -- the key management disciplines; it does these things highly professionally as it moves throughout the 140 million square miles of the world&amp;apost;s oceans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Here&amp;apost;s the surprising thing: the Royal Navy runs on &amp;quot;soft skills&amp;quot; (and never on shouted orders).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>These are the qualities of character and culture that are remarkably resilient and, most importantly, instilled in all Royal Navy personnel.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>They understand the uses of commitment, loyalty, integrity, respect and cheerfulness in ways that the commercial and public sector can only dream of.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>What I learned is that when people gather together to achieve an end (excellence in military operations or in business for example), what gets things done is those soft skills.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>And where two groups attempt the same thing, the successful group will be the one whose leaders understand how to use those soft skills in motivating their people and maintaining their effort.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The soft skills are pretty easy to identify and pretty hard to learn.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>They are a form of emotional intelligence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Produce a workplace with the soft skills, and your people will flourish.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>And remember that half the Royal Navy at any one time might be working in an office (even at sea or on land deployment), so their workplace is much more like yours or mine than you think.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Take cheerfulness.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Are you happy at work?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Happy with what you are being told to do, or with what you are asking your people to do?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Happy that your commitment and hard work are being nourished?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Do you work for someone cheerful?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Or are you happy to follow a pessimist?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Here is the opportunity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>There are over 1.5 million people employed in FTSE 250 companies in the UK; a further 13.8 million in small and medium-sized enterprises nearly three quarters of a million in London.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>All contain managers, whose job it is to do things right, and leaders, whose job it is to do the right thing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Improve leadership at work, and you improve the lives of over 15 million people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>And in this current uncertain and fast-moving global environment, there is even more need for leadership of the right kind.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Doing the right thing means three things: looking after your shareholders, looking after your customers, and looking after your people.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>And it&amp;apost;s in the latter where leaders fail.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>They tend to lack the emotional intelligence, the subtlety of character to elicit the best from their people when times get tough.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>These are not matters for management but for leadership.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>So here is the take-home -- or better, take-to-work -- advice for leaders.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>This is military philosophy applied to everyday working life.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>First, develop soft skills and see how employees who are trusted, valued, respected and treated cheerfully actually begin to flourish and prosper.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>In a recession, if money is not the first reward, then improving the individual&amp;apost;s relationship with work should be.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Your people will achieve more with fewer resources.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Second, figure out your ethos or culture -- &amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s the way we do things around here.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>If you achieve this, then customer service becomes a reality rather than a hopeful promise; innovation is inculcated into the way everyone thinks all the time; honesty is not a matter of compliance but a matter of fact.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Third, be clear in your thinking and you will be more efficient.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>The Royal Navy works with what the military call Mission Command, which sets out the intent, strategy, resources, contingency and inspiration for any large-scale activity (it actually derives from Nelson&amp;apost;s order of battle set out a month before Trafalgar).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The simplicity is compelling because it works.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>And it has been tested in all manner of fast, dangerous, uncertain and difficult conditions for hundreds of years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>How about when things go wrong?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Sir Edmund Hillary, the first man up Everest, used to say that if you were in real trouble in a difficult place you needed an explorer called Ernest Shackleton, because he understood his people, knew how hard it was to lead well, and was prepared to do the right thing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Shackleton never lost a man in the Antarctic, despite being marooned there in 1915, because he understood his people, got them to make sacrifices for the common good, and earned their love and respect.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>The love and respect found in Shackleton&amp;apost;s crew really count commercially.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>A Mercer survey in the U.S. last year found that half of U.S. employees were unhappy at work, and that a third were thinking of leaving their organization; even worse, 20% of U.S. workers were disgruntled and yet loath to move on.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>The declines in productivity from ignoring the soft skills are huge.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Conversely, high-performing teams tend to have high levels of employee engagement and satisfaction.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>They depend on shared culture, goals, and methods; which is precisely what makes the Royal Navy so good at getting things done.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>A survey by Aon Hewitt last year found that employee engagement must be over 67% if a company has any hope of success: the average UK level is 57% (the lowest since 2008).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>The soft skills that create happiness at work are not expensive to develop.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Yet we know CEO tenure is short and therefore leadership/business culture -- the vital essence that carries continuity -- is suffering.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>It takes time to develop something worthwhile.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>Yet it is a formula understood instinctively by every navy captain, every galley chef, every officer of the watch.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>How people are at work affects how they work.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>The culture counts.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>If businesses can get this right, like the Royal Navy, it will be revolutionary.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
