<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="945" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/17/opinion/talbott-arming-ukraine/index.html?hpt=ieu_r1" date_published="2014-09-17 19:36:33" category="opinion" author="Steven Pifer and Strobe Talbott" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Ukraine should get military assistance (Opinion)</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Ukrainian President Petro Poroshenko visits Washington on Thursday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="14">He seems intent on a peaceful settlement, write Strobe Talbott and Steven Pifer.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="18">Obama should agree to provide defensive arms on an expedited basis, authors say.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="33">Talbott and Pifer: Moscow has grossly violated the Budapest memorandum.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 08:02:16" annotation_time="29.483">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1"> When Ukrainian President Petro Poroshenko visits Washington on Thursday, he will almost certainly again ask for U.S. military assistance, including defensive weapons.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="2">The truce is shaky, but the Ukrainian president seems intent on pursuing a peaceful settlement.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="3">When he hosts Poroshenko in the Oval Office, Obama should agree to provide defensive arms on an expedited basis.</sentence>
      <sentence id="33" ids_highlights="4">Moscow has grossly violated the Budapest memorandum by its seizure of Crimea and assaults on Ukraine.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>When Ukrainian President Petro Poroshenko visits Washington on Thursday, he will almost certainly again ask for U.S. military assistance, including defensive weapons.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>President Barack Obama should say yes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Arming Kiev can deter Russian Vladimir Putin from further aggression and support the fragile Ukraine ceasefire and settlement process.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Doing so would also bolster U.S. efforts to prevent nuclear proliferation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Russia illegally occupied and annexed Crimea in March.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Just weeks later, armed separatists -- assisted and, in some cases, led by Russian intelligence officers -- began seizing government buildings in the eastern Ukrainian regions of Donetsk and Luhansk.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Ukrainian counterattacks started making headway in the summer.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Russia responded by supplying heavy weapons to the separatists -- including, it is widely believed, the Buk anti-aircraft system believed to have shot down Malaysia Airlines flight 17 in mid-July.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Despite the influx of arms, Ukrainian forces continued to make progress.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>By early August, the separatists looked on the verge of defeat.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>That would have stopped Putin&amp;apost;s strategy in its tracks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>So, as NATO noted, elite Russian military units invaded and occupied Ukrainian territory, hitting Ukrainian forces hard.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Vastly outgunned, Poroshenko had little choice but to accept a ceasefire on September 5.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The truce is shaky, but the Ukrainian president seems intent on pursuing a peaceful settlement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Whether common ground can be found among Kiev, the separatists and Moscow is unclear.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>At best, the negotiation will be long and arduous.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The Ukrainian government has for some time sought lethal military assistance, such as anti-armor weapons, as well as secure communications equipment and reconnaissance drones.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>When he hosts Poroshenko in the Oval Office, Obama should agree to provide defensive arms on an expedited basis.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Such assistance would enhance Kiev&amp;apost;s ability to deter further Russian aggression, aggression that would threaten, perhaps fatally, the possibility of a negotiated settlement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>A better-armed Ukrainian military would give Putin pause, because it could impose greater costs on the Russian army if the Russians break the ceasefire and renew the fighting.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Reports detail the extraordinary lengths, such as nighttime burials, to which the Kremlin has gone to hide from its public the fact that Russian soldiers have fought and died in Ukraine.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The more costly the Ukrainians can make any fighting for the Russians, the less Moscow&amp;apost;s interest in resuming the conflict.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Some may argue that providing lethal military assistance would provoke Putin to escalate.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>But he has already escalated the situation -- from instigating separatist actions to providing heavy weapons to sending in the Russian army.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>This suggests the opposite may well prove true: Arming Ukraine will raise the costs of escalation to Russia and thus make it less likely.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Putin has made clear his contempt for the Western response to date.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Inaction could embolden him to escalate in Ukraine and test the waters elsewhere, perhaps in a NATO member state such as Estonia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Moreover, the Ukrainians will bear the risks and brunt of any escalation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>If they are willing to accept those risks, we should give them the tools to defend themselves.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>And there is an additional important reason to respond favorably to Ukraine&amp;apost;s request for defensive arms: to restore credibility to the notion of security assurances.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>In December 1994, the leaders of the United States, Britain and Russia signed the Budapest memorandum on security assurances, which committed those countries to respect Ukraine&amp;apost;s sovereignty and territorial integrity and not use force against Ukraine.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Those commitments paved the way for Kiev&amp;apost;s decision to give up about 1,900 strategic nuclear warheads, at the time the world&amp;apost;s third-largest nuclear arsenal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Moscow has grossly violated the Budapest memorandum by its seizure of Crimea and assaults on Ukraine.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The United States and Britain have an obligation to respond.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Washington has imposed economic sanctions on Russia and provided Ukraine a modest amount of nonlethal military aid.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Those are appropriate steps, but they do not suffice.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Last Friday, former President Leonid Kuchma, who signed the Budapest memorandum for Ukraine, suggested his country had been cheated.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>That reflects general sentiment in Kiev.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>The widely held impression that Moscow has violated its Budapest commitments at low cost badly weakens the value of security assurances in the future.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>That is unfortunate, as security assurances could play a role as part of the package to resolve the Iran and North Korea nuclear issues.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>But how much value will security assurances have if Tehran and Pyongyang see that they can be violated with relative impunity?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Washington can change that impression.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Providing lethal military assistance to Ukraine could not only deter Putin from further war against Ukraine, but could help to reestablish security assurances as part of the solution to critical nuclear proliferation challenges.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>