<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="766" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/11/20/opinion/jfk-hammond-oped/index.html" date_published="2013-11-20 15:53:33" category="opinion" author="Andrew Hammond, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>50 years on, the enduring lessons of JFK&amp;apost;s presidency</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Friday marks the 50th anniversary of the assassination of John F. Kennedy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">Presidency offers lessons on U.S. policy in Mideast and China - Andrew Hammond.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">Hammond: JFK powerfully renewed U.S. global leadership, helping to thaw Cold War.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="13">Objective appraisal of JFK&amp;apost;s presidency must highlight lows and highs, he adds.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-01 11:14:54" annotation_time="42.379333">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">This Friday marks the 50th anniversary of the assassination of John F. Kennedy, one of history&amp;apost;s most notable figures.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">And it offers key lessons for today, ranging from U.S. policy in the Middle East post-9/11, to how to best engage a &amp;quot;rising&amp;quot; China.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">Through his skilful rebalancing of hard and soft power, he powerfully renewed U.S. global leadership, helping to thaw the Cold War.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="4">To be sure, an objective appraisal of JFK&amp;apost;s period in the White House must highlight lows as well as the highs.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>This Friday marks the 50th anniversary of the assassination of John F. Kennedy, one of history&amp;apost;s most notable figures.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Despite holding office for less than a full term, he has long been perceived by the U.S. public as one of the best occupants of the White House.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Yet JFK&amp;apost;s presidency is inspiring not just to Americans, but also to many others around the world too.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>And it offers key lessons for today, ranging from U.S. policy in the Middle East post-9/11, to how to best engage a &amp;quot;rising&amp;quot; China.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>At a time when U.S.-Soviet rivalry was becoming heavily militarized, JFK&amp;apost;s political genius was to appreciate that the superpower contest was as much a battle for ideas as strength of force.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Through his skilful rebalancing of hard and soft power, he powerfully renewed U.S. global leadership, helping to thaw the Cold War.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Here his projection of hope and optimism, and stirring rhetoric appealed to U.S. and international audiences alike, including those behind the Iron Curtain.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Landmark speeches included the one he made in Berlin in 1963 when he offered U.S. solidarity with West Germany.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>And his desire to re-set U.S.-Soviet relations was expressed eloquently too, including a compelling speech at the American University after the Cuban missile crisis.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>This was described even by Soviet Premier Nikita Khrushchev as the &amp;quot;the greatest speech by any U.S. president since [Franklin] Roosevelt.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Renewal of U.S. international policy was not just rhetorical, as initiatives like the Peace Corps and the South America-focused Alliance for Progress underline.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>And, through landmark achievements such as the International Nuclear Test Ban Treaty, JFK gave substance to his ambition of moving toward international peace.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>To be sure, an objective appraisal of JFK&amp;apost;s period in the White House must highlight lows as well as the highs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>In addition to successes such as his management of the Cuban missile crisis, there was also the Bay of Pigs invasion debacle.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>And JFK had a much more limited record of legislative success than his successor Lyndon Johnson.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Professional historians therefore tend to rate JFK&amp;apost;s presidency as &amp;quot;good,&amp;quot; rather than &amp;quot;great,&amp;quot; with reason.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Of course, the circumstances of today are transformed from those of the early 1960s.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>As well as the end of the Cold War, the United States has experienced relative decline: for instance, its economy now accounts for less than a quarter of global GDP compared to around a third then.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Yet, the relevance of JFK&amp;apost;s insights about international cooperation and peace endure.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>As does the wisdom of much of the way in which he harnessed U.S. leadership and power to try to achieve these ends.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Indeed, at a time of U.S. military cutbacks, and given the ongoing information revolution, the importance of achieving better balance between -- often expensive -- hard power assets and soft power resources is perhaps even more important today for Washington.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>And this is true right across the world from Asia-Pacific through the Middle East and South America.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>On China policy, for instance, some U.S. hawks advocate a much tougher stance toward Beijing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>However, as JFK would have recognized, Washington has much to gain from cooperation with Beijing too, and it would be a mistake to view the relationship solely through a lens of threat and suspicion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>To be sure, there remains a legitimate remaining need for maintaining significant U.S. military power in Asia, not least to re-assure key allies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>However, on issues ranging from North Korea, terrorism, through to the future stability of the global economy, China has a potentially key role to play in concert with the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Here the role of soft power is key as Washington seeks to better integrate Beijing into a network of regional and global institutions and alliances.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>In so doing, this will help incentivize China even more strongly toward a path of constructive partnership.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>In the Middle East meanwhile, U.S. standing in numerous countries has unfortunately been at a low ebb now for at least a decade.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Only 11% of the population in Pakistan, 14% in Jordan, 16% in Egypt and the Palestinian territories, and 21% in Turkey, currently have favourable views toward the United States, according to Pew Global.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Despite some U.S. overtures, the challenge remains monumental.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>This is such a critical issue given the wide-range of U.S. priorities in Middle Eastern and other Muslim-majority countries, including the &amp;quot;campaign against terrorism.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>As JFK would surely have appreciated, there is a compelling need for redoubling efforts to win the battle for moderate &amp;quot;hearts and minds.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>This can be best achieved through a vigorous re-assertion of U.S. soft power, combined with prudent use of hard power.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Such an agenda would require much greater resourcing for activities such as public diplomacy, broadcasting, development assistance and exchange programs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>U.S. public diplomacy is in particularly strong need of revitalization, with a clearer long-term strategy essential.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Taken overall, it is clear that JFK&amp;apost;s key insights about international relations retain much relevance and appeal.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>And for this reason alone, his presidency will continue to hold not just enduring value, but also inspiration, right across the world for many years to come.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
