<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="819" link="http://cnn.com/2014/03/21/opinion/asia-search-for-mh370-security/index.html?hpt=bosread" date_published="2014-03-21 08:50:16" category="opinion" author="Bridget Welsh, Special for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>How the search for MH370 will change Asia&amp;apost;s approach to security</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="9">Post MH370, attention will increasingly turn to the skies in terms of security, says Welsh.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="38, 5">Current focus on maritime security in Asia has led to tensions, especially with China.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="13">&amp;quot;No coordination or mechanism for effective information sharing&amp;quot; in the region.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="16, 43">Welsh: Asia needs better governance, stronger multilateral ties.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-08 22:42:01" annotation_time="54.68867" mapping_time_divergence="27.344336">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">But at times the focus on maritime security in Asia has led to tensions.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="1">Post MH370, attention will increasingly turn to the skies.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="3">Satellite intelligence has increased yet no coordination or mechanism for effective information sharing exists.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="4">The search for MH370 will lead to a rethink of the existing regional architecture, with the need for stronger multilateral ties to secure safer air travel.</sentence>
      <sentence id="38" ids_highlights="2">Unless checked, China-U.S. competition in Asia will deepen with pressure on both to increase their involvement in security in Asia.</sentence>
      <sentence id="43" ids_highlights="4">Now more than ever the burden is on Asia as a whole to better take care of itself, to come together to assure that its citizens and visitors get the protection and security they need.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Singapore In 2003, the SARS virus epidemic was a wake-up call for Asia, forcing China to increase transparency, fostering closer regional cooperation and bringing human security issues to the fore.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The disappearance of MH370 will have a similar transformative effect on regional security, but it will take a different form.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>In recent years, the focus -- driven by the need to protect the waters of approximately a third of the world&amp;apost;s trade, as well as access to energy and resources -- has been on sea lanes, concentrating on reducing piracy and enhancing naval cooperation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The United States, India, Japan and China have all ratcheted up their patrols, buttressed by the smaller naval operations of Singapore, Malaysia, Thailand and Indonesia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>But at times the focus on maritime security in Asia has led to tensions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>China has resented the encroachment of other powers into waters it views as its own, while spats have intensified between China and its regional neighbors, particularly over islands in the South China Sea.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>China&amp;apost;s increasingly assertive position has engendered a wariness among countries in the region that has been an undercurrent in the cooperation between neighbors during the current MH370 crisis.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Sky security.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Post MH370, attention will increasingly turn to the skies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The disappearance of the Malaysia Airlines jet has revealed shortcomings in monitoring air space.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>That no one even knew the plane had veered off course for seven hours raises serious questions -- even allowing for the fact the jetliner&amp;apost;s tracking mechanisms effectively turned off.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The contradictions and slow trickle of information from the Malaysian authorities and regional neighbors has highlighted how disjointed, uneven and vulnerable the monitoring of airspace across borders is.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Satellite intelligence has increased yet no coordination or mechanism for effective information sharing exists.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Many nations are not willing to reveal the technology at their disposal, as seems evident in the delays in sharing data, while some -- particularly in Southeast Asia -- have to turn to others to access satellite technology.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Despite the involvement of over 20 countries in the search, trust and capacity is seemingly lacking.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The search for MH370 will lead to a rethink of the existing regional architecture, with the need for stronger multilateral ties to secure safer air travel.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>One option on the table needs to be a credible investigative body to manage air security across the region.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Another important step clearly has to involve improved measures to secure transponders for communication.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>MH370 has also brought the issue of good governance to center stage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Malaysia&amp;apost;s response has raised serious concerns about accountability, transparency and competence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>From the get go, the Malaysian authorities were on the back foot, given that more than half of the country&amp;apost;s population voted against the current government in a 2013 election marred by allegations of fraud.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The government&amp;apost;s alleged persecution of political opponents has fostered deep alienation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Hours before he was due to contest in a by-election, a Malaysian court overturned opposition leader Anwar Ibrahim&amp;apost;s acquittal of the charge that he sodomized a former political aide.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The de facto leader of the People&amp;apost;s Justice Party has repeatedly said he is innocent, calling the case against him an attempt by the government to end his political career -- an assertion it has consistently denied.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Days after the plane&amp;apost;s disappearance, Anwar&amp;apost;s lawyer, Karpal Singh, was charged with sedition in another case viewed by some as politically motivated.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Even against this backdrop, many were willing to give the government a chance.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>But it fell short by failing to learn lessons from the SARS virus: countries need to share information in a timely manner and earn credibility, rather than expect it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Sadly, the international media effectively set the tone for the search for the plane, not the Malaysians.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The mystery of what happened to MH370 shows that without the basic practices of good governance, lives can be lost and security put in jeopardy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The MH370 crisis has also revealed that in spite of the rise of China, the U.S. and its allies still have an important security role to play in Asia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>When push came to shove, Malaysia&amp;apost;s Najib government turned to its Western partners for their investigative skills and search and rescue guidance.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>China-U.S. tensions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Yet Beijing was been increasingly irked by the rate of progress.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>With more than 150 of its own citizens on board the Boeing 777-200, China has been frustrated by the delays in information and its inability to effectively protect its own nationals.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>This frustration recently boiled over into criticism of Malaysia&amp;apost;s handling of the investigation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Whatever the outcome the MH370 mystery, China will take steps to enhance efforts to monitor and secure airspace in the region.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>This in turn will generate greater wariness among its neighbors and possibly bring it into more frequent contact with Western powers -- especially the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Unless checked, China-U.S. competition in Asia will deepen with pressure on both to increase their involvement in security in Asia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>An important constraint on this great power struggle will be a strong multilateral Asia-led initiative to enhance aviation security -- one that includes the United States but brings in all the key Asian stakeholders.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>We do not yet know what happened.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>We may never know.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>We do know however that security in Asia will never be the same.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Now more than ever the burden is on Asia as a whole to better take care of itself, to come together to assure that its citizens and visitors get the protection and security they need.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>From stronger multilateral ties to good governance, the case of MH370 can bring about the opportunity for a safer region.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
