<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="879" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/07/02/opinion/hong-kong-reforms-identity/index.html" date_published="2014-07-02 06:09:41" category="opinion" author="Douglas Young, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Opinion: Hong Kong should embrace its unique identity</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="14">Hong Kong is culturally and politically distinct from other Chinese cities.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="20">Douglas Young: I believe the majority of Hong Kong people recognizes that Hong Kong cannot exist as an independent country.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="32">Young: Hong Kong&amp;apost;s role in world culture is vital.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-06 09:02:27" annotation_time="11.296333">
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="1">It is a fact that Hong Kong is culturally and politically distinct from other Chinese cities.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="2">I believe the majority of Hong Kong people recognizes that Hong Kong cannot exist as an independent country.</sentence>
      <sentence id="32" ids_highlights="3">In tandem with China&amp;apost;s political and economic rise during our lifetime, Hong Kong&amp;apost;s role in world culture is vital.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>During my travels to some western countries, there have been occasions when people have asked me where I come from.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>When some hear that I&amp;apost;m from Hong Kong, they would often say: &amp;quot;So, you are Japanese!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>This has happened so often that I find it more convenient to simply tell them I&amp;apost;m Chinese, rather than explain how Hong Kong&amp;apost;s sits in relation to mainland China.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Hong Kong does not enjoy the global familiarity enjoyed by places like New York, Paris or London.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The residents of these cities can just say they are from those cities to anyone in the world and there would be little questions asked about their nationality.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Does the fact that the American doesn&amp;apost;t mention he is from the United States make him less American?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Of course not.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>One only has to walk down the streets of Manhattan and count the number of American flags to realize that New Yorkers are patriotic Americans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;apost;Mother China&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>In Hong Kong, whenever the Chinese flag and the Hong Kong flag are flown side by side, the Chinese flag is always placed a little higher.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>This rightly symbolizes the fact that Hong Kong is a city within the mother country of China.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>But this should not deny a Hong Kong person the right to explain the difference between their city and other Chinese cities.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Those that like to stoke dissent often accuse such behavior as unpatriotic.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>It is a fact that Hong Kong is culturally and politically distinct from other Chinese cities.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>We are under a different political and legal system.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>We have a unique history of British colonialism.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Our tradition of openness and internationalism has provided us with a unique set of circumstances.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>All in all, the Hong Kong identity is distinctive but one that China recognizes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>It is this difference that has endowed Hong Kong with an important role to play within China in the same way that Shanghai and Beijing have their respective reasons to be.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>I believe the majority of Hong Kong people recognizes that Hong Kong cannot exist as an independent country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>This is not just because of mere realism and practicality.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>It is fundamentally because we can readily identify with the traditions we share with our motherland and feel a substantial sense of pride in our ancient history.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Unique identity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Whether or not we place Hong Kong before or after China depends on certain undeniable cultural anomalies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>At the end of the day, the bond we have with our fellow countrymen in the mainland is stronger than our differences.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>If we can overcome this seeming contradiction and concentrate on celebrating our unique identity, we can fashion Hong Kong to be a place of global relevance and at the same time help China rise as a global player.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Hong Kong is Asia&amp;apost;s most culturally diverse city.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>We enjoy an international level of living standards.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Our rule of law and freedom are things we cherish.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>We are geographically well placed to be Asia&amp;apost;s cultural hub.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>It should be the place where all the world&amp;apost;s important cultural events should be staged.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>In tandem with China&amp;apost;s political and economic rise during our lifetime, Hong Kong&amp;apost;s role in world culture is vital.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>It is important to recognize that it is the soft power of a country that is most appealing the world over.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>It is the tonic that helps to alleviate tensions that arises from issues such as territorial disputes and tourists behaving badly overseas.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Countries that can handle their military, economic and cultural strengths with dexterity are those that are able to punch well above their weight.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>I believe the current generation of Chinese leaders are intelligent enough to recognize this fact.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Under appropriate circumstances, Hong Kong people should be able to wear all our different hats with confidence and pride.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>As Asians, we should even be able to embrace our affinity with fellow Asians.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Including the Japanese!</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
