<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="832" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2011/10/12/opinion/nemyria-ukraine-european-future/index.html" date_published="2011-10-12 18:13:35" category="opinion" author="Hryhoriy Nemyria, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Jailed leader could become Europe&amp;apost;s Suu Kyi</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">Keeping Mrs. Tymoshenko in prison simply not an option, says Hryhoriy Nemyria.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="17">Last week parliament refused to consider any modification of the articles needed to free her.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="18">Nemyria: Yanukovych playing a dangerous game, should not try to bluff EU and U.S.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 07:56:41" annotation_time="17.943">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">Keeping Mrs. Tymoshenko in prison is simply not an option.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="2">She would then walk free and back into political life -- although last week parliament refused to consider any modification of the articles needed to free her.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="3">President Yanukovych is playing a dangerous game and should not seek to bluff the U.S. and EU.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>By convicting and imprisoning former Ukrainian prime minister Yulia Tymoshenko, President Viktor Yanukovych has succeeded in doing what few politicians ever achieve.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>He has united Europe, the U.S. and even Russia in condemnation of a Soviet-style show trial, which saw the heroine of the Orange Revolution convicted for taking a courageous political decision to end a damaging gas dispute in the winter of 2009 -- a dispute which saw gas supplies cut to European households and Ukraine&amp;apost;s gas pipeline network come close to collapse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>This politically motivated gamble to get rid of his main political opponent ahead of parliamentary elections next year and presidential elections in 2015 backfired spectacularly.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>In upsetting the international community, the president also united a previously fractured opposition, cast himself as a dictator and revived the fortunes of his main political rival.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Keeping Mrs. Tymoshenko in prison is simply not an option.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Inside her cell her voice will merely get louder.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Unwittingly he is forging a strong symbol for freedom and democracy -- an eastern European Aung San Suu Kyi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Of course, the case is underpinned by geopolitics.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>At stake is the very direction of this nation of 46 million people.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Russia wants Ukraine to join its customs union with former Soviet republics, Belarus and Kazakhstan.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>This would mean abandoning negotiations with the EU on an association agreement encompassing a wide-ranging free trade accord.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The talks are due to be concluded in December.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Herein lays the rub.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>EU officials have made it clear that they don&amp;apost;t invite into their club authoritarian regimes that lock up opposition leaders for no good reason.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>They delivered a stern warning: Mrs. Tymoshenko and other detained members of her former government are to be released and allowed to participate fully in political life, or European states are unlikely to ratify the association agreement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Backpedaling furiously, the president hints that Ukraine&amp;apost;s rubber stamp parliament will decriminalize the discredited Soviet-era criminal code under which Mrs. Tymoshenko was tried.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>She would then walk free and back into political life -- although last week parliament refused to consider any modification of the articles needed to free her.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>President Yanukovych is playing a dangerous game and should not seek to bluff the U.S. and EU.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>He risks making his country an international pariah.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Meanwhile, the trial has shown to the world the inconsistent application of the rule of law and absence of fair, impartial and independent judicial proceedings.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>This should play heavily on the minds of European companies and would-be investors, as well as fans visiting the UEFA EURO 2012 soccer tournament, which Ukraine will co-host with Poland.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Yet at stake here is the country&amp;apost;s democratic future.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Under Mr Yanukovych&amp;apost;s stewardship, Ukraine has already been demoted from Freedom House&amp;apost;s list of &amp;quot;free&amp;quot; countries to &amp;quot;partly free.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The choice now is whether it heads down a Belarusian path -- facing isolation and further sanctions -- or shares Mrs. Tymoshenko&amp;apost;s vision of being European, democratic and free.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
