<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="784" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/07/23/opinion/royal-baby-childbirth-killer-africa/index.html" date_published="2013-07-23 04:46:23" category="opinion" author="Steve Murigi, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Celebrate royal baby, but remember childbirth is still a killer</title>
  <keywords>royal baby,childbirth,maternal mortality,africa,pregnancy</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">For many African women, giving birth is a dangerous process.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="45">440 women in sub-Saharan Africa die giving birth every day .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="14">Many African women cannot access adequate care during pregnancy, says campaigner.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-14 16:58:47" annotation_time="20.0825">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">For an African woman, one of the most natural of events in a woman&amp;apost;s life -- giving birth -- is also one of the most dangerous.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="3">With limited investment in health resources, many women in sub-Saharan Africa cannot access an adequate healthcare unit during pregnancy and childbirth.</sentence>
      <sentence id="45" ids_highlights="2">But whilst we celebrate the arrival of a royal newborn, perhaps we should also spare a thought for those 440 women across sub-Saharan Africa who will lose their lives today simply giving birth.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>As the world celebrates the long-awaited addition to the British royal family, it is worth taking some time to reflect on the women around the world for whom childbirth is not such a joyous, beautiful and celebrated occasion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Every year in sub-Saharan Africa, 162,000 mothers die needlessly because of complications during pregnancy and childbirth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>That figure represents a staggering 56% of the global total.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>For an African woman, one of the most natural of events in a woman&amp;apost;s life -- giving birth -- is also one of the most dangerous.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>As a result, each year close to 1 million African children are left motherless.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Many of these deaths are avoidable, but not enough is being done to prevent them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Since the turn of the last century, maternal mortality rates worldwide have been in decline but remain high in developing countries, including many African nations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>For these maternal death rates to improve in Africa, governments and international institutions must recognize and introduce policies that tackle the challenges faced by African women in accessing effective reproductive healthcare.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Whilst sub-Saharan Africa has seen a decrease in maternal mortality rates over the past 20 years, there is still a long way to go if the region is to meet its Millennium Development Goals.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>This is largely due to a failure to address political, socio-cultural and financial challenges.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>There has been slow progress in meeting the 2001 Abuja Declaration, in which countries pledged to assign 15% of their national budgets towards healthcare.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>This is compounded by deficits within the health ministries for numerous countries resulting in inadequate funding for maternal services.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Run down resources.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>With limited investment in health resources, many women in sub-Saharan Africa cannot access an adequate healthcare unit during pregnancy and childbirth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Many cannot access one at all, and countless women are forced to walk miles to their nearest health center.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Without transportation most women give birth at home or on the way to hospital, a journey on which too many will suffer fatal complications.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>For women in many rural communities, the norm is for a traditional birth attendant (TBA) to assist the delivery instead of making the trip.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>TBAs often have no formal training and deliver without sterilized equipment, if any, causing yet more risks for mother and baby.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>However, even if a woman does make it to a hospital, she is likely to find herself in one so under-resourced that soon-to-be mothers have to sleep on the floor following delivery because beds are in such short supply.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Women often have to arrive armed with basic resources such as paraffin to light lamps in the event that they go into labor at night.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Without paraffin and power, midwives such as Uganda&amp;apost;s Esther Madudu, who is also the face of the African Medical and Research Foundation (AMREF)&amp;apost;s Stand up for African Mothers global campaign, have to conduct deliveries using the light from their mobile phones and plastic bags over their hands as gloves.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;There is so much work to do&amp;quot;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Esther&amp;apost;s health center is located in the Soroti district in rural Uganda and serves a community of 37,000 people.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>She works tirelessly round the clock to assist mothers in deliveries, as well as trying to offer antenatal and postnatal care.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>But coping with the demand is tough.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>She says there are occasions when she must travel long distances to reach mothers-to-be who cannot reach a health center -- sometimes arriving after they have given birth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Her own health center has just two midwives.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;There is so much work to do and yet there are only a few of us.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>We are forced to work day and night,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>And Esther&amp;apost;s story is sadly not unique.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Many health units are overstretched.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>With no doctors and few qualified midwives, most hospitals and health units cannot accommodate the women that do manage to reach a healthcare facility.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Low pay and difficult working conditions lead to frustration within the existing workforce, which in turn leads to mismanagement of patients.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Women testify that they are mistreated in hospitals and this is just one more reality that encourages them to give birth at home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Lack of information.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>For the majority of Western mums-to-be, the months leading up to the big day are full of scheduled antenatal appointments, classes and ultrasounds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>The nine months of waiting and expecting are crammed full of information on how best to care for the growing life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Pregnancy and childbirth becomes the hot topic of discussion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>And, it doesn&amp;apost;t end when the baby arrives; postnatal care is a core part of midwives&amp;apost; duties in the West.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>For many women in Africa, an astounding lack of information means they simply do not see or understand the reasons for attending antenatal and postnatal health services, let alone see the value added by giving birth at a health center.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Moreover, the absence of information has hampered initiatives designed to prevent mother-to-child infections, as well as immunization.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s for all these reasons that AMREF launched its Stand Up for African Mothers Campaign, which aims to train 15,000 midwives by 2015 because, as AMREF asserts, midwives save lives.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Increasing the number of trained midwives will mean more than seven million mothers annually will be cared for and informed, which means many more children will be raised in the arms of their mothers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>The joyful birth of the Duke and Duchess of Cambridge&amp;apost;s baby is a wondrous occasion, an everyday miracle that deserves to be commemorated and honored.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>But whilst we celebrate the arrival of a royal newborn, perhaps we should also spare a thought for those 440 women across sub-Saharan Africa who will lose their lives today simply giving birth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
