<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="913" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/07/02/opinion/ghitis-israeli-teens/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-07-02 12:46:13" category="opinion" author="Frida Ghitis" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Opinion: Teens&amp;apost; killing bad for Mideast peace</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="53">Frida Ghitis: The killing of three Israeli students hurts Mideast peace process .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8">Ghitis: Israelis are consumed with grief, but they are watching how the world reacts .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="54">She says Palestinians who are outraged should speak out loudly against the tragedy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="55">Ghitis: That would spark a positive reaction and create energy toward reconciliation .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-05 10:34:45" annotation_time="25.917665">
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">Israelis today are consumed with grief, but they are watching how the world reacts.</sentence>
      <sentence id="53" ids_highlights="1">This killing hurts Israelis and Palestinians who want peace.</sentence>
      <sentence id="54" ids_highlights="3">The only way this tragedy could be turned into a positive step would be if the Palestinians who support reconciliation, who are outraged by what happened, would speak out loudly against it.</sentence>
      <sentence id="55" ids_highlights="4">That would spark a positive reaction and create energy toward reconciliation.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The people who killed three Israeli teenagers have hurt the Israeli people deeply, there&amp;apost;s no doubt about that.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But they have also harmed Palestinians, and they have hurt the cause of peace.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Anyone who fails to condemn this horrific act -- the murder of students going home from school -- is contributing to the poison that makes peace so difficult in the Mideast.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Anyone who hesitates, who equivocates, is helping to prolong the conflict.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>For Palestinians and their supporters around the world, if you remain silent about the killing of Israelis, you are adding to the duration and bitterness of this conflict.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Excuse this atrocity, and you condemn the people of this area to remain enemies for the foreseeable future.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>That does not mean you cannot criticize Israeli actions, but the cold-blooded murder of Israeli children will have the effect of making Israelis less willing to believe they can accept Palestinians as their neighbors and live in peace.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Israelis today are consumed with grief, but they are watching how the world reacts.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>They are watching how Palestinians react.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>I, for one, am convinced that the vast majority of Israelis would strongly support, even advocate and push for a withdrawal from the West Bank if they really believed that they would be safe living alongside a Palestinian state.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>These attacks undermine their confidence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>They provide evidence to back the claim that Palestinians will never let that happen, that what they really want is to destroy Israel.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>In the hours after we learned that bodies of the three teens -- Eyal Yifrach, 19, Gilad Shaar, 16 and Naftali Frankel, 16 -- had been found under a pile of rocks in a field near Hebron, reaction has been predictable and often disheartening, just as it was when we found out someone had kidnapped them on June 12.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Frankel, it&amp;apost;s worth noting, was an American citizen, which brings up the question of how the United States will respond to his killing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Secretary of State John Kerry said earlier that &amp;quot;many indications point to Hamas involvement,&amp;quot; noting that Hamas, designated as a terrorist organization by many countries, has used kidnappings in the past.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The FBI says it has launched an investigation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The atrocities were swiftly condemned by some countries.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>On social media, there has been a flurry of accusations against Israel ahead of what is expected to be a strong Israeli reaction against Hamas, which Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu says he is absolutely sure carried out the operation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>But others were slow to comment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>It took the European Union&amp;apost;s foreign policy chief almost a week to condemn the kidnappings.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>She did it only after Israel complained about European silence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Days earlier, Israeli forces rushed into the West Bank in an urgent and ultimately unsuccessful effort to find the three before they were killed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The military deployment produced clashes with protesters in which five Palestinians were killed by Israeli soldiers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>That received a great deal of attention.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The mothers of the kidnapped students appealed for help at the U.N. Human Rights Council in Geneva, describing &amp;quot;every mother&amp;apost;s nightmare...waiting and waiting endlessly for her child to come home.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>They described their children, one was an amateur pastry chef.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Another &amp;quot;loves to play guitar and basketball.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s a good student and a good boy,&amp;quot; said a heartbroken Racheli Frankel of her son Neftali.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>But the Human Rights Council reacted to her tearful words with chilling indifference.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Many others, including human rights organizations, tempered their criticism of the kidnapping by calling the boys &amp;quot;settlers.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The truth is that two of the three did not live on the West Bank.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>They lived west of the Green Line well inside Israel.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The third lived in a settlement called Efrat, in the Gush Etzion area, which was in Jewish hands before the 1967 war, even before the 1948 war, and even Jimmy Carter, a harsh critic of Israeli settlement, agrees it will remain in Israel after a Palestinian state is created.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Every peace plan has agreed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>But that&amp;apost;s hardly relevant.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>The teens were students, not warriors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Kidnappings are immoral.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Murder is inhuman.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>For some Palestinians, the kidnapping was cause for celebration.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>A new three-finger salute became popular, marking the capture of three Israelis.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>The Facebook page for Fatah, the Palestinian Authority&amp;apost;s main party, had a number of cartoons, including one showing the three teenagers as Jewish rats, wearing yarmulkes, caught on a fishing line.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>To his great credit, Palestinian Authority President Mahmoud Abbas condemned the kidnapping.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>For that, he came under fierce criticism.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Hamas, which is now part of the Palestinian Authority government in a unity deal with Fatah, made no effort to conceal its glee.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Hamas denies it had anything to do with the kidnapping.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>But earlier, its exiled chief, Khaled Meshal, was ambiguous about responsibility, saying only &amp;quot;I congratulate the abductors.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Opinion: Slain teens call for justice, not escalation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>When Israeli authorities named two Hamas members as the perpetrators, the mother of one of the men told Israeli television &amp;quot;If he did it, I&amp;apost;ll be proud of him.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>She joins other Palestinian mothers proud of children who commit murder, adding to Israelis&amp;apost; doubts about future coexistence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Israelis are watching closely to see what Abbas does about his unity deal with Hamas, an organization that is openly committed to Israel&amp;apost;s destruction.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>If Israel can show definitive proof that Hamas was indeed behind the kidnapping and killing, it is inconceivable that Abbas would let the unity deal stand.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>It is even more inconceivable that the United States and Europe would continue providing millions to support the Palestinian Authority under those conditions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>This killing hurts Israelis and Palestinians who want peace.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>The only way this tragedy could be turned into a positive step would be if the Palestinians who support reconciliation, who are outraged by what happened, would speak out loudly against it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>That would spark a positive reaction and create energy toward reconciliation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>Can that happen?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>In this atmosphere, we can only hope for a positive surprise.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>