<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="786" link="http://cnn.com/2014/05/16/opinion/landrieu-charter-schools/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-05-16 10:39:22" category="opinion" author="Mary L. Landrieu" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Charter schools: Let every child have access</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="11">Sen. Mary Landrieu believes that more kids should have access to charter schools.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12">Enrollment in charter schools, she says, has grown by 100% from 2007 to 2013.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="13">But she says there are still nearly 1 million students on waitlists for charter schools.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="20">Landrieu supports a bill that will allow for more than 500 schools to open in the next five years.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-10 14:45:48" annotation_time="26.052668">
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="1">Over the past 20 years, the growth of charter schools has shown not only the high demand for high-quality options, but also the importance for ensuring that students and families have the opportunity to seek an alternative rather than be trapped in a &amp;quot;one-size-fits-all,&amp;quot; low performing school, as too many students across the country are.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">Enrollment in charter schools has grown by 100% from 2007 to 2013.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="3">While that demand continues to grow, there are still nearly 1 million students on waitlists for charter schools -- a lost opportunity for families who seek quality options for their children.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="4">This legislation will allow for more than 500 schools to open annually in the next five years, allowing that waitlist of nearly 1 million students to happily be reduced.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>When my kids were young, I cherished watching their excitement when they shared what they learned at school, like the first time my daughter read &amp;quot;The Cat in the Hat&amp;quot; to me and my son correctly counted out his allowance.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Every parent deserves to share such moments with their child.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Unfortunately, in some communities, there is little or no choice for parents to provide their children with a good education from a quality school.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Our public education system is failing far too many children and their families, but there is a proven solution that we&amp;apost;ve in my home state and across the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Charter schools have successfully provided an education alternatives to children in our nation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>In the 1990s, there were a mere 20 charter schools in Minnesota.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Today, there are nearly 6,500 charter schools in the nation serving 2 million students.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Charter schools bring promise and opportunity to families and communities that might not otherwise have it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>In many neighborhoods in each of our states, we&amp;apost;ve seen how high-performing charter schools can literally build or rebuild a community.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>For example, in a study released recently, the Center for Research on Education Outcomes (CREDO) found that students in charter schools in Louisiana were outperforming their peers at traditional public schools in reading and math.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Over the past 20 years, the growth of charter schools has shown not only the high demand for high-quality options, but also the importance for ensuring that students and families have the opportunity to seek an alternative rather than be trapped in a &amp;quot;one-size-fits-all,&amp;quot; low performing school, as too many students across the country are.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Enrollment in charter schools has grown by 100% from 2007 to 2013.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>While that demand continues to grow, there are still nearly 1 million students on waitlists for charter schools -- a lost opportunity for families who seek quality options for their children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Earlier this year, we witnessed a huge success in the charter school movement as the newly elected and misguided Mayor Bill de Blasio of New York City stood down from his fight against charter schools thanks to the leadership of Gov. Andrew Cuomo and a leading, successful charter school champion, Success Academy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>This year, Congress was also able to convince the U.S. Department of Education to allow for the use of weighted lotteries to favor students with disabilities, educational challenges, and students from low-income families.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>In 2013, 12 states made improvements to their state laws, including laws around funding, facilities, and quality authorizing practices.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Perhaps what will be the most critical change in policy this year comes in the form of rare, but promising, bipartisan and bicameral support of an update to the Charter School Program.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>This week, we introduced the Expanding Opportunity through Quality Charter Schools Act, which offers funding to new and promising charter schools as well high-performing charter schools with a track record of success.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>This bill makes a smart update to the Charter School Program by allowing for increased and flexible use of funding, and it prioritizes access to facilities as well as continually increased student achievement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>This legislation will allow for more than 500 schools to open annually in the next five years, allowing that waitlist of nearly 1 million students to happily be reduced.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>More importantly, this legislation emphasizes the need for high-quality public charter schools to be an ever-important solution to ensuring access to a quality education.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Perhaps one day soon, even more American families will get to experience that joy of their child reading to them and their kids thriving at a quality school.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
