<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="875" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/06/21/opinion/robbins-campus-sexual-assaults/index.html" date_published="2014-06-21 17:12:28" category="opinion" author="Mel Robbins" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Opinion: George Will is so wrong about sexual assault</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7, 1">Mel Robbins: George Will&amp;apost;s views about sexual assault on campuses are wrong .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="55">Robbins: He&amp;apost;s out of touch with reality, trivializes the problem, and blames women.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="11">Colleges tried to sweep assault cases under the rug, but students complained .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="57">Robbins: Women who are assaulted are victims, not people with &amp;quot;coveted status&amp;quot;.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-28 13:37:08" annotation_time="157.38133" mapping_time_divergence="78.69067">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">By now you&amp;apost;ve either heard about or read George Will&amp;apost;s controversial column on the issue of sexual assault on college campuses.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">The fact is, George Will is so wrong.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="3">Colleges prefer to sweep sexual assault cases under the rug, but students have brought the issue to light.</sentence>
      <sentence id="55" ids_highlights="2">Actually, it&amp;apost;s George Will who&amp;apost;s trivializing the problem.</sentence>
      <sentence id="57" ids_highlights="4">The reason why so many women haven&amp;apost;t come forward until now is because victims assumed nothing would happen, or even worse, they&amp;apost;d face someone like George Will who&amp;apost;d put the blame right back on the victim.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>By now you&amp;apost;ve either heard about or read George Will&amp;apost;s controversial column on the issue of sexual assault on college campuses.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Will&amp;apost;s take is that the numbers are &amp;quot;preposterous&amp;quot; and using &amp;quot;simple arithmetic&amp;quot; he can prove the &amp;quot;supposed campus epidemic of rape&amp;quot; just ain&amp;apost;t so.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Worse, Will believes that progressivism, the Obama administration, a college hook-up culture and shady math are turning survivors of sexual assault into a &amp;quot;coveted status that confers privilege.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>He goes on to claim that efforts to address the issue on campuses is &amp;quot;making everyone hypersensitive, even delusional, about victimizations.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>I&amp;apost;d no more want to have a conversation with George Will about sexual assault on college campuses than I wish to discuss racism with Donald Sterling.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Both men are shockingly out of touch with reality.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The fact is, George Will is so wrong.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>1.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>George Will argues that &amp;quot;Washington&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;progressivism&amp;quot; are to blame for creating a &amp;quot;supposed&amp;quot; epidemic of campus rape.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Wrong.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Colleges prefer to sweep sexual assault cases under the rug, but students have brought the issue to light.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>In 2011, 16 Yale students and alumni filed a Title IX sexual assault complaint against the university.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Other similar lawsuits emerged across the nation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>As of this moment, there are 55 universities and colleges under investigation by the federal government.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>When Dartmouth (my alma mater) was confronted with the problem, the university experienced an astounding 14% drop in college applications.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Unlike George Will, the president of Dartmouth College, Philip Hanlon, hit it head on:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;From sexual assaults on campus ... to a culture where dangerous drinking has become the rule and not the exception ... to a general disregard for human dignity as exemplified by hazing, parties with racist and sexist undertones, disgusting and sometimes threatening insults hurled on the Internet ... to a social scene that is too often at odds with the practices of inclusion that students are right to expect on a college campus in 2014.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The actions I have detailed are antithetical to everything that we stand for and hope for our students to be.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>There is a grave disconnect between our culture in the classroom and the behaviors outside of it - behaviors which too often seek not to elevate the human spirit, but debase it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>2.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>George Will suggests that women, hook-up culture, alcohol, anything but men, are to blame.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>He cites an example of a student from Swarthmore College in 2013 and condenses her report into two paragraphs -- as if it&amp;apost;s representative of most sexual assault cases.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Is he trying to find a way to blame women?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Women who drink.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Women who say no and fall asleep.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Are they giving up their right to say no if they pass out or fall asleep?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>What about the morality of the man&amp;apost;s actions?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>What respectable young man rolls himself on top of a drunk, sleepy corpse of a woman and forces her to have sex, after she had said no?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Take 25 seconds and watch this brilliant PSA on what a guy should do if he finds himself with a woman passed out, asleep on his couch, or in his bed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s really simple and there&amp;apost;s no gray area or ambiguity: Good guys respect women.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Creeps and criminals take advantage of women.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>3.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>By addressing the problems, colleges are turning sexual assault victims into a &amp;quot;coveted status.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Ask any woman who&amp;apost;s been the victim of a sexual assault, unwanted groping, or date rape and you&amp;apost;ll learn there&amp;apost;s nothing to covet.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>And most definitely it&amp;apost;s not a privilege.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Dr. Jen Gunter, who wrote an open letter to George Will, offers a powerful first-hand perspective that will tell you what goes through the mind of a rape survivor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Victims often feel shame, guilt and fear.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>When they try to report it, they&amp;apost;ll be questioned about their conduct, whether there&amp;apost;s any drinking involved, what they were wearing, whether they&amp;apost;ve had sex with the man before.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>If it&amp;apost;s serious enough and not a &amp;quot;micro-aggression&amp;quot; the attacker might be quietly punished, in a way that makes sure that no parents find out.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>But the victim has to deal with whispers and rumors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>4.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>The simple arithmetic doesn&amp;apost;t make George Will&amp;apost;s point powerful.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>George Will makes a big stink about whether it&amp;apost;s true that &amp;quot;one in five women&amp;quot; could possibly be sexually assaulted during college.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>I could make arguments to counter his math.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>But let&amp;apost;s do this: What if we say there are &amp;quot;only&amp;quot; one in 20 women who are sexually assaulted, rather than one in five?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Does that make this problem less of a problem?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Are those women who are raped less deserving of help?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>If armed robberies on campus happened to one in 20, or one in 20 students got the measles or food poisoning, we would call it an epidemic.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Simply focusing on the validity of the numbers is not a way to invalidate the obligation and importance of universities taking this problem seriously.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>5.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>&amp;quot;I take sexual assault more seriously than you do.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>In his response to the backlash, George Will pulled out the Donald Sterling &amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m not a racist and I&amp;apost;ve never been a racist&amp;quot; defense.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>He says, &amp;quot;I think I take sexual assault much more seriously than you do.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>Which is why I worry about definitions of that category of crime that might, by their breadth, tend to trivialize it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>Actually, it&amp;apost;s George Will who&amp;apost;s trivializing the problem.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>When he summarizes a single story of sexual assault with a giant incredulous eye roll and suggests that a woman&amp;apost;s conduct should be scrutinized more than a man&amp;apost;s in assessing whether a sexual assault even occurred -- he is trivializing a creepy and criminal act.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>The reason why so many women haven&amp;apost;t come forward until now is because victims assumed nothing would happen, or even worse, they&amp;apost;d face someone like George Will who&amp;apost;d put the blame right back on the victim.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
