<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="932" link="http://us.cnn.com/2012/12/05/opinion/wolfe-syria-rape/index.html?hpt=op_t1 " date_published="2012-12-05 13:32:28" category="opinion" author="Lauren Wolfe, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Rape is shredding Syria&amp;apost;s social fabric</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="15">Lauren Wolfe: Rape is a weapon that destroys individuals, families, communities.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="17">Wolfe&amp;apost;s group is documenting reports of rape as they come in on live map of Syria.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="18">Wolfe: More than 20% of women in reports are killed after rape; some kill themselves.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="40">Social shame drives killings, she says, and international community must intervene.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-11 17:44:06" annotation_time="118.15034" mapping_time_divergence="29.537584">
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="1">And the story from the woman in Washington falls all too neatly into the pattern of ripping apart families -- rape and other forms of sexualized violence have long been used as a tool of war to destroy not only individual bodies but entire communities.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="2">In an attempt to not lose a single story that could be used as possible evidence for future war crimes trials, we are documenting reports of sexualized violence on a live, crowd-sourced map on Syria.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="3">We know, however, that evidence of crimes is being destroyed every day: More than 20% of the women in our reports are found dead or are killed after rape.</sentence>
      <sentence id="40" ids_highlights="4">Shame should never fall on victims, but should be used to compel Russia to join a U.N. Security Council call for the Syrian government&amp;apost;s alleged crimes to be referred to the International Criminal Court.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A woman approached me as I was rushing toward the D.C. Metro after giving a talk on rape in Syria last month.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>She asked in a low voice if she could share some information.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>She had DVDs, she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>On them were testimonies of Syrian women who&amp;apost;d been raped; in particular, a mother, a daughter and a sister all in one family.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>In a taxi recently en route to Heathrow Airport, I was told another startling story.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The driver turned to me and said, &amp;quot;I am Syrian.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>And I have a story to tell you that I keep wishing is not true.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>His eyes welled up as he relayed what his neighbor said happened to a friend.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The neighbor described being stopped in his car at a Syrian checkpoint on the road from Zabadani to Damascus.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>He said army officers told him to leave his daughter with them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>My driver said he knew no other details than this, that the man had been given a horrific choice to make: leave his daughter behind, or his wife and other children would be killed in front of his eyes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The man made a decision, the driver said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>He left his daughter at the checkpoint and drove on.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>I keep wishing it is not true, too, but what I told the driver that day is that his story sounds all too familiar: Of the hundreds of cases of sexualized violence against Syrian women and men I have heard and documented as the director of the Women Under Siege project at the Women&amp;apost;s Media Center, many fit this pattern of women and girls being raped at checkpoints.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>And the story from the woman in Washington falls all too neatly into the pattern of ripping apart families -- rape and other forms of sexualized violence have long been used as a tool of war to destroy not only individual bodies but entire communities.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>What is happening in Syria is no exception.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>In an attempt to not lose a single story that could be used as possible evidence for future war crimes trials, we are documenting reports of sexualized violence on a live, crowd-sourced map on Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>We know, however, that evidence of crimes is being destroyed every day: More than 20% of the women in our reports are found dead or are killed after rape.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Broken down by type of crime and perpetrator, each case is marked as a red dot on the map and contains up to dozens or even hundreds of victims.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Each dot is a life or lives potentially ripped apart by a horrific act of violence, an act that is particularly powerful as a weapon in Syria, where honor is so highly prized.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Rape is tearing Syrians apart.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The concept of purity is destroying their lives on top of it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The International Rescue Committee, referring to Syria, reported in August that &amp;quot;girl-child survivors of rape are frequently married to their older cousins or other male members of the community, to &amp;apost;save their honor.&amp;apost; &amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Participants in adolescent girl groups told the IRC that if a girl is raped, &amp;quot;Sometimes she might be killed by her family.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>She might kill herself.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>... She knows that she will be dishonored for the rest of her life.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Honor killings, forced marriages and divorce are just a few of the ways shame is destroying lives in Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>There is also suicide when the shame becomes too much to bear, such as the story on our map telling of a girl in Latakia who reportedly killed herself by jumping off a balcony after rape.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>But the concept of honor is failing Syrian women in another way.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;What I always think about is how women have tried to persuade the perpetrators not to attack them by asking to think of them as their sisters,&amp;quot; said one of the Syrian researchers on our mapping project.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;In Arab culture, a real man will protect his sister at any price.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>He is expected to take revenge if someone dishonors her.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>His sister is his responsibility even if she is married because blood relation is stronger than marriage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The women were appealing to whatever remnant of manhood and Arab honor these attackers might still have.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Unfortunately, they had none.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>The unending &amp;quot;dishonor&amp;quot; and manipulation of Syrians through sexualized violence is committed by all sides, although the majority of our reports indicate government perpetrators.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>It is creating an entire nation of traumatized people: not just the survivors of the acts, but their children as well.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>It is time to stop it all.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>There are measures the world can take to bring these horrors to an end.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Shame should never fall on victims, but should be used to compel Russia to join a U.N. Security Council call for the Syrian government&amp;apost;s alleged crimes to be referred to the International Criminal Court.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Governments can help humanitarian groups that offer medical and psychosocial services for survivors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Syrian women&amp;apost;s rights organizations are already taking action to combat and respond to gender-based violence, including organizing family-based care for displaced children of survivors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>The international community can and should support Syrian civil society in this work.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Shame is a powerful feeling that causes retreat.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>It causes us to lower our heads and look away.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>But we have a chance to lift up the survivors of sexualized violence in Syria and honor them by paying attention, by caring enough to bring their suffering to an end, by telling them that we do not accept the violence against them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Follow @CNNOpinion on Twitter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Join us at Facebook/CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
