<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="943" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/25/opinion/mccain-child-trafficking/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-09-25 17:59:28" category="opinion" author="Cindy McCain" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>To beat trafficking, change mindsets (Opinion)</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6">Human trafficking is a multibillion dollar global industry, Cindy McCain says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">Some 100,000 to 300,000 U.S. children are at risk of being trafficked each year, she says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="14">More training is needed to identify human trafficking victims, McCain says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-07 09:41:42" annotation_time="24.898">
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">Sadly, human trafficking is a multibillion dollar global industry, with some estimates suggesting more than 21 million people are enslaved worldwide.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">Here in the United States, between 100,000 to 300,000 American children are at risk of being trafficked each year, according to the Department of Homeland Security, with the average age of a child first being trafficked just 13.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="3">In addition, more training is needed to identify human trafficking victims.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The issue of human trafficking has exploded into the headlines in recent years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>State and federal legislation has been passed helping to define trafficking more specifically and prosecute traffickers, while services enabling victims to lead productive lives, safely beyond the reach of their traffickers, have been proliferating.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Meanwhile, anti-trafficking organizations are using technology in exciting new ways to find and rescue victims and provide network linkages to prosecute their traffickers successfully.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Yet while such progress is welcome, many groups are only just beginning to focus on a crucial element of beating human trafficking -- cutting demand.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>After all, less demand means fewer trafficked victims.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Sadly, human trafficking is a multibillion dollar global industry, with some estimates suggesting more than 21 million people are enslaved worldwide.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Here in the United States, between 100,000 to 300,000 American children are at risk of being trafficked each year, according to the Department of Homeland Security, with the average age of a child first being trafficked just 13.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Of course, while a trafficker can sell drugs or a gun once, sex with a child can be sold over and over again.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>It is hardly surprising then that there is also increasing evidence that many of the trafficking networks are interconnected with gang activity and drug and gun trafficking.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>A child cannot choose to sell sex for money.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>A minor being sold for sex is by definition being trafficked.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>There is no such thing as a child prostitute, only a sex-trafficked victim.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Thankfully, there is a much needed mindset shift taking place among law enforcement and treatment providers, a change being increasingly embraced by those trained to recognize trafficked victims, but which needs to be accepted by the global community for continued change.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>In addition, more training is needed to identify human trafficking victims.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Law enforcement, first responders, emergency room personnel, pediatricians, school personnel, foster care administrators, child welfare personnel, court-appointed advocates, hotel, airport and taxi staff -- many of whom come into contact with trafficked children without knowing it -- could all benefit from extra training.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Increased awareness and proper protocols can help to identify correctly and get appropriate help to trafficked victims faster.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Many of these victims find themselves in the social service system, where opportunities exist to get them the help they need if they can be correctly identified.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Too often, survivors recount how they crossed paths with adults who could have helped them escape but who didn&amp;apost;t see the situation clearly enough to offer them assistance.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>In the United States, Operation Cross Country, a joint sting operation between the FBI, U.S. Department of Justice and the National Center for Missing and Exploited Children, has recovered more than 3,500 minors since 2003.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The Innocence Lost program recovered 168 victims this summer and arrested 281 pimps.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Overseas, however, we have watched helplessly as Boko Haram has kidnapped hundreds of Nigerian schoolgirls with the stated intent to sell them for sex.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Four months later, and the international community has been unable to rescue them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The individual stories I&amp;apost;ve personally heard from trafficking survivors are heart-wrenching, yet it still happens every day in our country and around the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Sometimes, one victim at a time, sometimes in large groups.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Survivors&amp;apost; stories tell us that some victims are sold into trafficking by family members, some lured by attention and promises of glamour by an &amp;quot;older boyfriend,&amp;quot; only to be abused, branded and sold for sex; labor trafficking victims are often promised high-paying jobs far away from home, only to have their documents taken, their lives and families threatened and horrid working conditions waiting for them with no opportunity for escape.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Runaways are often picked up by traffickers within 48 hours of running away from home, and no one is looking to find them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The common thread is that traffickers prey on society&amp;apost;s most vulnerable.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>So what can we do?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>More than anything, it&amp;apost;s up to us to do everything we can to protect our vulnerable citizens and continue this fight to make our communities and ultimately our world safer.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s up to us to be a voice for the voiceless.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>While we may not yet have a clear strategy for tackling Boko Haram, we can still be aware of the signs of trafficking and speak up in our communities when we see something that just doesn&amp;apost;t look right.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>A shift in mindset about the definition of a trafficked victim, stronger legislation allowing better identification and services for victims and more vigorous prosecutions of traffickers offer a healthy start.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>But we have a long way to go -- there is more to do on all these fronts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>