<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="898" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/07/02/opinion/gingrich-public-confidence-america/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-07-02 16:26:16" category="opinion" author="Newt Gingrich" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Opinion: On America&amp;apost;s birthday, do we still believe?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="9, 7">Newt Gingrich is concerned about poll showing Americans have little faith in government.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="25">Gingrich: If most believe government is corrupt, we are teetering between an uprising and cynicism.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="26">Without change, he says, we could cease to be the land of the free and of opportunity.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-05 15:59:30" annotation_time="54.257" mapping_time_divergence="18.085667">
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">And an abysmal 7% had faith in the Congress.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="1">Our most trusted national institution, the unelected Supreme Court, has the confidence of almost (but not quite) one out of every three Americans.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="2">A country in which 4 out of 5 people believe their government is corrupt is a country teetering between a populist uprising and a collapse into cynicism, passivity, and fatalism.</sentence>
      <sentence id="26" ids_highlights="3">These results suggest we will either renew our commitment to the rule of law, the punishment of corruption and the insistence on honest self-government or we will cease to be America as the land of the free and the land of opportunity.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Americans are in a period of amazingly negative thinking about the state of our country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>A recent Gallup analysis drove home how deep and how threatening the current mood is.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Gallup asked Americans in early June how much confidence they had in our nation&amp;apost;s institutions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The answer: not much.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Only 30% had &amp;quot;a great deal&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;quite a lot of confidence&amp;quot; in the Supreme Court.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Just 29% felt that way about the presidency.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>And an abysmal 7% had faith in the Congress.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Think about what this means.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Our most trusted national institution, the unelected Supreme Court, has the confidence of almost (but not quite) one out of every three Americans.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The presidency is slightly weaker and the Congress collapses to fewer than 1 in 10 Americans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Gallup also did some comparative analysis using findings from its World Poll and the trends regarding Americans&amp;apost; views on government are even more sobering.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>In the poll, 79% of the American people believe corruption is widespread in government.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>That is a jump of 20 points since 2006, when 59% of the country thought government was corrupt (a year when the country was dissatisfied enough that the ruling Republicans lost control of both the House and Senate).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The Gallup analysis demonstrates that Americans are more likely to believe their government is corrupt than people in Brazil, Hungary or Tajikistan, to cite just three examples.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>In January of this year, Gallup found that more Americans picked bad government and corruption as our biggest problem than picked any other challenge, including the economy and unemployment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>These are stunning numbers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>When four out of five Americans believe government is corrupt, something is profoundly wrong.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>It is a lot bigger than Barack Obama or Hillary Clinton or for that matter George W. Bush.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Under the weight of this negativity, there has been a dramatic decline in satisfaction with the freedom we have to choose how we live our own lives.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The number of people saying they are dissatisfied has jumped from 9% in 2006 to 21% in 2013.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>This 12-point jump in dissatisfaction tied the United States for No. 10 among countries suffering the most rapid decline in satisfaction.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The other countries that have experienced drops of that scale are seriously troubled places, including Pakistan, Yemen, Cyprus, and Spain (where youth unemployment is approaching 60%).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>To put this in context, the Gallup numbers show that in 2006 the United States was one of the top countries in the world when it came to satisfaction with freedom.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>By 2013 it had dropped out of the top 25% of all countries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>A country in which 4 out of 5 people believe their government is corrupt is a country teetering between a populist uprising and a collapse into cynicism, passivity, and fatalism.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>These results suggest we will either renew our commitment to the rule of law, the punishment of corruption and the insistence on honest self-government or we will cease to be America as the land of the free and the land of opportunity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>This Fourth of July weekend, we need to remember what our Founding Fathers did to create the liberty we enjoy and dedicate ourselves to a new burst of freedom and a new wave of political reform that cleans up the corruption and re-establishes the right of every American to dream and to work to fulfill that dream.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
