<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="770" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/03/31/opinion/kluwe-gay-player-distraction/index.html" date_published="2013-03-31 22:02:15" category="opinion" author="Chris Kluwe, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>An openly gay player in the NFL is not a distraction</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Chris Kluwe: Pro athletes are told all the time, &amp;quot;Don&amp;apost;t be a distraction&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">He says yes, focus on the game, but revealing your identity is not a distraction.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="17">Gay athletes shouldn&amp;apost;t have to hide their personal lives, he says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="8">Kluwe: It isn&amp;apost;t right that we can&amp;apost;t accept people for who they are.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-05 13:42:40" annotation_time="131.088" mapping_time_divergence="98.315994">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;Don&amp;apost;t be a distraction.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">The message is pushed on us so hard, in fact, that players run the very real risk of losing their jobs if the team deems them too much of a distraction, and unfortunately it seems gay players feel that being comfortable with who they are has to take second place to keeping their jobs.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="4">It&amp;apost;s not right that we can&amp;apost;t just accept someone for who he is.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="3">He will have those of us who realize that people&amp;apost;s sexuality doesn&amp;apost;t define who they are, just as their jobs don&amp;apost;t define who they are, and that guys who bring our wives and children to games and team events are no different than those who would bring their husbands and children.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>&amp;quot;Don&amp;apost;t be a distraction.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>These words are pounded into every single NFL player&amp;apost;s head from the day he enters the league until the day he leaves (and I would imagine it holds true for just about every professional sport).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The same message, over and over and over -- &amp;quot;The team comes first,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Sacrifice your personal goals to win,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Only be judged by what goes on between the lines&amp;quot; -- which is why I find it unsurprising that there are no openly gay athletes in any of the big four professional sports leagues in the U.S.: the NFL, NBA, NHL, and MLB.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The message is pushed on us so hard, in fact, that players run the very real risk of losing their jobs if the team deems them too much of a distraction, and unfortunately it seems gay players feel that being comfortable with who they are has to take second place to keeping their jobs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>This isn&amp;apost;t right.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s not right that professional sports, and especially the professional sports media, have created an environment where gay players are willing to hide essential components of themselves as human beings in order to pursue their dreams, in order to not be a distraction.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s not right that our insatiable lust for sports coverage creates an atmosphere where someone would willingly subordinate his life to a backward and bigoted worldview in order to stay employed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s not right that we can&amp;apost;t just accept someone for who he is.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Why?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Why do people care so much about someone else&amp;apost;s sexuality?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Why do people give two s***s how someone else lives his life?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Why do people have this absolutely idiotic notion that being gay has any sort of effect on how well a player can play football, or basketball, or baseball?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Why the f*** do I even have to write this column for a major news organization to talk about something that shouldn&amp;apost;t even remotely be a factor in sports?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Well, the reason is simple.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>I&amp;apost;m writing this because no gay player is currently out, and the first gay player who eventually does come out needs to know that -- despite all the indoctrination from the league about not being a distraction -- if he&amp;apost;s the one to take the first step, he will have allies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>He will have support.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>He will have those of us who realize that people&amp;apost;s sexuality doesn&amp;apost;t define who they are, just as their jobs don&amp;apost;t define who they are, and that guys who bring our wives and children to games and team events are no different than those who would bring their husbands and children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Most importantly, I&amp;apost;m writing this so that coaches, managers, players, owners and fans realize that the first gay player who comes out won&amp;apost;t spontaneously cause rainbows to erupt out of everyone&amp;apost;s rear.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>In professional sports, the players on a team are a team.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>We eat together.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>We practice together.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>We watch film together, and we succeed or fail together.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>We see each other more than our own families during the season.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>To think that a gay player is suddenly going to destroy all that because he&amp;apost;s out is asinine.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The idea that a gay player will be a distraction needs to change.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Coaches, administrative personnel -- will an openly gay player bring extra attention?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Maybe, but guess what -- there&amp;apost;s a whole bunch of other crap that happens during the season every year, anything from sexting to arrests to profane letters, and somehow we&amp;apost;ve managed to find a way through it each time without the entire edifice of football collapsing into ruin.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Instead of looking at an openly gay player as a distraction, ask yourselves -- how much better would that player play if he didn&amp;apost;t have to worry about hiding a core part of who he is?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>How many more sacks would he have, free of that pressure?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>How many more receptions?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>How many more rushing yards?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Fans, media -- will an openly gay player be a distraction?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Only if you make it one.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Only if you insist on denying someone the freedom to live his own life on his own terms, instead of under someone else&amp;apost;s control.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Stop worrying about who a player dates; worry about his completion percentage, or tackles for loss, or return average.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>I can promise you, on Sundays the only thing he&amp;apost;s worried about is lining up and doing his job to the best of his ability, or else he&amp;apost;s going to be cut (just like any of us).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Players -- Those of you worried about a gay teammate checking out your ass in the shower, or hitting on you in the steam room, or bringing too much attention to the team -- I have four simple words for you.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Grow the f*** up.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>This is our job, we are adults, so would you kindly act like one?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>There are millions of people across America who work with gay co-workers every day, and they handle their business without riotous orgies consuming the work environment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>In the extremely unlikely event that a gay player harasses you?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>We have an HR department.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>File a complaint, just the way a female employee would if you harassed her.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>If the media want to ask you about a gay teammate?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s a teammate, and you&amp;apost;re focused on winning -- together.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>As a team.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>And finally, to the gay player who does eventually come out, whoever that brave individual happens to be -- will you have to deal with media attention, with heightened scrutiny?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Yes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Despite everything Brendon, Scott, myself, and all your other allies do, despite all the articles we write and interviews we give, despite the growing acceptance across this entire country, there are going to be people who insist on looking at you through the lens of your sexuality, and not at your skills as a football player.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>But you know what?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>All of us understand the truth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>You are a teammate, a friend, and you do not have to sacrifice who you are for the team to win, no matter what anyone else says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>You are not a distraction.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>Follow @CNNOpinion on Twitter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>Join us at Facebook/CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
