<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1141" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/05/30/politics/republicans-obamacare-issue/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-05-30 20:50:06" category="politics" author="Leigh Ann Caldwell, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Wait -- Obamacare isn&amp;apost;t an issue?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="24">Republicans are broadening their message beyond Obamacare.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">Polling suggests that fewer people want to repeal the law.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="30">Republicans voted more than 50 times to repeal Obamacare after it was enacted.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-11 10:40:42" annotation_time="294.845" mapping_time_divergence="98.28167">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">Senate Republican Leader Mitch McConnell, who is in a reelection bid against surprisingly strong Democrat Alison Lundergan Grimes, recently said that while he wants to repeal the law, Kentucky&amp;apost;s version, Kynect, is &amp;quot;unconnected&amp;quot; to the fate of Obamacare.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="1">Republicans are now retooling their message, after having emerged from primary battles of who&amp;apost;s farther to the right they must now try to appeal to a more diverse audience that has become more accepting of the federal health care program approved in 2010 without Republican support.</sentence>
      <sentence id="30" ids_highlights="3">Since Republicans gained control of the House in 2011, they voted more than 50 times on a full or partial repeal of the health care law, that&amp;apost;s more than one vote per month, but the pace has fallen off dramatically in recent months.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington The Affordable Care Act, aka Obamacare, might not be the Republican Party&amp;apost;s key to electoral victory as once thought.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Patterns are emerging that Republicans and like-minded groups are broadening their scope and not homing in on a singular anti-Obamacare message.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>In March, Reince Priebus, head of the Republican National Committee, told CNN&amp;apost;s Candy Crowley that Obamacare is &amp;quot;complete poison&amp;quot; and advised Republican candidates they &amp;quot;have to hit your main target which is Obamacare&amp;quot; in order to win.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>But in the political world, things change fast, and March is the equivalent to a millennium ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Senate Republican Leader Mitch McConnell, who is in a reelection bid against surprisingly strong Democrat Alison Lundergan Grimes, recently said that while he wants to repeal the law, Kentucky&amp;apost;s version, Kynect, is &amp;quot;unconnected&amp;quot; to the fate of Obamacare.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Kynect is relatively popular in Kentucky, providing insurance coverage to more than 413,000 people, but was created under the Affordable Care Act and is funded mostly through federal funds.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>McConnell&amp;apost;s shift is subtle but meaningful.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>During his primary campaign against a candidate who billed himself as more conservative than McConnell, the Senate leader took a hard-line stance on getting rid of -- or repealing -- Obamacare, which has been the Republican mantra until recently.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s not the only one.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Americans for Prosperity, which is expected to spend north of $100 million this election cycle backing issues that Republicans favor, has also shifted its strategy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>In the lead up to the launch of Obamacare last fall, during its disastrous rollout and in the months after, AFP had a laser-like focus on the issue, spending tens of millions of dollars in states and districts where Democrats are vulnerable.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;We do want to make sure that Obamacare is the Number One issue in the country,&amp;quot; AFP President Tim Phillips said in February.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>At that time, the law had been in effect for less than two months, it was lagging behind its target enrollment pace and the effects of a bad roll out still permeated.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Phillips said Obamacare is going to be the top issue because the &amp;quot;tidal wave affects are going to continue with Obamacare.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Furthermore, a March 15 statement on the organization&amp;apost;s website described itself as the &amp;quot;nation&amp;apost;s foremost advocate for health care freedom.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>But now, two months later, AFP has broadened its scope.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Its website now features a campaign against the Export-Import Bank, which is not related to Obamacare.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Also, an ad airing in Louisiana, where Democratic Sen. Mary Landrieu is locked in a tight reelection race, attacks her for &amp;quot;wasteful government spending.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Missing from the ad -- the word &amp;quot;Obamacare.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>In addition, its partner group, AFP Foundation, launched an $850,000 ad buy in Wisconsin earlier this week that focuses on taxes and also doesn&amp;apost;t mention the O-word.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>AFP doesn&amp;apost;t deny it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re responding to the changing environment,&amp;quot; AFP spokesman Levi Russell said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;That initial shock (of Obamacare) has changed a little bit, but it hasn&amp;apost;t gone away.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Republicans are now retooling their message, after having emerged from primary battles of who&amp;apost;s farther to the right they must now try to appeal to a more diverse audience that has become more accepting of the federal health care program approved in 2010 without Republican support.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Polling suggests that public attitudes are shifting.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The latest CNN poll from early May found that 38% of people wanted to either replace the law or get rid of it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The results are similar to a CBS poll which found 35% of respondents said the law needs to be repealed, which is a far better billing than the 43% who felt the same way in November.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Elizabeth Wilner with the Cook Political Report, a nonpartisan polling group, wrote that Republicans are starting to use the word &amp;quot;fix&amp;quot; in their campaigning, instead of &amp;quot;repeal.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;Republicans have been gearing up for months ... to run against Obamacare, then it started to work,&amp;quot; Michael Czin, spokesman for the Democratic National Committee said, noting that 8 million people have signed up.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Since Republicans gained control of the House in 2011, they voted more than 50 times on a full or partial repeal of the health care law, that&amp;apost;s more than one vote per month, but the pace has fallen off dramatically in recent months.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>That matters because in an election year, congressional business is connected to electoral politics as lawmakers want to either promote their agenda or tarnish the other party.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>But Russell predicts the issue will not go away, especially as the elections approach and new premium rates are announced this fall.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;Our role is going to be to remind folks how we got here in the first place,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
