<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="984" link="http://www.cnn.com/2011/11/09/politics/arizona-recall-vote/index.html" date_published="2011-11-09 06:52:51" category="politics" author="the CNN Wire Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Author of tough Arizona immigration law loses recall election</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="18">A petition drive forced the recall election for Russell Pearce.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">Jerry Lewis led with 53.4% of the vote with all precincts reporting.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">Pearce got 45.3% of the vote, election officials say .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="1">Pearce wrote Arizona&amp;apost;s controversial immigration law.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-28 13:46:06" annotation_time="33.836" mapping_time_divergence="8.459">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="4">The state senator who wrote Arizona&amp;apost;s controversial immigration law conceded defeat Tuesday night in a recall election widely seen as a referendum on tough measures against illegal immigrants.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">The recall petition pitted him against fellow Republican Jerry Lewis, who led with 53.4% of the vote with all precincts reporting.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">Pearce got 45.3%, election officials said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="1">The recall petition drive against Pearce collected more than 10,000 signatures.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The state senator who wrote Arizona&amp;apost;s controversial immigration law conceded defeat Tuesday night in a recall election widely seen as a referendum on tough measures against illegal immigrants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;I want to thank those people who have stood by me,&amp;quot; said Russell Pearce, who represented a suburban Phoenix district.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;It doesn&amp;apost;t look like the numbers are going my direction ... and I&amp;apost;m OK with that.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The recall petition pitted him against fellow Republican Jerry Lewis, who led with 53.4% of the vote with all precincts reporting.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Pearce got 45.3%, election officials said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;If being recalled is the price for keeping my promises, then so be it,&amp;quot; Pearce said surrounded by supporters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The heated campaign has included accusations of dirty tricks, with Lewis supporters saying a third candidate who later dropped out but remains on the ballot -- Olivia Cortes -- was intended to siphon votes from him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Pearce, a former Phoenix-area sheriff&amp;apost;s deputy known for his tough stance against illegal immigration, sponsored the state immigration law that became the focus of national media and legal attention.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;With Sen. Russell Pearce&amp;apost;s defeat in this recall election, everyone who practices the politics of fear and division was put on notice,&amp;quot; said Rep. Raul Grijalva, a Democrat from Arizona.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s not a substantive platform, and his own constituents clearly said they demand more from their elected officials.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a game-changer for the state of Arizona that&amp;apost;s going to have serious, and I think very positive, ripple effects all across this country.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Passed in 2010, the Arizona law aimed to &amp;quot;discourage and deter the unlawful entry and presence of aliens and economic activity by persons unlawfully present in the United States.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Among other provisions, it would require that local police, during the enforcement of other laws, check the immigration status of anyone they suspected of being undocumented.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The U.S. Court of Appeals for the 9th Circuit said the measure overstepped Arizona&amp;apost;s authority, and the state is seeking a U.S. Supreme Court ruling to settle the issue.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Pearce contends dozens of other states are trying to pass similar legislation, showing the popular support and need for such measures.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Lewis, who says the controversial law has made Arizona a national pariah, said he ran out of dissatisfaction with how Pearce has represented the 18th District.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Lewis has called for what he characterizes as a more cooperative stance against illegal immigration, one that seeks solutions in concert with the federal government and other players.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The recall petition drive against Pearce collected more than 10,000 signatures.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
