<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1082" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/23/politics/syria-airstrikes-congress-reaction/index.html?hpt=hp_t1" date_published="2014-09-23 05:36:42" category="politics" author="Deirdre Walsh, CNN Senior Congressional Producer " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Lawmakers react airstrikes in Syria</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Congress had already left town as airstrikes started in Syria.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Most statements of support came from congressional Republicans.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">Obama notified House Speaker and House Minority Leader.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="11">Sen. Lindsey Graham, one of Obama&amp;apost;s fiercest critics, was notified by vice president.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 08:04:31" annotation_time="21.005">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1"> As the Pentagon launched a barrage of airstrikes into Syria late Monday, Sen. Tim Kaine, D-Virginia, who was an early backer of President Obama&amp;apost;s first presidential campaign and his hand-picked chairman to run the Democratic National Committee, says he is concerned about presidential military action into Syria without congressional authorization.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">It was notable that most of the statements of support after the air campaign began came from congressional Republicans.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">On Monday Obama personally called House Speaker John Boehner and House Minority Leader Nancy Pelosi to notify them that the military operation inside Syria would begin later in the evening.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="4">Vice President Joe Biden reached out to one of the administration&amp;apost;s most vocal critics, South Carolina Sen. Lindsey Graham.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>As the Pentagon launched a barrage of airstrikes into Syria late Monday, Sen. Tim Kaine, D-Virginia, who was an early backer of President Obama&amp;apost;s first presidential campaign and his hand-picked chairman to run the Democratic National Committee, says he is concerned about presidential military action into Syria without congressional authorization.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>It was notable that most of the statements of support after the air campaign began came from congressional Republicans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Both the House and Senate recessed last week so that members could go home to campaign for the midterm elections.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Before Congress left both chambers voted on a narrow measure that gave President Barack Obama the authority to train and arm Syrian rebel groups.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>But Republicans and Democrats on Capitol Hill were split on the question about whether the administration had the authority to use an existing authorization to combat al Qaeda as the justification for continuing or expanding an airstrike campaign against ISIS in Iraq and Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The administration argued it didn&amp;apost;t need any new authority, but some members maintained that it was Congress&amp;apost; role, not the President&amp;apost;s, to declare war.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>House and Senate leaders said they were open to holding a vote on a new measure giving new parameters for military action against ISIS -- but not until after the election.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The news that five Arab nations joined the United States in the military operation will certainly help reassure those on Capitol Hill who warned against the United States taking the lead on a fight without the support of those in the region.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Most members of Congress expected the airstrikes to occur after they returned home to their districts, and privately many of them conceded that they were relieved not to have to take a vote on a controversial issue just weeks before voters went to the polls in November.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>On Monday Obama personally called House Speaker John Boehner and House Minority Leader Nancy Pelosi to notify them that the military operation inside Syria would begin later in the evening.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Vice President Joe Biden reached out to one of the administration&amp;apost;s most vocal critics, South Carolina Sen. Lindsey Graham.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Graham told CNN&amp;apost;s Dana Bash that Biden told him the airstrikes would be &amp;quot;intense&amp;quot; and a &amp;quot;sustained effort.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Biden also called both the Senate Intelligence Chair Dianne Feinstein, D-California, and the top Republican on the panel, Sen. Saxby Chambliss, R-Georgia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>In a statement Chambliss noted the support of other nations: &amp;quot;I commend our allies in the region for stepping up and demonstrating their commitment to the fight against ISIL.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>I&amp;apost;m hopeful these strikes directed at hard targets will result in measurable progress towards degrading ISIL&amp;apost;s capabilities and possibly even taking out ISIL fighters and leadership.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Key cabinet leaders also reached out to top committee leaders.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Defense Secretary Chuck Hagel called House Armed Services Chair Buck McKeon, and National Security Advisor Susan Rice called House Foreign Affairs Chairman Ed Royce.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>In a statement late Monday night McKeon said, &amp;quot;This is one step in what will be a long fight against ISIL.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>With strong coalition partners, a capable military, and a clear mission; it is a fight we can win.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>House Homeland Committee Chairman Michael McCaul released a statement shortly after the news broke, and the Texas Republican pledged his support for the mission.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;To defeat ISIS, we must cut off the head of the snake, which exists in Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>I support the administration&amp;apost;s move to conduct airstrikes against ISIS wherever it exists,&amp;quot; McCaul said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>But Michigan GOP Rep. Justin Amash, who opposed the legislation giving the administration the authority to send weapons to moderate Syrian groups, ripped congressional leaders for skipping out on a debate on military action.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s irresponsible &amp;amp; immoral that instead of debating &amp;amp; voting on war, congressional leaders chose to recess Congress for nearly two months,&amp;quot; Amash said in a tweet on Monday night.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>