<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1148" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/11/07/politics/fiscal-cliff/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2012-11-08 00:33:49" category="politics" author="Ted Barrett and Deirdre Walsh, CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>With &amp;apost;fiscal cliff&amp;apost; looming, Congress facing compromise or confrontation</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Congress faces an end-of-the-year deadline or &amp;quot;fiscal cliff&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">Massive spending cuts are scheduled to kick in and tax breaks begin to expire.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">Both parties agree Tuesday&amp;apost;s vote was a mandate to compromise, avoid the fiscal cliff.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="1">But party leaders continue to sharply disagree over the key issue of top tax rates.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-23 09:42:11" annotation_time="46.541">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="3, 4">Washington A day after an election that both parties agreed was a mandate to find compromise and avoid the so-called fiscal cliff, Democratic and Republican congressional leaders also continued to sharply disagree over the key issue of whether top tax rates should be raised to help resolve the looming crisis.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1, 2">Congress faces an end-of-the-year deadline before massive spending cuts kick in and tax breaks begin to expire, including the Bush-era tax cuts at the end of December.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington A day after an election that both parties agreed was a mandate to find compromise and avoid the so-called fiscal cliff, Democratic and Republican congressional leaders also continued to sharply disagree over the key issue of whether top tax rates should be raised to help resolve the looming crisis.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Republicans said higher rates would damage the economy, while Democrats said it was the only equitable way to tackle the debt.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Congress faces an end-of-the-year deadline before massive spending cuts kick in and tax breaks begin to expire, including the Bush-era tax cuts at the end of December.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The fiscal cliff also includes so-called sequestration -- automatic across-the-board spending cuts set to trigger at the beginning of 2013 if Capitol Hill fails to create a deficit-reduction plan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>In a formal speech on Capitol Hill Wednesday, House Speaker John Boehner sounded conciliatory even as he made it clear higher tax rates would be unacceptable to Republicans who control the House.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;For the purposes of forging a bipartisan agreement that begins to solve the problem, we&amp;apost;re willing to accept new revenue, under the right conditions,&amp;quot; Boehner said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The speaker then insisted the revenue come from &amp;quot;a growing economy, energized by a simpler, cleaner, fair tax code, with fewer loopholes and lower rates for all,&amp;quot; and not from higher rates on higher earners.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>As part of a broader compromise, Boehner said that tax reform must be coupled with &amp;quot;concrete steps to put our country&amp;apost;s entitlement programs on a sounder financial footing.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>A Senate Democratic leadership aide complained Boehner&amp;apost;s approach on revenue -- which might not require the wealthy to pay more -- was &amp;quot;insufficient&amp;quot; and would not raise enough money to have a significant impact on the deficit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Earlier Wednesday, Senate Majority Leader Harry Reid said that he and Boehner had a &amp;quot;pleasant conversation&amp;quot; by phone and that he didn&amp;apost;t expect either man to &amp;quot;draw any lines in the sand&amp;quot; ahead of negotiations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>But Reid insisted several times that raising taxes on wealthier Americans has to be part of any compromise to resolve the crisis and, emboldened by election gains in the House and Senate, Reid said Republicans &amp;quot;can&amp;apost;t push us around&amp;quot; on the issue.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;There was a message sent to us by the American people, based on the campaign,&amp;quot; Reid said at a news conference.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;People making all this money have to contribute a little bit more.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>In his speech, Boehner said he hopes an agreement can be reached &amp;quot;that sends a signal to our economy, and to the world, that after years of punting on the major fiscal challenges we face, 2013 is going to be different.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>But he also said he didn&amp;apost;t think a deal could be struck in the next month and a half during a lame duck session of Congress.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Instead, he wants to reach an agreement with Democrats on a framework or bridge that would postpone the cuts and tax-rate changes for one year until a broader deal on deficit reduction -- including entitlement and tax reform -- can be worked out.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s at odds with Reid who said he opposes &amp;quot;kicking the can down the road&amp;quot; anymore.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Waiting for a month, six weeks, six months, that&amp;apost;s not going to solve the problem,&amp;quot; Reid said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;We know what needs to be done.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>So, I think that we should just roll up our sleeves and get it done.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Boehner and top House GOP leaders held a conference call with all House Republicans shortly before the speaker made his speech.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>According to two participants on the call the speaker gave a full readout of what he planned to say publicly, and while he reinforced his pledge not to agree to tax increases, he did urge rank and file members to give him some room to negotiate with the White House.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>A senior GOP aide said that the ideas that Boehner outlined in his speech Wednesday were similar to the revenue proposal that Pennsylvania GOP Sen. Pat Toomey and other Republicans on the &amp;quot;supercommittee&amp;quot; offered last summer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is the framework that everyone has been talking about,&amp;quot; the aide said, and admitted, referring to the two parties&amp;apost; differences on the details on the revenue side.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;We haven&amp;apost;t been able to thread the needle yet.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Boehner&amp;apost;s spokesman said there are no meetings scheduled yet between the speaker and the president, and reiterated that any deal needs to be hashed out between the principals, not in a public back-and-forth series of photo ops.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Senate Republican Leader Mitch McConnell reinforced Boehner&amp;apost;s opposition to higher tax rates and he argued it&amp;apost;s up to President Obama to &amp;quot;propose a way for both parties to work together in avoiding the fiscal cliff without harming a weak and fragile economy.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;Now is the time for the President to propose solutions that actually have a chance of passing the Republican-controlled House and a closely-divided Senate,&amp;quot; McConnell said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>To that point, a top Senate GOP aide argued that many of the Democrats who won Senate seats Tuesday in swing states like North Dakota, Montana, Virginia and West Virginia, didn&amp;apost;t campaign on raising top rates.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The aide said there are several moderate Democrats from GOP-leaning states up for re-election in two years who will chafe against raising taxes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>President Obama weighed in as well by placing separate calls to Reid, Boehner, McConnell, and House Democratic Leader Nancy Pelosi.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The White House said he told them tax increases for wealthy Americans need to be part of a deal avoid the fiscal cliff and reduce the debt.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Speaking to the seriousness given to his speech, Boehner employed a teleprompter to help him deliver it smoothly.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Such devices, popular with presidents, are rarely used on Capitol Hill.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The speaker did not take any questions when it ended.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
