<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1124" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/06/25/politics/health-care-ruling/index.html" date_published="2012-06-25 04:52:32" category="politics" author="Bill Mears, CNN Supreme Court Producer" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Supreme Court to rule Thursday on health care</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">NEW: The Supreme Court decision on health care will come Thursday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="36">A ruling is expected later in the week .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="14">The Affordable Care Act was passed in March 2010 along partisan lines.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="18">The law requires individuals to buy health insurance or face a fine.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-25 08:22:49" annotation_time="95.539505">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Washington The U.S. Supreme Court will rule Thursday on the constitutionality of the sweeping health care law championed by President Barack Obama.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="3">After a lengthy and heated debate marked by intense opposition from the health insurance industry and conservative groups, the law passed Congress along strictly partisan lines in March 2010.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="4">It also required individuals to buy health insurance, either through their employers or a state-sponsored exchange, or face a fine beginning in 2014.</sentence>
      <sentence id="36" ids_highlights="2">But 76% of respondents in the March CNN/ORC poll said a Supreme Court ruling against the law still wouldn&amp;apost;t change their minds about whom to vote for in November.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington The U.S. Supreme Court will rule Thursday on the constitutionality of the sweeping health care law championed by President Barack Obama.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The high court announced a series of other decisions on Monday, but not the most anticipated one.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>It announced that all remaining rulings for the year will come in three days.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The stakes cannot be overstated -- what the justices decide will have an immediate and long-term impact on all Americans, both in how they get medicine and health care, and also in vast, yet unknown areas of &amp;quot;commerce.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Saving this ruling for the final day &amp;quot;may not be political, but they understand drama,&amp;quot; said David Cole, a Georgetown University constitutional law professor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>He added, &amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s also the most difficult case, the most important case, so they may want the extra few days to make sure that they&amp;apost;re happy with their written opinions.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The nation&amp;apost;s highest court heard three days of politically charged hearings in March on the 2010 Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act, a landmark but controversial measure passed by congressional Democrats despite pitched Republican opposition.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The challenge focused primarily on the law&amp;apost;s requirement that most Americans buy health insurance or pay a fine.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Supporters of the plan argued the &amp;quot;individual mandate&amp;quot; is necessary for the system to work, while critics argued it is an unconstitutional intrusion on individual freedom.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Four different federal appeals courts heard challenges to parts of the law before the Supreme Court ruling, and came up with three different results.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Courts in Cincinnati and Washington voted to uphold the law, while the appeals court in Atlanta struck down the individual mandate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>A fourth panel, in Richmond, Virginia, put its decision off until penalties for failing to buy health insurance take effect in 2014.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The polarizing law, dubbed &amp;quot;Obamacare&amp;quot; by many, is the signature legislation of Obama&amp;apost;s time in office.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>After a lengthy and heated debate marked by intense opposition from the health insurance industry and conservative groups, the law passed Congress along strictly partisan lines in March 2010.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>When Obama signed the legislation later that month, he called it historic said it marked a &amp;quot;new season in America.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>While it was not the comprehensive national health care system liberals initially sought, supporters said the law would reduce health care costs, expand coverage and protect consumers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The law establishes a staged series of reforms over several years, including banning insurance companies from denying coverage to people with pre-existing conditions, forbidding insurers from setting a dollar limit on health coverage payouts, and requiring them to cover preventative care at no additional cost to consumers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>It also required individuals to buy health insurance, either through their employers or a state-sponsored exchange, or face a fine beginning in 2014.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Supporters argue the individual mandate is critical to the success of the legislation, because it expands the pool of people paying for insurance and ensures that healthy people do not opt out of buying insurance until they needed it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Critics said the provision gave the government too much power over what they said should be a personal economic decision.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Twenty-six states led by Florida say individuals cannot be forced to buy insurance, a &amp;quot;product&amp;quot; they may neither want nor need.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>And they argue that if that provision is unconstitutional, the entire law must go.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The Justice Department countered that since every American will need medical care at some point in their lives, individuals do not &amp;quot;choose&amp;quot; whether to participate in the health care market.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The partisan debate around such a sweeping piece of legislation has encompassed almost every traditional hot-button topic: abortion and contraception funding, state and individual rights, federal deficits, end-of-life care, and the overall economy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>During arguments on March 27, Justice Anthony Kennedy said the law appeared to &amp;quot;change the relationship between the government and the individual in a profound way.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Chief Justice John Roberts argued that &amp;quot;all bets are off&amp;quot; when it comes to federal government authority if Congress was found to have the authority to regulate health care in the name of commerce.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Liberal justices, however, argued people who don&amp;apost;t pay into the health system by purchasing insurance make care more expensive for everyone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is not your free choice&amp;quot; to stay out of the market for life, Justice Ruth Bader Ginsburg said during arguments.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think the justices probably came into the argument with their minds made up.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>They had hundreds of briefs and months to study them,&amp;quot; said Thomas Goldstein, publisher of SCOTUSblog.com and a prominent Washington attorney, though he conceded that &amp;quot;the oral arguments (in March) might have changed their minds around the margin.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Americans are largely split over the reform effort and its legality, according to polling.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>A March poll for CNN by ORC International found that while support for the law appears to be growing, 50% of Americans opposed the law, 43% supported it and 7% had no opinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Nearly three-quarters of respondents said they wanted the Supreme Court to overturn at least some of the law&amp;apost;s provisions, although the poll did not specify which ones.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The law, which helped spur the creation of the conservative tea party movement, is likely to be a centerpiece of the presidential election campaign.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Obama&amp;apost;s presumptive Republican opponent, Mitt Romney, has promised to repeal the measure if elected.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>But 76% of respondents in the March CNN/ORC poll said a Supreme Court ruling against the law still wouldn&amp;apost;t change their minds about whom to vote for in November.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>The 2010 passage of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act came after months of bare-knuckled fights over politics and policy and a century of federal efforts to offer universal health care.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>The legislation signed by Obama reached 2,700 pages, nine major sections and 450-some provisions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>The first lawsuits challenging the health care overhaul began just hours after the president signed the legislation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
