<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1026" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/10/02/politics/cnn-poll-debt-ceiling" date_published="2013-10-02 10:01:29" category="politics" author=" Paul Steinhauser, CNN Political Editor" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>CNN Poll: Majority says raise debt ceiling</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Americans don&amp;apost;t think tying Obamacare to debt ceiling hike a good idea, CNN/ORC poll.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">Nation&amp;apost;s ability to borrow more money to pay its bills expires in mid-October.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">Survey indicates a majority of the public would blame Republicans if debt ceiling not increased.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="6">President Barack Obama said he will not negotiate with Congress on debt ceiling.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 18:12:25" annotation_time="654.16" mapping_time_divergence="375.0">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Surveys indicate that most Americans didn&amp;apost;t think shutting down the government in an attempt to dismantle the new health care law was a good idea.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">A CNN/ORC International survey also indicates that a majority of the public would point fingers at Republicans in Congress if the nation&amp;apost;s ability to borrow more money is not increased.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">The government faces a debt ceiling crunch around October 17, when it expects to run out of options to keep below the legal cap on federal borrowing.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="4">Congressional Republicans have signaled they want to use this issue to again go after Obamacare, which would set up a new fight with Senate Democrats and Obama, who says he won&amp;apost;t negotiate.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Surveys indicate that most Americans didn&amp;apost;t think shutting down the government in an attempt to dismantle the new health care law was a good idea.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>They apparently feel the same way about blocking an increase in the nation&amp;apost;s debt ceiling to stop Obamacare, according to a new national poll released on Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>A CNN/ORC International survey also indicates that a majority of the public would point fingers at Republicans in Congress if the nation&amp;apost;s ability to borrow more money is not increased.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>With the federal government shut down due to a bitter partisan standoff over spending and the Affordable Care Act, an even more chilling deadline is approaching.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The government faces a debt ceiling crunch around October 17, when it expects to run out of options to keep below the legal cap on federal borrowing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Congressional Republicans have signaled they want to use this issue to again go after Obamacare, which would set up a new fight with Senate Democrats and Obama, who says he won&amp;apost;t negotiate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>According to the poll, 56% of Americans said it would be a bad thing if the debt ceiling was not raised, with 38% saying it would be a good thing for the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>By a 51% to 43% margin, the public said it is more important to raise the debt ceiling than to delay Obamacare.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>A larger majority, 64% to 27%, in a Quinnipiac University survey released Tuesday said they opposed blocking an increase in the debt ceiling as a way to dismantle the health care law.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>If the debt ceiling is not raised, just over half of those questioned in the CNN poll, 53%, said congressional Republicans would be more responsible rather than Obama, with 31% pointing more fingers at the president.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Those numbers are little changed from July 2011, the last time Obama and Congress fought over the debt ceiling, which was eventually raised.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>As with the battle over the government shutdown, the poll indicated that Democrats and Republicans don&amp;apost;t see eye to eye over raising the debt ceiling.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;Most Republicans think that it would be a good thing for the country if the debt ceiling is not raised, but only 18% of Democrats agree,&amp;quot; said CNN Polling Director Keating Holland.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;Among most other major demographics groups, failure to raise the debt ceiling is seen as a bad thing.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;You have bipartisan consensus among economists that not raising the debt ceiling would be a disaster, but politically you have a divide.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Yes, more people say raise the debt ceiling and fight the health care debate somewhere else, but you have Republican lawmakers going home, most of them to safe Republican districts.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>And they&amp;apost;re being told by many of their constituents not to worry about it ,&amp;apost; you don&amp;apost;t have to raise the debt ceiling&amp;apost;,&amp;quot; CNN Chief National Correspondent John King said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The survey also indicates independents are split.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;Here&amp;apost;s a sales problem for the president.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Even among independents, a pretty even divide on whether raising the debt ceiling is a good or bad thing,&amp;quot; King added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The poll was conducted for CNN by ORC International September 27-29, with 803 adults nationwide questioned by telephone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The survey&amp;apost;s overall sampling error is plus or minus 3.5 percentage points.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>What do you think?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Here&amp;apost;s your chance to weigh in below.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Which do you think is more important for Congress to do?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Raising the debt ceiling to make sure the government has enough money to pay its debts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Delaying the date on which major provisions in the new health care law will take effect.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Or are both equally important?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
