<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="964" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/01/08/politics/new-jersey-state-of-the-state/index.html" date_published="2013-01-08 18:01:24" category="politics" author="David Ariosto, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>41,000 families still displaced in Sandy aftermath, Christie says</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7">Latest tally from the storm put damages to the state at $36.9 billion.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">More than 340,000 homes were damaged or destroyed, Christie&amp;apost;s office said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="7">Nearly 1,400 vessels either sank or were abandoned in New Jersey waterways, his office said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="4">Superstorm Sandy left lawmakers in nation&amp;apost;s capital wrangling.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-01 11:11:03" annotation_time="37.186">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="4">His speech homed in on the effects of the storm, which barreled into New Jersey on October 29 and left lawmakers in the nation&amp;apost;s capital wrangling over how to best address a $60 billion aid package.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1, 2, 3">The latest tally from the storm put damages to the state at $36.9 billion, with more than 340,000 homes damaged or destroyed and nearly 1,400 vessels that either sank or were abandoned in state waterways, Christie&amp;apost;s office said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Gov. Chris Christie, the outspoken New Jersey Republican whose popularity soared after Superstorm Sandy, said Tuesday that 41,000 storm-affected families remained displaced from their homes, while calling for a &amp;quot;full, clean Sandy aid bill&amp;quot; to pass quickly through Congress.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have waited 72 days, seven times longer than victims of Hurricane Katrina waited,&amp;quot; Christie said in his annual State of the State address before a joint legislative session in Trenton.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;One thing I hope everyone now clearly understands - New Jersey, both Republicans and Democrats, will never stand silent when our citizens are being short-changed.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>His speech homed in on the effects of the storm, which barreled into New Jersey on October 29 and left lawmakers in the nation&amp;apost;s capital wrangling over how to best address a $60 billion aid package.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Christie, a former federal prosecutor, has emerged as a leading voice pressing Congress to pass the full measure to repair damaged infrastructure and help residents and business owners affected by the storm.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have stood with the citizens of Florida, Alabama, Mississippi, Louisiana, Iowa, Vermont, California and Missouri in their times of need - now I trust that they will stand with us,&amp;quot; Christie said.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The latest tally from the storm put damages to the state at $36.9 billion, with more than 340,000 homes damaged or destroyed and nearly 1,400 vessels that either sank or were abandoned in state waterways, Christie&amp;apost;s office said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Congress last week approved $9.7 billion in immediate assistance after delays brought on by fiscal cliff bickering, warnings of dwindling federal funds and controversy over millions of dollars for unrelated projects.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The measure passed the House, 354-67.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The Senate passed it unanimously and without debate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Congress is expected to consider $51 billion in broader aid later this month.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Christie, alongside Republican and Democratic lawmakers from New York and New Jersey, heaped criticism on House Republicans for having earlier shelved the bill.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;New Jersey deserves better than the duplicity we saw on display,&amp;quot; he said last week, adding that this is &amp;quot;why the American people hate Congress.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Christie&amp;apost;s comments, as well as his earlier praise of the Obama administration&amp;apost;s response to the storm, have raised questions about whether the he will remain a rising star within the GOP.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Yet his public leadership role after the storm also probably contributed to a surge in his home-state popularity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;Some things are above politics,&amp;quot; Christie said Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;Sandy was and is one of those things.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>According to a recent Fairleigh Dickinson University PublicMind survey, 73% of registered voters say they approve of the job Christie is doing as governor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>His approval rating is his second-highest in Fairleigh Dickinson polling, down just four points from his 77% level in the days after Sandy slammed into his state.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The survey also indicated that nearly two-thirds of residents say the state is headed in the right direction, with only 26% saying it&amp;apost;s on the wrong track.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;The state is facing significant challenges in the post-Sandy era.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Yet voters appear largely pleased with not only where the state is headed, but are even happier with the governor&amp;apost;s leadership,&amp;quot; said Krista Jenkins, director of PublicMind and professor of political science at Fairleigh Dickinson University.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s hard to find such a well-liked political figure in this politically rancorous day and age.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Analysts say the recent groundswell of support may have also led Newark Mayor Cory Booker, who&amp;apost;s thought to be a rising Democratic star capable of unseating Christie, to announce that he would not be running for the governorship.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Booker said he would instead run to replace Sen. Frank Lautenberg, a fellow Democrat, when his term is up in 2014.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Still, New Jersey&amp;apost;s Democratic-dominated legislature has worked to block many of Christie&amp;apost;s initiatives, including judicial appointments and tax reforms.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Considered a budget maven who has drawn contentious battles with union leaders -- especially the teachers&amp;apost; union -- his office on Tuesday blasted the prior administration&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;fiscal mismanagement&amp;quot; while hailing its own ability to pass a balanced budget.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
