<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1120" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/06/20/politics/supreme-court-pay/index.html" date_published="2014-06-20 20:46:02" category="politics" author="Bill Mears, CNN Supreme Court Producer" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Supreme Court justices: Well off and like to travel</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Justices release financial disclosure forms.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">At least six have investments worth at least $1 million.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">Only Sonia Sotomayor listed any financial liabilities.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-11 15:09:40" annotation_time="15.634666">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Amid calls for greater openness at the Supreme Court and the federal judiciary, the nine justices released their financial disclosure reports Friday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">The figures show at least six and as many as eight of the nine justices have investments worth at least $1 million.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">Only Justice Sonia Sotomayor listed any financial liabilities, mostly minor credit card debt.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Amid calls for greater openness at the Supreme Court and the federal judiciary, the nine justices released their financial disclosure reports Friday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>They did so in the old-fashioned way, in person and on paper.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The figures reaffirm the members of the nation&amp;apost;s highest court, despite earning a government salary, are generally well off financially, and like to travel.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The figures show at least six and as many as eight of the nine justices have investments worth at least $1 million.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The reports only require they list only a range from investment income.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Only Justice Sonia Sotomayor listed any financial liabilities, mostly minor credit card debt.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>But a lucrative rental property she owns, her former New York City residence, brought in between $1 million and $5 million last year, although she still carries a hefty mortgage.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Sotomayor also previously earned more than $2 million from her popular 2013 memoir, &amp;quot;My Beloved World.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>But in the latest financial disclosure, the Bronx native reported no &amp;quot;non-investment income&amp;quot; last year, indicating royalties from book sales did not exceed her previous advances.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Justices Antonin Scalia, $77,000, and Stephen Breyer, about $11,000, separately listed royalty income from earlier books they wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>And Scalia earned the annual prize for most traveled justice: 28 separate trips for speeches, lectures, and teaching, including visits to New Orleans, Montana, Italy, and Peru.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Three out-of-town appearances were before the conservative Federalist Society, which liberal groups have criticized Scalia in the past as an ideological conflict-of-interest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>But other members of the court have also participated in events sponsored by ideological non-profits.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>All nine members of the court reported at least one trip overseas, including to Austria, the Czech Republic, Scandinavia, and Poland.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>And seven members claimed teaching income from universities, including lectures, which generally earned them about $3,000-$20,000 for one or more days of extracurricular work.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Most such stints occur during the court&amp;apost;s three-month recess, scheduled this year to begin in late June, when the last of the session&amp;apost;s rulings will be issued.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Even retired justices have to report their income.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Sandra Day O&amp;apost;Connor, who stepped down from the bench in 2006, maintains a remarkable schedule.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The 84-year-old said she has 21 positions on various boards and committees, and made 32 separate trips across the country, including promotion for a new book.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>For their day jobs, the eight associate justices earned a healthy pay raise to $244,400, while Chief Justice John Roberts gets a bit extra at $255,500 per year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>It was the first salary increase for members of the federal bench.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The Coalition for Court Transparency, an alliance of legal and media groups, has launched a public campaign, urging the court to post its financial reports online, for the convenience of the press and public.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The President and members of Congress already do so.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;The media have the right to know about any activities public officials engage in that may influence how they conduct the people&amp;apost;s business,&amp;quot; said Mike Cavender, executive director of the Radio Television Digital News Association and Foundation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;That our nation&amp;apost;s top judges make it purposely harder to obtain this information -- especially given the Internet-- does not conform to 21st century expectations of transparency from public officials.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>All federal judges are required to list on annual financial disclosure forms any out-of-town travel for speeches and other appearances that was paid for by private groups.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
