<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="981" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/09/20/politics/eric-harroun-plea-deal-syria/index.html" date_published="2013-09-20 22:56:22" category="politics" author="Carol Cratty, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Army veteran pleads to lesser charge in Syria fighting case</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">Eric Harroun initially charged with fighting alongside group affiliated with al Qaeda.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">He allegedly posted videos on the Web showing him with weapons.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="8">U.S. said he had been on &amp;apost;no fly&amp;apost; llist, but was removed to fly him home where he was arrested .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="2">Harroun, who is from Phoenix, released from custody after being sentenced to time served.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 14:45:53" annotation_time="34.8" mapping_time_divergence="8.7">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="4">Eric Harroun was sentenced to time served by a federal judge in Alexandria, Virginia, on Thursday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">Harroun was arrested in March and charged with conspiring to use a rocket propelled grenade while fighting with the al-Nusra Front, an alias name for the terrorist group al Qaeda in Iraq.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">Harroun allegedly posted videos on the Internet showing him with weapons.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="3">At a court hearing the next month, a federal prosecutor took the unusual step of revealing Harroun had been on a &amp;quot;no-fly&amp;quot; list and had been removed so he could fly from Turkey to the United States where he was arrested.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington A former U.S. soldier accused of fighting with terrorists against Syrian forces pleaded guilty to a lesser charge and was released from custody.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Eric Harroun was sentenced to time served by a federal judge in Alexandria, Virginia, on Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Court documents showed he pleaded guilty to an export charge involving conspiracy to transfer defense articles and services.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The Phoenix man entered into a plea agreement with the government which remains under seal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Harroun was arrested in March and charged with conspiring to use a rocket propelled grenade while fighting with the al-Nusra Front, an alias name for the terrorist group al Qaeda in Iraq.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>If convicted of that charge, he faced a possible sentence of 30 years to life.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Harroun allegedly posted videos on the Internet showing him with weapons.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>At a court hearing the next month, a federal prosecutor took the unusual step of revealing Harroun had been on a &amp;quot;no-fly&amp;quot; list and had been removed so he could fly from Turkey to the United States where he was arrested.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>This allowed U.S. authorities to take custody of Harroun without asking Turkey to arrest him and hand him over.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The prosecutor did not say how long Harroun had been on the &amp;quot;no fly&amp;quot; list or whether he was aware of it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>FBI agents observed him during the flight although he was not taken into custody until after he arrived in the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s also not clear whether Harroun&amp;apost;s name is back on the list.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>According to an FBI affidavit made public at the time of his arrest, Harroun crossed into Syria in January where he received training from the al-Nusra Front on how to use rocket propelled grenades and posted still photos and videos of himself on the Internet handling the RPGs and other weapons.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The FBI interviewed him three times in Istanbul about his activities before he flew to the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The case appeared to present the United States with a thorny problem -- Harroun allegedly was fighting against the Syrian government which the United States also opposes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>But the United States considers the al-Nusra Front a terrorist group.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>At the April hearing, federal public defender Geremy Kamens noted an FBI agent who testified said there was no evidence Harroun was involved in any terrorist activities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Harroun served in the Army from 2000 to 2003.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
