<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1040" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/01/17/politics/wisconsin-walker-recall/index.html" date_published="2012-01-17 06:21:42" category="politics" author="Paul Steinhauser, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Democrats: 1 million signatures collected for Wisconsin governor recall</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">NEW: The Wisconsin Democratic Party says it has collected more than 1 million signatures.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Gov. Scott Walker drew the ire of labor unions and public school teachers last year.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">State Democratic Party chair: The &amp;quot;impressive number&amp;quot; is &amp;quot;beyond any challenges&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="14">&amp;quot;The overwhelming majority of the people in the state chose not to sign,&amp;quot; Walker says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 20:37:02" annotation_time="35.332996">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">More than a million people have signed a petition to recall Wisconsin&amp;apost;s governor, the state&amp;apost;s Democratic Party said Tuesday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">That&amp;apost;s nearly twice the 540,208 signatures required to seek a recall of first-term Republican Gov. Scott Walker, who drew the ire of labor unions and public school teachers after he stripped public employees of their collective bargaining rights.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;I think it&amp;apost;s going to be a very impressive number that we hand in, beyond any challenge that this election is going to happen,&amp;quot; Wisconsin Democratic Party Chairman Mike Tate told CNN affiliate WTMJ Monday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="4">&amp;quot;The optimist in me looks at that and says: the overwhelming majority of the people in the state chose not to sign that and I earned the trust of the majority the last time.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>More than a million people have signed a petition to recall Wisconsin&amp;apost;s governor, the state&amp;apost;s Democratic Party said Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s nearly twice the 540,208 signatures required to seek a recall of first-term Republican Gov. Scott Walker, who drew the ire of labor unions and public school teachers after he stripped public employees of their collective bargaining rights.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>State Democratic Party officials said they would submit the signatures by close of business Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The officials also said they would turn in more than the required number of signatures needed for recall elections for the state&amp;apost;s Republican lieutenant governor and three state senators.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The Wisconsin elections board will review the recall petitions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think it&amp;apost;s going to be a very impressive number that we hand in, beyond any challenge that this election is going to happen,&amp;quot; Wisconsin Democratic Party Chairman Mike Tate told CNN affiliate WTMJ Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Walker&amp;apost;s administration gained national attention last year when he, along with Republican legislators, pushed forward a bill to cut state workers&amp;apost; collective bargaining rights.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>That bill was signed into law in March, following weeks of protests at the state capitol building in Madison.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>This would be the first time in Wisconsin&amp;apost;s history that a governor has faced recall.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>In fact, there have only been two successful gubernatorial recalls in United States history, that of California Gov. Gray Davis in 2003 and that of North Dakota Gov. Lynn Frazier in 1921.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The more difficult battle will begin once the signatures are approved, and the state schedules a recall election.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Both sides will be well financed and ready to battle, said Kenneth Goldstein, president of the Campaign Media Analysis Group.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Walker was undaunted by the recall effort, WTMJ reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;The optimist in me looks at that and says: the overwhelming majority of the people in the state chose not to sign that and I earned the trust of the majority the last time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>My hope is I will earn their trust again,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Walker set off a firestorm in January 2010 when he moved to curtail the collective bargaining rights of most state employees.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>With majorities in both houses of the Legislature, Walker and his GOP allies voted to limit raises for public employees except police and firefighters to the rate of inflation, bar unions from deducting dues from workers&amp;apost; paychecks and force them to hold a new certification vote every year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Republicans insisted it was necessary to control the skyrocketing costs of public employee benefits and close the budget shortfall.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Democrats argued it was an attempt to gut public-sector labor unions, one of their core constituencies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The public brouhaha all but shut down the Wisconsin state legislature for weeks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>It also drew protesters by the tens of thousands, among them union supporters and public employees, who called the measure an attack on workers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>A group of Democratic lawmakers left the state for some time in an effort to not allow a quorum for a vote.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Eventually, the law was passed and signed by Walker in March.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The state Supreme Court upheld the law in June but the battle birthed a storm of political activism that led to the recall effort.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
