<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1091" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/14/politics/nfl-ray-rice-reactions/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-09-14 22:34:48" category="politics" author="Mary Grace Lucas, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Obama &amp;apost;shocked&amp;apost; by Ray Rice video</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">White House chief of staff: &amp;quot;The President was shocked&amp;quot; by punching video.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12">Lawmakers criticize the NFL and the league&amp;apost;s commissioner.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="14">&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m waiting to see if there is a major cover-up,&amp;quot; senator says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-07 09:48:01" annotation_time="25.597">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;The President was shocked by what he saw.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">Other lawmakers Sunday were far more critical of Goodell and the league.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m waiting to see if there is a major cover-up, if it shows [Goodell] lies, there could be many factual situations where, in fact, he should step down.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington The growing outcry over how the NFL and Commissioner Roger Goodell deal with incidents of domestic violence has reached the nation&amp;apost;s highest office.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Even President Barack Obama has seen the footage of Baltimore Ravens running back Ray Rice punching his then-fiancee.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;The President was shocked by what he saw.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Let&amp;apost;s put it that way,&amp;quot; White House Chief of Staff Denis McDonough said told NBC&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;Meet the Press&amp;quot; on Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The incident involving Rice is one of several high-profile scandals involving NFL players that have spurred complaints that the National Football League is too lenient on players.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>A few months after the Rice incident, Goodell suspended him without pay and fined him an additional game check.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>However, after the TMZ Sports video so clearly showed the forceful nature of the punch, Goodell suspended Rice indefinitely.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Last week, the White House addressed the suspension with a statement saying the President believes domestic violence &amp;quot;contemptible and unacceptable in a civilized society,&amp;quot; but it wasn&amp;apost;t clear whether he had seen the video of the incident from inside the elevator.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>McDonough said the White House wouldn&amp;apost;t at this point try to characterize how the NFL is handling the Rice case.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>But he did speak generally about Rice&amp;apost;s indefinite suspension.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;We all know that Ray Rice being suspended indefinitely seems to be exactly the right thing,&amp;quot; McDonough said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Other lawmakers Sunday were far more critical of Goodell and the league.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;I have a feeling there&amp;apost;s a lot of people that know stuff, what went on here,&amp;quot; Democratic Sen. Amy Klobuchar of Minnesota told CNN&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;State of the Union.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m waiting to see if there is a major cover-up, if it shows [Goodell] lies, there could be many factual situations where, in fact, he should step down.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Klobuchar, a former prosecutor, is one of 16 female senators who sent a letter to Goodell calling on the football league to institute a &amp;quot;real zero-tolerance policy&amp;quot; in such cases.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The NFL announced late Wednesday that former FBI Director Robert Mueller will lead an independent inquiry into the league&amp;apost;s investigation and how it gathered evidence in the case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;Bob Mueller&amp;apost;s integrity is on the line here, and hopefully he&amp;apost;ll get the facts out,&amp;quot; Klobuchar said of the investigation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;The fact that (the NFL) gave only a two-game suspension and then turn around and after the evidence goes public say, &amp;apost;Oh, oh, we made a mistake.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Now we&amp;apost;re going to let him go.&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>I think that&amp;apost;s problematic for the NFL and deeply concerning about how they handle these kinds of cases.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Sen. Kirsten Gillibrand of New York, who also signed the letter to Goodell, had scathing words for the NFL.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think the way the NFL handled this was awful.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>It was outrageous,&amp;quot; Gillibrand told CBS&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;Face the Nation.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;They had all the facts they needed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>They had a player who admitted to beating his wife.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>They had video of him dragging her out an elevator.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>There was nothing left to determine.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>That player should&amp;apost;ve been fired immediately.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>So we are now looking to the commissioner to enforce a zero-tolerance policy.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Gillibrand also said that if Goodell has covered up what he knew about the Rice incident, he should be benched.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;Initially, I want him to lead the reform to actually create and enforce a zero-tolerance policy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>But, given the recent debate, you know, if he lied, if he lied to the American people, then he has to step down,&amp;quot; she said, &amp;quot;because he won&amp;apost;t have the force of authority to change how they address these issues.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Gillibrand said the bipartisan letter from lawmakers to Goodell may be merely the beginning of a broader congressional push for more accountability in the NFL.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;If the NFL doesn&amp;apost;t police themselves, then, you know, we will be looking more into it,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;I wouldn&amp;apost;t be surprised if we have hearings.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Sen. Richard Blumenthal, D-Connecticut, recently told CNN that he would not &amp;quot;rule out&amp;quot; congressional action to force the NFL&amp;apost;s hand on domestic abuse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>In the past, members of Congress have leveraged their titles and hearing rooms to press major U.S. sports leagues to face difficult issues.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>In 2007, the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee released the landmark Mitchell Report on steroid use in Major League Baseball.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Household names such as Roger Clemens and Andy Pettitte were named, and MLB Commissioner Bud Selig responded that the report was a &amp;quot;a call to action, and I will act.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Baseball fans would eventually see both Selig and Clemens, along with baseball titans Mark McGwire, Sammy Sosa, Rafael Palmeiro and Jose Canseco, testify before Congress.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Outcry over the NFL&amp;apost;s response to the Rice incident has been compounded by two more recent incidents of domestic violence allegedly involving NFL players.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Adrian Peterson of the Minnesota Vikings was indicted last week by a grand jury in Texas on a child abuse charge.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Shortly afterward, he was placed on the inactive list for his team.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>The Carolina Panthers placed defensive end Greg Hardy on the team&amp;apost;s inactive list in a surprise announcement Sunday, months after he was convicted of a domestic violence charge.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Authorities say Hardy choked his then-girlfriend, threw her around, dragged her by her hair and threatened to kill her.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Hardy -- 6-foot-4 and 275 pounds -- says he is innocent, and he has appealed a July guilty verdict rendered by a Mecklenburg County judge in North Carolina.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Beyond the D.C. Beltway, California&amp;apost;s second most powerful government official has called on the San Francisco 49ers to bench one of its own players involved in a domestic violence investigation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Ray McDonald, a starting defensive end, was arrested on felony domestic violence charges last month.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>&amp;quot;The 49ers&amp;apost; continued insistence on playing Ray McDonald during his ongoing criminal investigation is a painful affront to every victim of domestic violence and sends a troubling message to our community,&amp;quot; Lt. Gov. Gavin Newsom and his wife said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>&amp;quot;We strongly urge the 49er organization we grew up revering to do the right thing -- right now -- and bench Ray McDonald, pending the outcome of his felony domestic violence investigation by San Jose law enforcement.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>McDonald told CNN affiliate KTVU last month that he couldn&amp;apost;t say much about what happened.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>&amp;quot;The truth will come out,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>&amp;quot;Everybody knows what kind of person I am ... a good-hearted person.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
