<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1123" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/06/26/politics/scotus-same-sex-doma" date_published="2013-06-26 14:02:49" category="politics" author="Bill Mears, CNN Supreme Court Producer" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Supreme Court strikes down provision on same-sex marriage benefits</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="31, 30, 11">NEW: Edith Windsor, who sued the federal government, says she is overjoyed by the ruling.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">In a 5-4 decision, the high court says Congress cannot deny equal protection.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="13">&amp;quot;Today&amp;apost;s DOMA ruling is a historic step forward,&amp;quot; president&amp;apost;s twitter account posts.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="23">Justice Antonin Scalia issues a thunderous dissent saying &amp;quot; the court has cheated both sides&amp;quot;.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-08 23:30:17" annotation_time="50.256332">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;Although Congress has great authority to design laws to fit its own conception of sound national policy, it cannot deny the liberty protected by the Due Process Clause of the Fifth Amendment,&amp;quot; said Justice Anthony Kennedy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="1">So, Windsor sued the federal government.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;Today&amp;apost;s DOMA ruling is a historic step forward for #MarriageEquality.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="4">&amp;quot;Few public controversies touch an institution so central to the lives of so many, and few inspire such attendant passion by good people on both sides,&amp;quot; he said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="30" ids_highlights="1">Windsor was in New York when the ruling came down.</sentence>
      <sentence id="31" ids_highlights="1">She told reporters that she was overjoyed.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington In a dramatic slap at congressional authority, a divided Supreme Court has struck down a key part of a law that denies to legally married same-sex couples the same federal benefits provided to heterosexual spouses.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The Defense of Marriage Act defines marriage as only between a man and a woman.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The vote Wednesday was 5-4.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;Although Congress has great authority to design laws to fit its own conception of sound national policy, it cannot deny the liberty protected by the Due Process Clause of the Fifth Amendment,&amp;quot; said Justice Anthony Kennedy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>He was supported by four more liberal colleagues: Justices Ruth Bader Ginsburg, Stephen Breyer, Sonia Sotomayor and Elena Kagan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The case examined whether the federal government can deny tax, health and pension benefits to same-sex couples in states where they can legally marry.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>At issue was whether DOMA violates equal protection guarantees in the Fifth Amendment&amp;apost;s due process clause as applied to same-sex couples legally married under the laws of their states.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The key plaintiff is Edith &amp;quot;Edie&amp;quot; Windsor, 84, who married fellow New York resident Thea Spyer in Canada in 2007, about 40 years into their relationship.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>By the time Spyer died in 2009, New York courts recognized same-sex marriages performed in other countries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>But the federal government didn&amp;apost;t recognize Windsor&amp;apost;s same-sex marriage, and she was forced to assume an estate tax bill much larger than those that other married couples would have to pay.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>So, Windsor sued the federal government.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>A federal appeals court last year ruled in Windsor&amp;apost;s favor, saying DOMA violated the Constitution&amp;apost;s equal protection clause.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;Today&amp;apost;s DOMA ruling is a historic step forward for #MarriageEquality.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>#LoveIsLove,&amp;quot; President Barack Obama&amp;apost;s official Twitter account posted soon after the decision was handed down.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Kennedy, in his opinion, used sweeping language to affirm the rights of gays and lesbians.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;For same-sex couples who wished to be married, the state (of New York) acted to give their lawful conduct a lawful status.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>This status is a far-reaching legal acknowledgment of the intimate relationship between two people, a relationship deemed by the state worthy of dignity in the community equal with all other marriages,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;DOMA seeks to injure the very class New York seeks to protect.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>But Kennedy -- a moderate-conservative who proved once again to be the &amp;quot;swing,&amp;quot; or deciding, vote -- made clear the ruling is limited: &amp;quot;This opinion and its holding are confined to those lawful marriages.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Thirty-five states have laws banning same-sex marriage.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Under DOMA, Social Security, pension and bankruptcy benefits, along with family medical leave protections and other federal provisions, did not apply to gay and lesbian couples legally married in states that recognize such unions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>In a thunderous dissent, read from the bench, Justice Antonin Scalia slammed the majority for its &amp;quot;exalted conception of the role of this institution&amp;quot; -- the Supreme Court -- &amp;quot;in America.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;Few public controversies touch an institution so central to the lives of so many, and few inspire such attendant passion by good people on both sides,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;Few public controversies will ever demonstrate so vividly the beauty of what our (Constitution) framers gave us, a gift the court pawns today to buy its stolen moment in the spotlight: a system of government that permits us to rule ourselves.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Scalia added, &amp;quot;Some will rejoice in today&amp;apost;s decision, and some will despair at it; that is the nature of a controversy that matters so much to so many.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>But the court has cheated both sides, robbing the winners of an honest victory, and the losers of the peace that comes from a fair defeat.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>We owed both of them better.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>I dissent.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Chief Justice John Roberts and Justices Clarence Thomas and Samuel Alito also dissented.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Windsor was in New York when the ruling came down.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>She told reporters that she was overjoyed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;We won everything we asked and hoped for.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Wow,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m honored and humbled and overjoyed to be here today to represent not only the thousands of Americans whose lives have been adversely impacted by the Defense of Marriage Act, but those whose hopes and dreams have been constricted by the same discriminatory law.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Windsor thanked the supporters who cheered her on throughout the case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;Because of today&amp;apost;s Supreme Court ruling, the federal government can no longer discriminate against the marriages of gay and lesbian Americans.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Children born today will grow up in a world without DOMA, and those same children who happen to be gay will be free to love and get married as Thea and I did, but with the same federal benefits, protections and dignity as everyone else,&amp;quot; Windsor said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;If I had to survive Thea, what a glorious way to do it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>And she would be so pleased.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The Defense of Marriage law was defended in the high court by House Republicans, after Obama concluded the law was unconstitutional.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Traditionally, that role would fall to the solicitor general&amp;apost;s office.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>But president ordered Attorney General Eric Holder not to defend DOMA in court.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>That raised the question of whether any party could rightfully step in and defend the law.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>By striking down the DOMA provision, the court decided the standing question was not at play in this case, and it had jurisdiction to decide the larger questions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>A bill known as the Respect for Marriage Act is working its way through Congress and would repeal DOMA.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>That law does not prohibit states from allowing same-sex marriages, but it also does not force states to recognize such marriages performed in other states.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Most of the current plaintiffs are federal workers, who are not allowed to add their spouses to health care plans and other benefits.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>The case is U.S. v. Windsor (12-307).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
