<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1098" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/11/26/politics/obama-deportations-immigration/index.html?iref=allsearch" date_published="2013-11-26 20:17:47" category="politics" author="Leigh Ann Caldwell, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Obama said he can&amp;apost;t stop deportations of immigrants, but maybe he can</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="13">Obama heckler wanted Obama to provide his &amp;quot;legal analysis&amp;quot; for continuing deportations.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="19">The President said at San Francisco event he has to &amp;quot;follow the law&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">Experts say exercising executive discretion too broadly is fraught with political and legal land mines.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="25">Obama has deported more people than any other chief executive.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 15:31:37" annotation_time="125.832664" mapping_time_divergence="62.916332">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">But the administration has latitude in how to enforce those laws, though legal experts say exercising that discretion too broadly is fraught with political and legal land mines.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="1">In a statement Monday, the group asked him for his &amp;quot;legal analysis&amp;quot; of why he can&amp;apost;t stop deportations.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="2">Obama told Univision In January that he&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;required to follow the law,&amp;quot; which makes it a misdemeanor to be in the country illegally.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="4">Obama has deported more people than any other president.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington A heckler standing just behind Barack Obama in San Francisco this week yelled to the President that he &amp;quot;has the power to stop deportation.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>A clearly irritated Obama interrupted his speech and shot back that he doesn&amp;apost;t have that authority, saying the United States is &amp;quot;a nation of laws.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>So, who&amp;apost;s right?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Federal immigration law provides for the deportation, or removal, of an individual under several circumstances -- including being in the country illegally, overstaying a legal visa, violation of criminal statutes or a number of other offenses - after a judicial process.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>But the administration has latitude in how to enforce those laws, though legal experts say exercising that discretion too broadly is fraught with political and legal land mines.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Ju Hong, the 24-year old heckler, is a University of California, Berkeley graduate and a member of Asian Students Promoting Immigrant Rights Through Education, ASPIRE.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>After the event on Monday at a community center, the group insisted the President can use his executive authority to halt deportations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Hong and his group want Obama to stop all deportations, which they say creates a culture of fear among undocumented immigrants and breaks up families.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Obama spokesman Josh Earnest pushed back, saying the President does not have that authority.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;As I think the President said rather definitively, there is also not an executive action that would address all of the concerns that that young man had raised,&amp;quot; said Earnest Tuesday from Los Angeles.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>But that doesn&amp;apost;t convince May Liang, an organizer for ASPIRE.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>She told CNN Tuesday that she still thinks Obama &amp;quot;blatantly lied&amp;quot; when he said he didn&amp;apost;t have the power to stop deportations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>In a statement Monday, the group asked him for his &amp;quot;legal analysis&amp;quot; of why he can&amp;apost;t stop deportations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Obama, however, stood firm.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;The easy way out is to try to yell and pretend like I can do something by violating our laws,&amp;quot; Obama told Hong Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;And what I&amp;apost;m proposing is the harder path, which is to use our democratic processes to achieve the same goal that you want to achieve.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>But it won&amp;apost;t be as easy as just shouting.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>It requires us lobbying and getting it done,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Obama told Univision In January that he&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;required to follow the law,&amp;quot; which makes it a misdemeanor to be in the country illegally.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Those found guilty can be deported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>But the President has exercised discretion on deportations in the past.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>In 2012, he announced that the Department of Homeland Security&amp;apost;s Immigration and Customs Enforcement was not going to deport Dreamers, children of undocumented immigrants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>And in August, he announced that parents would not deport parents caring for children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>But still, he has been aggressive on that front.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Obama has deported more people than any other president.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>For instance, 410,000 people were deported in 2012 compared to 116,000 in 2001.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Obama has shifted the type of immigrants targeted for deportation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>While the administration of President George W. Bush targeted working immigrants by raiding workplaces, Obama is focusing on convicted criminals and &amp;quot;egregious&amp;quot; immigration violators, including recent border crossers and illegal re-entrants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Immigration and Customs Enforcement said 55% of people deported last year were convicted criminals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Richard A. Boswell, immigration law professor at the University of California&amp;apost;s Hastings College of the Law, said the President is &amp;quot;partially correct.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s called prosecutorial discretion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The executive branch has the &amp;quot;inherent power to choose which cases to act on,&amp;quot; Boswell said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Think of the police.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>They can theoretically give someone driving four miles over the speed limit a ticket, but the police officer also has the ability to use discretion to give a warning instead.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s the validation Obama used in his decision to halt deportations of youth and parents.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>But Philip Schrag, professor of public interest law at Georgetown Law School, said the President&amp;apost;s position is that putting an end to all deportations would &amp;quot;abuse&amp;quot; his discretion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Immigration law attorney Austin Gragomen said he thinks Obama &amp;quot;has an obligation to enforce the law&amp;quot; even if he chooses how and to what extent to enforce it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Boswell disagreed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>He said the President can use his discretion to hold deportations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The President is &amp;quot;making a tactical political move to force Congress to act.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>He could just as easily told Congress that he would withhold deportations on broad categories of cases pending their action,&amp;quot; Boswell wrote in an e-mail.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>The Senate passed comprehensive immigration reform earlier this year, which includes a path to citizenship for the 11 million undocumented immigrants already in the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>The legislation has been stalled in the House and is unlikely to be taken up before the end of the year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>The issue of deportations hasn&amp;apost;t just upset immigration advocates.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>The top Republican on the House Judiciary Committee, Rep. Bob Goodlatte, R-Virginia, announced he would hold a hearing on the issue to investigate the President&amp;apost;s decision to not deport some people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>The hearing is titled, &amp;quot;The President&amp;apost;s Constitutional Duty to Faithfully Execute the Laws.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
