<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1111" link="http://articles.cnn.com/2012-05-16/politics/politics_senate-budget-debate_1_budget-debate-obama-budget-budget-proposal" date_published="2012-05-17 00:01:11" category="politics" author="Ted Barrett, CNN Senior Congressional Producer " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Senate&amp;apost;s all-day budget debate dominated by politics</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">The GOP&amp;apost;s McConnell hits Democrats for not passing a formal budget this year.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">Majority Leader Reid fires back, referring to &amp;quot;stunt budgets&amp;quot; by Republicans.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">Much of the day&amp;apost;s exercise was an effort by both parties to score political points.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-10 20:12:58" annotation_time="26.84">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="3">But the reality was none of the measures had enough votes to pass, and much of the exercise was an effort by both parties to score political points and embarrass the other side -- another display of partisan maneuvering that polls show frustrates voters.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">Senate Minority Leader Mitch McConnell opened the debate by accusing Democrats of being &amp;quot;irresponsible&amp;quot; for not passing a formal budget this year.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">Senate Majority Leader Harry Reid fired back, saying the Senate had already agreed to funding levels for 2013 and was too busy to deal with &amp;quot;stunt budgets&amp;quot; offered by Republicans.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington It had all the appearances of a serious-minded debate: Republicans insisted the Senate spend all day Wednesday arguing which party had better budget proposals to fix the economy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But the reality was none of the measures had enough votes to pass, and much of the exercise was an effort by both parties to score political points and embarrass the other side -- another display of partisan maneuvering that polls show frustrates voters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Senate Minority Leader Mitch McConnell opened the debate by accusing Democrats of being &amp;quot;irresponsible&amp;quot; for not passing a formal budget this year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;If you&amp;apost;re looking for a simple, three-word description of the Democrat approach to the problems we face, it&amp;apost;s this: duck and cover.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>They don&amp;apost;t have a budget of their own.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>They&amp;apost;re going to vote against their own president&amp;apost;s budget later today and they&amp;apost;re going to vote against every budget Republicans put up.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Senate Majority Leader Harry Reid fired back, saying the Senate had already agreed to funding levels for 2013 and was too busy to deal with &amp;quot;stunt budgets&amp;quot; offered by Republicans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;We can&amp;apost;t afford to waste any time,&amp;quot; Reid said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;Yet today Republicans will force the Senate to waste a day on a series of political show votes.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Republicans commandeered the floor by taking advantage of a seldom-used Senate rule that allows any senator to offer a budget if the Budget Committee has not passed a budget resolution by April 1.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>In this case, Republicans called up five budgets: one that closely mirrored President Obama&amp;apost;s budget proposal submitted earlier this year; another, authored by House Budget Chairman Paul Ryan, R-Wisconsin, which the House approved; and three from very conservative senators aimed at making drastic reductions to entitlements costs, government spending and taxes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Going into the day, everyone knew none of the bills would get the 51 votes needed to succeed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>And, as Republicans had calculated, the president&amp;apost;s budget got zero yes votes, providing Republicans with the political ammunition they sought for the campaign trail this year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;The president&amp;apost;s 2013 budget would expand the scope of government by spending more money, increase taxes on job creators, and continue on the path of enormous deficits and record debt,&amp;quot; explained Sen. Chuck Grassley, R-Iowa.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Several Democrats, however, said they voted against the president&amp;apost;s budget not because they oppose its broad principles but because it was submitted several months ago and is now out of date.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;It misrepresents the president&amp;apost;s budget,&amp;quot; said Sen. Ben Cardin, D-Maryland, a liberal who is up for re-election &amp;quot;The numbers have changed since then.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Sen. Sherrod Brown, D-Ohio, another liberal who also is running for re-election, said he was not going to fall for a GOP trap.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s become too much of a game for these guys,&amp;quot; he said just as he entered the chamber to cast his vote against the motion representing the Obama budget.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Centrist Democrat Joe Manchin, who is also up for re-election in closely divided West Virginia, said he opposed all the GOP budgets because &amp;quot;they would destroy Social Security and Medicare -- all while protecting the wealthy&amp;quot; and the president&amp;apost;s budget because &amp;quot;it digs an even deeper debt hole for the next generation.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The House Republican budget got 41 Republican votes and zero Democratic votes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Five Republicans, including Sen. Scott Brown who is facing a tough re-election fight in Massachusetts, voted against it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>A proposal from Sen. Pat Toomey, R- Pennsylvania, that would balance the budget in eight years got 42 Republican votes and no Democratic votes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>A proposal from Sen. Rand Paul, R-Kentucky, that would cut eliminate several cabinet agencies -- including Commerce, Education, Housing and Urban Developments and Energy -- only got 16 votes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>And a proposal from Sen. Mike Lee, R-Utah, which would institute a flat tax, raise the eligibility age for Social Security, and repeal &amp;quot;Obamacare&amp;quot; only got 17 votes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Senate Budget Committee Chairman Kent Conrad, D-North Dakota, complained the GOP budget proposals &amp;quot;would take us right back to the failed policies that brought this country to the brink of economic collapse.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s what happened the last time they were in charge.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>At a news conference, authors of the three conservative budgets bristled at the suggestion they were involved in &amp;quot;gotcha&amp;quot; politics.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Instead, they argued they deserved credit for having the political courage to put their ideas up for votes, and criticized Democrats for not doing the same.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think this suggestion this could be, as you put it, a &amp;apost;gotcha&amp;apost; moment, ignores the rather striking reality which is the failure to put forward something, and the willingness simply to stand back and criticize those who have put forward something is itself a gotcha,&amp;quot; said Lee.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;That&amp;apost;s really the problem.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Putting forward something isn&amp;apost;t a gotcha.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Criticizing those who do, while doing nothing, is.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
