<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="987" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/05/10/politics/obama-same-sex-marriage/index.html" date_published="2012-05-10 05:06:24" category="politics" author="Jessica Yellin, CNN Chief White House Correspondent" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Biden apologizes to Obama for marriage controversy</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Senior officials say Biden apologized to Obama on Wednesday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">Obama responded that Biden was speaking from the heart, they say.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">Biden&amp;apost;s weekend remarks spurred Obama to announce his support for same-sex marriage.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 20:40:01" annotation_time="13.968667">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">Two senior administration officials said Biden and Obama met Wednesday morning, and Biden apologized for putting Obama in a tough spot.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">Obama responded by saying that he knew Biden was speaking from the heart, said the officials, who didn&amp;apost;t want to be named discussing private conversations between the president and vice president.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">Biden&amp;apost;s remarks on NBC&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;Meet the Press&amp;quot; on Sunday launched a controversy that led to Obama announcing that his position on same-sex marriage, which he had previously called &amp;quot;evolving,&amp;quot; had shifted to support.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington Vice President Joe Biden has apologized to President Barack Obama for putting him in a tough position that led to Obama&amp;apost;s announcement that he now supports same-sex marriage, senior administration officials said Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Obama said in an interview that aired Thursday on ABC that he made his decision public earlier than he had planned after Biden&amp;apost;s weekend remark that he was &amp;quot;absolutely comfortable&amp;quot; with letting gays and lesbians marry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Two senior administration officials said Biden and Obama met Wednesday morning, and Biden apologized for putting Obama in a tough spot.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Obama responded by saying that he knew Biden was speaking from the heart, said the officials, who didn&amp;apost;t want to be named discussing private conversations between the president and vice president.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Biden&amp;apost;s remarks on NBC&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;Meet the Press&amp;quot; on Sunday launched a controversy that led to Obama announcing that his position on same-sex marriage, which he had previously called &amp;quot;evolving,&amp;quot; had shifted to support.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>When Obama&amp;apost;s full interview aired Thursday, he said his disclosure came sooner than planned as a result of Biden&amp;apost;s comments.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;I had already made a decision that we were going to probably take this position before the election and before the convention,&amp;quot; Obama said on ABC&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;Good Morning America.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Biden &amp;quot;probably got out a little bit over his skis, but out of generosity of spirit,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>He added that he would have &amp;quot;preferred to have done this in my own way, on my own terms,&amp;quot; but &amp;quot;all&amp;apost;s well that ends well.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Separately, Biden spokeswoman Kendra Barkoff said Obama &amp;quot;has been the leader on this issue from day one, and the vice president never intended to distract from that.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Once Biden&amp;apost;s comments drew attention to the issue, Obama made plans to announce his support next week on a previously scheduled appearance on the ABC talk show &amp;quot;The View,&amp;quot; a senior administration official said Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The president and his advisers knew Obama would be asked about the issue in the wake of Biden&amp;apost;s NBC interview, said the official, who didn&amp;apost;t want to speak publicly about internal administration discussions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Ultimately, they decided to move up the timeline and have him announce his support during the ABC interview at the White House, the official said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>And a top Democrat told CNN that Obama knew the issue would come up at the convention, partly because of a push for support for same-sex marriage to be included in the Democratic Party platform, and in debates.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Multiple top Democrats told CNN the president&amp;apost;s senior aides are annoyed with Biden for forcing the conversation on same-sex marriage now.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>One source said Biden has, in the past, counseled the president against coming out for same-sex marriage, making this move that much more frustrating.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>But the sources said they don&amp;apost;t believe it will create a lasting rift between the two leaders.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Biden is known to go off-script, something Obama knew when he selected his vice president.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>In explaining to ABC how his position has evolved, Obama noted that his daughters Malia and Sasha have &amp;quot;friends whose parents are same-sex couples.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>It wouldn&amp;apost;t dawn on them that somehow their friends&amp;apost; parents would be treated differently.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>And frankly that&amp;apost;s the kind of thing that prompts a change of perspective, not wanting to somehow explain to your child why somebody should be treated differently when it comes to the eyes of the law.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Asked about whether his new position is a calculated move in an election year, Obama said it would &amp;quot;be hard to argue that somehow this is something that I&amp;apost;d be doing for political advantage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Because frankly, you know, the politics -- it&amp;apost;s not clear how they cut.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The interview aired the same day Obama attended a fundraiser in Los Angeles, where support for same-sex marriage is strong.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Movie star George Clooney hosted the event, which is raking in $15 million, according to a top Democratic source.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>And on Monday, openly gay singer Ricky Martin is hosting a fundraising event for Obama in New York.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>But some in the African-American community have expressed strong disapproval of Obama&amp;apost;s endorsement of same-sex marriage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>A Democratic official said the White House has been actively reaching out to African-American community leaders and pastors and will continue to do so in the wake of the president&amp;apost;s decision, but the official noted that even the president&amp;apost;s base won&amp;apost;t always agree with him on everything.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;There are going to be issues you don&amp;apost;t agree on,&amp;quot; the official said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>And Obama told ABC he won&amp;apost;t spend much time talking about the issue, because he&amp;apost;s focused on the economy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The announcement puts Obama squarely at odds with presumptive Republican presidential nominee Mitt Romney, who has since reiterated his opposition to same-sex marriage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;And I do not favor civil unions if they are identical to marriage other than by name,&amp;quot; Romney said during a Wednesday visit to Fort Lupton, Colorado.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;My view is the domestic partnership benefits, hospital visitation rights and the like are appropriate, but that the others are not.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The issue is a divisive one in American politics, but it&amp;apost;s uncertain how the development might play out at the voting booth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>A Gallup Poll released Tuesday indicated 50% of Americans believe same-sex marriages should be recognized by law as valid, with 48% saying such marriages should not be legal -- a dramatic shift from a few years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>A Gallup poll in 2009 found 40% supported same-sex marriage and 57% were opposed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>But a CNN/ORC International poll, taken in late March, indicated policies toward gays and lesbians were tied for last in people&amp;apost;s opinions of the most-important issues facing the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Obama said he supports states deciding the issue on their own, but added that he was &amp;quot;disappointed&amp;quot; by Tuesday&amp;apost;s vote on the issue in North Carolina, where a ban on same-sex marriage was added to the constitution.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Obama called the amendment discriminatory against gays and lesbians, a spokesman said earlier Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Six states -- Massachusetts, Connecticut, Iowa, Vermont, New Hampshire and New York -- and the District of Columbia issue marriage licenses to same-sex couples, while 31 states have voted in favor of constitutional amendments that seek to defend traditional definitions of marriage as a heterosexual union.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>In February, Washington Gov. Christine Gregoire signed a bill that would legalize same-sex marriage beginning in June, but opponents there have pledged to block the bill and called for voters to decide the issue.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Maryland Gov. Martin O&amp;apost;Malley signed into law a bill that permits the state&amp;apost;s same-sex couples to wed as of January 1, and state residents may vote to affirm such a law.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Minnesota will vote on a state constitutional amendment similar to the one in North Carolina, while Maine will have a referendum on allowing same-sex marriage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Meanwhile, two cases seeking to overturn laws forbidding the practice, one from California and another from Massachusetts, could be headed to the U.S. Supreme Court in coming months.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
