<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1010" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/04/08/politics/asian-american-immigration/index.html" date_published="2013-04-08 19:34:02" category="politics" author="Sudip Bhattacharya, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Caught in the middle: Asian immigrants struggle to stay in America</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="14">More than 1.3 million Asians are undocumented in the U.S.; many arrived here as children.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12">The Asian population in the U.S. grew by more than 40% between 2000 and 2010.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="15">The Gang of Eight in the Senate is negotiating a sweeping immigration reform bill .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-14 15:17:45" annotation_time="68.496666">
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">But the Asian population in the U.S. grew by more than 40% between 2000 and 2010, according to the U.S. Census Bureau.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="1">Of the more than 11 million undocumented immigrants in the U.S., 1.3 million are from Asia, according to the Department of Homeland Security.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="3">As this year&amp;apost;s immigration reform efforts began, Asian-American advocacy groups laid out their priorities to the Gang of Eight negotiating a bill in the Senate, along with other key legislators like House Speaker John Boehner and Minority Leader Nancy Pelosi.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington It should have been a happy day for Raymond Jose: He had been accepted to college, with scholarships to help pay for it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But when he told his parents, his mother started to cry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;I was puzzled why she was crying after hearing such great news,&amp;quot; said Jose, who was to attend Montgomery College in Maryland.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;That was when she started to explain to me we were undocumented, that we had overstayed our tourist visas.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Jose&amp;apost;s family had come to the United States from the Philippines in 2000, when Jose was 9.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>They first lived in the Tampa Bay, Florida, area but moved four years later to Maryland.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Jose had been assimilated into American life and culture and didn&amp;apost;t know that he was undocumented until that day.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>When he found out, he was heartbroken.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>His undocumented status prevented him from using scholarship money to help pay for school.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;Every day after that, it was really hard to get out of bed,&amp;quot; Jose said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The debate over immigration reform has been focused on border security and immigrants from Latin America.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>But the Asian population in the U.S. grew by more than 40% between 2000 and 2010, according to the U.S. Census Bureau.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The number of those identifying themselves as Asians, either alone or in combination with another racial group, grew from 11.9 million to 17.3 million.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Of the more than 11 million undocumented immigrants in the U.S., 1.3 million are from Asia, according to the Department of Homeland Security.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>As this year&amp;apost;s immigration reform efforts began, Asian-American advocacy groups laid out their priorities to the Gang of Eight negotiating a bill in the Senate, along with other key legislators like House Speaker John Boehner and Minority Leader Nancy Pelosi.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Their priorities in the immigration debate include establishing a humane pathway to citizenship, restricting the use of electronic employment verification systems such as E-Verify and reducing visa backlogs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The groups are also trying to fight efforts to increase the number of business-related visas at the expense of those that allow immigrants to join resident family in the U.S. and change the policy of deportations for minor offenses.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The Asian American Justice Center, based in Washington, has been focused on family visas.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;Lindsey Graham and others have been very public on eliminating the married adult children category and brother-sister category,&amp;quot; Mee Moua, president and executive director, said of the Republican senator from South Carolina.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The justice center has met with legislators to argue that such visa categories shouldn&amp;apost;t be eliminated and has provided information for Asian-Americans, Latino Americans and those in the African and Caribbean communities on the impact if these visas were to be eliminated.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;Our aim is to fight for and be the champion for a common-sense solution for the family visa situation,&amp;quot; Moua said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Meeran Mahmud, a staff attorney at the Asian Pacific American Legal Center, has an older sister in Pakistan who is waiting to be reunited with her family in the U.S.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Her uncle applied for their papers in 1986.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Mahmud was able to come to the U.S. 10 years later, but her sister had turned 22 and was no longer eligible.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Her sister has since married and had children of her own.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;Been waiting since she was a little girl, and she will be turning 40 this year,&amp;quot; Mahmud said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Another major issue for the Asian Pacific American Legal Center is the detention and deportation of immigrants and refugees.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Anoop Prasad, a staff attorney for immigrant rights at the Asian Law Caucus, points to the Illegal Immigration Reform and Immigrant Responsibility Act of 1996 as increasing deportations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Prasad says that under the law, the U.S. can deport someone who was convicted of minor offenses as a teenager, like possession of a small amount of drugs or shoplifting.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The law has severely affected the Cambodian, Laotian and Vietnamese communities, Prasad said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is a complicated question but has a good deal to do with issues with refugee resettlement issues in the &amp;apost;80s.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Many were dealing with mental health issues from the (Vietnam) war.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Almost all Cambodian refugees had lost a relative in the genocide, and many had seen relatives killed or starved to death.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Post-traumatic stress disorder and depression rates among Cambodian refugees are over 80%, Prasad said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;Yet mental health services weren&amp;apost;t available when they arrived.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Most were resettled in neighborhoods with high unemployment and poverty rates along with drugs and high incarceration rates.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>In the absence of a strong family support structure, many joined gangs when they were in high school and picked up convictions.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Prasad wants more discretion when dealing with deportation cases rather than having someone&amp;apost;s fate decided simply by a look at their convictions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;These are actual people with names and stories and families,&amp;quot; Prasad said, &amp;quot;and it&amp;apost;s our job to make sure their voices get heard.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The Chicago-based Asian American Institute has also been meeting with legislators and organizing Asian-Americans to talk with their congressmen about issues like immigration.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>The institute has been collecting and posting personal stories from Asian-Americans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>For example, Connie wants to bring her son from the Philippines to live with her in the U.S.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>&amp;quot;Applications where her son&amp;apost;s is categorized normally take 11-12 years,&amp;quot; Connie&amp;apost;s story says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;In the interim they have tried to spend every Christmas together for the past 8 years since Connie came to the US.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a form of bonding; a pact that only gets more painful and emotional every goodbye time -- and expensive.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>As for Jose, he&amp;apost;s making do, whatever ultimately happens in Washington.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>After he graduated high school, his father handed him an envelope with enough money for one semester at community college.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Since then, his family has been helping him pay for school.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>His father does landscaping and sometimes works as a vendor at RFK Stadium in Washington.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>His mother babysits, take cares of the elderly and cleans houses.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>Even his older sister has taken odd jobs to help.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Jose has had to skip semesters so he could work and help his family financially.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>He also took part in the campaign to help pass the Maryland DREAM Act, which grants in-state tuition rates to undocumented immigrants, last year and has continued to raise awareness about others like him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="37">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re here, and we&amp;apost;re not leaving, and we want a just and inclusive immigration reform,&amp;quot; Jose said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
