<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1060" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/12/politics/general-john-allen-isis-coalition/index.html?hpt=imi_c2" date_published="2014-09-12 17:12:04" category="politics" author="Jamie Crawford, CNN National Security Producer" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Gen. Allen on familiar ground battling ISIS</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Retired Gen. John Allen was commander of American forces in Afghanistan.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">Allen developed a security plan for Israel, West Bank during Israeli-Palestinian negotiations.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="13">Ex-Marine caught up in David Petraeus scandal, but Defense Department cleared him.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-02 10:34:07" annotation_time="138.65565" mapping_time_divergence="46.21855">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Washington John Allen, the retired four-star Marine general and former commander of American forces in Afghanistan, will take on the role of coordinating the international coalition to battle ISIS, Secretary of State John Kerry announced Friday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">Kerry later appointed him to develop a security plan for Israel and the West Bank during negotiations between Israelis and Palestinians over the possibility of a future Palestinian state that eventually collapsed.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="3">An investigation into &amp;quot;flirtatious&amp;quot; email exchanges between Allen and Jill Kelley, the Florida woman whose complaints about threatening emails from Petraeus&amp;apost; mistress, Paula Broadwell, brought the scandal into the public, led Allen to withdraw his nomination by Obama to become NATO&amp;apost;s supreme allied commander in 2013.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington John Allen, the retired four-star Marine general and former commander of American forces in Afghanistan, will take on the role of coordinating the international coalition to battle ISIS, Secretary of State John Kerry announced Friday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The move marks a return to the head of a difficult and challenging mission that bears no clear or obvious solutions for a successful outcome.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Allen is a veteran of many of many of those.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Allen is certainly familiar with the rocky terrain he is about to enter having been one of the top commanders in western Iraq during the &amp;quot;Sunni Awakening,&amp;quot; a program that worked to turn Sunni tribes in Anbar province against the al Qaeda affiliate then operating in Iraq.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The militant organization now swallowing portions of both Syria and Iraq that President Barack Obama has vowed to destroy is the successor to what was once that al Qaeda group.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Allen graduated with honors from the U.S. Naval Academy in 1976, and has racked up a long and distinguished list of accomplishments both on the battlefields of Afghanistan and Iraq as well as an attempted role as peacemaker to one of the longest and most intractable conflicts in the Middle East.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Obama tapped him in 2011 to take command of the International Security Assistance Force in Afghanistan -- the NATO-led coalition of military forces in that country -- after Obama nominated Gen. David Petraeus, then that coalition&amp;apost;s commander, to become director of the CIA.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Allen was the first Marine tapped to head up the military effort in Afghanistan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Kerry later appointed him to develop a security plan for Israel and the West Bank during negotiations between Israelis and Palestinians over the possibility of a future Palestinian state that eventually collapsed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Before his command in Afghanistan, Allen was deputy commander at U.S. Central Command, which oversees all military operations in the Middle East.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>He is also a decorated veteran of the armed forces, having received the Defense Distinguished Service Medal and the Defense Superior Service Medal among others.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>While controversy mostly eluded his impressive rise to the top ranks of the U.S. military, Allen was briefly caught up in the 2012 scandal involving Petraeus&amp;apost; infidelity that ultimately led the widely admired retired general to resign his CIA post.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>An investigation into &amp;quot;flirtatious&amp;quot; email exchanges between Allen and Jill Kelley, the Florida woman whose complaints about threatening emails from Petraeus&amp;apost; mistress, Paula Broadwell, brought the scandal into the public, led Allen to withdraw his nomination by Obama to become NATO&amp;apost;s supreme allied commander in 2013.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The Defense Department eventually cleared him of any wrongdoing, and Allen retired from the Marines.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Allen is the married father of two daughters and holds master&amp;apost;s degrees from Georgetown University, the Defense Intelligence College and the National War College.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
