<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="985" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/04/10/politics/background-checks-explainer/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2013-04-10 04:22:27" category="politics" author="Corinne Jones, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Background checks on gun sales: How do they work?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Few Americans understand how background checks actually work.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">For some Republicans, the idea of expanded record-keeping is a deal breaker.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">The background check system is linked to several databases managed by the FBI.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="13">Since 1998, almost 2% of background checks have been denied.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-10 22:01:43" annotation_time="18.409666">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">But few Americans understand how background checks actually work.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">For some Republicans and gun rights activists, the idea of any type of national gun registry is a deal-breaker.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">The NICS system is linked to several databases managed by the FBI, including the National Crime Information Center, and runs an individual&amp;apost;s name through federal and state criminal records.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="4">Since its implementation in 1998, 2.1 million background checks have been denied out of 118 million requests, or almost 2%.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington A central part of the gun legislation Congress is expected to take up this week is the idea of expanded background checks on gun purchases.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But few Americans understand how background checks actually work.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Leaders from both sides of the aisle -- and an overwhelming number of Americans in national opinion polls -- support expanded background checks before the purchase of guns.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>But when it comes to specifics, the divide shows.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Meanwhile, some congressional Democrats are pushing not only for expanded background checks, but also for broadening the requirement for records of sale transactions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>For some Republicans and gun rights activists, the idea of any type of national gun registry is a deal-breaker.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Here&amp;apost;s how the current system works:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Once you have decided to purchase a gun from a retail outlet -- it could be a local gun shop or national chain such as Bass Pro Shops, Cabelas or Walmart -- the store enters your name and information into the National Instant Criminal Background Check System, or NICS, via a toll-free number or the Internet, to check the eligibility of the buyer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The check usually takes a few minutes to complete.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The NICS system is linked to several databases managed by the FBI, including the National Crime Information Center, and runs an individual&amp;apost;s name through federal and state criminal records.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Individuals can also be added to the NICS index outside of potential gun sales, on the recommendation of psychiatrists, mental health institutions and family members.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Under the current NICS system, buyers may be denied the purchase of a firearm for reasons such as being indicted or convicted of a felony, admitting to being addicted to a controlled substances, having been dishonorably discharged from the Armed Forces, being subject to a restraining order, as well as other regulations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Since its implementation in 1998, 2.1 million background checks have been denied out of 118 million requests, or almost 2%.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The use of the NICS however is not required for private sales of firearms, which make up about 20% of all firearm transactions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>A Democrat-backed bill being discussed in Congress closes this loophole, requiring background checks for all gun transactions, even private ones.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>This would extend background checks to purchases made at gun shows and on the internet.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The current NICS is required by federal law -- the Brady Act of 1993 -- to destroy background check request records within 24 hours.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>And since the passage of the Gun Control Act of 1968, licensed gun dealers -- called FFLs or Federal Firearms License holders -- are required by the ATF to also have gun purchasers to fill out a federal Form 4473, which allows law enforcement officials to trace guns to their original purchasers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>That document -- which contains the name, address, date of birth, copy of ID, NICS background check transaction number and model and serial number of the gun purchased -- must be retained by the dealer for 20 years and carries with it the same federal privacy restrictions as a federal tax return.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Some opponents of changes to background checks cite the ineffectiveness of the current system as a reason not to expand it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The current system cannot force states to share all of their records with the NICS database, especially ones regarding mental health.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>This lack of records allows some people with mental issues to legally purchase guns.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Seung-Hui Cho, the shooter in the Virginia Tech massacre in 2007, had been declared mentally ill by a judge two years before he murdered 32 people.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>But Cho had gone through a background check and been cleared.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Others see the expansion as another waste of government dollars, believing that people who are not likely to have background checks approved, like felons, won&amp;apost;t even attempt the process, and instead will go straight to the black market to purchase firearms.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>A recent CNN/ORC poll showed that nine out of 10 Americans said that they support a background check on every gun sale.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Hope grows for compromise proposal on gun control.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
