<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1042" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/12/05/politics/democrats-immigrant-deportation/index.html?iref=allsearch" date_published="2013-12-05 19:41:54" category="politics" author="Leigh Ann Caldwell, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Dems to Obama: Suspend deportations</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Some lawmakers call on President Obama to suspend deportations.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">They are the most prominent of a growing chorus of voices pushing the President.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">Immigration reform is stalled in the House of Representatives.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-06 10:31:00" annotation_time="71.611">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="3">Washington While immigration reform is stalled in Congress, some members are calling on President Barack Obama to take the matter into his own hands, urging him to suspend deportations of undocumented immigrants.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1, 2">The lawmakers are the most prominent of a growing chorus calling on Obama to use his executive authority to exercise &amp;quot;prosecutorial discretion&amp;quot; to suspend deportations of undocumented immigrants.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington While immigration reform is stalled in Congress, some members are calling on President Barack Obama to take the matter into his own hands, urging him to suspend deportations of undocumented immigrants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Thirty Democratic members of Congress wrote in a letter that he has the authority to pause deportations of undocumented immigrants, urging &amp;quot;the sensible and moral step of stopping deportations.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;In fact, taking a strong step toward granting relief would move us in the direction of where the immigration debate rightfully should start, with the legalization of eleven million men and women who call the United States their home,&amp;quot; the letter states.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The lawmakers are the most prominent of a growing chorus calling on Obama to use his executive authority to exercise &amp;quot;prosecutorial discretion&amp;quot; to suspend deportations of undocumented immigrants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The issue catapulted to prominence last week when an audience member, Ju Hong, shouted at the President during an event in San Francisco, demanding that he stop deportations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The President immediately rejected Hong&amp;apost;s demand, saying he doesn&amp;apost;t have the authority.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Now, some members of Congress say he does.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;Mr. President, you do have the power to stop what&amp;apost;s going on,&amp;quot; Rep. Charlie Rangel, D-New York, said at a news conference on Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>In their letter, the members point to executive action in 201,2 when Obama exercised his discretion to suspend deportations of children of undocumented immigrants, known as Deferred Action of Childhood Arrivals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;Please, Mr. President, do something,&amp;quot; said Rep. Luis Gutierrez, D-Illinois.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;We need you to take the kinds of positive action to help our families.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Although Obama has used his discretion to save some from deportation, he has aggressively expanded the program.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>He has expelled more people than any other president: For instance, 410,000 people were deported in 2012, compared with 116,000 in 2001.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>In their letter, the lawmakers say that 1,100 people are deported every day.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Obama has shifted the type of immigrants targeted for deportation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>While the administration of President George W. Bush targeted working immigrants by raiding workplaces, Obama is focusing on convicted criminals and &amp;quot;egregious&amp;quot; immigration violators, including recent border-crossers and illegal re-entrants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Immigration and Customs Enforcement says its efforts are effective, pointing out that 55% of people deported last year were convicted criminals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Criminalizing American families or giving local law enforcement the responsibility to choose who stays and who goes is not the right option,&amp;quot; the letter reads.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The Senate passed comprehensive immigration reform this year, including a path to citizenship for the 11 million undocumented immigrants already in the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The legislation has been stalled in the House and is unlikely to be taken up before the end of the year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
