<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1068" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/23/politics/obama-syria-strikes-policy/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-09-23 17:27:34" category="politics" author="Kevin Liptak, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>How Obama came to launch strikes in Syria</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Saudi Arabia, UAE, Qatar, Bahrain and Jordan joined in the attack on ISIS targets.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">Obama has moved from reluctance to launch airstrikes to ordering Monday¹s campaign.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="8">Coalition strikes began the evening before Obama visits U.N. General Assembly.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="9">Focus is on stemming the flow of foreign-born fighters who join up with ISIS, other groups.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 16:25:07" annotation_time="53.003998">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">The U.S. said Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates, Qatar, Bahrain and Jordan had joined in the attack on ISIS targets near Raqqa in Syria.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">Initially hesitant to become involved in the Syrian conflict, which pits an authoritarian regime led by President Bashar al-Assad against a patchwork of rebel groups, Obama has moved from sending weapons to opposition fighters last year, to backing away from airstrikes against al-Assad, to ordering Monday¹s campaign to take out ISIS terrorists who have used the Syrian unrest to gain a foothold.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="3">The coalition strikes began the evening before Obama made his annual visit to the United Nations General Assembly, where the White House hopes to secure broader support for the anti-ISIS campaign from a range of allies.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="4">The main focus, officials say, is on stemming the flow of foreign-born fighters who have joined up with ISIS and other terror groups in Syria and Iraq.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>New York President Barack Obama&amp;apost;s policy toward Syria -- three years of red lines and calls for regime change -- culminated Monday in a barrage of airstrikes on terror targets there, marking a turning point for the conflict and thrusting the President further into it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The U.S. said Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates, Qatar, Bahrain and Jordan had joined in the attack on ISIS targets near Raqqa in Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The U.S. also launched airstrikes against another terrorist organization, the Khorasan Group.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Obama described its members as &amp;quot;seasoned al Qaeda operatives in Syria,&amp;quot; and U.S. officials said the group was plotting attacks against the United States and other Western targets.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Initially hesitant to become involved in the Syrian conflict, which pits an authoritarian regime led by President Bashar al-Assad against a patchwork of rebel groups, Obama has moved from sending weapons to opposition fighters last year, to backing away from airstrikes against al-Assad, to ordering Monday¹s campaign to take out ISIS terrorists who have used the Syrian unrest to gain a foothold.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>It¹s new ground for the U.S., which lacks robust intelligence capabilities in Syria and hasn&amp;apost;t sent any ground forces there.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Unlike the campaign against ISIS in Iraq, the U.S. doesn¹t have al-Assad¹s permission to launch airstrikes in Syria, though the U.S. notified him before the attacks began.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The coalition strikes began the evening before Obama made his annual visit to the United Nations General Assembly, where the White House hopes to secure broader support for the anti-ISIS campaign from a range of allies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The main focus, officials say, is on stemming the flow of foreign-born fighters who have joined up with ISIS and other terror groups in Syria and Iraq.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The U.S. intelligence community believes there are 15,000 foreign fighters from 80 countries who are fighting alongside ISIS and other similar terror groups -- 2,000 from Europe and roughly 100 from the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>A senior administration official said on Monday that some of those Americans had already returned to the United States and were being tracked by the FBI.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Not all of those who have returned were fighting for ISIS.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Administration officials are confident in the prospects of a U.S.-backed resolution that would compel nations to try to stop citizens from leaving to fight for terror groups.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Obama will personally chair a session of the U.N. Security Council on Wednesday to push for the measure.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>He last chaired the panel in 2009, and was the first American president to do so.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Here is a timeline of the major events leading up to U.S. action in Syria:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>August 2012: President Obama lays out a &amp;quot;red line&amp;quot; in the Syrian conflict, saying that the use of chemical weapons would &amp;quot;change his calculus&amp;quot; on Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>March, April, June 2013: The Syrian government uses chemical weapons against opposition forces in Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>August 2013: The al-Assad regime continues to use chemical weapons and Obama lays out a plan for limited military intervention against the Syrian regime while asking Congress to weigh in.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>September 2013: Congress is reticent to endorse U.S. military action in Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>But then, in a plan engineered by Russia, al-Assad agrees to give up Syria&amp;apost;s chemical weapons and Obama begins to back away from military strikes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>June 2014: Obama sends more than 300 military advisers to Iraq to advise Iraqi forces and protect U.S. interests.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>July 2014: Obama sends more advisers to Iraq.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>August 7, 2014: Obama authorizes targeted airstrikes in Iraq to guard American interests and protect minorities facing impending massacre by ISIS militants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>August 20, 2014: American journalist James Foley is beheaded by ISIS.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The video is posted online.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Within the next few weeks, ISIS beheads another American journalist, Steven Sotloff, and a British aid worker, David Haines, and posts those videos online as well.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>September 10, 2014: Obama announces he&amp;apost;s authorized the U.S. military to strike ISIS in Iraq and Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>In addition, he announces a plan to arm and train 5,000 moderate Syrian rebels, pending congressional approval.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>September 18, 2014: Congress approves the President&amp;apost;s plan to arm and train Syrian rebels.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>September 22, 2014: The U.S. launches its first airstrikes in Syria in coordination with five Arab nations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>