<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1031" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/11/09/politics/petraeus-cia-resignation/index.html" category="politics" author="Dana Ford, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>CIA chief Petraeus resigns over affair</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="18">David Petraeus, a retired four-star general, led forces in Iraq and Afghanistan.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="10">Source: The FBI investigated a tip that he was involved with his biographer.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">President Obama praises Petraeus&amp;apost; dedication and patriotism.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="40, 39">He and his wife, Holly, live in Virginia, and have two grown children.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-09 14:50:11" annotation_time="89.896">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">The president hailed Petraeus&amp;apost; dedication and patriotism, while leaders from both parties said he would be missed.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="2">According to a U.S. official, the FBI had a tip that Petraeus was involved with his biographer, Paula Broadwell, and investigated the alleged affair to determine whether it posed a security risk.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="1">Petraeus, 60, had a distinguished 37-year career in the military before joining the CIA, helping turn the tide against insurgents while commanding forces in Iraq and Afghanistan.</sentence>
      <sentence id="39" ids_highlights="4">Petraeus and his wife, Holly, live in Virginia.</sentence>
      <sentence id="40" ids_highlights="4">They have two grown children.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Only two people know how the affair started, but the world knows now about its inglorious end.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Admitting to the extramarital affair, David Petraeus stepped down as director of the CIA on Friday in a surprise move that shocked the intelligence community just days after President Barack Obama was re-elected.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Immediate praise for the man poured in.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The president hailed Petraeus&amp;apost; dedication and patriotism, while leaders from both parties said he would be missed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>It appeared an abrupt end to a spectacularly successful career in public service.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;After being married for over 37 years, I showed extremely poor judgment by engaging in an extramarital affair.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Such behavior is unacceptable, both as a husband and as the leader of an organization such as ours,&amp;quot; Petraeus said in a letter to colleagues, explaining his decision to step down.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;Teddy Roosevelt once observed that life&amp;apost;s greatest gift is the opportunity to work hard at work worth doing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>I will always treasure my opportunity to have done that with you and I will always regret the circumstances that brought that work with you to an end,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>According to a U.S. official, the FBI had a tip that Petraeus was involved with his biographer, Paula Broadwell, and investigated the alleged affair to determine whether it posed a security risk.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The FBI was not investigating Petraeus for wrongdoing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The concern was that he could potentially be blackmailed or put &amp;quot;in a vulnerable spot,&amp;quot; the official said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Broadwell spent a year with Petraeus in Afghanistan interviewing him for the book she co-wrote, &amp;quot;All In: The Education of General David Petraeus.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>It is not clear whether Broadwell is the woman with whom Petraeus has admitted having an affair.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>CNN has not been able to reach Broadwell for comment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Other sources close to the CIA director told HLN anchor Kyra Phillips that the woman involved in the affair was not under Petraeus&amp;apost; command.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The woman was not a member of the armed forces and not a CIA employee, they said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Petraeus, 60, had a distinguished 37-year career in the military before joining the CIA, helping turn the tide against insurgents while commanding forces in Iraq and Afghanistan.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Earning praise from both sides of the political aisle, the retired four-star general took the helm of the CIA in September 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Director of National Intelligence James Clapper hailed Petraeus, saying his &amp;quot;decision to step down represents the loss of one of our nation&amp;apost;s most respected public servants.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Petraeus met with Obama on Thursday to offer his resignation and explain the circumstances behind it, according to a senior administration official.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The president accepted Petraeus&amp;apost; resignation during a phone call Friday, said the official.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;By any measure, he was one of the outstanding general officers of his generation, helping our military adapt to new challenges and leading our men and women in uniform through a remarkable period of service in Iraq and Afghanistan, where he helped our nation put those wars on a path to a responsible end,&amp;quot; Obama said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;As director of the Central Intelligence Agency, he has continued to serve with characteristic intellectual rigor, dedication and patriotism.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The president expressed confidence that the CIA will continue to move forward, under the direction of Acting Director Michael Morell.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Morell, a career agency officer, was sworn in as deputy director of the CIA in May 2010.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>He previously served as associate deputy director and director for intelligence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Petraeus assumed command of the NATO International Security Assistance Force and U.S. Forces Afghanistan in July 2010, after serving for more than 20 months as commander of United States Central Command.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>He previously commanded multinational forces in Iraq, leading the so-called surge.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The general literally wrote the book on counterinsurgency techniques by overseeing development of the Army/Marine Corps Counterinsurgency Manual.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Before his nomination as CIA director, Petraeus was considered the nation&amp;apost;s most well-known and popular military leader since Colin Powell.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>But his reputation was potentially tarnished by the controversy over the terror attack on the U.S. mission in Benghazi, Libya, that killed Ambassador Christopher Stevens and three other Americans in September.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Petraeus was expected to testify before the Senate Intelligence Committee next week on the Benghazi attack.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Morell will take his place, according to the office of Sen. Dianne Feinstein, who is chairman of that committee.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;I wish President Obama had not accepted this resignation, but I understand and respect the decision.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>David Petraeus is one of America&amp;apost;s best and brightest, and all Americans should be grateful for his service,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Rep. Peter King, chairman of the House Committee on Homeland Security, described Petraeus as a &amp;quot;true American patriot.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is a real loss for the country; a real loss for the CIA,&amp;quot; he told CNN&amp;apost;s Erin Burnett.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Petraeus and his wife, Holly, live in Virginia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>They have two grown children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
