<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1056" link="http://www.cnn.com/2011/11/23/politics/debate-5-things/index.html" date_published="2011-11-23 06:28:16" category="politics" author="Paul Steinhauser and Peter Hamby, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Five things we learned from the CNN debate</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="8">Gingrich calls for a limited amnesty for longtime illegal immigrants.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="19">Hunstman and Bachmann shine.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="29">Debate highlights Ron Paul&amp;apost;s lonely antiwar beliefs.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="49">Herman Cain lays low for most of the debate.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-19 19:06:28" annotation_time="37.7775">
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="1">Newt Gingrich called for a limited amnesty for longtime illegal immigrants.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="2">Huntsman and Bachmann shine: For the candidates stuck in single digits in national and state polling, the debate offered moments for breakout performances.</sentence>
      <sentence id="29" ids_highlights="3">Ron Paul -- the loneliest man in the GOP: Tuesday&amp;apost;s debate was bound to highlight Texas Rep. Ron Paul&amp;apost;s lonely antiwar beliefs in a party that&amp;apost;s had a hawkish bent for decades.</sentence>
      <sentence id="49" ids_highlights="4">After a forceful start where he touted his &amp;quot;targeted identification&amp;quot; airport security screening plan, the businessman, former Godfather&amp;apost;s Pizza CEO and radio talk show host seemed to lay low for the rest of the debate.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington Can a debate without many zingers and gotcha moments be interesting and newsworthy?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The answer appears to be yes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Tuesday night&amp;apost;s GOP presidential debate in the nation&amp;apost;s capital was short on action, but long on drama.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>And the debate, like its 10 predecessors so far this campaign season, will most likely have an impact on the race for the Republican nomination.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Here&amp;apost;s what we learned from the showdown:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Did Gingrich enter danger zone over immigration reform?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>: The former House Speaker was having one of his best performances to date, until the issue of immigration reform came up late in the debate.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Newt Gingrich called for a limited amnesty for longtime illegal immigrants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;I don&amp;apost;t see how the party that says it&amp;apost;s the party of the family is going to adopt an immigration policy which destroys families which have been here a quarter century,&amp;quot; Gingrich said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;And I am prepared to take the heat for saying let&amp;apost;s be humane in enforcing the law without giving them citizenship, but finding a way to give them legality so as not to separate them from their families.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>And take heat, he did.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Amnesty is a four-letter word to many in the Republican base.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>And the other front-runner in the nomination battle, former Massachusetts Gov. Mitt Romney, was quick to push back against Gingrich, saying that allowing illegal immigrants to stay as legal citizens would only invite more people to try to do the same.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;People respond to incentives,&amp;quot; Romney added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>While Gingrich spokesman R.C. Hammond played down the issue as he was peppered by reporters&amp;apost; questions in the spin room after the debate, the Romney campaign was quick to highlight the controversy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think it&amp;apost;s a major difference of opinion between Mitt Romney and Newt Gingrich,&amp;quot; top Romney adviser Eric Fehrnstrom told reporters.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;Newt Gingrich supported the 1986 amnesty and even though he concedes it was a mistake he&amp;apost;s willing to repeat that mistake today by granting amnesty all over again to people who are in the country illegally.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Mitt Romney does not.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Huntsman and Bachmann shine: For the candidates stuck in single digits in national and state polling, the debate offered moments for breakout performances.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>And two of the candidates connected.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Jon Huntsman was on his game.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Thanks to a debate that focused heavily on foreign affairs and national security, the former Utah governor and former ambassador to China arguably had his best performance to date.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Huntsman went mano a mano against Romney in arguing for drastic cuts in U.S. military forces in Afghanistan, saying that while he would listen to his military advisers, &amp;quot;at the end of the day, the president of the United States is commander-in-chief.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Rep. Michele Bachmann had her best debate since her first, back in June in New Hampshire.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The congresswoman from Minnesota, who sits on the House Intelligence Committee, got questions in her wheelhouse on national security and international affairs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Her standout moment may have been her ringing the alarm bell on the instability of Pakistan&amp;apost;s nuclear sites.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;They also are one of the most violent, unstable nations that there is.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>We have to recognize that 15 of the sites, nuclear sites are available or are potentially penetrable by jihadists,&amp;quot; cautioned Bachmann, adding that, &amp;quot;Pakistan is a nation, that it&amp;apost;s kind of like &amp;apost;too nuclear to fail.&amp;apost; &amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Ron Paul -- the loneliest man in the GOP: Tuesday&amp;apost;s debate was bound to highlight Texas Rep. Ron Paul&amp;apost;s lonely antiwar beliefs in a party that&amp;apost;s had a hawkish bent for decades.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>In that respect, he did not disappoint.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Out of the gate, Paul sparred with Gingrich over the Patriot Act.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Gingrich called on the legislation to be strengthened &amp;quot;because the dangers that are posed are so great.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Paul, who has long opposed the legislation on the grounds that it grants the government powers to investigate American citizens without their knowledge, called the Patriot Act &amp;quot;unpatriotic&amp;quot; because it &amp;quot;undermines our liberty.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Later, Paul broke with his rivals when they said they would side with Israel if it launched an attack on Iran.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>And he called humanitarian aid to fight disease in Africa &amp;quot;worthless.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>(His argument: Aid money gets scooped up by foreign despots instead of the people who really need it.).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Paul may be in line with the Republican base on matters of spending and debt, but when it comes to foreign policy, he is on an island.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Republicans agree: We love Israel: Tuesday&amp;apost;s debate made clear that in the wake of George W. Bush&amp;apost;s eight years in office, the Republican Party lacks any sort of cohesive foreign policy vision.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>There remains one point of consensus, however: That the United States should do whatever it takes to protect and defend Israel.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>With the exception of Paul, the Republican candidates have all taken stridently pro-Israel positions throughout the campaign.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>The ante was upped Tuesday by Romney, who made this promise: &amp;quot;If I&amp;apost;m president of the United States, my first trip -- my first foreign trip will be to Israel to show the world we care about that country and that region.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Former Pennsylvania Sen. Rick Santorum said he would do the same.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Cain said he would side with Israel if it launched an attack on Iran to disable its nuclear capabilities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Huntsman went out of his way to praise Israel later, saying this: &amp;quot;Our interest in the Middle East is Israel.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>And our interest is to ensure that ... Iran does not go nuclear.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>And Bachmann said Obama has undertaken &amp;quot;a doctrine of appeasement&amp;quot; toward Iran.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Paul was the lone voice of dissent, telling the debate crowd that &amp;quot;Israel should take care of themselves.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Herman Cain: The missing man: Was Herman Cain trying to stay under the radar?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>After a forceful start where he touted his &amp;quot;targeted identification&amp;quot; airport security screening plan, the businessman, former Godfather&amp;apost;s Pizza CEO and radio talk show host seemed to lay low for the rest of the debate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Domestic policy, aka &amp;quot;9-9-9,&amp;quot; is Cain&amp;apost;s strong suit, but the debate offered the candidate a chance to improve his foreign policy and national security chops.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>Cain didn&amp;apost;t seem willing to take up the challenge.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Cain didn&amp;apost;t appear to do himself any favors with brief generic answers like &amp;quot;number one, secure the border for real&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;I would first make sure that they had a credible plan for success, clarity of mission and clarity of success.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>And rule No. 1 for any candidate at a debate: Get the name of the moderator correct.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>Cain initially called CNN&amp;apost;s Wolf Blitzer &amp;quot;Blitz.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>