<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1117" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/11/11/politics/court-veterans/index.html?iref=allsearch" date_published="2013-11-11 17:43:29" category="politics" author="Bill Mears, CNN Supreme Court Producer" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Special veterans court marks 25th anniversary</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">Court gives veterans chance to challenge individual decisions made by Veterans Affairs.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">The court&amp;apost;s work is little noticed, but experts say it provides invaluable service.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="27">Claims appeal process is potentially time-consuming and bureaucratically complex.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="30">Nearly all the nine judges on the current court have served in the military.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-07 11:33:00" annotation_time="38.559334">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">The nation&amp;apost;s newest federal court is celebrating its 25th anniversary this week, giving those who served in the military a chance to challenge individual decisions made by the Department of Veterans Affairs.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">The court&amp;apost;s work is little noticed, but legal experts and veterans advocates say it provides an invaluable service.</sentence>
      <sentence id="27" ids_highlights="3">The claims appeal process is potentially time-consuming and bureaucratically complex, and can involve numerous offices, including internal reviews by the Veterans Benefits Administration, then upward to the U.S. Court of Appeals for Veterans Claims, the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit, and ultimately the U.S. Supreme Court.</sentence>
      <sentence id="30" ids_highlights="4">Nearly all the nine judges on the current court have served in the military, and all have prior experience dealing with veterans and related service organizations.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The tiny courtroom tucked away in a downtown office building had almost no spectators on a recent Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>And the cases being argued before a panel of judges were not blockbusters or precedent-setting in any way.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>But to current and former military men and women seeking judicial relief, the U.S. Court of Appeals for Veterans Claims is a legal lifeline.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Perhaps it is their last chance to get the full disability compensation they believe they&amp;apost;re owed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The nation&amp;apost;s newest federal court is celebrating its 25th anniversary this week, giving those who served in the military a chance to challenge individual decisions made by the Department of Veterans Affairs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The court&amp;apost;s work is little noticed, but legal experts and veterans advocates say it provides an invaluable service.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;That we have a specialized veteran&amp;apost;s court is a credit to our national commitment to do justice by &amp;apost;him who shall have borne the battle&amp;apost; in President Lincoln&amp;apost;s words,&amp;apost;&amp;quot; said Justice Antonin Scalia in April.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>About 60,000 such appeals have been filed with the court in the past quarter century, and the nine judges now take on about 4,000 cases annually.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Wilson Ausmer, Jr.&amp;apost;s claim is typical.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The decorated U.S. Army veteran served stateside in Operation Desert Storm, and in Iraq during Operation Iraqi Freedom, as well as in Qatar and Afghanistan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>According to his appeal, the Missouri man was awarded VA disability compensation for diseases and injuries during his military service, which included post-traumatic stress disorder.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>But he had a pending claim with the Veterans Affairs for an earlier physical ailment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>It was while he was in Afghanistan for Operation Enduring Freedom-- after being recalled to active duty in 2001-- that he received a notice from the department&amp;apost;s internal review board, denying part of the claim.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The letter was sent to his home in Missouri and Ausmer argues he was not able to file an appeal until after he returned home.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>By then it was too late, and the missed deadline was not extended.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The issue was whether the way the notice was mailed-- while he was overseas -- and the &amp;quot;particular circumstances&amp;quot; of Ausmer&amp;apost;s mental and physical condition, should have merited him extra time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;LTC Ausmer states that for the first few months after returning home, he had anxiety attacks and a difficult time adjusting to civilian life,&amp;quot; said his lawyers, who also pointed out chronic foot, back, and knee pain.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Consequently, he spent the first few months at home trying to &amp;apost;de-stress&amp;apost; from his service in Afghanistan.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>His attorneys at the oral arguments included three Harvard Law School students, who had volunteered their service.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>One of them, Christopher Melendez is a former Marine.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The judges had traveled from Washington to Cambridge to conduct the hearing in Harvard&amp;apost;s ceremonial Ames courtroom.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>It is part of a nationwide outreach program by the federal court to inspire young lawyers to help needy veterans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Advocates say there is a national need for such legal representation, especially pro bono work.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Citing a massive claims backlog, the House of Representatives last month passed a bill to streamline the disability claims appeal process.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The measure would create a 15-member commission to find ways to simplify and reduce the paperwork.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>VA records shows there were more than 404,000 claims pending this month.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The claims appeal process is potentially time-consuming and bureaucratically complex, and can involve numerous offices, including internal reviews by the Veterans Benefits Administration, then upward to the U.S. Court of Appeals for Veterans Claims, the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit, and ultimately the U.S. Supreme Court.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The special federal court with national jurisdiction where Ausmer&amp;apost;s case was heard was signed into law by President Ronald Reagan.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Until that time the department had been sheltered from independent judicial review, and VA officials had initially opposed creation of the court.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Nearly all the nine judges on the current court have served in the military, and all have prior experience dealing with veterans and related service organizations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>They are nominated by the president and typically serve 15-year terms.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Chief Judge Bruce Kasold is a retired U.S. Army lieutenant colonel, with service in the Air Defense Artillery and Judge Advocate General&amp;apost;s Corps.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>He also served in various offices at the U.S. Senate, as well as in private practice.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>As for Ausmer, his case is pending, with the Veterans Claims Court set to issue a written ruling in coming months.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
