<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="982" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/12/03/politics/biden-asia-trip-2016/index.html" date_published="2013-12-03 18:40:39" category="politics" author="Paul Steinhauser, CNN Political Editor" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Asia trip gives Biden chance to show off diplomatic cred</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Asia trip gives Biden opportunity to remind people why Obama chose him as running mate.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="11">Biden was to discuss economic issues on trip but focus shifted to rising tensions with China.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4, 3">VP has decades of experience from his time on Senate Foreign Relations Committee.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="16">Biden tells Asian allies -- and China -- that &amp;quot;we will remain a resident Pacific power&amp;quot;.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-19 10:27:05" annotation_time="242.914" mapping_time_divergence="60.7285">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">The spotlight also provides Biden with an opportunity to remind people why Barack Obama chose him as his running mate and to tout his strong suit as he&amp;apost;s mentioned as a possible presidential candidate in 2016.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">Biden has decades of experience in international relations.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">He served as chairman or the ranking Democrat of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee from 1997 until he left Congress in 2008 following Obama&amp;apost;s victory.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="2">The long-planned trip, which was originally to focus on economic issues, comes as tensions in East Asia are on the rise.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="4">And in an interview with the Ashai daily newspaper, Biden rejected concerns that the United States may not have staying power in the region, saying &amp;quot;economically, diplomatically, militarily, we have been, we are, and we will remain a resident Pacific power.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington Vice President Joe Biden faces a very delicate task this week as he makes a diplomatic visit to East Asia in hopes of turning down the volume on an increasingly noisy territorial tug of war.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The spotlight also provides Biden with an opportunity to remind people why Barack Obama chose him as his running mate and to tout his strong suit as he&amp;apost;s mentioned as a possible presidential candidate in 2016.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Biden has decades of experience in international relations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>He served as chairman or the ranking Democrat of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee from 1997 until he left Congress in 2008 following Obama&amp;apost;s victory.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;This trip, if nothing else, reinforces the notion of why Joe Biden was put on the ticket in the first place and has emerged as one of the best vice presidents in history,&amp;quot; Larry Rasky, a longtime senior political adviser to the Democrat, told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;He was equipped for this job before he got there.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s not going to China for that reason, of course, but it certainly doesn&amp;apost;t hurt.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s definitely his wheelhouse.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>He has the relationships, the global credibility.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>There&amp;apost;s no on-the-job training necessary.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The long-planned trip, which was originally to focus on economic issues, comes as tensions in East Asia are on the rise.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Vice President&amp;apost;s trip comes at an important time for the country and therefore it makes him that more relevant and reminds Americans of his longtime role in the Senate and his experience with foreign policy,&amp;quot; Stuart Rothenberg, editor and publisher of the non-partisan Rothenberg Political Report, told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Biden&amp;apost;s first stop was Tokyo, where longtime ally Japan and the United States are pushing back against China&amp;apost;s recent declaration of a restricted flight zone over parts of the East China Sea that include some islands claimed by both China and Japan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>In a meeting on Tuesday with Japanese Prime Minister Shinzo Abe, Biden said the United States was &amp;quot;deeply concerned by the attempt to unilaterally change the status quo in the East China Sea.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Biden reaffirmed that &amp;quot;the United States looks to our alliance with Japan as the cornerstone of stability and security in East Asia, and we are fully committed to our announced strategy of rebalancing as well in the Pacific,&amp;quot; according to a White House transcript of the meeting.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>And in an interview with the Ashai daily newspaper, Biden rejected concerns that the United States may not have staying power in the region, saying &amp;quot;economically, diplomatically, militarily, we have been, we are, and we will remain a resident Pacific power.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The White House highlighted Biden&amp;apost;s experience in global diplomacy on Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;He has an excellent relationship with the leaders of all three countries and he will underscore how important it is to avoid actions that raise tensions and to prevent miscalculations that could undermine peace, security and prosperity in the region,&amp;quot; White House Press Secretary Jay Carney told reporters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is an opportunity for Vice President Biden to raise our concerns directly with policy makes in Beijing and to seek clarity in regarding the Chinese intentions in making this move at this time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s also an opportunity for us to confer with our allies, Japan and the Republic of Korea, both of whom are directly affected by China&amp;apost;s actions,&amp;quot; Carney added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Rasky said the most important thing for Biden right now, as it relates to any possible White House run in 2016, is to continue to serve as a strong No. 2.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;The main thing that the Vice President has to do is do his job, and do it well,&amp;quot; Rasky added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Biden has not said whether he&amp;apost;ll make a third run for the Democratic presidential nomination following unsuccessful bids in 1988 and 2008.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;I can die a happy man never having been president of the United States of America.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>But it doesn&amp;apost;t mean I won&amp;apost;t run,&amp;quot; Biden said in a July interview with GQ magazine.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>His trip in September to Iowa, the state that traditionally kicks off the presidential primary and caucus calendar, sparked more speculation about his ambitions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Biden, who went to the Hawkeye State to headline Democratic Sen. Tom Harkin&amp;apost;s annual steak fry, a must stop for Democratic White House hopefuls, joked, &amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s amazing when you come to speak at the steak fry, a whole lot of people seem to take notice.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>I don&amp;apost;t know why the hell that is.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Most of the speculation about possible 2016 Democratic candidates is focused on whether former Secretary of State Hillary Clinton will run again.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>All polling suggests Clinton would be the immediate and overwhelming frontrunner for the nomination if she does.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The most recent national survey on a potential Democratic field came from CNN/ORC International two weeks ago and indicated that 63% of Democrats and Independents who lean towards the Democratic Party said Clinton was their early choice for the nomination, with Biden second at 12%.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>But how would the race for the Democratic nomination shape up if Clinton forgoes another run for the White House?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>If that&amp;apost;s the case, the poll suggested that 43% of Democrats would support the Vice President, with freshman Sen. Elizabeth Warren of Massachusetts at 17%, and New York Gov. Andrew Cuomo at 15%.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Of course, polls conducted this early in an election cycle, far before any possible contenders have declared their candidacy, are partially a reflection of name recognition.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>And Biden of course, has a lot of name recognition.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>While the headlines this week from Biden&amp;apost;s trip will add to that name recognition and further beef up his foreign policy and commander-in-chief credentials, Biden has a problem if Clinton runs again.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;Clearly, Joe Biden is not an amateur when it comes to U.S. foreign policy, but unfortunately for him former Secretary of State Hillary&amp;apost;s Clinton&amp;apost;s experience in that realm trumps his,&amp;quot; Rothenberg added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
