<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1013" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/12/31/politics/fiscal-cliff-roberts/index.html" date_published="2012-12-31 22:59:02" category="politics" author="Bill Mears, CNN Supreme Court Producer" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Chief justice laments &amp;apost;fiscal cliff&amp;apost; effects on federal courts</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">A prolonged reduction in funding would be hard to overcome, Chief Justice Roberts says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">He notes 27 federal judicial vacancies are &amp;apost;designated as presenting judicial emergencies&amp;apost;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">&amp;apost;Aggressive&amp;apost; cost containment has been in place for federal courts since 2004, he says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-10 14:49:43" annotation_time="10.3289995">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">He said a prolonged reduction would be extremely hard to overcome.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">At the close of 2012, 27 of the existing judicial vacancies are designated as presenting judicial emergencies.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">Roberts noted the judicial branch generally receives less attention when it comes to its spending, but an &amp;quot;aggressive&amp;quot; cost-containment strategy has been in place since 2004.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington Chief Justice John Roberts is warning leaders in the other two branches of the federal government that the pending &amp;quot;fiscal cliff&amp;quot; would &amp;quot;inevitably result in the delay or denial of justice for the people the courts serve.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>In his annual year-end report on the federal judiciary, Roberts on Monday said the federal courts have already made significant cuts in their funding, representing only about two-tenths of 1% of the entire federal budget.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>He said a prolonged reduction would be extremely hard to overcome.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;I therefore encourage the president and Congress to be especially attentive to the needs of the judicial branch and provide the resources necessary for its operations,&amp;quot; said the chief justice.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;Those vital resource needs include the appointment of an adequate number of judges to keep current on pending cases.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>At the close of 2012, 27 of the existing judicial vacancies are designated as presenting judicial emergencies.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Roberts made his remarks in a 16-page summary of U.S. courts, part of his role as head of the entire federal judiciary.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>President Barack Obama said Monday an agreement to avert the &amp;quot;fiscal cliff&amp;quot; of automatic tax increases and spending cuts appeared to be &amp;quot;within sight.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Senate and House leaders were continuing to meet behind closed doors with White House officials, including Vice President Joe Biden, to reach at least a temporary tax and spending agreement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Roberts noted the judicial branch generally receives less attention when it comes to its spending, but an &amp;quot;aggressive&amp;quot; cost-containment strategy has been in place since 2004.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;Our country faces new challenges, including the much publicized &amp;apost;fiscal cliff&amp;apost; and the longer-term problem of a truly extravagant and burgeoning national debt,&amp;quot; Roberts said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;No one seriously doubts that the country&amp;apost;s fiscal ledger has gone awry.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The public properly looks to its elected officials to craft a solution.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>We in the judiciary stand outside the political arena, but we can continue to do our part to address the financial challenges within our sphere.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The federal court system and its administrative offices operate on an annual budget of nearly $7 billion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>That includes judges trying and hearing cases and appeals, both criminal and civil; managing pretrial, defender, and probation offices; and maintaining the bankruptcy court system.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Most of the money -- about 62% -- goes for personnel costs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Roberts said the Supreme Court itself requested a 2.8% decrease in its $75.55 million operations budget in fiscal year 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>He added a 3.7% decrease is expected for fiscal year 2014.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>There currently are 75 judicial vacancies, according to the Administrative Office of the U.S. Courts.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Thirty-two nominations by the president are pending, awaiting Senate confirmation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>There are 874 federal judges, including the nine-member Supreme Court, the district and appeals courts, and the nine-member Court of International Trade.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Past year-end reports from the current chief justice have focused on budget cutbacks, frozen salaries, rising caseloads, and court security.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>These summaries have been an annual tradition for about four decades.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>They were begun by the late Chief Justice Warren Burger as a way to speak to the executive branch and Congress, the judiciary itself, and the public at large.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
