<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1088" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/06/25/politics/bergdahl-investigation/index.html" date_published="2014-06-25 21:35:28" category="politics" author="Laura Koran, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>No lawyer yet for Bergdahl even though probe underway</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Army Sgt. Bowe Bergdahl is being reintegrated into normal life at a base in Texas.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Army investigators haven&amp;apost;t yet begun to question him.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="11">Some members of his old unit said he deserted before being captured in Afghanistan.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-26 08:21:33" annotation_time="81.5565">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">Senior military officials said Wednesday investigators have not begun questioning Bergdahl, who was captured and held for five years before militants released him last month in exchange for five Taliban commanders held by the United States.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">He is undergoing reintegration at Joint Base San Antonio-Fort Sam Houston in Texas.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="3">Several former members of Bergdahl&amp;apost;s unit allege he deserted his post before being captured, endangering his comrades.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Sgt. Bowe Bergdahl does not yet have a lawyer or been informed of his legal rights even though the Army has begun its investigation of circumstances surrounding his 2009 disappearance in Afghanistan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Senior military officials said Wednesday investigators have not begun questioning Bergdahl, who was captured and held for five years before militants released him last month in exchange for five Taliban commanders held by the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>He is undergoing reintegration at Joint Base San Antonio-Fort Sam Houston in Texas.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>That process is designed to gradually reintroduce him to normal life.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>While the Army&amp;apost;s investigation into Bergdahl&amp;apost;s disappearance only covers the events leading up to his capture, the reintegration debriefings focus on the days and years that follow.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have no reason to believe that he engaged in any misconduct during that period of time,&amp;quot; said one of the officials, referring to his time in captivity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;That&amp;apost;s why he hasn&amp;apost;t been read his rights.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>But, the officials added that if Bergdahl says something incriminating during his debriefings, the process would be halted so he could be informed of his rights.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>One confirmed that he does not yet have a lawyer, but has not been interviewed by investigators either.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Though, anything he says during the reintegration process could be used against him in future disciplinary proceedings.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Several former members of Bergdahl&amp;apost;s unit allege he deserted his post before being captured, endangering his comrades.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Maj. Gen. Kenneth Dahl is leading the formal Berghdal probe by the Army, which began on June 16.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>It must be completed within 60 days.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Dahl will review the findings of a previous investigation conducted just after Bergdahl went missing from his post.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The two-star general can also ask to re-interview anyone he believes can shine light on the case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Interviewing Bergdahl, said one official, would likely be the last step in the investigation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Separately, Bergdahl has received his military salary since he was returned from captivity, and will continue to do so as long as he remains in the Army.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>He is also entitled to the pay that accrued during his years in captivity as long as there is no finding that he deserted or gone absent without leave.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Neither official would say how much Bergdahl is earning, other than to say it&amp;apost;s consistent with his rank and years of service.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>According to the Army&amp;apost;s website, an E-5 classified Sergeant with six years of service would receive $32,814 in basic pay, though he could be eligible for additional compensation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
