<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1076" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/05/05/politics/scotus-new-york-public-prayer/index.html" date_published="2014-05-05 14:27:15" category="politics" author="Bill Mears, CNN Supreme Court Producer" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Justices allow public prayers at New York town&amp;apost;s council meetings</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Two residents of Greece, New York, objected to invocations at town board meetings.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">Opening meetings with traditional prayer doesn&amp;apost;t violate First Amendment, high court says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="13">Dissent warns of &amp;quot;government-sponsored worship that divides&amp;quot; citizens &amp;quot;along religious lines&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="3">Ruling offers little on how other communities should offer civic prayers.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-31 12:45:58" annotation_time="295.09634">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="4">It was confined to the specific circumstances and offered few bright-line rules on how other communities should offer civic prayers without violating the Constitution.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">Two local women sued officials in Greece, New York, objecting to invocations at monthly public sessions on government property.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;The town of Greece does not violate the First Amendment by opening its meetings with prayer that comports with our tradition,&amp;quot; Justice Anthony Kennedy said, &amp;quot;and does not coerce participation by nonadherents.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="3">And that means that even in a partly legislative body, they should not confront government-sponsored worship that divides them along religious lines.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The Supreme Court gave limited approval on Monday to public prayers at a New York town&amp;apost;s board meetings, citing the country&amp;apost;s history of religious acknowledgment in the legislature.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The 5-4 ruling came in yet another contentious case over the intersection of faith and the civic arena.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>It was confined to the specific circumstances and offered few bright-line rules on how other communities should offer civic prayers without violating the Constitution.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Two local women sued officials in Greece, New York, objecting to invocations at monthly public sessions on government property.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The invocations, according to the plaintiffs, have been overwhelmingly Christian in nature over the years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;The town of Greece does not violate the First Amendment by opening its meetings with prayer that comports with our tradition,&amp;quot; Justice Anthony Kennedy said, &amp;quot;and does not coerce participation by nonadherents.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Just moments before the opinion was announced from the bench, the high court began its public session as it has for decades: with the marshal invoking a traditional statement that ends, &amp;quot;God save the United States and this honorable court.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The several hundred people in attendance, along with the justices, stood for the brief ceremony.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The conservative majority offered varying interpretations of when such &amp;quot;ceremonial&amp;quot; prayers would be permissible.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Kennedy, along with Chief Justice John Roberts and Justice Samuel Alito, focused on the specifics of the Greece case and did not offer a broad expansion of legislative prayer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Fellow conservative Justices Clarence Thomas and Antonin Scalia went further, suggesting that even any &amp;quot;subtle pressure&amp;quot; that local citizens might feel would not be enough to ban such prayers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>In dissent, Justice Elena Kagan said, &amp;quot;When the citizens of this country approach their government, they do so only as Americans, not as members of one faith or another.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>And that means that even in a partly legislative body, they should not confront government-sponsored worship that divides them along religious lines.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;apost;It&amp;apost;s just not appropriate&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The town of about 94,000 residents outside Rochester began allowing prayers to start its meetings in 1999, after years of having a &amp;quot;moment of silence.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Co-plaintiffs Linda Stephens and Susan Galloway challenged the revised policy, saying officials repeatedly ignored their requests to modify or eliminate the practice, or at least make it more inclusive.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s very divisive when you bring government into religion,&amp;quot; Stephens told CNN from her home.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;I don&amp;apost;t believe in God, and Susan is Jewish, so to hear these ministers talk about Jesus and even have some of them who personally question our motives, it&amp;apost;s just not appropriate.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The town government counters that after concerns from the two women and others, it sought diverse voices, including a Wiccan priestess, to offer invocations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Officials say they do not review the content of the remarks, nor censor any language.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;The faith of the prayer giver does not matter at all,&amp;quot; said John Auberger, Greece&amp;apost;s board supervisor, who began the practice shortly after taking office.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;We accept anyone who wants to come in and volunteer to give the prayer to open up our town meetings.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>A federal appeals court in New York found the board&amp;apost;s policy to be a violation of the Constitution&amp;apost;s Establishment Clause, which forbids any government &amp;quot;endorsement&amp;quot; of religion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Those judges said it had the effect of &amp;quot;affiliating the town with Christianity.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Congress and state legislatures regularly open their sessions with a prayer.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The question in part before the court is whether local government bodies are different, in that there might be more active involvement with local residents, who may want to personally petition the town in zoning, tax and other matters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Kagan suggested the court&amp;apost;s ruling could lead to sectarian prayers at such government venues as trials, polling places, and naturalization ceremonies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>But Alito expressed concern &amp;quot;some readers will take these hypotheticals as a warning that this is where today&amp;apost;s decision leads -- to a country in which religious minorities are denied the equal benefits of citizenship.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;Nothing could be further from the truth,&amp;quot; added Alito.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;All that the court does today is to allow a town to follow a practice that we have previously held is permissible for Congress and state legislatures.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Widely varying interpretations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Nearly 120 members of Congress, mostly Republicans, along with 18 state attorneys general, filed supporting legal briefs backing the city.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The Obama administration did the same.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The high court has generally taken a case-by-case approach on determining just when the state intrudes unconstitutionally into religion, while generally allowing faith to be acknowledged in a limited basis in a public forum.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;In God We Trust&amp;quot; remains on currency; the Pledge of Allegiance and oaths of office mention a creator; and menorah and crèche displays are permitted in local parks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>But the justices, in their widely varying interpretations of this case, acknowledged the tricky line they must walk -- politically, socially, legally-- when deciding Establishment Clause appeals.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>It was Kennedy&amp;apost;s views that ultimately controlled.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;By inviting ministers to serve as chaplain for the month, and welcoming them to the front of the room alongside civic leaders, the town is acknowledging the central place that religion, and religious institutions, hold in the lives of those present,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;Indeed, some congregations are not simply spiritual homes for town residents but also the provider of social services for citizens regardless of their beliefs.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The Alliance Defending Freedom, which represented the town in court, agreed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Supreme Court has again affirmed that Americans are free to pray,&amp;quot; said the group&amp;apost;s senior counsel David Cortman.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;In America, we tolerate a diversity of opinions and beliefs; we don&amp;apost;t silence people or try to separate what they say from what they believe.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>But the ACLU said it was disappointed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;Official religious favoritism should be off-limits under the Constitution,&amp;quot; said the group&amp;apost;s Daniel Mach.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>&amp;quot;Town-sponsored sectarian prayer violates the basic rule requiring the government to stay neutral on matters of faith.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>The case of Town of Greece, NY v. Galloway (12-696).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>