<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1142" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/07/24/politics/political-supportive-wives/index.html?hpt=us_c1" date_published="2013-07-24 19:46:15" category="politics" author="Dan Merica, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Weiner wouldn&amp;apost;t have been in race without wife by his side</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Huma Abedin&amp;apost;s blessing was critical to his mayoral campaign.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="15">Consultant says winning the trust of the person you harmed most is key to moving on.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="29">Women who are wronged by cheating spouse are often in no-win situation, psychologist says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-13 16:17:49" annotation_time="43.15">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">From the start of Weiner&amp;apost;s campaign, Huma Abedin&amp;apost;s blessing had been critical.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="2">Vorhaus said that winning the support of the person closest to you -- the person whose trust you damaged the most -- is the most important part of that formula.</sentence>
      <sentence id="29" ids_highlights="3">Women in Abedin&amp;apost;s position are in a no-win situation, said Dr. Jeff Gardere, a clinical psychologist.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington Without Huma Abedin publicly forgiving him, it is unlikely that Anthony Weiner would be running to become New York&amp;apost;s next mayor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;If his wife had not been by his side, Weiner&amp;apost;s hot dog would be cooked,&amp;quot; said Ana Navarro, a Republican political consultant and CNN contributor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>From the start of Weiner&amp;apost;s campaign, Huma Abedin&amp;apost;s blessing had been critical.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Once Weiner acknowledged a desire to run for mayor, a year after the former New York congressman resigned over a sexting scandal in 2011, Abedin blessed her husband&amp;apost;s political aspirations in a number of high profile interviews.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>And on Tuesday, after another round of sexting allegations emerged, Abedin once again stood beside him and publicly announced her forgiveness.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;It took a lot of work and a whole lot of therapy to get to a place where I could forgive Anthony,&amp;quot; Abedin said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;It was not an easy choice in any way, but I made the decision that it was worth staying in this marriage.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Political consultants, psychologists and crisis communicators all give different opinions on why Abedin, a powerful Washington adviser and close confidant to former Secretary of State Hillary Clinton, publicly forgave her husband.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>But by standing next to Weiner on Tuesday, Abedin joins a long line of political wives -- including Clinton, her mentor -- who stood next to their men as they answered questions about sexual impropriety.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Winning back trust -- from your wife.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Most experts said if Abedin hadn&amp;apost;t stood next to him, Weiner&amp;apost;s campaign for mayor could have been finished.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Instead the campaign is severely damaged, but not irreparably.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;From a communication standpoint, I or any other person in my field would say the same thing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Tell the truth, get your wife up there with you, get her support and win the election,&amp;quot; crisis communication expert Robbie Vorhaus said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Vorhaus said that winning the support of the person closest to you -- the person whose trust you damaged the most -- is the most important part of that formula.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;Once you have a wife, a spouse, standing up there and saying, &amp;apost;I forgive him,&amp;apost; what right do we have, theoretically, to hold it against him,&amp;quot; Vorhaus said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;The truth is the ultimate spin and if he comes out and says, &amp;apost;I made a mistake, I made my peace with my wife and she has forgiven me and now I want to be mayor of New York.&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>What do you, as a voter, say?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Does a wife&amp;apost;s blessing help make a political comeback?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;Yes, it is critical,&amp;quot; said Don Goldberg, a former adviser to President Bill Clinton and a partner at the Bluetext communications company.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>But that might be changing, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think we are in a real transition period here,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>As proof, Goldberg points to newly elected Republican U.S. Rep. Mark Sanford of South Carolina.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>After the then-governor admitted to sneaking away to Argentina to be with his mistress in June 2009, Jenny Sanford moved out of the governor&amp;apost;s mansion and later divorced him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>But Sanford, after offering a mea culpa to the people of South Carolina, triumphed in special election last month.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think the conventional wisdom that the wife has to be supportive and that they can&amp;apost;t be out there trashing you,&amp;quot; Goldberg said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;South Carolina may show that is changing, though.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Politics and publicity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Women in Abedin&amp;apost;s position are in a no-win situation, said Dr. Jeff Gardere, a clinical psychologist.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;If they don&amp;apost;t stand by that person, their family could be very much hurt by this,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>There are a number of reasons that women stay with an unfaithful man, Gardere said: Children, religious beliefs, a feeling that they can change.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>But when politics and publicity are involved, the situation is dramatically altered.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Hillary Clinton was with her husband in January 1998 when he denied having &amp;quot;sexual relations with that woman, Miss Lewinsky.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Though she notably distanced herself from him as they later walked to Marine One, the duo is still married today.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think the campaign is much more difficult when the person next to you walks away,&amp;quot; Gardere said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;The message is &amp;apost;I am through with this person, I think he is deeply flawed.&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>If you, the person who knows him best, walks away from him, it is harder for the public to believe in him.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>The enduring image of Tuesday&amp;apost;s news conference -- where a uncomfortable Abedin stood next to her husband -- sent mixed messages to voters and was a risky proposal, Navarro said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;Not having the wife next to you can be certainly, in the short term, a death knell,&amp;quot; Navarro said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;But having her out there is a risky proposal because for most people, certainly most women, it was painful to watch her public humiliation and the guy responsible standing right next to her, looking over her shoulder.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>I think every woman watching that puts herself in that position.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>But according Goldberg, sort of public awkwardness is better than the alternative.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think that having the wife somehow involved, to whatever degree is very important,&amp;quot; Goldberg said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;What is important is to be viewed as not totally accepting, because then it looks like the marriage is a joke.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>But you have to have enough sense of acknowledgment and contrition that is looks and sounds genuine.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>A mutually dependent relationship.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>The theory Darrell Hayes, a crisis communications professor at American University, thinks about most when he sees a news conference like Weiner&amp;apost;s is &amp;quot;co-dependency.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is the idea that people assume that it is better to fight through the relationship than break it off,&amp;quot; Hayes said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>&amp;quot;I get the sense that is the case with Anthony Weiner.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>The reason for co-dependency, Hayes speculates, is possibly political aspirations for the family, not just her husband.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>That opinion was echoed by a number of experts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="37">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>As for why Abedin stood next to Weiner, Goldberg said, &amp;quot;It is probably a combination of support, humility, embarrassment and ego.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="38">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>Navarro, who described Abedin as &amp;quot;a very strong, independent, successful&amp;quot; woman, said her standing beside Weiner on Tuesday opened the family up to a different line of questioning.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="39">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>&amp;quot;Why do people want this so bad that they are willing to subject themselves to this humiliation again?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
