<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="969" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/01/22/politics/five-things-south-carolina-primary/index.html" date_published="2012-01-22 08:52:41" category="politics" author="Peter Hamby, Paul Steinhauser and John Helton, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>5 things we learned from South Carolina primary</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="8">Endorsements didn&amp;apost;t match in South Carolina primary.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="27">65% of S.C. voters said prior debates were factor in their vote.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="33">Battle for GOP presidential nomination may last through Super Tuesday.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-11 10:22:31" annotation_time="38.307335" mapping_time_divergence="12.769112">
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="1">Though endorsements are great for generating media coverage and conveying a sense of credibility, they ultimately mattered little in the South Carolina race.</sentence>
      <sentence id="27" ids_highlights="2">According to exit polls of people who voted in the GOP presidential primary, 65% said the debates were important to their vote, with Gingrich winning those people by a more than 2-1 margin over Romney.</sentence>
      <sentence id="33" ids_highlights="3">Gingrich&amp;apost;s strong double-digit victory in South Carolina ensures that the battle for the GOP presidential nomination will at least go through Super Tuesday on March 6.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Newt Gingrich&amp;apost;s stunningly strong win in the South Carolina primary capped an incredible week in the Republican presidential nominating cycle., but what did we learn from it?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Endorsements matter little.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Two-thirds of Republicans who voted Saturday approved of South Carolina Gov. Nikki Haley&amp;apost;s job performance, exit polls showed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Haley endorsed former Massachusetts Gov. Mitt Romney in December and campaigned aggressively for him across the state down the final stretch.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>However, the general goodwill that Republicans have toward their governor made little impact on the race.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Voters who approved of Haley went for Gingrich.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Voters who disapproved of Haley went for Gingrich, too.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Though endorsements are great for generating media coverage and conveying a sense of credibility, they ultimately mattered little in the South Carolina race.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Gingrich proved it, handily winning the primary without many big names behind him, aside from state House Speaker Bobby Harrell who only backed Gingrich after the Republican he had previously supported, Texas Gov. Rick Perry, dropped out of the race.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Meanwhile, one-time candidates like Perry and Jon Huntsman stumped through South Carolina touting their endorsements from well-known state legislators and state Republican icons.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Neither man made it to Election Day.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Moderates love Mitt.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Romney didn&amp;apost;t win much on Saturday, but he did win moderates.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Exit polls showed that voters who identified themselves as &amp;quot;moderate or liberal&amp;quot; went for Romney.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;Conservative&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;very conservative&amp;quot; Republicans, meanwhile, voted for Gingrich.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The demographic groups that Romney did win, according to the exit polls, are not exactly the ground troops of the Republican base.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Voters opposed to the Tea Party movement?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Romney won &amp;apost;em.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Voters who have attained some level of postgraduate education?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Romney won &amp;apost;em.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Voters who think abortion should be legal?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Romney won &amp;apost;em.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Romney&amp;apost;s distant second-place finish Saturday raises questions about his ability to win over conservatives in the South -- the beating heart of the Republican Party -- if he eventually wins the GOP presidential nomination.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Did we say debates do matter?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The GOP presidential showdowns have been the storyline of the cycle, with the debates seemingly more influential than retail politics, early organization, campaign cash, and campaign advertising.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>It appears that strong performances by Gingrich in this past week&amp;apost;s two debates in the Palmetto State were crucial in helping the former House Speaker erase Romney&amp;apost;s lead in the public opinion polls and storm back to win the South Carolina primary.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>According to exit polls of people who voted in the GOP presidential primary, 65% said the debates were important to their vote, with Gingrich winning those people by a more than 2-1 margin over Romney.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Need more proof?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Fifty-five percent said they decided in the last few days and Gingrich won those voters by a 2-1 margin over Romney.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>With two debates next week in Florida ahead of the state&amp;apost;s January 31 primary, expect the debate storyline to continue.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Here we go again.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Maybe the marathon primary battle between Barack Obama and Hillary Clinton in 2008 wasn&amp;apost;t a fluke.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Gingrich&amp;apost;s strong double-digit victory in South Carolina ensures that the battle for the GOP presidential nomination will at least go through Super Tuesday on March 6.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>If Gingrich can survive Florida and the February contests (which right now favor Romney), Super Tuesday provides more friendly territory.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>If Rick Santorum runs out of steam over the next couple of weeks, Gingrich would become the final conservative alternative to Romney.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Rep. Ron Paul of Texas said Saturday despite a fourth-place finish in South Carolina, he has no intention of giving up, which means this GOP race could last into the spring.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Get ready for a nastier battle ahead.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>You think the South Carolina primary was rough, imagine what the next 10 days before the Florida primary will be like.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Romney signaled that he was throwing down the gloves in his &amp;quot;concession&amp;quot; speech Saturday night.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>After congratulating Gingrich on his win, Romney accused him of the same kind of class warfare that Republicans accuse Obama of -- Gingrich wielding the &amp;quot;weapons of the left&amp;quot; to bring him down.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;If Republican leaders want to join the president in demonizing success and disparaging conservative values then they&amp;apost;re not going to be fit to be our nominee.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>If you live in Florida and are turned off by negative ads, consider a 10-day vacation to a colder climate.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Romney&amp;apost;s campaign and the super PACs that support him have millions of dollars to saturate Florida airwaves with attack ads of the same ilk.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>After trying to appear as the presumptive nominee, Romney tried to reverse field and go on the attack against Gingrich to stop his momentum before Saturday, but probably too late.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>His Saturday night speech signals that he knows he&amp;apost;s in a fight.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
