<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1332" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/01/11/showbiz/montreux-founder-death/index.html" date_published="2013-01-11 12:53:52" category="showbiz" author="Peter Wilkinson, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Montreux jazz festival co-founder dies after ski accident</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Claude Nobs, the founder of the Montreux Jazz Festival, dies after skiing accident.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">Nobs, who had been in a coma after a fall, died in hospital in Lausanne - Swiss media.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">Nobs co-founded jazz festival in small Swiss town in 1967.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="16">Tributes pour in from Chic star Nile Rodgers, George Clinton and Queen guitarist Brian May.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 20:37:38" annotation_time="28.503">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Tributes are pouring in from the entertainment world for Claude Nobs, the founder of the Montreux Jazz Festival, who has died aged 76 following a skiing accident.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">Nobs, who had been in a coma since December 24 after a fall, died in hospital in Lausanne on Thursday, Swiss media reported.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">He co-founded the jazz festival in the small Swiss town in 1967 with then-president of Atlantic Records Nesuhi Erteguen.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="4">And Brian May, guitarist of rock band Queen, wrote on his Facebook page: &amp;quot;We mourn the sudden and tragic loss of Claude Nobs, the father of the Montreux Jazz Festival, and a long-standing dear friend.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Tributes are pouring in from the entertainment world for Claude Nobs, the founder of the Montreux Jazz Festival, who has died aged 76 following a skiing accident.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The death was announced on the official website of the jazz festival &amp;quot;a few days after your accident in Caux-sur-Montreux, in your beloved mountains, overlooking the lake that you were so fond of.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Nobs, who had been in a coma since December 24 after a fall, died in hospital in Lausanne on Thursday, Swiss media reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>He co-founded the jazz festival in the small Swiss town in 1967 with then-president of Atlantic Records Nesuhi Erteguen.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The festival was originally staged at the Montreux casino, but in 1971 a fire broke out while Frank Zappa was performing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Deep Purple immortalized the event the following year in their global hit &amp;quot;Smoke on the Water.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The song referred to Nobs, who saved many people in the blaze, as &amp;quot;Funky Claude.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Since then the Montreux Jazz Festival has attracted many music legends, including Miles Davis, Ray Charles, David Bowie and Prince.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Following news of his death, several stars took to Twitter to pay tribute.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>American musician Nile Rodgers, co-founder of 1970s funk band Chic, wrote: &amp;quot;Claude Nobs, CEO Montreux Jazz RIP - Proud to have been with you at your last Festival.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Forever, Nile &amp;amp; CHIC.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Fellow funk legend George Clinton added: &amp;quot;We are #thankfulfor friend Claude Nobs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Rest in Power.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>He made Montreux Jazz Festival festival amazing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>#PFUNK...&amp;quot;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>And Brian May, guitarist of rock band Queen, wrote on his Facebook page: &amp;quot;We mourn the sudden and tragic loss of Claude Nobs, the father of the Montreux Jazz Festival, and a long-standing dear friend.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>We salute his unparalleled contribution to Blues, Jazz and Rock culture in Europe, and will miss him greatly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Our deepest sympathies to his family and those near and dear to Claude.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The official festival website also added its condolences: &amp;quot;You always had a sparkle in your eyes whenever you dealt with people.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>For all of us, who were fortunate enough to cross your path, you will always remain the one who questioned certainties.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>And, why not ?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>You would repeatedly ask the same question when we tried to explain why a project would not be feasible.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Reality was never challenged only your wildest dreams.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The Montreux Jazz Festival is the ultimate proof of that!</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>But not the only one!</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;Your audacity resonates in each one of us, a strong sense of generosity and sharing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Thank you for taking us where we never thought we could go.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>And in your typical spirit, you left by surprise as if to remind us once more, that in life as in music, each great performance could be the last one even if the show must go on.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>You hoped for an exit that reflected your life, you succeeded this as well.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>We carry, and will continue to carry on in your spirit everything you taught us.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
