<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1167" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/02/28/showbiz/midnight-rider-production-halted/index.html" date_published="2014-02-28 19:33:01" category="showbiz" author="Ray Sanchez, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>&amp;apost;Midnight Rider&amp;apost; production halted after crew member death</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Sarah Elizabeth Jones, 27, was hit and killed by a train on set .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Her death rocked local film community, with many asking who was to blame .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="7">Preliminary NTSB report says train was traveling about 58 mph.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-21 14:13:42" annotation_time="42.473">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Production of musician Gregg Allman&amp;apost;s biopic &amp;quot;Midnight Rider&amp;quot; has been halted following the death of a 27-year-old camera assistant who was struck and killed by a freight train near Savannah, Georgia, according to Savannah&amp;apost;s film office.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">Last week&amp;apost;s death of Sarah Elizabeth Jones rocked the local film community, with many asking who was to blame.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="3">A preliminary report on the February 20 accident -- which also injured six crew members -- from the National Transportation Safety Board said the CSX Transportation train, with two locomotives and 37 cars, was traveling about 58 mph.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Production of musician Gregg Allman&amp;apost;s biopic &amp;quot;Midnight Rider&amp;quot; has been halted following the death of a 27-year-old camera assistant who was struck and killed by a freight train near Savannah, Georgia, according to Savannah&amp;apost;s film office.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Last week&amp;apost;s death of Sarah Elizabeth Jones rocked the local film community, with many asking who was to blame.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>A group of friends set up a Facebook page in tribute to Jones with a simple call to action: &amp;quot;Sarah Elizabeth Jones, friend and family to so many, made every day awesome.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Show your slate love here along with all the good stories of her life.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;The production of &amp;apost;Midnight Rider&amp;apost; has been halted in Savannah,&amp;quot; film office spokesperson William Hammargren told CNN Friday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;The production company withdrew all their existing permit requests and indicated they would not be requesting more at this time.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>A preliminary report on the February 20 accident -- which also injured six crew members -- from the National Transportation Safety Board said the CSX Transportation train, with two locomotives and 37 cars, was traveling about 58 mph.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The maximum authorized train speed at the railroad trestle where the accident occurred was 70 mph.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Jones and others were filming on train tracks at the time of the accident, according to a police report from the Wayne County Sheriff&amp;apost;s Office.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Film crew members from various countries have been sharing photo tributes, holding clapboards with messages of remembrance for Jones.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>There hundreds of images shared on the Facebook group Slates for Sarah, which was created on Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>As of Friday, more than 50,000 people had liked the page.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Friends and co-workers are asking the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences to add Jones&amp;apost; name to the In Memoriam list displayed during the Oscars this weekend.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>So far, there has been no comment from the Academy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Jones&amp;apost; primary job on set was to operate the slate at the beginning of each take.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Jones, an Atlanta resident and member of the International Cinematographers Guild, used her &amp;quot;spunk and determination&amp;quot; to climb up in the industry, according to her obituary.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Gregg Allman, the focus of the movie Jones was working on, shared his condolences.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am so terribly saddened by the news of the tragedy that took the young life of Sarah Elizabeth Jones on the film set,&amp;quot; he wrote on his website Saturday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;My thoughts and prayers go out to her family, friends and colleagues during this time of mourning.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Actors who worked on set with her, notably stars from &amp;quot;The Vampire Diaries,&amp;quot; as well as crew members from TV shows &amp;quot;Glee,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Scandal&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Downton Abbey,&amp;quot; are among the hundreds who have shared messages of &amp;quot;RIP Sarah Jones.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
