<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1352" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/05/03/showbiz/movies/avengers-review-charity/index.html" date_published="2012-05-03 12:22:30" category="showbiz" author="Tom Charity, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Review: &amp;apost;The Avengers&amp;apost; is a Friday Night SmackDown</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">&amp;quot;The Avengers&amp;quot; -- interspersing flip one-liners with a host of larger-than-life characters.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="15">Robert Downey Jr.&amp;apost;s Tony Stark gets a good measure of the movie&amp;apost;s best lines.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="18">Mark Ruffalo is more dangerous and more fun than either Edward Norton or Eric Bana.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-11 15:13:34" annotation_time="13.321334">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">Interspersing flip one-liners with a host of larger-than-life characters and the usual flurry of fight-and-flight scenes, the film is never less than amusing.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="2">Not surprisingly, Robert Downey Jr.&amp;apost;s flip, cynical Stark (Iron Man) gets a good measure of the movie&amp;apost;s best lines, bouncing off Steve Rogers&amp;apost; (Captain America) boy scout idealism and Thor&amp;apost;s guileless sledgehammer style (sometimes literally).</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="3">Mark Ruffalo is the third actor to play Bruce Banner/Hulk in the past decade, and even though the soft-spoken star would seem to have the longest fuse (when we first see him he&amp;apost;s tending to the sick in an Indian slum) he&amp;apost;s immediately both more dangerous and more fun than either Edward Norton or Eric Bana in the same role.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A celebration of specialness, Joss Whedon&amp;apost;s slick blockbuster &amp;quot;The Avengers&amp;quot; presents what may be the ultimate team: half a dozen Marvel Comics superheroes for the price of one.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>You don&amp;apost;t need me to tell you it&amp;apost;s the culmination of a five-year plan that began with Samuel L. Jackson&amp;apost;s Nick Fury taking Tony Stark aside at the end of the first &amp;quot;Iron Man&amp;quot; to tip him off as to the &amp;quot;Avengers Initative.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>There is a bigger picture, he told him -- and here it is: The be-all but not (they&amp;apost;re hoping) the end-all of the current craze for CGI-enhanced superheroics.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Interspersing flip one-liners with a host of larger-than-life characters and the usual flurry of fight-and-flight scenes, the film is never less than amusing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Still, it&amp;apost;s never more than amusing either.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Marvel Studios has made it a point of pride to diverge from the grim severity popularized in the DC / Warner Bros Batman films.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The lightness is fun but it doesn&amp;apost;t offer much of a foundation on which to build an epic.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>And let&amp;apost;s face it, there&amp;apost;s more than a whiff of opportunism about a project that pits a defrosted World War II hero, Captain America (Chris Evans), an inventor-industrialist, Iron Man (Robert Downey Jr.), the pagan lightning god, Thor (Chris Hemsworth), a scientist with anger-management issues, Hulk (Mark Ruffalo), and SHIELD agents Black Widow (Scarlett Johansson) and Hawkeye (Jeremy Renner) against the Norse god of mischief, Loki (Tom Hiddleston) and a legion of marauding aliens.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>In 3-D.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Still, Whedon (who shares a screenplay credit with Zak Penn) is a very sharp operator.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>He knows which buttons to press and where there&amp;apost;s room for a little diversion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The improbability of this misfit coalition becomes the movie&amp;apost;s most rewarding asset.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Imagine the bristling egos of so many power players cooped up in the same room!</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The movie delivers the kind of pleasures usually reserved for fan fiction or playground stand-offs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Not surprisingly, Robert Downey Jr.&amp;apost;s flip, cynical Stark (Iron Man) gets a good measure of the movie&amp;apost;s best lines, bouncing off Steve Rogers&amp;apost; (Captain America) boy scout idealism and Thor&amp;apost;s guileless sledgehammer style (sometimes literally).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Whedon also crafts a couple of choice scenes beautifully tailored for Scarlett Johansson&amp;apost;s Black Widow, a far more interesting character here than she appeared to be in &amp;quot;Iron Man 2.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>But no question, the movie&amp;apost;s not-so-secret weapon is Hulk.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Mark Ruffalo is the third actor to play Bruce Banner/Hulk in the past decade, and even though the soft-spoken star would seem to have the longest fuse (when we first see him he&amp;apost;s tending to the sick in an Indian slum) he&amp;apost;s immediately both more dangerous and more fun than either Edward Norton or Eric Bana in the same role.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Whedon gives him a long build up.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>For the first hour of the movie we&amp;apost;re invited to speculate along with his new allies just how much havoc Banner&amp;apost;s rampaging id might cause.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Then the leash comes off!</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Never underestimate the entertainment value of the Hulk Smash.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s probably the most important lesson to be drawn here, and one that clearly hasn&amp;apost;t been lost on the filmmakers, who have reportedly signed Ruffalo to a six-picture deal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Beyond that, the movie wants us to believe that these action figures have learned to play nice and work as a team -- which is good news for humanity, but maybe not so promising for the inevitable sequels.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>A climax on the war-torn streets of Manhattan could almost be an extended outtake from the last &amp;quot;Transformers&amp;quot; flick -- Whedon can only push the blockbuster form so far -- but if it&amp;apost;s a Friday Night SmackDown you&amp;apost;re after, &amp;quot;Avengers&amp;quot; gets the job done.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
