<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1214" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/01/14/showbiz/natalie-wood-coroner/index.html?iref=allsearch" date_published="2013-01-14 19:23:02" category="showbiz" author="Alan Duke and Tom Watkins, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Bruises cited in amending Natalie Wood&amp;apost;s death certificate</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7, 6">&amp;quot;Found floating in the ocean ... Circumstances not clearly established,&amp;quot; report says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">The case is &amp;quot;open and ongoing,&amp;quot; a sheriff&amp;apost;s spokesman says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">Wood&amp;apost;s widower, actor Robert Wagner, is not a suspect, spokesman Whitmore adds.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-31 13:49:07" annotation_time="29.612665">
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;How injury occurred will be listed as found floating in the ocean,&amp;quot; it adds.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;Circumstances not clearly established.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">The case is &amp;quot;open and ongoing; nothing definitive has closed it,&amp;quot; said Los Angeles County Sheriff&amp;apost;s Department spokesman Steve Whitmore.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">He said that Wood&amp;apost;s widower, actor Robert Wagner, is not a suspect.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Questions about bruises on the body of actress Natalie Wood, whose body was found floating off Catalina Island in 1981, led the Los Angeles County coroner&amp;apost;s office to change the cause of death from &amp;quot;accidental drowning&amp;quot; to &amp;quot;drowning and other undetermined factors.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;With the presence of fresh bruises in the upper extremities in the right forearm/left wrist area and a small scratch in the anterior neck, this examiner is unable to exclude non-accidental mechanism causing these injuries,&amp;quot; wrote Dr. Lakshmanan Sathyavagiswaran, the chief medical examiner.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;The location of the bruises, the multiplicity of the bruises, lack of head trauma, or facial bruising support bruising having occurred prior to entry in the water.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Since there are unanswered questions and limited additional evidence available for evaluation, it is opined by this medical examiner that the manner of death should be left as undetermined.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Based on a number of factors, including the lack of a life jacket, lack of a suicide note, &amp;quot;this Medical Examiner is unable to exclude non-volitional, unplanned entry into the water,&amp;quot; the report says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;How injury occurred will be listed as found floating in the ocean,&amp;quot; it adds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;Circumstances not clearly established.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The change in the cause of death was made public last year, but the report outlining the reasons -- which was dated June 15, 2012 -- was not made public until Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The case is &amp;quot;open and ongoing; nothing definitive has closed it,&amp;quot; said Los Angeles County Sheriff&amp;apost;s Department spokesman Steve Whitmore.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>He said that Wood&amp;apost;s widower, actor Robert Wagner, is not a suspect.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>A security hold was placed on the report when it came out because of concern &amp;quot;that the frenzy that&amp;apost;s surrounding this could contaminate the investigation,&amp;quot; Whitmore said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The hold was lifted last week and the report made public Monday after next of kin were notified.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Homicide investigators decided to take a new look at one of Hollywood&amp;apost;s most enduring mysteries in November 2011 after they were contacted by people who said they had additional information about the actress&amp;apost;s death, the sheriff&amp;apost;s department said last summer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The announcement persuaded tipsters to come forward with additional &amp;quot;intriguing&amp;quot; information, sheriff&amp;apost;s spokesman Whitmore told CNN last January.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Investigators did not comment directly on statements made in news reports in November by Dennis Davern, the captain of a yacht owned by Wood and her husband.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Davern offered a previously unreported account of how Wood&amp;apost;s death was reported, saying that Wagner waited hours to call the Coast Guard after Wood went missing off Catalina Island following an argument between the couple.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Wood died on November 29, 1981, off the isthmus of Catalina Island.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Dressed in a flannel nightgown, socks and a down jacket, her body was found floating about a mile from the yacht, according to police reports.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The autopsy report showed the 43-year-old actress had two dozen bruises on her body, including a facial abrasion on her left cheek and bruises on her arms.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;My sister was not a swimmer and did not know how to swim, and she would never go to another boat or to shore dressed in a nightgown and socks,&amp;quot; said Lana Wood, referring to theories that the actress may have voluntarily jumped from the boat, last year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Although the county coroner&amp;apost;s office ruled at the time that Wood&amp;apost;s death was an accident, others said then that that made no sense.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>In 2010, Lana Wood told CNN she believed an argument between her sister and Wagner on the yacht&amp;apost;s back deck preceded Wood&amp;apost;s drowning.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>She told CNN in 2011 that she did not suspect foul play.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;I just want the truth to come out, the real story,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Davern, the former captain of the yacht Splendour, broke his silence with an account of that day in &amp;quot;Goodbye Natalie, Goodbye Splendour,&amp;quot; a book he co-wrote that was published in 2009.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Davern has said he believes Wood&amp;apost;s death was a direct result of a fight with Wagner.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>In an interview with CNN in 2010, Davern said he believed the investigation was incompetent and suggested there was a cover-up.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>He said he regretted misleading investigators by keeping quiet at Wagner&amp;apost;s request.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Wood and Wagner married in 1957, divorced in 1962, then remarried in 1972.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>They invited Wood&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;Brainstorm&amp;quot; co-star, Christopher Walken, to join them on the Thanksgiving weekend sail that preceded her death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The Hollywood rumor mill was abuzz with speculation that Wagner was jealous of Walken, but authorities have said Walken witnessed only the events leading up to an argument between the couple.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>In his book.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;Pieces of My Heart,&amp;quot; also published in September 2009, Wagner acknowledged being jealous and having fought with Wood.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>After Wagner then argued with Walken and broke a wine bottle, Wood left in disgust and went to her stateroom, Davern told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Walken also retired to a guest room, Davern added, and Wagner followed his wife to their room.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>A few minutes later, Davern said, he could hear the couple fighting.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Embarrassed, Davern said, he turned up the volume on his stereo.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>At one point, Davern recalled, he glanced out of the pilot house window and saw Wagner and Wood on the yacht&amp;apost;s aft deck.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;They&amp;apost;d moved their fight outside ... you could tell from their animated gestures they were still arguing,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>A short time later, Wagner, appearing to be distraught, told Davern he couldn&amp;apost;t find Wood.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Davern searched the boat but couldn&amp;apost;t find her.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>He noticed the rubber dinghy also was missing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Wagner shrugged and poured them both drinks, Davern said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>He suggested his wife had probably gone off in a temper.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Wagner&amp;apost;s story, as told in his book, differs from Davern&amp;apost;s.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>He maintains that after the argument with Walken, Wood went to her room and prepared for bed while he and Walken sat on the deck, cooling off.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Wagner writes that he went to check on Wood, but she wasn&amp;apost;t there.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>He maintains that he and Davern searched the boat and noticed the dinghy was missing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Wagner assumed his wife had gone ashore on her own, he wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>He radioed the restaurant on shore where they&amp;apost;d had dinner and called the harbor master to see if anyone had seen Wood.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>The dinghy was found about a mile from the yacht, and a mile from where Wood&amp;apost;s body was found.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Wood&amp;apost;s first starring role was as a child in &amp;quot;Miracle on 34th Street&amp;quot; in 1947, and she played alongside some of Hollywood&amp;apost;s top leading men -- James Dean in &amp;quot;Rebel Without a Cause&amp;quot; and Warren Beatty in &amp;quot;Splendor in the Grass.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>She was nominated for Oscars in both of those films, as well as for &amp;quot;Love with the Proper Stranger&amp;quot; (1963), according to IMDb.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>One of her more memorable roles was as Maria in &amp;quot;West Side Story.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>Wagner landed roles in dozens of films in the 1950s and &amp;apost;60s before he hit it big in television.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>He starred in two series, &amp;quot;It Takes a Thief&amp;quot; (1968-70) and &amp;quot;Hart to Hart&amp;quot; (1979-84), and more recently as Number Two in the &amp;quot;Austin Powers&amp;quot; spy spoofs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
