<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1201" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/08/28/showbiz/celebrity-news-gossip/brad-pitt-angelina-jolie-married/index.html?iref=allsearch" date_published="2014-08-28 13:38:29" category="showbiz" author="Lisa Respers France, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Angelina Jolie and Brad Pitt married</title>
  <keywords>Brad Pitt,Angelina Jolie,celeb marriages,Jennifer Aniston,celeb news,France</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">The couple married in France over the weekend.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">They are the parents of six children.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">Pitt and Jolie have been together for almost a decade.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-09 09:49:41" annotation_time="14.302">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Brad Pitt and Angelina Jolie married over the weekend in France, a representative for Jolie confirmed Thursday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2, 3">The couple, who are the parents of six children, have been together for almost a decade.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Brad Pitt and Angelina Jolie married over the weekend in France, a representative for Jolie confirmed Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The couple, who are the parents of six children, have been together for almost a decade.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>They got married Saturday in a small, private ceremony in a chapel at Château Miraval in the village of Correns.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Pitt and Jolie have been the source of speculation about their relationship almost since the beginning.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Tongues first started wagging after the pair met on the set of &amp;quot;Mr. &amp;amp; Mrs. Smith&amp;quot; in the summer of 2004, when Pitt was still married to actress Jennifer Aniston.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>In January 2005, Pitt and Aniston announced that they were splitting.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Aniston filed for divorce in March 2005.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The following month, photos surfaced of Pitt, Jolie and her adopted son Maddox together in Kenya.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Jolie later adopted daughter Zahara from an orphanage in Ethiopia and in early 2006 she announced that she and Pitt were expecting a baby.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Shortly thereafter, Pitt was granted the right to legally adopt Maddox and Zahara.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Their daughter Shiloh was born in May 2006 and son Pax was adopted from an orphanage in Vietnam in March 2007.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Jolie gave birth to twins Vivienne and Knox in July 2008.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The couple announced their engagement in 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Pitt and Jolie recently told People that the wedding would be a family affair.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are discussing it with the children and how they imagine it might be,&amp;quot; Jolie said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;Which is verging on hysterical, how kids envision a wedding...They will, in a way, be the wedding planner.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s going to be Disney or paintball -- one or the other!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>According to a statement from the family &amp;quot;Angelina was walked down the aisle by her eldest sons Maddox and Pax.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Zahara and Vivienne threw petals, gathered from the garden.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Shiloh and Knox were the ring bearers.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;In the days before coming to France, and as citizens of California, Brad and Angelina filled out their paperwork and obtained a marriage licence from a local judge, who also travelled to France to conduct the ceremony at Chateau Miraval,&amp;quot; the statement said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;They are therefore married under Californian law.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The uniting of Pitt and Jolie in matrimony has been one of the most anticipated marriages in Hollywood.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In 2006 Pitt told Esquire magazine that he and Jolie would not marry until &amp;quot;everyone else in the country who wants to be married is legally able.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>He reaffirmed their commitment to marriage equality in a 2011 interview with People.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;Thanks to the tireless work of so many, someday soon this discrimination will end and every American will be able to enjoy their equal right to marriage,&amp;quot; Pitt said in a statement to the magazine following the legalization of same-sex marriage in New York State.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>