<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1230" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/02/28/showbiz/philip-seymour-hoffman-autopsy/index.html" date_published="2014-02-28 20:57:17" category="showbiz" author="Ray Sanchez, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Coroner: Philip Seymour Hoffman died of acute mixed drug intoxication</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Academy Award-winning actor was found dead February 2 with a needle in his arm .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Coroner says he died of acute mixed drug intoxication.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">Dr. Sanjay Gupta says chronic drug users may not necessarily feel effects of drugs .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-02 11:14:40" annotation_time="44.87833">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1, 2">New York Actor Philip Seymour Hoffman, who was found dead February 2 on the bathroom floor of his New York apartment with a syringe in his left arm, died of acute mixed drug intoxication, including heroin, cocaine, benzodiazepines and amphetamine, the New York medical examiner&amp;apost;s office said Friday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">Dr. Sanjay Gupta, CNN&amp;apost;s chief medical correspondent, said that as addicts take mixtures of drugs more chronically, they may not necessarily feel the effects of the narcotics, which still suppress the respiratory system.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>New York Actor Philip Seymour Hoffman, who was found dead February 2 on the bathroom floor of his New York apartment with a syringe in his left arm, died of acute mixed drug intoxication, including heroin, cocaine, benzodiazepines and amphetamine, the New York medical examiner&amp;apost;s office said Friday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The manner of death was ruled an accident, the medical examiner&amp;apost;s office said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Dr. Sanjay Gupta, CNN&amp;apost;s chief medical correspondent, said that as addicts take mixtures of drugs more chronically, they may not necessarily feel the effects of the narcotics, which still suppress the respiratory system.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;They&amp;apost;re not feeling it, but it&amp;apost;s still having an impact on their ability to breathe, and that&amp;apost;s the real problem,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s called stacking.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>You can stack the same drug too close together, or you can start to stack other drugs, one on top of the other.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s how people get into trouble.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>They do call it accidental death as well.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Police found nearly 50 envelopes branded &amp;quot;Ace of Spades&amp;quot; filled with what they believe was heroin in the actor&amp;apost;s Manhattan apartment, two law enforcement sources familiar with the inquiry said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Used syringes, prescription drugs and empty bags that authorities suspect were used to hold heroin also were found in the apartment where Hoffman, 46, was found dead, sources said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>He was expected to pick up his children that day but didn&amp;apost;t show up, the official said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Playwright David Katz and another person went to the apartment and found him dead, the official said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Police officers found him in a T-shirt and shorts with his eyeglasses still on his head.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Robert Vineberg, a 57-year-old musician, was arrested in connection with Hoffman&amp;apost;s death and released on bail earlier this month.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Vineberg was among four people arrested in Manhattan in the days after Hoffman&amp;apost;s death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Prosecutors said Vineberg, who was arrested on a felony charge of criminal possession of a controlled substance, had just under 50 small bags of heroin as well as packaging paraphernalia in his apartment during a raid.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>In another one of his apartments in the same Mott Street building, prosecutors said, 250 small bags of heroin were found.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Vineberg was found to have the actor&amp;apost;s phone number stored in his cell phone, a law enforcement official told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Two other people arrested in connection with Hoffman&amp;apost;s death -- Juliana Luchkiw and Max Rosenblum, both 22 -- were released earlier this month until their next court dates.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Prosecutors did not file charges against a fourth person arrested in the raid.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Hoffman was mourned in New York February 7 in a star-studded private funeral attended by family and close friends.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Hoffman, who was nominated for Academy Awards four times, won the Oscar for best actor in 2006 for his portrayal of writer Truman Capote in &amp;quot;Capote.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>He earned Academy Award nominations for roles in &amp;quot;Charlie Wilson&amp;apost;s War,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Doubt,&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;The Master.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
