<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1159" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/05/16/showbiz/movies/godzilla-reviews-roundup/index.html" date_published="2014-05-16 19:43:17" category="showbiz" author="Lisa Respers France, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>&amp;apost;Godzilla&amp;apost;: What&amp;apost;s the verdict?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">Some complain that &amp;quot;Godzilla&amp;quot; is disjointed.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12">One critic complains that the script forces the actors to &amp;quot;over-emote&amp;quot; .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="20">Another calls it &amp;quot;a summer blockbuster that actually leaves you wanting more&amp;quot;.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-09 14:11:00" annotation_time="78.784">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">Chris Nashawaty of Entertainment Weekly found that mix of stories to be disjointed, saying the film &amp;quot;feels like two movies Scotch-taped together.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;The actors are top-tier, but they over-emote to sell a human drama that never rises above soap opera.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;The result may not be the monster movie some audiences are expecting, but it&amp;apost;s something better: a summer blockbuster that actually leaves you wanting more.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s expected to be a monster of a movie this weekend, but what&amp;apost;s the buzz on &amp;quot;Godzilla&amp;quot;?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Director Gareth Edwards&amp;apost; film, starring Bryan Cranston, Aaron Taylor-Johnson and Ken Watanabe, has been eagerly anticipated by fans (some of whom still haven&amp;apost;t gotten over the 1998 version with Matthew Broderick), and critics are sounding off.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The new &amp;quot;Godzilla&amp;quot; focuses on an engineer (Cranston) determined to solve a yearslong mystery and his frustrated son (Taylor-Johnson), who just wants his dad to let it go.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>And of course, there are monsters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Chris Nashawaty of Entertainment Weekly found that mix of stories to be disjointed, saying the film &amp;quot;feels like two movies Scotch-taped together.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;In one, Bryan Cranston plays a nuclear engineer with a tragic past who&amp;apost;s racing to expose the truth about a series of seismic anomalies, Aaron Taylor-Johnson is his estranged soldier son, and Ken Watanabe and Sally Hawkins are a pair of exposition-spouting scientists trying to keep straight faces while talking about electromagnetic pulses and mankind&amp;apost;s hubris,&amp;quot; he wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;In the other, mammoth CG beasts knock the snot out of one another.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Only one of these movies is any good.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Thankfully, it&amp;apost;s the monster one.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Peter Travers of Rolling Stone seemed to agree.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;It would take an insomniac to wade through all these plot complications without dozing,&amp;quot; Travers wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;The actors are top-tier, but they over-emote to sell a human drama that never rises above soap opera.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Cranston deserves better than a script that confuses hysterics with breaking bad.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The New York Daily News&amp;apost; Joe Neumaier said that &amp;quot;60 years after he first stomped on Tokyo, the big green lizard has been given fresh scales for the rebooted &amp;apost;Godzilla.&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Yet despite a few fiery breaths, there&amp;apost;s mostly hot air from a lot of serious actors slumming it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Drew McWeeny of HitFix found much to praise in the scenes featuring the monster.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;For better or for worse, depending on how you like the end result, Edwards has made a film that stands apart from how pretty much anyone else would have handled this, and I like that he remembered how important &amp;apost;awe&amp;apost; is to something that hopes to be &amp;apost;awesome,&amp;apost; &amp;quot; McWeeny wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The Verge&amp;apost;s Bryan Bishop said that Edwards delivers as a director.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;Rather than reaching for the low-hanging fruit of wall-to-wall action, Edwards conjures up a mix of slowly escalating tension and visual-effects wizardry,&amp;quot; he wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;The result may not be the monster movie some audiences are expecting, but it&amp;apost;s something better: a summer blockbuster that actually leaves you wanting more.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Speaking of wizardry, here are some fun facts about &amp;quot;Godzilla&amp;quot;: The sound design team of Erik Aadahl and Ethan Van der Ryn used a Rolling Stones tour rig with a 100,000-watt speaker about the size of a city block that they then pumped the monster&amp;apost;s sounds through so they could capture recordings in cars, rooftops and other places to get the most realistic echo possible.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>But what you think you are hearing with that Godzilla roar may be deceiving.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The roar is actually octaves beyond the human range of hearing, so the design duo used special Japanese microphones to slow the sound so it falls within audience&amp;apost;s hearing range.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
