<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1368" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/07/20/showbiz/movies/dark-knight-shooting-film/index.html" date_published="2012-07-20 18:12:54" category="showbiz" author="Lisa Respers France, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Shootings cast pall over &amp;apost;Dark Knight Rises&amp;apost; blockbuster weekend</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">&amp;quot;The Dark Knight Rises&amp;quot; was one of the most eagerly awaited summer blockbusters.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">Experts say it&amp;apost;s too soon to tell if Friday&amp;apost;s attack will keep fans away.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="16">Studio pulls trailer showing men attacking movie theater with machine guns.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-13 16:47:08" annotation_time="68.2415">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">The early Friday release of &amp;quot;The Dark Knight Rises&amp;quot; was one of the most eagerly anticipated movie events of the summer.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">Experts said it&amp;apost;s difficult to determine what, if any, effect the tragedy may have on either ticket sales or fan turnout in the days and weeks to come.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="3">That film trailer features scenes of men armed with machine guns attacking a movie theater.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The early Friday release of &amp;quot;The Dark Knight Rises&amp;quot; was one of the most eagerly anticipated movie events of the summer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>On Thursday, movie ticket seller Fandango reported that the last installment in the Christopher Nolan-directed Batman trilogy was &amp;quot;outpacing summer blockbuster &amp;apost;The Avengers&amp;apost; in ticket sales at the same point in the sales cycle.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;The final chapter of Christopher Nolan&amp;apost;s Batman trilogy has sold out on Fandango more than 2,000 showtimes nationwide and it&amp;apost;s currently on track to become one of Fandango&amp;apost;s top-selling movies of all time,&amp;quot; the ticket seller reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>An attack by an armed gunman in Aurora, Colorado, at a midnight screening of &amp;quot;The Dark Knight Rises&amp;quot; was met with shock and grief throughout the country, and cast a shadow over what for fans was set to be a blockbuster weekend.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Experts said it&amp;apost;s difficult to determine what, if any, effect the tragedy may have on either ticket sales or fan turnout in the days and weeks to come.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;For somebody to go into a movie theater, a place of fun and escapism, and bring that kind of violence into that world is shocking and tragic,&amp;quot; said Paul Dergarabedian, president of the box office division of Hollywood.com.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;How this will affect the movie, I just don&amp;apost;t know.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>According to Exhibitor Relations, the film did brisk business for its midnight screenings, raking in $30.6 million.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Many fans had pre-purchased tickets for screenings across the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Dergarabedian said the current focus has been rightfully on those injured and killed because of the violence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Beyond that it is up to Warner Bros., the studio that released the film, to decide how to proceed with marketing in the wake of the tragedy, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Warner Bros., which is owned by the parent company of CNN, has been heavily marketing the action film that includes scenes featuring lots of gunplay and violence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>A full-page newspaper ad heralding the opening weekend contains a pull quote from Marlow Stern, assistant culture editor of Newsweek, which says, &amp;quot;A monumental conclusion to the epic trilogy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Audiences will be blown away.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Warner Bros. pulled the trailer for the film &amp;quot;Gangster Squad,&amp;quot; which had been running before showings of &amp;quot;The Dark Knight Rises.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>That film trailer features scenes of men armed with machine guns attacking a movie theater.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>A representative for the company told CNN that Warner Bros. did not plan to cancel any screenings.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Thelma Adams, contributing editor for Yahoo Movies, said the tragedy poses a conundrum for the studio.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;I know people at Warner Bros. who were called and woken up this morning who now have a huge problem on their hands,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think in the long run, a lot of the money is made globally with a movie like this and that will not have an impact.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Adams continued, &amp;quot;Also it&amp;apost;s not just an opening weekend movie.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>There (are) no other movies kind of in competition this weekend as a lot of other movies stepped off this weekend and next weekend.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Yes, there will be some impact of the revenue stream, but it&amp;apost;s not going to really hurt.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Warner Bros. canceled the film&amp;apost;s planned premiere in Paris on Friday and released the following statement: &amp;quot;Warner Bros. and the filmmakers are deeply saddened to learn about this shocking incident.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>We extend our sincere sympathies to the families and loved ones of the victims at this tragic time.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>An official with Paris police told CNN there was a police presence outside the Bristol Hotel, where cast members of &amp;quot;The Dark Knight Rises&amp;quot; were staying before the premiere, to &amp;quot;protect all those who could be threatened.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Actor Gary Oldman, who portrays Commissioner Jim Gordon in the film, said in a statement, &amp;quot;My prayers and deepest sympathies are with the victims and their families of this horrific act.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Scott Beggs, managing editor of the website Film School Rejects, said the film franchise has been popular because &amp;quot;at the heart of (the film) is a central heroic figure that gives hope to people.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Beggs pointed out that the death of actor Heath Ledger from a toxic combination of prescription drugs in 2008 cast a bit of a pall over &amp;quot;The Dark Knight,&amp;quot; but did not taint the legacy of what went on to become a critically acclaimed film.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Ledger was posthumously awarded an Academy Award for best supporting actor for his role as The Joker in that movie.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;(That second film) was touched by tragedy, but I believe the art ended up speaking for itself,&amp;quot; Beggs said. &amp;quot;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>(The shootings in Colorado) were a tragic event that took place, which hopefully will not stop us from living our lives.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Are you there?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Share your story on CNN iReport and post tributes to the victims.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
