<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1218" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/06/06/showbiz/casey-kasem-family-dispute/index.html" date_published="2014-06-07 03:51:14" category="showbiz" author="Jane Caffrey, CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Casey Kasem&amp;apost;s children hope family will put differences aside</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">The ailing 82-year-old is in critical condition .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Kasem &amp;quot;won&amp;apost;t be with us much longer,&amp;quot; rep says .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="22, 21">&amp;quot;My dad taught us that family comes first. We want to honor him,&amp;quot; daughter says .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 16:59:47" annotation_time="17.018667" mapping_time_divergence="5.672889">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">Kasem &amp;quot;won&amp;apost;t be with us much longer,&amp;quot; said Danny Deraney, the rep for the &amp;quot;American Top 40&amp;quot; host&amp;apost;s daughter, Kerri Kasem.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">His family is gathering at St. Anthony Hospital in Washington, where the ailing 82-year-old was in critical condition as of Thursday, according to the hospital.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;My dad taught us that family comes first.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="3">We want to honor him and make sure all of his family, including Jean and Liberty, are surrounding him with love at this critical time,&amp;quot; she said in a statement.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>As the battle surrounding Casey Kasem brought his relatives into the courtroom again Friday, the iconic radio host&amp;apost;s health is declining, and his family is preparing to say goodbye.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Kasem &amp;quot;won&amp;apost;t be with us much longer,&amp;quot; said Danny Deraney, the rep for the &amp;quot;American Top 40&amp;quot; host&amp;apost;s daughter, Kerri Kasem.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>His family is gathering at St. Anthony Hospital in Washington, where the ailing 82-year-old was in critical condition as of Thursday, according to the hospital.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>His son, Mike Kasem, traveled from Singapore to be with his father, and Kasem&amp;apost;s brother flew in from Detroit.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Kasem suffers from Lewy body dementia, which has no cure.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Kasem&amp;apost;s children from his first marriage hope the family will look past their dispute during his last moments.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>They want him to be surrounded by loved ones, including their stepmother and half-sister, Jean and Liberty Kasem.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;If he opens his eyes, I want my dad just once to see everyone standing around him, putting our differences aside and let him know how much he is loved by everyone, including Jean and Liberty,&amp;quot; Kerri Kasem said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Deraney said the Kitsap County Superior Court recognized a previous California court order that gave Kerri Kasem full health conservatorship over her father.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>During the hearing Friday, the court also found Casey Kasem&amp;apost;s wife, Jean Kasem, in contempt, but did not penalize her with a fine, Deraney said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>He added that Jean Kasem was granted a private family moment for more than two hours with her husband of 34-years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Attorneys for Jean Kasem said the judge&amp;apost;s findings and order will be prepared and circulated for signature next week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Jean Kasem presented her side of the story in a declaration filed at the Kitsap County Superior Court on Wednesday, which was obtained by CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>It includes documentation that the Kitsap County Sheriff&amp;apost;s Office had no concern for her husband&amp;apost;s well-being in her care, and supporting declarations from the family friends the Kasems were visiting in Washington.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The declaration also claims that Kerri Kasem owes $1.3 million to Casey and Jean Kasem after accepting various financial gifts from her father since she turned 18.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Jean Kasem further alleges that Kerri Kasem is a Scientologist, citing an unverified celebrity website, and includes an article about the FBI investigating the Church of Scientology for human trafficking.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Deraney denies that Kerri Kasem has ever been a Scientologist, adding, &amp;quot;She loves studying religions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Jean picked out the most controversial one to distract from what&amp;apost;s really going on.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>In light of the ongoing family feud, a court order signed by a Kitsap County judge on Thursday dictated that visits to Casey Kasem would be equally shared by both sides of the family, and that during his final hours everyone would be permitted to visit him at the same time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Kasem&amp;apost;s daughter, Julie Kasem, also said she hoped for peace during her father&amp;apost;s final moments.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;My dad taught us that family comes first.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>We want to honor him and make sure all of his family, including Jean and Liberty, are surrounding him with love at this critical time,&amp;quot; she said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
