<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1226" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/12/16/showbiz/chris-brown-probaton-revoked/index.html?iref=allsearch" date_published="2013-12-17 00:35:33" category="showbiz" author="Alan Duke, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Chris Brown&amp;apost;s probation yanked over D.C. fight; jail may follow rehab</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Chris Brown returns for a hearing in February to decide if he&amp;apost;ll serve jail time after rehab.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">The singer has an anger-management problem, according to a probation report .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">Brown is serving 90 days in court-ordered rehab.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="4">He&amp;apost;s on felony probation for beating singer Rihanna in 2009.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-06 18:41:53" annotation_time="90.338">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1, 3">Brown, who appeared before a Los Angeles County Superior Court judge Monday, must return for a hearing on February 10 that will decide if he&amp;apost;ll serve jail time after his three months in rehab.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">The singer has an anger-management problem and drug-abuse issues, according to a probation report obtained by CNN.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="4">He&amp;apost;s been on felony probation since pleading guilty to beating up singer Rihanna on the eve of the Grammys in 2009.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Los Angeles A judge revoked Chris Brown&amp;apost;s probation because of his October arrest in Washington, but the singer&amp;apost;s not going to jail because he&amp;apost;s already in a court-ordered residential rehab program.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Brown, who appeared before a Los Angeles County Superior Court judge Monday, must return for a hearing on February 10 that will decide if he&amp;apost;ll serve jail time after his three months in rehab.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The singer has an anger-management problem and drug-abuse issues, according to a probation report obtained by CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s been on felony probation since pleading guilty to beating up singer Rihanna on the eve of the Grammys in 2009.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Judge James Brandlin ordered Brown to check into a rehab program a month ago after he had been booted from another rehab facility a week earlier for smashing his mother&amp;apost;s car window during a family session.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>A report submitted to the judge by Brown&amp;apost;s probation officer included a letter from his current rehab facility saying he &amp;quot;has made significant progress&amp;quot; since starting in the program on November 20.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;The clinical and medical team have witnessed very positive change in Mr. Brown since his psychotropic medications have been changed and he has been taken off medical marijuana,&amp;quot; the program director said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;His ability to emotionally regulate himself has improved markedly.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m pleased that he&amp;apost;s doing well,&amp;quot; Brandlin said Monday, explaining why he did not send him to jail Monday afternoon.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Brown was arrested on an assault charge in Washington on October 27.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>That case is why Brandlin ruled Monday that he was tentatively revoking Brown&amp;apost;s probation for the Rihanna assault.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>He will decide in February if he will order Brown to complete his sentence in prison instead of probation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Brown&amp;apost;s girlfriend Karrueche Tran accompanied him to the Los Angeles County courtroom Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>For the second time, his mother was not with him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Brown&amp;apost;s freedom has been in question since he was arrested on a sidewalk near the White House after allegedly punching a man.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The probation imposed when he pleaded guilty to a felony charge in the attack on Rihanna -- his girlfriend at the time -- requires that he stay out of legal trouble.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Brown voluntarily entered a rehab center on October 28, a day after he was released from a Washington jail.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The probation report given to the judge last month revealed that he was kicked out of the program.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>It quoted a center official saying he was ordered out for &amp;quot;breaking program rules by acting violently.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The violence involved Brown &amp;quot;throwing a rock through his mother&amp;apost;s car window&amp;quot; after a family session at the center in which she said she wanted him to stay in treatment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;Mr. Brown preceded to walk outside and pick up a rock and threw it through his mother&amp;apost;s car window and it shattered,&amp;quot; according to letter from the rehab center included in the probation report.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Brown&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;prognosis is very guarded&amp;quot; unless he gets professional help, the letter said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Brown leaves the new rehab center three days a week to work eight-hour shifts of community labor so that he can complete the 1,000 hours of work still remaining in his punishment for attacking Rihanna.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The report estimated he will have to work on community labor three days of every week until next August to meet the deadline for completing the labor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>He may also travel to Washington for a court hearing on January 8 in the assault case there, the judge said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
