<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1298" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/03/19/showbiz/justin-bieber-vandalism-case/index.html" date_published="2014-03-19 17:03:06" category="showbiz" author="Alan Duke, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Justin Bieber egging &amp;apost;a silly prank,&amp;apost; not a felony, lawyers argue</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Prosecutors must decide if egging is prosecuted as a felony or a misdemeanor.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">Bieber attorneys met with prosecutors Tuesday to argue egging was &amp;quot;a silly prank&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">L.A. County Sheriff&amp;apost;s detectives are pushing for a felony charge .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="7">Bieber sold his Calabasas home to Khloe Kardashian and has moved out.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-02 13:03:47" annotation_time="51.095997">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">The potential vandalism charge is what lawyers called a &amp;quot;wobbler,&amp;quot; meaning the district attorney must decide if it will be prosecuted as a felony -- which has much more serious consequences -- or as a misdemeanor.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">Bieber attorneys Howard Weitzman and Shawn Holley met with prosecutors Tuesday to argue that since the egging was &amp;quot;a silly prank&amp;quot; and Bieber has no criminal record, it should be treated as a misdemeanor, two sources said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">Los Angeles County Sheriff&amp;apost;s Department detectives are pushing for a felony charge, based on the estimated $20,000 in damage caused by the eggs to the mansion next door.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="4">Bieber, 20, sold his Calabasas, California, mansion to Khloe Kardashian earlier this month and has already moved his skateboard ramp, video games and fast cars from the home where he&amp;apost;s lived for the past two years, a source close to him confirmed.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Los Angeles Justin Bieber&amp;apost;s lawyers are trying to persuade Los Angeles County prosecutors not to charge the singer with a felony in the alleged egg attack on a neighbor, sources close to the case told CNN Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The potential vandalism charge is what lawyers called a &amp;quot;wobbler,&amp;quot; meaning the district attorney must decide if it will be prosecuted as a felony -- which has much more serious consequences -- or as a misdemeanor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Several sources close to the investigation tell CNN there is little doubt Bieber will be charged with vandalism for the January incident and a decision should be announced soon.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Bieber attorneys Howard Weitzman and Shawn Holley met with prosecutors Tuesday to argue that since the egging was &amp;quot;a silly prank&amp;quot; and Bieber has no criminal record, it should be treated as a misdemeanor, two sources said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Los Angeles County Sheriff&amp;apost;s Department detectives are pushing for a felony charge, based on the estimated $20,000 in damage caused by the eggs to the mansion next door.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Justin&amp;apost;s on the move.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Bieber, 20, sold his Calabasas, California, mansion to Khloe Kardashian earlier this month and has already moved his skateboard ramp, video games and fast cars from the home where he&amp;apost;s lived for the past two years, a source close to him confirmed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Despite tabloid speculation that Bieber planned to make Atlanta his new home, a source close to him told CNN that would not happen.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>He spent most of February in Atlanta, where he began his professional recording career, but in recent weeks he has flown to Florida, Texas and Canada.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Bieber is now in Toronto, where he is working on new music, according to his Twitter postings.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>He is scheduled to be tried on a DUI charge in Miami on May 4.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>He also has an assault charge pending in Toronto, related to an alleged attack on his limo driver.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>None of the criminal charges facing Bieber, including the expected vandalism count, appear to threaten his freedom.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Probation sentences, fines, community service and counseling are routinely given in such cases.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Bieber&amp;apost;s Los Angeles lawyers are experienced in keeping their celebrity clients out of jail, although that can be a challenge if the client fails to comply with probation requirements.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Attorney Shawn Holley also represents actress Lindsay Lohan, who became the poster child for probation violators after two drunken driving convictions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Lohan&amp;apost;s career was derailed by supervised probation, which was interrupted several times by trips to jail and court-ordered rehab.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Singer Chris Brown sits in a Los Angeles jail now because of repeated probation violations stemming from his 2009 assault conviction for the beating of then-girlfriend Rihanna.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Brown&amp;apost;s prospects for resuming his music career anytime soon are dimmed by the requirement that he work on a highway cleanup crew three days a week for eight months after he is released from jail.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
