<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1225" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/10/04/showbiz/chris-brown-rihanna/index.html?iref=allsearch" date_published="2012-10-04 18:17:32" category="showbiz" author="Alan Duke, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Chris Brown renews &amp;apost;friendship&amp;apost; with Rihanna</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Chris Brown announces breakup with girlfriend Karrueche Tran.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">&amp;quot;I don&amp;apost;t want to see her hurt over my friendship with Rihanna,&amp;quot; Brown says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="9">Talk of a Rihanna-Brown reunion was fueled when she kissed, hugged him at the MTV VMAs.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="11">Brown remains on probation for assaulting Rihanna in 2009.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-24 09:43:51" annotation_time="61.225002">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">The singer sent an unsolicited statement to CNN announcing he was breaking up with Karrueche Tran, the 24-year-old model he began dating a year after he was arrested for the felony assault.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;I love Karrueche very much but I don&amp;apost;t want to see her hurt over my friendship with Rihanna.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="3">The talk of their reunion was fueled last month when Rihanna gave Brown a quick kiss and a hug at the MTV Video Music Awards last month as Brown walked to the stage to accept an award.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="4">The judge overseeing Brown&amp;apost;s case imposed a &amp;quot;stay away&amp;quot; order when she sentenced him to five years of probation, community service and domestic violence counseling for his felony assault conviction in August 2009.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Los Angeles Chris Brown acknowledged Thursday he has renewed his &amp;quot;friendship&amp;quot; with Rihanna, the woman he was convicted of beating on the eve of the Grammys in February 2009.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Brown, 23, has two more years of probation to serve for his felony assault conviction, although the judge lifted the &amp;quot;stay away&amp;quot; order that kept him from his victim last year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The singer sent an unsolicited statement to CNN announcing he was breaking up with Karrueche Tran, the 24-year-old model he began dating a year after he was arrested for the felony assault.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;I have decided to be single to focus on my career,&amp;quot; Brown said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;I love Karrueche very much but I don&amp;apost;t want to see her hurt over my friendship with Rihanna.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>I&amp;apost;d rather be single allowing us to both be happy in our lives.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Tran tweeted a short message Wednesday that appeared directed at Brown: &amp;quot;Bye baby.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The announcement follows publication of paparazzi photos showing Brown and Rihanna together in public and rumors the two entertainers had reunited romantically.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The talk of their reunion was fueled last month when Rihanna gave Brown a quick kiss and a hug at the MTV Video Music Awards last month as Brown walked to the stage to accept an award.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Rihanna told Oprah Winfrey in an emotional interview in August that Brown had been her &amp;quot;best friend&amp;quot; and she still loved him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The judge overseeing Brown&amp;apost;s case imposed a &amp;quot;stay away&amp;quot; order when she sentenced him to five years of probation, community service and domestic violence counseling for his felony assault conviction in August 2009.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The order, which was to expire in 2014, required Brown to stay 50 yards away from Rihanna, 10 yards if the two are at the same industry event.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The judge lifted the order in February 2011 with Rihanna&amp;apost;s consent.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;He just can&amp;apost;t bother her,&amp;quot; Rihanna&amp;apost;s lawyer, Donald Etra, said at the time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Brown has made several public apologies to Rihanna for the attack, which he seemed to blame on his youth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>He was 19 at the time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;I feel like that we&amp;apost;re young,&amp;quot; Brown told CNN&amp;apost;s Larry King days after his sentencing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re both young.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>So nobody taught us how to love one another.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Nobody taught us a book on how to control our emotions or our anger.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>I&amp;apost;m not trying to fall on the fact that I&amp;apost;m young.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>I&amp;apost;m just saying it&amp;apost;s a lot of stuff that I wish I could have changed that night.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Brown was arrested after an early morning argument inside a rented Lamborghini on a Hollywood street on February 8, 2009.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>According to Brown&amp;apost;s probation report, the argument began over an incident at a Beverly Hills party.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>An earlier, sworn statement by Los Angeles Police Detective DeShon Andrews said the incident began when Rihanna found a text message on his cell phone from &amp;quot;a woman who Brown had a previous sexual relationship with.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The pair argued while in the car driven by Brown, the police statement said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>It went on to describe the assault in great detail, saying Brown punched Rihanna -- identified in the statement by her real first name, Robyn, and the first initial of her last name, Fenty -- numerous times and put her in a headlock, restricting her breathing and causing her to start to lose consciousness.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>He threatened to beat her and kill her, according to the statement, and he bit her ear and her fingers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Eventually, the statement said, &amp;quot;Robyn F. began screaming for help and Brown exited the vehicle and walked away.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>A resident in the neighborhood heard Robyn F.&amp;apost;s plea for help and called 911, causing a police response.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>An investigation was conducted and Robyn F. was issued a domestic violence emergency protective order.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The detective said Brown sent a text message nine days later, apologizing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Rihanna&amp;apost;s injuries included cuts and bruises inflicted by a large ring on Brown&amp;apost;s right hand, which he used to punch her, the probation report said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;Officers at the scene observed numerous contusions and abrasions to the victim&amp;apost;s face and forehead, as well as bruising to her left arm near the bicep,&amp;quot; it said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;They also saw abrasions to her arms near both wrists and on her upper chest near her collarbone and around her neck.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>There were abrasions on her left leg and on the inside of her upper lips.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Rihanna declined to speak to the probation investigator, so the probation report&amp;apost;s details were gathered from police detectives who interviewed her soon after the attack.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;He beat me up,&amp;quot; Rihanna told the police, the report said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Brown made a public apology that July in a video statement posted on his personal Web site.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;I have told Rihanna countless times, and I&amp;apost;m telling you today, that I&amp;apost;m truly, truly sorry in that I wasn&amp;apost;t able to handle the situation both differently and better,&amp;quot; Brown said in the Web site statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;What I did was unacceptable, 100 percent.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>I can only ask and pray that you forgive me.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Please.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
