<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1357" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/08/14/showbiz/robin-williams-parkinsons-disease/index.html?hpt=en_bn4" date_published="2014-08-14 18:39:38" category="showbiz" author="Alan Duke, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Robin Williams had early stages of Parkinson&amp;apost;s disease</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="21">NEW: &amp;quot;A true friend; I wish him peace,&amp;quot; tweets actor Michael J. Fox .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">The diagnosis was &amp;quot;an additional fear and burden in his life,&amp;quot; a source says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="7">Williams&amp;apost; widow says he was &amp;quot;not yet ready to share publicly&amp;quot; his diagnosis.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="3">Williams was found dead in his Northern California home Monday.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-11 19:25:11" annotation_time="52.970497">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">The diagnosis of the progressive illness was &amp;quot;an additional fear and burden in his life,&amp;quot; a person familiar with Williams&amp;apost; family told CNN on Thursday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="4">Williams was found dead in his Northern California home Monday from what investigators suspect was a suicide by hanging.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;Robin&amp;apost;s sobriety was intact and he was brave as he struggled with his own battles of depression, anxiety as well as early stages of Parkinson&amp;apost;s disease, which he was not yet ready to share publicly.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="1">A true friend; I wish him peace,&amp;quot; Fox tweeted.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Robin Williams was sober but was struggling with depression, anxiety and the early stages of Parkinson&amp;apost;s disease when he died, his widow said Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The diagnosis of the progressive illness was &amp;quot;an additional fear and burden in his life,&amp;quot; a person familiar with Williams&amp;apost; family told CNN on Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Williams was found dead in his Northern California home Monday from what investigators suspect was a suicide by hanging.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>While fans and friends have looked for answers to why the 63-year-old comedy icon would take his own life, his wife, Susan Schneider, issued a written statement about Williams&amp;apost; health that he had kept a secret.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;Since his passing, all of us who loved Robin have found some solace in the tremendous outpouring of affection and admiration for him from the millions of people whose lives he touched,&amp;quot; Schneider said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;His greatest legacy, besides his three children, is the joy and happiness he offered to others, particularly to those fighting personal battles.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;Robin&amp;apost;s sobriety was intact and he was brave as he struggled with his own battles of depression, anxiety as well as early stages of Parkinson&amp;apost;s disease, which he was not yet ready to share publicly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is our hope in the wake of Robin&amp;apost;s tragic passing, that others will find the strength to seek the care and support they need to treat whatever battles they are facing so they may feel less afraid.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Williams had been active as an actor in the last year of his life, performing in a CBS sitcom that was canceled this year and acting in four films that have yet to hit theaters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>It is not clear whether the early-stage Parkinson&amp;apost;s disease affected his ability to work.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;Friends and family can usually detect changes in the Parkinson&amp;apost;s patient including poor posture, loss of balance, and abnormal facial expressions,&amp;quot; according to the National Parkinson Foundation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;During this initial phase of the disease, a patient usually experiences mild symptoms.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>These symptoms may inconvenience the day-to-day tasks the patient would otherwise complete with ease.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Typically these symptoms will include the presence of tremors or experiencing shaking in one of the limbs.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Parkinson&amp;apost;s disease &amp;quot;causes certain brain cells to die,&amp;quot; according to the website of the National Institutes of Health.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>It is more likely to affect men than women and most often develops after age 50.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Williams used exercise and cycling to manage his stress and depression, and the prospect that the illness would prevent him from doing that was extremely upsetting, adding to the depression, the person familiar with his family said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Fellow actor Michael J. Fox, who has Parkinson&amp;apost;s and established the Michael J. Fox Foundation, said Thursday that he was unaware of his friend&amp;apost;s condition.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;Stunned to learn Robin had PD.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Pretty sure his support for our Fdn predated his diagnosis.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>A true friend; I wish him peace,&amp;quot; Fox tweeted.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Investigators believe Williams used a belt to hang himself from a bedroom door sometime between late Sunday and when his personal assistant found him just before noon Monday, according to Marin County Assistant Deputy Chief Coroner Lt. Keith Boyd.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Boyd would not confirm or deny whether Williams left behind a letter, saying that investigators would discuss &amp;quot;the note or a note&amp;quot; later.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The coroner&amp;apost;s investigation &amp;quot;revealed he had been seeking treatment for depression,&amp;quot; Boyd said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>He spent time in a treatment facility in July, a time when his wife and representative have said he was battling depression.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Media reports at the time speculated that Williams had resumed drinking alcohol, but the statement from his wife appears to dispute those reports.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Williams entered rehab because of drug and alcohol addiction at least twice previously.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;Robin spent so much of his life helping others,&amp;quot; his wife said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Whether he was entertaining millions on stage, film or television, our troops on the front lines, or comforting a sick child -- Robin wanted us to laugh and to feel less afraid.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
