<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1184" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/07/26/showbiz/zambezia-animation-south-africa/index.html" date_published="2012-07-26 10:00:29" category="showbiz" author="Teo Kermeliotis, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>&amp;apost;Zambezia&amp;apost;: 3D animation puts South Africa film in the picture</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">&amp;quot;Zambezia&amp;quot; is a new South African 3D animation feature film.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">The movie stars the voices of Samuel L. Jackson, Jeremy Suarez and Jeff Goldblum .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">It has been chosen to close the 33rd edition of the Durban International Film Festival.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="7">&amp;quot;Zambezia&amp;quot; is targeted toward children aged five to 11.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 16:45:24" annotation_time="24.970667">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1, 2">A high-spirited young falcon, Kai is the main character in &amp;quot;Zambezia,&amp;quot; a new South African 3D animation film featuring an all-star voice cast, including Hollywood A-listers Samuel L. Jackson, Abigail Breslin, Jeff Goldblum, Leonard Nimoy and Jeremy Suarez.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">The movie, produced by Cape Town-based Triggerfish Animation Studios, has been selected as the closing film of the 33rd edition of the Durban International Film Festival, which runs until July 29.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="4">The movie, which is targeted toward children aged five to 11, tells the story of Kai, an intrepid young falcon that&amp;apost;s brought up by his strict father in an isolated outpost.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s got blue wings, an adventurous spirit and is poised to be the latest film star to come out of South Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>A high-spirited young falcon, Kai is the main character in &amp;quot;Zambezia,&amp;quot; a new South African 3D animation film featuring an all-star voice cast, including Hollywood A-listers Samuel L. Jackson, Abigail Breslin, Jeff Goldblum, Leonard Nimoy and Jeremy Suarez.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Set in the majestic Victoria Falls and inspired by southern Africa&amp;apost;s startling artwork, &amp;quot;Zambezia&amp;quot; is hoping to put South African animation on the map while enthralling children around the world with its uplifting message of togetherness.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The movie, produced by Cape Town-based Triggerfish Animation Studios, has been selected as the closing film of the 33rd edition of the Durban International Film Festival, which runs until July 29.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;The film is a wonderful ambassador, in a way, of South Africa and I think as it travels the world it&amp;apost;s going to spread the word about an industry that is young and vibrant and extremely talented,&amp;quot; says &amp;quot;Zambezia&amp;quot; director and co-writer Wayne Thornley.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;In and of itself, I think it&amp;apost;s just an enjoyable ride for children and they&amp;apost;re going to come away wishing they could fly.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The movie, which is targeted toward children aged five to 11, tells the story of Kai, an intrepid young falcon that&amp;apost;s brought up by his strict father in an isolated outpost.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>His lonely life is turned upside down when a kooky bird crashes into his world and tells him of Zambezia -- a bustling bird city where &amp;quot;there&amp;apost;s amazing food, music, sights and sounds.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>A talented flier, Kai decides to leave his isolated upbringing behind him and explore life in Zambezia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>He quickly realizes, however, that getting by in a city can be more difficult and demanding than living alone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Yet, after joining Zambezia&amp;apost;s air force and defending it from a band of marauding lizards, he also discovers the true values of teamwork and community sharing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Thornley says the movie was guided by the traditional African principle of ubuntu, which he describes roughly as &amp;quot;a person is a person only because of other people&amp;quot; -- he says that the movie&amp;apost;s heartwarming theme will resonate with both African and international audiences.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;Everyone can relate to that idea that it&amp;apost;s better, it&amp;apost;s easier to do things together, that teams are just more vibrant and get more things done,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;They are difficult and messy and it&amp;apost;s not always easy but it is worth it -- I think that&amp;apost;s a universal theme and I hope that audiences around the world come away with that kind of message going: it&amp;apost;s safer to stay alone but it&amp;apost;s not better.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The concept for the movie originated about seven years ago but production took just over two years to be completed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The third computer generated 3D film to be made in South Africa, &amp;quot;Zambezia&amp;quot; is &amp;quot;probably the biggest budget animated film ever to come out of anywhere in Africa,&amp;quot; says Thornley -- Triggerfish was unable to disclose how much the film cost, but said its budget was under $20 million.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The movie&amp;apost;s international appeal is expected to be raised by the high-profile roster of actors lending their voices to the characters.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Thornley says it all became possible after well-known U.S. producer Mace Neufeld saw the film by chance.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;He liked what he saw and he finally got involved and started opening doors for us.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Read more: &amp;apost;Netflix of Africa&amp;apost; brings Nollywood to world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Working with top Hollywood stars such as Jackson and Goldblum was &amp;quot;an honor&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;really fun&amp;quot;, says Thornley.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;It was gratifying that they treated it seriously like any project,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;We tend to think of ourselves that we&amp;apost;re this little studio but they were fantastic and it was really a great experience,&amp;quot; he adds.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;Zambezia&amp;quot; had its world premiere at France&amp;apost;s Annecy Animation Festival last month and was released in Israel earlier in July.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>It will hit the big screen in Germany and Switzerland on August 30, while its South Africa release is scheduled for December 26.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>It has already been sold in more than 30 territories for screening in over 50 countries, including a distribution deal in English-speaking territories with Sony, according to Triggerfish Animation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Thornley says South Africa&amp;apost;s animation industry is still young and small but it is &amp;quot;definitely punching above its weight.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;I want people to sit back and have a fantastic time with the characters and have a fantastic insight into some of the amazing African landscapes that we&amp;apost;ve put into this film,&amp;quot; says Thornley.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;But also I want them to come away really surprised that something like that could come out of Africa and South Africa in particular.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
