<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1224" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/10/27/showbiz/chris-brown-arrested/index.html?hpt=hp_t2" date_published="2013-10-27 14:43:49" category="showbiz" author="Alan Duke, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Chris Brown jailed on felony assault charge</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6">NEW: Alleged victim says he was attacked when he tried to get into a photo with Brown.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">NEW: Brown allegedly said &amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m not down with that gay s--t&amp;quot; .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">Brown and a bodyguard were booked at D.C.&amp;apost;s Second District police station.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="15">Brown is on probation for a felony domestic violence conviction involving Rihanna.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-06 18:39:44" annotation_time="47.745003">
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1, 2">Parker told police that he tried to jump into a photo that Brown was posing for with a female fan on the sidewalk when the singer said, &amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m not down with that gay s--t&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;I feel like boxing,&amp;quot; the police report said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">Brown and the bodyguard were taken into custody and were being held at the Second District police station, police said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="4">Brown is on probation in California for a felony domestic violence conviction involving Rihanna.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Singer Chris Brown and a bodyguard were arrested Sunday morning and charged with felony assault, the Washington Metropolitan Police Department said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The arrest could have serious legal consequence for Brown, 24, since he is serving probation for the felony domestic violence conviction relating to his 2009 attack on former girlfriend Rihanna.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Brown and bodyguard Christopher Hollosy allegedly attacked a man with their fists outside the W Hotel in downtown Washington at 4:25 a.m. Sunday, police said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The police incident report obtained by CNN identified the alleged victim as Isaac Adams Parker, 20, of Beltsville, Maryland.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Parker did not immediately respond to a CNN call for comment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Parker told police that he tried to jump into a photo that Brown was posing for with a female fan on the sidewalk when the singer said, &amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m not down with that gay s--t&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;I feel like boxing,&amp;quot; the police report said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Parker said that Brown then punched him in the face with his closed fist, the report said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Parker said Brown&amp;apost;s bodyguard -- who stands 6-foot-5 and weighs 240 pounds -- stepped between them and punched Parker in the face, the report said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The bodyguard then grabbed Brown by his arm and pulled him toward his tour bus, which was parked near by, it said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Brown and the bodyguard were taken into custody and were being held at the Second District police station, police said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Both men were later transferred to a central jail cell block for processing, police said,.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Parker was treated and released at a hospital for treatment for a bruised and swollen face, police spokesman Anthony Clay told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Brown was in Washington to host a &amp;quot;homecoming party&amp;quot; at The Park at Fourteen nightclub Saturday night, according to his Twitter feed, just four blocks away from where he was arrested Sunday morning.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>His representative and lawyer did not immediately respond to CNN calls for comment Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Brown is on probation in California for a felony domestic violence conviction involving Rihanna.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Any arrest could be considered a violation of that probation, which could result in jail time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Prosecutors filed probation violation charges against him twice in the past year, resulting in the judge ordering him to complete an additional 1,000 hours of community service.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Brown was arrested in February 2009 for punching Rihanna inside a rented Lamborghini on a Hollywood street.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The altercation left the face of Rihanna, also a chart-topping singer, bruised and bloody on the eve of the Grammy Awards.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>He entered a guilty plea seven months later and was sentenced to serve five years probation and ordered to spend more than 1,400 hours in &amp;quot;labor-oriented service.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>His probation reports were glowing until the past year, when the district attorney&amp;apost;s office accused him of not completing the 1,400 hours of community labor, which he was allowed to do in his home state of Virginia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>He was also accused of hit-and-run after a minor traffic crash earlier this year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The driver of the other car told investigators that Brown &amp;quot;went ballistic&amp;quot; and screamed at her after his Range Rover rear-ended her Mercedes on a Los Angeles street.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In August, Brown&amp;apost;s lawyer reached a settlement with prosecutors to end their efforts to revoke his probation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The deal called for Brown to complete another 1,000 hours of community service.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Probation rules require Brown to stay out of all legal trouble.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Even an arrest that does not lead to a conviction could result in a probation violation charge.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>He is scheduled to appear before Los Angeles County Superior Court Judge James Brandlin on November 20 for a probation status hearing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
