<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1331" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/08/27/showbiz/miley-cyrus-homeless-date/index.html?hpt=en_bn3" date_published="2014-08-27 16:31:10" category="showbiz" author="Alan Duke, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Miley Cyrus&amp;apost; &amp;apost;homeless&amp;apost; VMA date faces arrest in Oregon</title>
  <keywords>Jesse Helt,Miley Cyrus VMAs</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">An arrest warrant was issued for Jesse Helt in 2011, a corrections official says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Helt stopped checking in with probation officer after criminal trespass conviction, he says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="18">Cyrus: &amp;quot;You&amp;apost;ve chosen to go after Jesse instead of covering&amp;quot; the youth homelessness issue.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="14">Helt could spend a year in jail for his probation violation, the official says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-11 19:23:28" annotation_time="52.115997">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1, 2">An arrest warrant was issued for Jesse Helt, 22, when he stopped checking in with his probation officer for a criminal trespass conviction in November 2011, said Polk County, Oregon, Community Corrections Director Martin Silbernagel.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="4">If police find Helt, who some media reports said returned to Salem, Oregon, to visit his mother, he will be taken before a judge to decide whether he will spend up to a year in jail or be allowed to resume his probation, Silbernagel said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="3">You&amp;apost;ve chosen to go after Jesse instead of covering the issue of youth homelessness :(&amp;quot; Cyrus said on Twitter after online reports of his arrest warrant were first published Tuesday.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The young man Miley Cyrus chose to represent homeless youths at the MTV Video Music Awards on Sunday faces arrest in Oregon, a corrections official said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>An arrest warrant was issued for Jesse Helt, 22, when he stopped checking in with his probation officer for a criminal trespass conviction in November 2011, said Polk County, Oregon, Community Corrections Director Martin Silbernagel.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;Reportedly, he has returned to the Polk County area,&amp;quot; Silbernagel said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;We will be attempting to serve him his warrant, at which time he will be taken into custody.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Polk County sheriff&amp;apost;s deputies are not actively searching for Helt because of a staff shortage, but they would arrest him if they encounter him, spokesman Dean Bender said Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Helt took center stage at Sunday&amp;apost;s VMA broadcast to accept the best video of 2014 award &amp;quot;on behalf of the 1.6 million runaways and homeless youths in the United States who are starving, lost and scared for their lives right now.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Cyrus, whose &amp;quot;Wrecking Ball&amp;quot; video was being honored, appeared to be near tears as she watched Helt, who said he was homeless, read the acceptance speech calling attention to the large population of homeless young people in Los Angeles.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;ve survived in shelters all over this city,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;ve cleaned your hotel rooms.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>I&amp;apost;ve been an extra in your movies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>I&amp;apost;ve been an extra in your life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Though I may have been invisible to you on the streets, I have a lot of the same dreams that brought many of you here tonight.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Along with raising awareness of the problem of young people living on the streets of Los Angeles, Helt&amp;apost;s story caught the attention of corrections officials in northwest Oregon, where he grew up and where his mother lives.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>If police find Helt, who some media reports said returned to Salem, Oregon, to visit his mother, he will be taken before a judge to decide whether he will spend up to a year in jail or be allowed to resume his probation, Silbernagel said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Helt was initially arrested in October 2010 on burglary, criminal mischief and criminal trespass charges.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The burglary count was dismissed, but he was convicted of the mischief and trespass counts, Bender said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;The media never fails to disappoint.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>You&amp;apost;ve chosen to go after Jesse instead of covering the issue of youth homelessness :(&amp;quot; Cyrus said on Twitter after online reports of his arrest warrant were first published Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;While the media obsesses over one homeless mans legal issue, let&amp;apost;s help the other 1.6 million homeless youth http://www.prizeo.com/miley,&amp;quot; Cyrus said in an Instagram posting.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>In a video posted on her Facebook page, she instructs fans to donate through a Prizeo fundraising site to My Friend&amp;apost;s Place, a Los Angeles-area charity that provides support for homeless people ages 12 to 25.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>