<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1345" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/07/02/showbiz/paula-deen-defense/index.html" date_published="2013-07-02 16:16:40" category="showbiz" author="Alan Duke, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Paula Deen invokes same-sex marriage ruling in lawsuit defense</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="15">NEW: Law professor says the Prop 8 ruling is not relevant to the Deen case.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">A white woman can&amp;apost;t sue for racial discrimination, Deen&amp;apost;s lawyer argues.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="11">Deen&amp;apost;s motion cites last week&amp;apost;s Supreme Court ruling on California&amp;apost;s Prop 8.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="19">The high court ruled private citizens had &amp;quot;no standing&amp;quot; to appeal same-sex ruling.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 16:51:20" annotation_time="82.67999">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">The woman alleging that she was subjected to a hostile work environment while working as an assistant manager at Deen&amp;apost;s restaurants is white and therefore doesn&amp;apost;t have the &amp;quot;standing,&amp;quot; or legal right, to claim racial discrimination, according to a motion filed Monday by Deen&amp;apost;s lawyer.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="3">Deen attorney William Franklin&amp;apost;s motion, filed Monday with the U.S. District Court in Savannah, cited the June 26 Supreme Court decision in Hollingsworth v. Perry, the California case.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="1">George Washington University law professor Jonathan Turley told CNN Tuesday the contention that the Prop 8 ruling is relevant to the Deen case won&amp;apost;t hold water.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="4">Private citizens picked it up, ultimately to be told by the high court last week that they had no standing to do so.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Celebrity chef Paula Deen hopes the Supreme Court&amp;apost;s ruling allowing same-sex marriage to be legal in California will help in her defense against a racial discrimination lawsuit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The woman alleging that she was subjected to a hostile work environment while working as an assistant manager at Deen&amp;apost;s restaurants is white and therefore doesn&amp;apost;t have the &amp;quot;standing,&amp;quot; or legal right, to claim racial discrimination, according to a motion filed Monday by Deen&amp;apost;s lawyer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The high court rejected an appeal of California&amp;apost;s Proposition 8 law last week on the grounds that the private parties behind the appeal did not have standing to defend the ballot measure barring gay and lesbian couples from state-sanctioned wedlock.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Even if the federal judge in Savannah, Georgia, accepts the argument and tosses the lawsuit, much damage has already been done to Deen&amp;apost;s career and businesses by the public fallout from a deposition in which she acknowledged using the &amp;quot;N-word.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Asked by the lawyer taking the deposition if she had ever used the word, she said, &amp;quot;Yes, of course.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>She said she had probably used the racial slur when talking to her husband about &amp;quot;when a black man burst into the bank that I was working at and put a gun to my head&amp;quot; -- an incident that took place 30 years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Asked if she had used it since then, she said, &amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m sure I have, but it&amp;apost;s been a very long time.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>She noted that circumstances have changed &amp;quot;since the &amp;apost;60s in the South.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Many of Deen&amp;apost;s lucrative business relationships have crumbled in the wake of media coverage of the lawsuit.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>She has lost at least nine endorsements along with her Food Network cooking show, and publication of her eagerly anticipated cookbook has been canceled.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Deen attorney William Franklin&amp;apost;s motion, filed Monday with the U.S. District Court in Savannah, cited the June 26 Supreme Court decision in Hollingsworth v. Perry, the California case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Writing for the majority, Chief Justice Roberts made this observation: Article III of the Constitution confines the judicial power of federal courts to deciding actual &amp;apost;Cases&amp;apost; or &amp;apost;Controversies,&amp;apost;&amp;quot; the motion said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;One essential aspect of this requirement is that any person invoking the power of a federal court must demonstrate standing to do so.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>This requires the litigant to prove that he has suffered a concrete and particularized injury that is fairly traceable to the challenged conduct, and is likely to be redressed by a favorable judicial decision.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>George Washington University law professor Jonathan Turley told CNN Tuesday the contention that the Prop 8 ruling is relevant to the Deen case won&amp;apost;t hold water.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The concept of standing is hardly new, and the Supreme Court bringing it into the spotlight in Hollingsworth v. Perry doesn&amp;apost;t not advance Deen&amp;apost;s motion to dismiss the case, Turley said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Lisa Jackson, the plaintiff in the suit against Deen is white, has no standing because she couldn&amp;apost;t have suffered &amp;quot;a personal and tangible harm&amp;quot; from hearing the &amp;quot;N-word&amp;quot; on the job, the Franklin&amp;apost;s , motion says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>In the Prop 8 case, state officials refused to pursue an appeal when a federal judge struck down the same-sex marriage ban.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Private citizens picked it up, ultimately to be told by the high court last week that they had no standing to do so.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Jackson is a former manager at Deen&amp;apost;s restaurants in Savannah, Georgia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>She is suing Deen and her brother, Bubba Hier, alleging they committed numerous acts of violence, discrimination and racism that resulted in the end of her five-year employment at Deen&amp;apost;s Lady &amp;amp; Sons and Bubba&amp;apost;s Seafood and Oyster House eateries in Savannah.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>She gave a statement to CNN&amp;apost;s Don Lemon through her lawyer, Matthew Billips, on Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;This lawsuit has never been about the N-word,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is to address Ms. Deen&amp;apost;s patterns of disrespect and degradation of people that she deems to be inferior.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>I may be a white woman, but I could no longer tolerate her abuse of power as a business owner, nor her condonation of Mr. Hier&amp;apost;s despicable behavior on a day-to-day basis.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>I am what I am, and I am a human being that cares about all races, and that is why I feel it is important to be the voice for those who are too afraid to use theirs.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Deen&amp;apost;s lawyer has called the allegations false, and Deen has said she does not tolerate prejudice.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Deen made an emotional appearance on NBC&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;Today Show&amp;quot; last week in which she called the accusations &amp;quot;horrible, horrible lies.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;I believe that every creature on this Earth, every one of God&amp;apost;s creatures, was created equal,&amp;quot; she said. &amp;quot;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>... I believe that everyone ought to be treated equal.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Deen was raised to never be unkind to anyone, she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
