<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1203" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/10/28/showbiz/chris-brown-assault-charge/index.html?iref=allsearch" date_published="2013-10-28 17:26:06" category="showbiz" author="Alan Duke, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Assault charge against Chris Brown reduced in D.C. brawl</title>
  <keywords>Chris Brown assault charge,Chris Brown fight,Chris Brown Washington fight,Chris Brown DC fight</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">NEW: &amp;quot;Christopher Brown committed no crime,&amp;quot; his attorney says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8">Brown and his bodyguard had been facing felony assault charges.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="9">The arrest could have serious legal consequence for Brown, who is on probation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="12">Brown&amp;apost;s probation officer will prepare a report on the D.C. arrest for a Los Angeles judge.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-14 15:34:32" annotation_time="29.112665">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;Christopher Brown committed no crime,&amp;quot; his attorney Danny Onorato told reporters after the hearing.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">He and bodyguard Christopher Hollosy had been facing felony assault charges, the Washington Metropolitan Police Department said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="3">The arrest could have serious legal consequences for Brown because he is on probation for the felony domestic violence conviction relating to his 2009 attack on former girlfriend Rihanna.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="4">The next step in Los Angeles is for Brown&amp;apost;s probation officer to prepare a report on the arrest for Los Angeles County Superior Court Judge James Brandlin, who had already ordered Brown to appear in his court on November 20 for a probation status hearing.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The charges against singer Chris Brown and his bodyguard stemming from a weekend fight were reduced to simple assault misdemeanors Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The two men, who had spent the previous 36 hours in a Washington jail, entered a packed courtroom in leg irons and handcuffs, but at the end they were unshackled and released without bail Monday afternoon.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Brown, 24, was ordered to report to his California probation officer within 48 hours and to stay at least 100 yards away from the man he is accused of assaulting early Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Both men must return to court on November 24.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;Christopher Brown committed no crime,&amp;quot; his attorney Danny Onorato told reporters after the hearing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;We understand that his security acted to protect Mr. Brown and his property, as he is authorized to do under District of Columbia law.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>We are confident that Mr. Brown will be exonerated of any wrongdoing.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>He and bodyguard Christopher Hollosy had been facing felony assault charges, the Washington Metropolitan Police Department said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The arrest could have serious legal consequences for Brown because he is on probation for the felony domestic violence conviction relating to his 2009 attack on former girlfriend Rihanna.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The Los Angeles County district attorney&amp;apost;s office is not commenting Monday about Brown&amp;apost;s arrest, but prosecutors have been aggressive in the past year in monitoring Brown&amp;apost;s compliance with rules of his California probation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>They have twice filed probation violation charges against the singer this year, resulting in an additional 1,000 hours of community labor being added to his sentence for beating Rihanna.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The next step in Los Angeles is for Brown&amp;apost;s probation officer to prepare a report on the arrest for Los Angeles County Superior Court Judge James Brandlin, who had already ordered Brown to appear in his court on November 20 for a probation status hearing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Police say Brown and Hollosy attacked a man with their fists outside the W Hotel in downtown Washington at 4:25 a.m. Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>A police incident report obtained by CNN identified the alleged victim as Isaac Adams Parker, 20, of Beltsville, Maryland.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Parker did not respond to a CNN call for comment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Parker told police that he tried to jump into a photo that Brown was posing for with a female fan on the sidewalk when the singer said, &amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m not down with that gay s--t&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;I feel like boxing,&amp;quot; the police report said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Parker said that Brown then punched him in the face with his closed fist, the report said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Parker said Brown&amp;apost;s bodyguard -- who stands 6-foot-5 and weighs 240 pounds -- stepped between them and punched Parker in the face, the report said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The bodyguard then grabbed Brown by his arm and pulled him toward his tour bus, which was parked nearby, it said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Brown and the bodyguard were taken into custody and were being held at the Second District police station, police said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Both men were later transferred to a central jail cell block for processing, police said,.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Parker was treated for a bruised and swollen face at a hospital and released, police spokesman Anthony Clay told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Brown was in Washington to host a &amp;quot;homecoming party&amp;quot; at The Park at Fourteen nightclub Saturday night, according to his Twitter feed, just four blocks away from where he was arrested Sunday morning.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>His representative and lawyer did not respond to CNN calls for comment Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Brown was arrested in February 2009 for punching Rihanna inside a rented Lamborghini on a Hollywood street.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The altercation left the face of Rihanna, also a chart-topping singer, bruised and bloody on the eve of the Grammy Awards.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>He entered a guilty plea seven months later and was sentenced to serve five years of probation and ordered to spend more than 1,400 hours in &amp;quot;labor-oriented service.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>His probation reports were glowing until the past year, when the district attorney&amp;apost;s office accused him of not completing the 1,400 hours of community labor, which he was allowed to do in his home state of Virginia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>He was also accused of hit-and-run after a minor traffic crash this year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The driver of the other car told investigators that Brown &amp;quot;went ballistic&amp;quot; and screamed at her after his Range Rover rear-ended her Mercedes on a Los Angeles street.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>In August, Brown&amp;apost;s lawyer reached a settlement with prosecutors to end their efforts to revoke his probation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The deal called for Brown to complete another 1,000 hours of community service.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Probation rules require Brown to stay out of all legal trouble.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Even an arrest that does not lead to a conviction could result in a probation violation charge.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
