<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1376" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/02/05/showbiz/justin-bieber-marijuana-flight" date_published="2014-02-05 21:55:20" category="showbiz" author="Susan Candiotti and Alan Duke, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Source: Justin Bieber, dad ignored pilot&amp;apost;s demand to put pot away</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Law enforcement source gives details of Bieber&amp;apost;s flight from Canada.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">Pot smoke was so strong in jet&amp;apost;s cabin the flight crew put on oxygen masks, source says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">Pilot claims Bieber and his father were verbally abusive to the flight crew, source says .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="14">Bieber rep Matthew Hiltzik declines comment to CNN.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-26 09:34:09" annotation_time="44.348">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">A law enforcement official gave details to CNN about what the flight crew on the chartered jet told federal officials after they ferried Bieber and his entourage from Canada to New Jersey&amp;apost;s Teterboro Airport.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">Marijuana smoke was so strong in the jet&amp;apost;s cabin that flight crew members put on oxygen masks because they were concerned they might inhale so much it would cause them to test positive for drug use, said the source.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">The pilot said the singer and his father were verbally abusive to the flight crew.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="4">Bieber rep Matthew Hiltzik declined comment to CNN.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>New York Justin Bieber and his father allegedly refused a pilot&amp;apost;s warning to stop smoking pot during a flight from Canada to New Jersey on Friday, according to a law enforcement source.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>A law enforcement official gave details to CNN about what the flight crew on the chartered jet told federal officials after they ferried Bieber and his entourage from Canada to New Jersey&amp;apost;s Teterboro Airport.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The official asked not to be identified.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Marijuana smoke was so strong in the jet&amp;apost;s cabin that flight crew members put on oxygen masks because they were concerned they might inhale so much it would cause them to test positive for drug use, said the source.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The pilots repeatedly asked the pop star, his father, Jeremy Bieber, and other passengers to put away marijuana during the flight, according to the source.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The pilot said the singer and his father were verbally abusive to the flight crew.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>This prompted the pilot to have the flight attendant stay close to the cockpit to avoid contact with Bieber as much as possible, the source said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Bieber and his entourage of 10 were granted re-entry into the United States after a search of the chartered plane by federal officials, who said they detected an odor of marijuana after it landed at Teterboro Airport, a law enforcement official told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>A number of federal agents from Customs and Border Protection, the Drug Enforcement Administration and Immigration and Customs Enforcement said they detected the odor, which prompted the search by drug-sniffing dogs, the source said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>No sign of drugs were detected and no illegal substances were found, a law enforcement source told CNN last week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Bieber, a Canadian citizen living in the United States on a work visa, was detained by border agents for several hours of questioning.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The interview is routinely conducted to ensure people entering the country are in compliance with U.S. law, another law enforcement source said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>A Customs and Border Protection spokesman declined comment, citing privacy requirements involving the questioning of people applying to enter the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Bieber rep Matthew Hiltzik declined comment to CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Bieber, 19, was arrested last week in Toronto, accused of assaulting his limousine driver in December.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>He also faces charges of drunken driving, resisting arrest and driving on an expired license after being stopped by police in Miami Beach, Florida, last month.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The Los Angeles County district attorney is considering whether to charge Bieber with felony vandalism in the egging of his neighbor&amp;apost;s house on January 9, 2014.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
