<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1342" link="http://cnn.com/2014/03/14/showbiz/paul-walker-sunglasses-auction/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-03-14 20:09:55" category="showbiz" author="Lisa Respers France, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Outrage over auction of alleged Paul Walker sunglasses</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">A seller claims to have found items at Walker crash site.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">Rep for auction site said sunglasses match photo of actor.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="17">Police told LA Weekly they doubt glasses are authentic.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-11 14:16:29" annotation_time="79.002">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1"> Some fans are upset about an auction of items alleged to have been taken from the site of a fatal crash that killed &amp;quot;Fast &amp;amp; Furious&amp;quot; star Paul Walker.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">The New York Daily News reported that a rep from the auction site said the authenticity of the glasses was determined by the company using photos of Walker from the day of the crash.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;As a department we doubt that they are actually Paul Walker&amp;apost;s sunglasses,&amp;quot; a spokesman for the Santa Clarita sheriff&amp;apost;s department told the publication.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Some fans are upset about an auction of items alleged to have been taken from the site of a fatal crash that killed &amp;quot;Fast &amp;amp; Furious&amp;quot; star Paul Walker.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>A pair of of Maui Jim sunglasses purported to have been worn by Walker during the crash, a fire extinguisher and and an alleged piece of debris from the accident scene have been put up for auction on BidAMI.com.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>According to a description on the site, the consigner of the lot of items up for auction was nearby when the fiery crash occurred on November 30, 2013, in the Santa Clarita, California, community of Valencia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The lot consigner collected the items &amp;quot;once the site investigation was cleared with car debris hauled away and tape taken down,&amp;quot; according to the description.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;As the consigner walked the scene in disbelief and grief, he found a pair of sunglasses nearby in the ivy,&amp;quot; a description of the auction items on the site notes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;After showing one of the officers, he was waved off.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The glasses were dirty so he wrapped them in a handkerchief and put them in his pocket.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Walker and friend Roger Rodas died after the 2005 Porsche Carrera GT Rodas was driving slammed into a light pole and burst into flames.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The New York Daily News reported that a rep from the auction site said the authenticity of the glasses was determined by the company using photos of Walker from the day of the crash.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>CNN has reached out for comment, but has not confirmed that the glasses did indeed belong to Walker.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The sale announcement apparently garnered so much traffic that the BidAMI site crashed on Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>A Change.org petition has been started to stop the sale, and some fans have reacted negatively on Twitter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>User Chloe Dawn tweeted, &amp;quot;Someone is selling the sunglasses Paul Walker was wearing when he died.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>So disrespectful... what is wrong with people?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The founder and editor-in-chief of the celebrity site Rickey.org tweeted, &amp;quot;Some terrible person is selling the sunglasses that #PaulWalker was supposedly wearing when he died.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>LA Weekly reported that police are doubtful that the glasses actually are those worn by Walker when he died.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;As a department we doubt that they are actually Paul Walker&amp;apost;s sunglasses,&amp;quot; a spokesman for the Santa Clarita sheriff&amp;apost;s department told the publication.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;But who knows, maybe they are.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Right now we doubt it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>At the time of his death, Walker was filming &amp;quot;Fast &amp;amp; Furious 7,&amp;quot; the latest in the very successful franchise that made him a star.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>On Thursday, Universal confirmed that filming of movie would resume March 31 in Atlanta, Georgia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The studio had earlier said they don&amp;apost;t plan to kill Walker&amp;apost;s character in the movie, but will instead &amp;quot;retire&amp;quot; him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>