<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1532" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/01/08/sport/football/valcke-qatar-world-cup-2022-football/index.html" date_published="2014-01-08 11:41:44" category="sport" author="CNN Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Top FIFA official envisions winter World Cup for Qatar</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">2022 World Cup might be held in European winter months, says leading FIFA official.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">Jerome Valcke says weather in Qatar is perfect between mid-November, end of December.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="7">The World Cup is traditionally held in June and July.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="7">Qatar&amp;apost;s intense heat in those months raises potential health risks for players and fans.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-13 16:55:32" annotation_time="15.686">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">The 2022 World Cup in Qatar probably will not be played in the traditional months of June and July, FIFA Secretary General Jerome Valcke has told a French radio station.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;If it&amp;apost;s played between November 15 and the end of December, that is when the weather is most favorable,&amp;quot; he said, according to a CNN translation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="3, 4">The tournament is traditionally held in June and July, but concerns have been raised over the potential health risks of staging a World Cup during the intense heat.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The 2022 World Cup in Qatar probably will not be played in the traditional months of June and July, FIFA Secretary General Jerome Valcke has told a French radio station.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But the governing body for world football quickly distanced itself from its second-in-command&amp;apost;s comments, saying, &amp;quot;the precise event date is still subject to an ongoing consultation process.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>There has been controversy around plans to stage the month-long tournament in Qatar&amp;apost;s intense summer heat, prompting calls to move the event to the winter.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Qatar has said it will use cooling technology to make the environment pleasant for players and fans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Valcke, who is FIFA President Sepp Blatter&amp;apost;s deputy, told France Info that he thinks the event will be played between November 15 and January 15 at the latest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;If it&amp;apost;s played between November 15 and the end of December, that is when the weather is most favorable,&amp;quot; he said, according to a CNN translation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The tournament is traditionally held in June and July, but concerns have been raised over the potential health risks of staging a World Cup during the intense heat.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Moving the tournament could also create problems for lucrative club competitions such as Europe&amp;apost;s Champions League while affecting American broadcasters, which have deals with domestic sports leagues that play through the first months of winter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Valcke, referring to the idea of staging the event between November and January, said the weather will be about 25 degrees Celsius (77 degrees Fahrenheit), perfect for playing football.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>In October, Blatter said that no decision on the scheduling of Qatar 2022 will be made until after this year&amp;apost;s World Cup in Brazil, which will take place between June 12 and July 13.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;As the event (in Qatar) will not be played until eight years&amp;apost; time the consultation process will not be rushed and will be given the necessary time to consider all of the elements relevant for a decision,&amp;quot; FIFA said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Consequently, no decision will be taken before the upcoming 2014 FIFA World Cup Brazil as agreed by the FIFA Executive Committee.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The FIFA Executive Committee is due to meet in March at its headquarters in Zurich, Switzerland.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The organizing committee for Qatar&amp;apost;s first World Cup said in a statement that it would be ready to host the tournament at any time of the year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;During the FIFA Executive Committee meeting in October it was agreed that FIFA would enter a period of consultation on the ideal time of year to host the World Cup in Qatar-- with a recommendation expected after the World Cup in Brazil,&amp;quot; said the Qatar 2022 Supreme Committee.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;We await the outcome of this consultation period.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>We will be ready to host the World Cup regardless of the outcome,&amp;quot; it said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Valcke&amp;apost;s remarks also came as a shock to his colleagues within football&amp;apost;s corridors of power.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;As far as I&amp;apost;m concerned, I am totally surprised by the news today,&amp;quot; FIFA Vice President Jim Boyce said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;I had been told that the FIFA Executive Committee is awaiting results of a working party on this issue.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>I was told no announcement on this would be made until after the World Cup in Brazil.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>If the World Cup was to be held between November and January, it would probably create a logistical headache for many major European leagues -- such as the English Premier League -- and for the prestigious Champions League, organized by the continent&amp;apost;s UEFA confederation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>American broadcaster Fox, which paid $425 million for the rights to broadcast the 2018 and 2022 tournaments, has expressed concern that a &amp;quot;winter&amp;quot; World Cup could clash with the National Football League&amp;apost;s regular season and the Super Bowl.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The decision to award Qatar football&amp;apost;s showpiece event has drawn widespread condemnation and focused attention on workers&amp;apost; rights in the state.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>A report released by Amnesty International in November alleged that the abuse of migrant workers was rife within Qatar&amp;apost;s construction sector, while British newspaper The Guardian likened the conditions for such workers to &amp;quot;modern-day slavery.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The recent furor around &amp;quot;stranded&amp;quot; footballer Zahir Belounis also raised questions regarding Qatar&amp;apost;s Kafala law.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Blatter himself described the conditions for migrant workers in Qatar as &amp;quot;unacceptable,&amp;quot; but he refuses to entertain the idea of moving the 2022 competition to another location.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>In response to Amnesty&amp;apost;s allegations, the director of the Human Rights Department at Qatar&amp;apost;s Foreign Ministry said laws are in place to protect workers from mistreatment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
