<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1476" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/05/11/sport/motorsport/spansih-garnd-prix-hamilton-rosberg/index.html" date_published="2014-05-11 14:04:16" category="sport" author="" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Lewis Hamilton holds off Nico Rosberg to claim Spanish Grand Prix</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Lewis Hamilton claims victory at Spanish Grand Prix.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Mercedes claim fourth consecutive one-two finish.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">Home favorite Fernando Alonso finishes race in sixth position.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-22 17:25:32" annotation_time="29.411999">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Lewis Hamilton held off Mercedes teammate Nico Rosberg to claim victory by the narrowest of margins at the Spanish Grand Prix in Barcelona Sunday and take the lead in the F1 standings for the first time this season.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">The win represents a fourth straight checkered flag for the British driver while Rosberg&amp;apost;s second place means Mercedes have now secured four consecutive one-two finishes and five successive race wins.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">Home favorite Fernando Alonso claimed sixth position behind Williams Valtteri Bottas in fifth.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Lewis Hamilton held off Mercedes teammate Nico Rosberg to claim victory by the narrowest of margins at the Spanish Grand Prix in Barcelona Sunday and take the lead in the F1 standings for the first time this season.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The win represents a fourth straight checkered flag for the British driver while Rosberg&amp;apost;s second place means Mercedes have now secured four consecutive one-two finishes and five successive race wins.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Hamilton started the day on pole and led into the first corner, a position he wouldn&amp;apost;t relinquish all afternoon as he claimed his first career victory in Spain.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Rosberg pushed him all the way, however, eventually finishing just 0.6 seconds behind after a tense chase on the final laps.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Red Bull&amp;apost;s Daniel Ricciardo finished fully 40 seconds back in third while the Australian&amp;apost;s teammate and four-time world champion, Sebastian Vettel ended the day fourth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Home favorite Fernando Alonso claimed sixth position behind Williams Valtteri Bottas in fifth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Speaking on the podium after the race, Hamilton said: &amp;quot;A big thank you for my team, they have done an incredible job this year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The support here is the best I have ever had and my first win in Spain means everything to me.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Hamilton seemed edgy over the team radio as Rosberg cut into his lead on the final laps and admitted he was concerned after the race.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;I was not upset, I was not fast enough today, Nico was quicker,&amp;quot; he continued.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;I struggled with the balance and needed to rely on my engineers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>I was moving my settings up and down and fortunately I was able to keep Nico behind.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Hamilton&amp;apost;s relief was contrasted by Rosberg&amp;apost;s frustration at having come so close.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>I think one more lap and I could have given it a good go,&amp;quot; the Greman driver said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;Unfortunately that was it and I am bit gutted but still, second place, second in the championship and many more races to go.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Third placed Ricciardo, meanwhile, was content with a podium finish, given the superiority of the Mercedes cars.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>We knew we didn&amp;apost;t really have the pace for Mercedes,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;We looked like a third-place car and in the end that&amp;apost;s what it was.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>We had a pretty comfortable third- place and we just had to focus on getting the tires to last two stops and that was it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;(It was) really nice to be on the podium and I&amp;apost;m sure I&amp;apost;ll be able to keep it this time,&amp;quot; he added, referring to the second place finish that was taken away from him in the season&amp;apost;s first race in Melbourne due to breaching fuel-flow regulations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The result means Mercedes continue to dominate both the driver&amp;apost;s and constructors&amp;apost; championship.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Hamilton sits atop the driver&amp;apost;s standings on 100 points, three ahead of Rosberg.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>In the driver&amp;apost;s, meanwhile, Mercedes lead the way on 197 points, 113 ahead of second placed Red Bull.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Elsewhere in the race, Kimi Raikonen took seventh position for Ferrari while Romain Grosjean secured a first points position of the season for Lotus in eighth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Force Indias Sergio Perez and Nico Hulkenberg secured the final two point scoring positions in ninth and tenth respectively.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
