<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1537" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/05/08/sport/football/alex-ferguson-asia-man-utd-appeal/index.html?hpt=isp_mid" date_published="2013-05-08 13:36:44" category="sport" author="Paul Armstrong, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>United under Ferguson: Manchester&amp;apost;s mass appeal in Asia</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="24">Under Alex Ferguson, Manchester United has become hugely popular globally.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Recent survey reveals United has 325 million fans in Asia alone.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="16">English champions regularly play in lucrative pre-season Asia tours.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="24">Journalist: &amp;quot;The one thing Asian football fans value above anything else is winning&amp;quot;.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-09 10:03:42" annotation_time="50.502">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">To put this in perspective, a study recently commissioned by the newly-crowned English Premier League champions showed that the team&amp;apost;s global fan base had doubled to 659 million people between 2007 and 2012 -- with 325 million fans from Asia alone.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="3">United has not been slow to recognize the benefits of this global appeal, regularly taking part in lucrative pre-season tours at packed venues across Asia to connect with local fans.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="1, 4">&amp;quot;The one thing Asian football fans value above anything else is winning, and under Alex Ferguson, Manchester United have simply been one of the most successful clubs in the world.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Hong Kong The news that Alex Ferguson is stepping down as Manchester United manager after 26 trophy-laden seasons will be reverberating far beyond British shores Wednesday, and no more so than in Asia where the club has a huge following.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>To put this in perspective, a study recently commissioned by the newly-crowned English Premier League champions showed that the team&amp;apost;s global fan base had doubled to 659 million people between 2007 and 2012 -- with 325 million fans from Asia alone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The figures are staggering, though the number of Manchester United shirts -- official merchandise or not -- that can be seen around the streets of any major city in the region, from Bangkok to Shanghai, goes some way towards illustrating this phenomenal interest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Social interest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>And the interest goes beyond simply wearing a replica shirt.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Within minutes of the shock announcement, football fans in China flocked to Weibo, the country&amp;apost;s version of Twitter, to lament Ferguson&amp;apost;s departure.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;Farewell Fergie,&amp;quot; posted one netizen, known as @HuxuanzheChuckHoo.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;Sir Alex Forever!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>declared @Yesmanduomehao.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Another, known as @Drshankui, said: &amp;quot;Although I don&amp;apost;t really like Manchester and their red polo shirts, I have to say Ferguson is one of the most respected coaches.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Now that he&amp;apost;s going to retire soon, I felt really sad.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>I want to thank him for bringing all the splendidness to the team!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Wednesday&amp;apost;s news also found its way into the mainstream media in China, including 163.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>com, one of the country&amp;apost;s most popular news platforms.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Lucrative.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>United has not been slow to recognize the benefits of this global appeal, regularly taking part in lucrative pre-season tours at packed venues across Asia to connect with local fans.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>In July, the team will visit Hong Kong, Thailand, Japan and Australia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The club has also signed a number of sponsorship deals with &amp;quot;Asian partners,&amp;quot; including banks in Vietnam and a Japanese social gaming company -- though this Asian &amp;quot;sweet spot&amp;quot; has also been clear in the minds of sponsors beyond the region.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;ve gone from no brand awareness in countries like Japan and South Korea to incredible brand awareness,&amp;quot; Phil Clement, chief marketing officer at Aon, told the Financial Times when explaining the U.S. insurance giant&amp;apost;s decision to put pen to paper on a $23 million sponsorship deal earlier this year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>United even explored the idea of an Asian stock market floatation in either Hong Kong or Singapore last year, as it eyed investors -- though market volatility at the time put these plans on hold.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Winning habit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>So why is the club so popular in Asia?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The reason is fairly straightforward, according to James Porteous, a sports journalist at the South China Morning Post in Hong Kong.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;The one thing Asian football fans value above anything else is winning, and under Alex Ferguson, Manchester United have simply been one of the most successful clubs in the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Liverpool have a big following in Asia because of their great history, but that&amp;apost;s taken a dent given their recent trophy-starved years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;While newer champions such as Chelsea and Manchester City have been on the rise, United have had a consistent record of success under Ferguson, gaining new fans in Asia with every trophy won over the last two decades.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;United&amp;apost;s history also gives them great glamor and prestige, from the great names of the 1960s and the tragedy of the Busby Babes, and that is also attractive to fans in the region.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>But most of their popularity is down to their triumphs in the last 20 years under Ferguson.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Title after title, the Champions League twice, global megastars such as Eric Cantona, David Beckham, Cristiano Ronaldo ... all these ingredients have made United&amp;apost;s football brand Asia&amp;apost;s best-loved.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>United has also invested wisely in talented Asian players, most recently signing Japan&amp;apost;s brightest talent, Shinji Kagawa.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The attacking midfielder follows in the footsteps of South Korean star Park Ji-Sung, who spent seven hugely successful years at the club.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The result is United&amp;apost;s appeal borders on the fanatical at times.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>When the club announced plans to play in Hong Kong this year, its first visit to the city since 2005, tickets for the friendly against a local club sold out almost instantly.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Porteous said former United goalkeeper Peter Schmeichel was mobbed by fans when he arrived at Hong Kong airport to promote the game, and again by local journalists at a press conference -- despite leaving the club in 1999.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;The reception I&amp;apost;ve had in only a couple of hours is incredible,&amp;quot; Schmeichel told journalists at the time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;No doubt the club&amp;apost;s vast marketing arm will have many plans to maintain this popularity in Asia,&amp;quot; said Porteous.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;But the key factor is simple: whoever the new manager is, he&amp;apost;ll have to keep winning trophies.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
