<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1480" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/05/28/sport/football/football-glazer-manchester-united/index.html?hpt=ifo_mid" date_published="2014-05-28 20:43:26" category="sport" author="" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Manchester United and Buccaneers owner Malcolm Glazer dies aged 85</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Manchester United owner Malcolm Glazer dies aged 85.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">Glazer assumed control of NFL team the Tampa Bay Buccaneers in 1995.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">The Buccaneers won their first Super Bowl crown in 2002.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="5">Despite loading the club with debt Man Utd have maintained their success.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-02 13:22:31" annotation_time="28.743002">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1"> Malcolm Glazer, owner of the Tampa Bay Buccaneers and English soccer club Manchester United, has died aged 85.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2, 3">One of seven children, Glazer assumed control of the Buccaneers in 1995 and they went on to claim their first Super Bowl crown in 2002.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="4">Despite this discontent, the club continued to enjoy huge success on the field, winning five Premier League titles and one European Champions League crown under his stewardship.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Malcolm Glazer, owner of the Tampa Bay Buccaneers and English soccer club Manchester United, has died aged 85.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The NFL franchise released a statement on their official website announcing Glazer had passed away on Wednesday morning.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>One of seven children, Glazer assumed control of the Buccaneers in 1995 and they went on to claim their first Super Bowl crown in 2002.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>He bought English Premier League team Manchester United in 2005 in a controversial takeover that was heavily criticized by a large section of their fans for loading debt onto the club.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Despite this discontent, the club continued to enjoy huge success on the field, winning five Premier League titles and one European Champions League crown under his stewardship.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Tampa Bay Buccaneers are saddened to announce the passing of Owner/President Malcolm Glazer earlier this morning at the age of 85,&amp;quot; read the statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;Mr. Glazer&amp;apost;s long established estate succession plan has assured the Buccaneers will remain with the Glazer family for generations to come.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;Linda Glazer, along with their five sons and daughter, will continue to own and operate the team as they have throughout the family&amp;apost;s ownership.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;A private family funeral service will be held for Mr.Glazer.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The opportunity for others to remember and celebrate Mr. Glazer&amp;apost;s life will be announced at a future date.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Glazer took control of his family&amp;apost;s business when he was just 15, and developed a wide portfolio of international holdings as it grew exponentially.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The Buccaneers had been perennial underachievers in the NFL prior to Glazer&amp;apost;s takeover in 1995 but he transformed their fortunes and led them to a maiden Super Bowl title in 2002.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>His Glazer Family Foundation, which was established in 1999, has donated millions to charitable causes in the Tampa Bay area.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Glazer suffered a pair of strokes in 2006, which impaired his speech and affected his mobility in his right arm and right leg.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>His sons have long been running both the Bucs and United.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>NFL commissioner Roger Goodell paid tribute to Glazer on his official Twitter account: &amp;quot;Malcolm Glazer was the guiding force behind the building of a Super Bowl-champion organization,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;His dedication to the community was evident in all he did, including his leadership in bringing Super Bowls to Tampa Bay.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Malcolm&amp;apost;s commitment to the Bucs, the NFL and the people of the Tampa Bay region are the hallmarks of his legacy.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>If Glazer was lauded by Bucs fans for his achievements it was a different story in England after his purchase of Manchester United in 2005.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>United are one of the world&amp;apost;s richest clubs -- behind Spanish pair Real Madrid and Barcelona in Forbes&amp;apost; most recent rich list with a value of $2.81 billion -- and are one of the globe&amp;apost;s best-supported teams.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Glazer had to borrow money to complete his takeover, the deal plunging the club into over $1 billion worth of debt overnight, and installed his sons Bryan, Joel and Avram to the board.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Protests were widespread, fans burning effigies of Glazer outside the stadium, but despite this animosity United&amp;apost;s success on the pitch endured.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Under the stewardship of Alex Ferguson, the club won five English Premier League titles after Glazer&amp;apost;s takeover, as well as the coveted European Champions League crown in 2008.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>But their fortunes nosedived after Ferguson retired at the end of the 2013/14 season.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>His replacement, David Moyes, lasted barely 10 months and was sacked with the club languishing in seventh.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Louis Van Gaal will take over after leading Netherlands to the World Cup in Brazil, with the club desperate for a top four finish next season and a return to the lucrative Champions League.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>A statement on Man Utd&amp;apost;s official website read: &amp;quot;The thoughts of everyone at Manchester United are with the Glazer family tonight following the news that Malcolm Glazer has passed away.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>He was 85.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;The news was announced earlier on the official website of the Tampa Bay Buccaneers, the NFL franchise he acquired ownership of in 1995.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;Malcolm leaves behind his wife Linda, six children and 14 grandchildren.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Staff at Manchester United extend deep and sincere condolences to them all at this difficult time.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>