<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1550" link="http://cnn.com/2014/06/23/sport/football/world-cup-brazil-cameroon-croatia-mexico-football/index.html" date_published="2014-06-23 21:53:26" category="sport" author="James Masters, CNN" highlights_mapped="false" mapping_error="false">
  <title>World Cup: Neymar inspires Brazil to victory</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6">Brazil defeats Cameroon to seal top spot in Group A.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">Host will now take on Chile in last 16 on Saturday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="7">Mexico defeats Croatia 3-1 to claim second place.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="34">Mexico faces Netherlands in knockout phase.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_time="26.454666">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">Neymar, the face of this World Cup, scored his fourth goal in three games to book his country a date with destiny and Chile in Belo Horizonte on Saturday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">His two goals and further strikes from the much maligned Fred and substitute Fernandinho ensured Brazil claimed a 4-1 win over Cameroon and secured top spot in Group A .</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="3">Mexico, which defeated Croatia 3-1, took second place and will now face the Netherlands in Fortaleza on Sunday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="34" ids_highlights="4">Mexico will now face a Dutch side which won all three of its group games and reached the final in South Africa four years ago.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Was there ever any doubt?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>When it mattered most, the man which this Brazilian team&amp;apost;s quest may depend on, delivered once again.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Neymar, the face of this World Cup, scored his fourth goal in three games to book his country a date with destiny and Chile in Belo Horizonte on Saturday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The 22-year-old, for so long hailed as the savior of Brazilian football, has not disappointed at a time where the likes of Portugal&amp;apost;s World Player of the Year Cristiano Ronaldo have flattered to deceive.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>While Lionel Messi has rescued Argentina, Neymar&amp;apost;s 35th goal in 52 international appearances gives an insight into how crucial his role is likely to be in the next few weeks should Brazil go all the way.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>His two goals and further strikes from the much maligned Fred and substitute Fernandinho ensured Brazil claimed a 4-1 win over Cameroon and secured top spot in Group A .</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Mexico, which defeated Croatia 3-1, took second place and will now face the Netherlands in Fortaleza on Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>But the night belonged to Neymar -- the man who scored the 100th goal of this tournament in his country&amp;apost;s 100th match World Cup match.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Brazil will need its talisman to provide his magic once again when it meets Chile, a team which it knocked out of the tournament four years ago in South Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Jorge Sampaoli&amp;apost;s men will represent a far more difficult proposition than a Cameroon side which briefly threatened to cause embarrassment by drawing level at 1-1.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>But Neymar, having already netted the opener, then took charge by scoring his side&amp;apost;s second and guiding Brazil home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Cameroon, thrashed 4-0 in its previous game by Croatia and already out of the tournament, was hardly supposed to represent the most difficult of challenges.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Leading through Neymar&amp;apost;s 17th minute strike, Brazil allowed Cameroon back into the contest as its cumbersome defending was once again exposed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Just minutes after Joel Matip&amp;apost;s header had been deflected onto the crossbar, Cameroon leveled to silence those packed inside the Arena Pernambuco.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Allan Nyom escaped down the right and after beating the non-existent challenge of Dani Alves, crossed for Matip to tap home from close range.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Suddenly, from a carnival of color and celebration, a dark cloud hung over Brazil&amp;apost;s World Cup dream.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>But any negativity was soon washed away by a rampant yellow swagger which ripped through the very heart of the Cameroon defense.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Neymar, the chief tormentor, was afforded far too much room and after leading the defenders a samba-like dance, he unleashed a fine effort which wrongfooted the goalkeeper.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Suddenly Brazil was rampant.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Neymar threatened a third when his powerful effort was tipped away by Charles Itandje, while Hulk failed to hit the target after a wonderful flowing move.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The interval offered little respite for Cameroon and within five minutes it fell further behind when the previously luckless Fred converted David Luiz&amp;apost;s cross to net his first goal of the tournament.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Fernandinho, the Manchester City midfielder, added a fourth with six minutes remaining to ensure Brazil finished top on goal difference from Mexico.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;Maybe we tried to hurry things a bit too much early on, when we scored our first goal and let anxiety get to us,&amp;quot; Brazil&amp;apost;s coach Luiz Felipe Scolari said after the match.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;We need to show more calm and composure.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Fortunately we ironed out some flaws at half-time and after the break we used the ball better again.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>El Tri had threatened to usurp the host nation at the top of the table after putting Croatia to the sword in Recife.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>After a goalless first half, Rafael Marquez, the first man to captain his country at four World Cups, headed Mexico in front with 18 minutes remaining.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Andres Guardado rounded off a slick counter attack soon after to double his side&amp;apost;s advantage before Manchester United star Javier Hernandez added a third.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>It was a just reward for Mexico, which hit the crossbar in the first half and was denied what appeared to be a blatant penalty with the game still goalless.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;(We&amp;apost;ll) have a few more great days yet,&amp;quot; Miguel Herrera, the Mexico manager said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;There is still room for improvement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>We stayed calm and maintained our focus, that was the key to success.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Croatia, which could have qualified with a victory, pulled a goal back through Ivan Perisic but was then reduced to 10 men when Ante Rebic was sent off.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Mexico will now face a Dutch side which won all three of its group games and reached the final in South Africa four years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>