<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1428" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/04/11/sport/football/champions-league-semifinal-draw/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-04-11 10:51:02" category="sport" author="" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Bayern Munich to face Real Madrid, Atletico to meet Chelsea</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Real Madrid and Bayern Munich paired together in the European Champions League semifinals.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="17">Atletico Madrid and Chelsea to meet in the other last four tie.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">Bayern looking to become the first team to defend the Champions League title.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="2">The final will take place in the Portuguese capital of Lisbon on May 24.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-27 17:04:29" annotation_time="31.887">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Two European football heavyweights will collide in the UEFA Champions League semifinals after Bayern Munich and Real Madrid were drawn together in Switzerland on Friday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="4">Bayern, winners of the competition last season, and nine-time champions Real will both be looking to book a place in the final, which will take place in Lisbon on May 24.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">German champions Bayern are looking to become the first team to defend the European Cup in the post-1992 Champions League era.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="2">While Chelsea are appearing in the semifinals for the seventh time in the last 11 seasons, Atletico haven&amp;apost;t reached this stage since 1974.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Two European football heavyweights will collide in the UEFA Champions League semifinals after Bayern Munich and Real Madrid were drawn together in Switzerland on Friday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Bayern, winners of the competition last season, and nine-time champions Real will both be looking to book a place in the final, which will take place in Lisbon on May 24.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The other semifinal paired Real&amp;apost;s city rivals Atletico Madrid with Chelsea, who lifted the trophy for the first time in their history in 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The semifinal first leg matches will take place on April 22-23, with the ties concluding with the second legs on April 28-29.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>German champions Bayern are looking to become the first team to defend the European Cup in the post-1992 Champions League era.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Led by former Barcelona coach Josep Guardiola, Bayern fought from behind to defeat Manchester United on Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Real will appear in the semifinals of Europe&amp;apost;s premier club competition for the 25th time in their illustrious history, with Cristiano Ronaldo and co. out to secure Los Blancos a record 10th triumph.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Carlo Ancelotti&amp;apost;s team survived a spirited comeback from Borussia Dortmund on Wednesday to reach the last four with a 3-2 aggregate win.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The two teams met at the same stage of the competition in 2012, with Bayern prevailing after a nerve-shredding penalty shootout.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Bayern went on to lose to Chelsea in the final two years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The London club&amp;apost;s manager Jose Mourinho is bidding to win the tournament with a third different club after previous successes with Porto in 2004 and Inter Milan in 2010.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Chelsea needed a late goal from striker Demba Ba to register an away-goals win over Paris Saint-Germain in the last eight.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Atletico Madrid could be without the services of goalkeeper Thibaut Courtois, who is on-loan at the Vicente Calderon stadium from Chelsea.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Rumors surfaced on Thursday that an agreement between the two teams meant Courtois would only be able to play in both matches against his parent club if Atletico pay Chelsea €6 million ($8.3 million.).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>European football&amp;apost;s governing body UEFA announced Friday that any such agreement would be &amp;quot;null, void and unenforceable.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;Furthermore, any attempt to enforce such a provision would be a clear violation of both the UEFA Champions League and the UEFA Disciplinary Regulations and would therefore be sanctioned accordingly,&amp;quot; read a statement from the organization.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>While Chelsea are appearing in the semifinals for the seventh time in the last 11 seasons, Atletico haven&amp;apost;t reached this stage since 1974.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Atletico&amp;apost;s coach Diego Simeone has led something of a renaissance at the club, leading them to the top of the Spanish league table with just six games left of the campaign.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>A goal from talented playmaker Koke was enough to see off four-time European champions Barcelona in Tuesday&amp;apost;s quarterfinal second leg.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
