<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1489" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/03/13/sport/obama-basketball/index.html" date_published="2012-03-13 07:08:51" category="sport" author="Lateef Mungin, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Obama, Cameron to go to basketball game</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">There will be two games played in Ohio on Tuesday, tipping off the NCAA tournament.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">The two leaders will conduct a joint interview at halftime of the first game.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">Obama also launched an NCAA bracket challenge on his campaign website.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-11 14:40:11" annotation_time="29.803001">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">There will be two games tipping off the tournament in Dayton, Ohio, a swing state.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">During halftime of the first game, Western Kentucky versus Mississippi Valley State, the two leaders will conduct a joint interview.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">The leaders&amp;apost; trip to the game comes as Obama launched his new tournament &amp;quot;bracket challenge&amp;quot; on his campaign website.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>President Barack Obama, a well-known basketball fan, will treat British Prime Minister David Cameron to a little March Madness Tuesday as the two head to Ohio to catch an NCAA men&amp;apost;s tournament basketball game.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>There will be two games tipping off the tournament in Dayton, Ohio, a swing state.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>During halftime of the first game, Western Kentucky versus Mississippi Valley State, the two leaders will conduct a joint interview.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The leaders&amp;apost; trip to the game comes as Obama launched his new tournament &amp;quot;bracket challenge&amp;quot; on his campaign website.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Obama is asking those who visit the website to predict who will win the college basketball championship and to compare their picks against his.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s college basketball time again - and as friends and co-workers gather around the water cooler to talk top seeds and Cinderellas, here&amp;apost;s your chance to fill out a bracket with the President himself,&amp;quot; the website says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The site promises to publish the names of anyone who does better than the president once the tournament is over.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Obama has publicly picked brackets in years past, drawing heat from Republicans last year for appearing in an ESPN segment to unveil his picks in March 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>RNC spokeswoman Kirsten Kukowski said the White House should &amp;quot;explain why filming an ESPN special on the NCAA tournament should be a priority on his public schedule.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Before revealing the picks, the president did urge viewers to go to usaid.gov to donate to charities that were assisting in the aftermath of the earthquake and tsunami that had devastated Japan that month.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>For the record, Obama picked Kansas, Duke, Ohio State, Pitt for his 2011 final four and chose Kansas to take the championship.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>It didn&amp;apost;t.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>UConn won, beating Butler.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>It is unclear if Obama would reveal this year&amp;apost;s picks during his interview with Cameron on Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>But Cameron&amp;apost;s visit will not be all fun and games.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>On Wednesday, the two leaders will be back in Washington conducting extensive meetings about a range of topics including Afghanistan and Syria, the White House said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;There&amp;apost;s a strong working relationship and actually even a strong personal bond between Prime Minister Cameron and President Obama,&amp;quot; White House deputy press secretary Josh Earnest said last week.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;We maintain a special and a essential friendship and partnership with the government and people of the United Kingdom.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The United Kingdom is our NATO ally and our closest partner in the world.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>On Tuesday, the two co-authored an op-ed piece in the Washington Post titled &amp;quot; An alliance the world can count on.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;The alliance between the United States and Great Britain is a partnership of the heart, bound by the history, traditions and values we share.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>But what makes our relationship special - a unique and essential asset - is that we join hands across so many endeavors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Put simply, we count on each other and the world counts on our alliance,&amp;quot; the leaders said in the article.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
