<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1483" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/01/30/sport/motorsport/motorsport-schumacher-reduced-sedation/index.html" date_published="2014-01-30 12:09:04" category="sport" author="" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Michael Schumacher: Doctors start &amp;apost;waking up process&amp;apost;</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Doctors reduce Michael Schumacher&amp;apost;s sedation to start &amp;apost;waking up process&amp;apost;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Former F1 world champion has been in a medically-induced coma for a month.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">45-year-old suffered a severe head injury when skiing in France in late December.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-14 13:34:48" annotation_time="42.67267">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1, 2">He has been in a medically induced coma for over a month, but former Formula 1 world champion Michael Schumacher&amp;apost;s sedation is being reduced to start the &amp;quot;waking up process,&amp;quot; his agent said Thursday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="3">Schumacher suffered severe head trauma in a skiing accident at the French Alps resort of Meribel on December 29.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>He has been in a medically induced coma for over a month, but former Formula 1 world champion Michael Schumacher&amp;apost;s sedation is being reduced to start the &amp;quot;waking up process,&amp;quot; his agent said Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Schumacher suffered severe head trauma in a skiing accident at the French Alps resort of Meribel on December 29.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The announcement marks a key change to Schumacher&amp;apost;s condition, which has been routinely described as &amp;quot;stable&amp;quot; by agent Sabine Kehm in recent weeks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;Michael&amp;apost;s sedation is being reduced in order to allow the start of the waking up process which may take a long time,&amp;quot; she said in a statement on Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;For the protection of the family, it was originally agreed by the interested parties to communicate this information only once this process was consolidated.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;Please note that no further updates will be given.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Kehm went on to repeat previous requests for the media to respect the privacy of Schumacher&amp;apost;s family.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;The family of Michael Schumacher is again requesting to respect its privacy and the medical secret, and to not disturb the doctors treating Michael in their work.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>At the same time, the family wishes to express sincere appreciation for the worldwide sympathy.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>A seven-time world champion whose F1 career ended in 2012, Schumacher has been treated in Grenoble since his accident.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Neurosurgeons there operated twice to remove blood clots on the brain and reduce swelling, the reason he has been kept asleep since the surgery.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The German has been inundated with support from around the world during his stay, with his former stable Mercedes running the message &amp;quot;Keep Fighting Michael&amp;quot; on its silver livery when they revealed their new car for testing on Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The Ferrari team, who Schumacher raced for between 1996 and 2006, also showed their support for their five-time world champion this week in the Spanish city Jerez, where teams are conducting winter testing ahead of the new F1 season.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>On the eve of the first day of testing, the team&amp;apost;s crew posed with a pit board showing the message &amp;quot;Forza Michael&amp;quot; while the new F14-T scarlet racer made its track debut with the same words of encouragement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>On Tuesday, the team published a note from Niki Lauda, who won two world championships for Ferrari in the 1970s, which read: &amp;quot;Michael, every day I follow your improvements and every day I am close to you.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>I hope I can speak to you very, very soon!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Ferrari driver Fernando Alonso told CNN that F1 was &amp;quot;still in shock&amp;quot; over Schumacher&amp;apost;s accident and condition.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;The day that I received the news I could not believe it to be honest,&amp;quot; Alonso, who was speaking in Madrid on Wednesday at an exhibition that charts the course of the driver&amp;apost;s career.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;He was the man that can beat anything and can win any race and can do anything without any worries, so to see him and to see the accident ...</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re all hoping every day to have some good news coming from the hospital,&amp;quot; added Alonso.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>In early January, a French prosecutor investigating the accident said that speed was not a reason for Schumacher&amp;apost;s fall.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>His investigative team believe the experienced skier hit a rock hidden beneath the snow, while traversing an area between two marked pistes, which catapulted him face first onto another rock.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Schumacher ended up 9 meters (30 feet) from the edge of the piste, said prosecutor Patrick Quincy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Footage filmed on a small camera attached to Schumacher&amp;apost;s helmet has been used to help the investigators&amp;apost; analysis.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
