<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1542" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/01/03/sport/football/vilanova-barcelona-cruyff-football/index.html" date_published="2013-01-03 12:29:45" category="sport" author="" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Vilanova returns as Barca get back to work</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Tito Vilanova returns to Barcelona training ground after operation to remove a tumor.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">The Barca coach had a tumor removed from his parotid gland on December 20.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">Vilanova visited players ahead of the match between Catalan national team and Nigeria.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="3">Barca continuing their charge towards the Spanish title against Espanyol on Sunday.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-26 11:13:26" annotation_time="146.5675">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Barcelona coach Tito Vilanova has returned to the Catalan club&amp;apost;s training ground just two weeks after undergoing surgery to remove a tumor from his throat.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">Vilanova suffered a recurrence of a tumor on his parotid gland -- located at the back of the mouth -- and was released from hospital on December 22.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="4">The former assistant coach, who replaced Josep Guardiola in June, returned to training on Wednesday ahead of the Spanish league leaders&amp;apost; derby match with Espanyol on Sunday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">Vilanova also dropped in on the Catalan national team -- featuring nine Barca players -- as it prepared for a friendly match with Nigeria.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Barcelona coach Tito Vilanova has returned to the Catalan club&amp;apost;s training ground just two weeks after undergoing surgery to remove a tumor from his throat.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Vilanova suffered a recurrence of a tumor on his parotid gland -- located at the back of the mouth -- and was released from hospital on December 22.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The former assistant coach, who replaced Josep Guardiola in June, returned to training on Wednesday ahead of the Spanish league leaders&amp;apost; derby match with Espanyol on Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Vilanova also dropped in on the Catalan national team -- featuring nine Barca players -- as it prepared for a friendly match with Nigeria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;The manager ... led the team&amp;apost;s second training session of the year,&amp;quot; read a statement on the club&amp;apost;s official website.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;This morning, Vilanova stopped by the Ciutat Esportiva to meet with the Catalan players ahead of this afternoon&amp;apost;s Catalonia vs. Nigeria match.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Barca president Sandro Rosell said last weekend he hoped Vilanova would be fit to return to work in two-to-three weeks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Despite not being recognized by football&amp;apost;s global governing body FIFA, a squad made up entirely of Catalan players occasionally plays exhibition matches.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The team, led by Dutch former Barca player and coach Johan Cruyff, was held to a 1-1 draw by Nigeria at the Camp Nou.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Midfielder Sergio Gonzalez, without a club since being released by Levante in 2011, gave the Catalan team the lead from the penalty spot after three minutes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>But Nigeria earned a draw when U.S.-born Portland Timbers striker Bright Dike equalized after 55 minutes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Super Eagles coach Stephen Keshi is preparing Nigeria for this month&amp;apost;s 2013 African Cup of Nations in South Africa, where the two-time tournament winners have been drawn in a group with 2012 champions Zambia, Burkina Faso and Mali.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Barca goalkeeper Victor Valdes picked up an injury in the match which will see him sit out training on Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Vilanova&amp;apost;s team, under the temporary guidance of assistant Jordi Roura, is looking to continue a run which saw them pick up a record 16 wins from their first 17 league matches of the season.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The Espanyol tie will see Argentine star Lionel Messi take to the field for the first time this year, after a record-breaking 2012 which saw him score 91 goals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Barca currently lead second-placed Atletico Madrid, who face Mallorca on Sunday, by nine points, with archrivals Real Madrid a further seven points back.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Cruyff described Real&amp;apost;s start to the season as a &amp;quot;failure&amp;quot;, while also questioning coach Jose Mourinho&amp;apost;s decision to drop Spanish international goalkeeper Iker Casillas.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;At this stage of the season Real Madrid being 16 points behind Barcelona can only be called a failure,&amp;quot; Cruyff was reported to have said by Spanish newspaper Marca.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>On Mourinho favoring Antonio Adan over World Cup winner Casillas, Cruyff commented: &amp;quot;You don&amp;apost;t lose your place overnight.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Real host Real Sociedad on Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
