<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1421" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/05/19/sport/motorsport/formula-one-jack-brabham-dead/index.html" date_published="2014-05-19 08:29:10" category="sport" author="Tim Hume, CNN and Matt Majendie, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Australian F1 legend Jack Brabham dies at 88</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Australian Formula One legend Jack Brabham has died aged 88.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="23">Brabham is the only driver to win the title in a car he built himself.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">He won three drivers&amp;apost; world championships and founded a successful racing team.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="23">McLaren boss Ron Dennis said his achievements would never be matched.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-28 10:53:32" annotation_time="185.195">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Australian motor racing legend Jack Brabham -- a three-time Formula One world champion and the only driver to win the title in a car bearing his name -- has died aged 88.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="3">Over the course of a 15-year Formula One career beginning in 1955, Brabham won three drivers&amp;apost; world championships, becoming the first Australian to win the title despite coming late to the sport.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="2, 4">Dennis paid tribute to the man who gave him his first break in a statement on McLaren&amp;apost;s website, calling him &amp;quot;one of the most illustrious names in motor racing history&amp;quot; and said Brabham&amp;apost;s achievement in becoming Formula One champion in a car he built himself &amp;quot;will surely never be matched.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Australian motor racing legend Jack Brabham -- a three-time Formula One world champion and the only driver to win the title in a car bearing his name -- has died aged 88.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Over the course of a 15-year Formula One career beginning in 1955, Brabham won three drivers&amp;apost; world championships, becoming the first Australian to win the title despite coming late to the sport.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The first two titles, in 1959 and 1960, were earned as a driver for the Cooper team.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The third and most notable occurred in 1966, when, at 40-years-old, he won racing for Brabham, the successful car manufacturer and racing team he founded.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The team won the constructors&amp;apost; championships that season and the following year, with teammate Denny Hulme following in Brabham&amp;apost;s footsteps to finish top of the drivers&amp;apost; standings in 1967.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;He lived an incredible life, achieving more than anyone would ever dream of and he will continue to live on through the astounding legacy he leaves behind,&amp;quot; Brabham&amp;apost;s youngest son, David, wrote in a message on the family&amp;apost;s website.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>David, who, like his two brothers, followed his father into a career in motorsport, said the racing legend had passed peacefully at his home on Australia&amp;apost;s Gold Coast.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>He had eaten breakfast with his wife, Lady Margaret.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s a very sad day for all of us,&amp;quot; said David, who spent two seasons in F1 in the 1990s but made a name for himself in sports cars, winning the 24 Hours of Le Mans in 2009.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Australian Prime Minister Tony Abbott declared that &amp;quot;Australia has lost a legend&amp;quot; as the news of his passing was announced.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;With his pioneering spirit, Sir Jack Brabham personified many great Australian characteristics.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>He was respected and admired for his spirit and for his great skill as an engineer.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Late bloomer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The son of a Sydney greengrocer, Jack Brabham was an engineer by trade, working as a flight mechanic for the Royal Australian Air Force during the Second World War, as well as running a small engineering workshop.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>He moved to Britain to pursue his racing career in the 1950s, and was eventually given his chance behind the wheel by Cooper in 1955, his appearance in the cockpit coinciding with the end of front-engined cars in the sport.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Four years later, he won the first of his three drivers&amp;apost; crowns, famously sealing his 1959 victory in the driver&amp;apost;s championship by pushing his car to the finishing line after having run out of fuel on the last lap at the inaugural U.S. Grand Prix.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>He finished the race in fourth place to secure the title.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Brabham retired at the end of the 1970 season, the year of his 14th and final grand prix victory, selling his racing team at the same time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>In 1979, he became the first driver to be knighted for services to motorsport.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Brabham, the team he founded with Australian designer Ron Tauranac, won four Formula One drivers&amp;apost; championships and two constructors&amp;apost; championships during its three decades in operation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Noted figures associated with the team included Hulme, Nelson Piquet, Bernie Ecclestone and McLaren chairman and CEO Ron Dennis.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;apost;Most illustrious&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Dennis paid tribute to the man who gave him his first break in a statement on McLaren&amp;apost;s website, calling him &amp;quot;one of the most illustrious names in motor racing history&amp;quot; and said Brabham&amp;apost;s achievement in becoming Formula One champion in a car he built himself &amp;quot;will surely never be matched.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;The word &amp;apost;legend&amp;apost; is often used to describe successful sportsmen, but often it exaggerates their status.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>In the case of Sir Jack Brabham, however, it&amp;apost;s entirely justified,&amp;quot; he wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;When I started out in Formula One in the late 1960s, I worked first for Cooper and then for Brabham.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Even as a callow youth, I could recognize greatness when I saw it, and I&amp;apost;ll always regard it as an honor and a privilege to have worked for Sir Jack.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>I learned a lot from him too.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Mick Doohan, a five-time motorcycle world champion, said he was in awe of Brabham&amp;apost;s achievements.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;He set the bar pretty high,&amp;quot; said Doohan.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;He was a great guy and, looking back on what he achieved, it was just amazing.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Red Bull racer Daniel Ricciardo tweeted: &amp;quot;Sorry to hear about Sir Jack Brabham.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>A great Australian who inspired many Aussies to pursue our dreams.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Australian actor Eric Bana, himself a keen racer, also paid his respects.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;Build them, race them, win them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>We will never see another like the great Sir Jack Brabham,&amp;quot; he tweeted.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
