<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1493" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/02/11/sport/football/qatar-2022-workers-charter-football/index.html" date_published="2014-02-11 15:57:29" category="sport" author="" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Qatar 2022: Will new charter protect migrant workers at World Cup?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Qatar&amp;apost;s World Cup 2022 organizers adopt a &amp;apost;workers&amp;apost; charter&amp;apost;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Charter is response to criticism of treatment of migrant workers on building projects.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">FIFA set Qatar a deadline of February 12 to update on improvements.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="13, 10">Critics say Qatar&amp;apost;s &amp;apost;kafala&amp;apost; system needs to be reformed.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 16:08:19" annotation_time="49.886" mapping_time_divergence="12.4715">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1, 2">Organizers of the 2022 World Cup in Qatar have responded to criticism over the plight of migrant workers on stadia and infrastructure projects by saying Tuesday that &amp;quot;tangible progress&amp;quot; had been made in addressing widespread concerns over their welfare.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">FIFA had set the Qatari authorities a deadline of February 12 to give an update on measures to improve conditions for workers.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="4">Nicholas McGeehan, the Gulf researcher of Human Rights Watch, one of the most trenchant critics of the Qatari government, told CNN that its authorities &amp;quot;deserve credit for its efforts to improve standards on the projects within its control&amp;quot; -- but he urged caution.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="4">McGeehan&amp;apost;s call echoes that of other human rights groups for an end to practices under the kafala system, which ties workers to their employer and stops them leaving the country without their permission.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Organizers of the 2022 World Cup in Qatar have responded to criticism over the plight of migrant workers on stadia and infrastructure projects by saying Tuesday that &amp;quot;tangible progress&amp;quot; had been made in addressing widespread concerns over their welfare.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>They published an updated 50-page &amp;quot;workers&amp;apost; charter&amp;quot; -- developed in consultation with the International Labor Organization -- detailing measures to improve wages, accommodation as well as promising regular inspections.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>FIFA had set the Qatari authorities a deadline of February 12 to give an update on measures to improve conditions for workers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Theo Zwanziger, a senior member of the world governing body&amp;apost;s executive committee, is to report its findings to the European parliament Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Zahir Belounis, a French Algerian striker who was trapped in Qatar after a dispute with his club, is also to due to appear to give his perspective.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>FIFA acted after its president Sepp Blatter condemned working conditions in the Gulf state as &amp;quot;unacceptable&amp;quot; as he responded to damning reports last year from Amnesty International and the International Trade Union Confederation (ITUC).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>They detailed systematic abuse and the ITUC claimed that fatal construction injuries were eight times higher in Qatar than other developed nations, with migrant workers from India and Nepal the worst affected.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;apost;We have always believed that Qatar&amp;apost;s hosting of the World Cup would be a catalyst to accelerate positive initiatives, already being undertaken by Qatar, which will leave a legacy of enhanced, sustainable and meaningful progress in regards to worker welfare across the country,&amp;quot; said Hassan Al Thawadi, the secretary general of Qatar&amp;apost;s Supreme Committee for Delivery and Legacy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;We already see this progress taking place across Qatar on a daily basis, and will continue to work hard to make our vision become the ever-present reality on the ground.&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Nicholas McGeehan, the Gulf researcher of Human Rights Watch, one of the most trenchant critics of the Qatari government, told CNN that its authorities &amp;quot;deserve credit for its efforts to improve standards on the projects within its control&amp;quot; -- but he urged caution.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;They not guaranteeing workers&amp;apost; rights to change employer, or their right to leave the country or their right to bargain collectively for decent pay and conditions if things go wrong.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;If the Qatari government is serious about reform it should apply these standards to the whole migrant worker population, back them up with sanctions, and get to work on reform of the kafala system.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>McGeehan&amp;apost;s call echoes that of other human rights groups for an end to practices under the kafala system, which ties workers to their employer and stops them leaving the country without their permission.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>It has been compared with modern-day slavery and was highlighted by the Belounis affair, the footballer who was unable to leave Qatar following a pay dispute with his club side El Jaish and was left stranded in the country with his family for two years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Despite threatening a hunger strike and suicide, Belounis, who eventually flew home to France last November, has told CNN that the Gulf state still deserves the right to stage the World Cup.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Qatar is spending a reported $200 billion on infrastucture and building projects associated with its staging of football&amp;apost;s global showpiece, but work has only just started on one of the stadiums to be used.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Only 38 workers are currently employed at the Al Wakrah Stadium, where a &amp;quot;successful inspection&amp;quot; was held January 13, according to the organizers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>They said that they would be meeting representatives from other building projects in the &amp;quot;coming months&amp;quot; to achieve a &amp;quot;unified standard&amp;quot; across the whole of Qatar for migrant workers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;apost;We will continue to work closely with our partners to achieve practical solutions which will leave a sustainable legacy for Qatar long after 2022,&amp;apost; said Farah Al-Muftah, who chairs the Supreme Committee&amp;apost;s Workers&amp;apost; Welfare Committee.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>But critics pointed out it is unclear what projects are covered by the new charter and which are under the control of the Supreme Committee.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s not the state-led, cross-sector regulation that Qatar&amp;apost;s migrant workers desperately need,&amp;quot; said McGeehan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>FIFA has also still to decide the actual dates for the 2022 World Cup after fears that the searing heat in Qatar in the summer will be dangerous for players and spectators.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>There have been widespread calls for a &amp;quot;Winter World Cup&amp;quot; and FIFA says it&amp;apost;s consulting stakeholders, including the major European leagues, before making a final decision.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
