<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1496" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/03/20/sport/football/qatar-2022-world-cup-vote-football/index.html?hpt=hp_mid" date_published="2014-03-20 11:14:35" category="sport" author="Piers Edwards, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Qatar World Cup 2022: FIFA reformer calls for vote rerun</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Former FIFA insider calls for a fresh vote on the 2022 World Cup.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">The tournament was awarded to Qatar following a FIFA ballot in December 2010.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="13">Alexandra Wrage says rerunning the vote is the only way to restore confidence in the World Cup.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="18">Former New York attorney Michael Garcia is investigating allegations of corruption around the vote.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-27 17:06:52" annotation_time="25.835">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Leading former FIFA insider Alexandra Wrage is calling for a new vote over the selection of the 2022 World Cup hosts given the ongoing controversy surrounding the decision to award Qatar the event.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">Without any football pedigree and despite concerns over staging the world&amp;apost;s most prestigious tournament in a desert climate, the Middle East nation emerged as the surprise winner of the vote by FIFA&amp;apost;S Executive Committee in December 2010, when beating the United States in a 14-8 vote in the decisive round.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;The only way to restore confidence in the World Cup selection process is to rerun the vote,&amp;quot; Wrage, the president of non-profit international anti-bribery group Trace, told CNN.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="4">FIFA&amp;apost;s Ethics Committee, headed by the former United States attorney for the Southern District of New York -- Michael Garcia -- is also busy, currently investigating allegations of corruption regarding the vote for the 2022 World Cup site.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Leading former FIFA insider Alexandra Wrage is calling for a new vote over the selection of the 2022 World Cup hosts given the ongoing controversy surrounding the decision to award Qatar the event.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Without any football pedigree and despite concerns over staging the world&amp;apost;s most prestigious tournament in a desert climate, the Middle East nation emerged as the surprise winner of the vote by FIFA&amp;apost;S Executive Committee in December 2010, when beating the United States in a 14-8 vote in the decisive round.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The choice has raised far more questions than answers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Notably regarding the season in which the World Cup would be played.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>There has been repeated talk of switching the tournament to winter in a bid to avoid the sweltering heat of Qatar&amp;apost;s summers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>FIFA president Sepp Blatter has also admitted that the vote to decide both the 2018 and 2022 World Cups led to possible collusion among bidding nations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Another issue has been many allegations of corruption -- with the latest surrounding former FIFA official, Jack Warner, which were revealed earlier this week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The Qatari World Cup committee as well as prominent FIFA officials have steadfastly denied the allegations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>But the questions prompted FIFA to create an Independent Governance Committee (IGC) in 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The aim was for the IGC to propose methods to restore the reputation of football&amp;apost;s global body.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Yet former member Wrage -- an anti-corruption authority who resigned in April 2013 over frustration at what she described as FIFA&amp;apost;s resistance to reform -- believes drastic action is needed to correct the decision to award the tournament to Qatar.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Even current Executive Committee member Theo Zwanziger has described it as a &amp;quot;blatant mistake.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;The only way to restore confidence in the World Cup selection process is to rerun the vote,&amp;quot; Wrage, the president of non-profit international anti-bribery group Trace, told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;Having said that, I don&amp;apost;t expect it to happen and expect, instead, that the process will be further contorted with a controversial move to winter and a great deal of stalling and shifting on the human rights issues raised by the selection of Qatar.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The treatment of migrant construction workers toiling around the clock to deliver new stadiums and, in some cases, whole new cities ahead of the finals has been another unwanted aspect of FIFA&amp;apost;s decision to hand the finals to Qatar.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The global body has since tasked Germany&amp;apost;s Zwanziger with addressing the convoluted issue of labor rights in Qatar.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>A report is expected at this week&amp;apost;s FIFA conference in Zurich, which starts on Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>FIFA&amp;apost;s Ethics Committee, headed by the former United States attorney for the Southern District of New York -- Michael Garcia -- is also busy, currently investigating allegations of corruption regarding the vote for the 2022 World Cup site.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The American may have more paperwork to sift through after a British newspaper published a damning story this week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The Daily Telegraph claims a company owned by former Executive Committee member Jack Warner invoiced one owned by Qatar&amp;apost;s former FIFA vice-president and Asian football chief Mohammed Bin Hammam for a substantial sum of funds within a month of the 2022 voting decision.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;I have no comment to make on any article -- but feel free to write whatever you wish,&amp;quot; Warner told CNN in response to the claims.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Qatar&amp;apost;s 2022 World Cup Organising Committee has also issued a statement to refute the allegations made in the Daily Telegraph on Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;The 2022 Bid Committee strictly adhered to FIFA&amp;apost;s bidding regulations in compliance with their code of ethics,&amp;quot; it read.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Supreme Committee for Delivery &amp;amp; Legacy and the individuals involved in the 2022 Bid Committee are unaware of any allegations surrounding business dealings between private individuals.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Amidst the constant questioning over the decision to take the World Cup to the Middle East for the first time since the competition started in 1930, Wrage believes more still needs to be done by FIFA.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;To restore confidence, the public needs to see a serious and broad investigation of all allegations - with prompt and meaningful consequences for any wrongdoing,&amp;quot; she argues.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;In spite of some recent governance improvements, there is still a widespread sense that FIFA provides far too little transparency.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Shortly after her resignation from the IGC, Wrage wrote a piece for Forbes.com stating her belief that the &amp;quot;only entity capable of insisting on transparency at FIFA is the Swiss government.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>This came after FIFA rejected proposals from the IGC to introduce two members to the Executive Committee who were independent as well as a compromise proposal that the Chairman of FIFA&amp;apost;s Audit Committee should be an independent observer at all ExCo meetings.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Seeking comment, CNN contacted the four other nations beaten by Qatar: the U.S., Australia, South Korea and Japan.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Only the latter replied, saying that it &amp;quot;does not have a comment on a supposition.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Australia has previously said it will pursue compensation if the 2022 finals are switched from summer to winter months.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
