<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1544" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/03/03/sport/tennis/amelie-mauresmo-wimbledon-france-tennis/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-03-03 14:11:23" category="sport" author="Chris Murphy, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Wine maker and entrepreneur: What Amelie Mauresmo did next</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="22">Amelie Mauresmo is still immersed in world of tennis four years after retirement.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Frenchwoman won two grand slam titles in a 15-year professional career.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">She now is France&amp;apost;s Fed Cup captain and is a tournament director in Paris.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="1">Mauresmo hopes to have second life away from tennis, indulging her passion for wine.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-10 13:28:29" annotation_time="130.30667">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="4"> Amelie Mauresmo wants a second life -- one away from tennis.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">After calling time on an illustrious playing career with two grand slams safely tucked away, the Frenchwoman is arguably just as entrenched in the game as she ever was.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">Mauresmo is currently juggling roles as tournament director in Paris and captain of France&amp;apost;s Fed Cup team, alongside coaching and commentating stints.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="1">Fast forward five years and Mauresmo is still intrinsically linked with tennis.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Amelie Mauresmo wants a second life -- one away from tennis.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>After calling time on an illustrious playing career with two grand slams safely tucked away, the Frenchwoman is arguably just as entrenched in the game as she ever was.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Mauresmo is currently juggling roles as tournament director in Paris and captain of France&amp;apost;s Fed Cup team, alongside coaching and commentating stints.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>But the 34-year knows there will come a time when she walks away from the court once and for all, hopefully in the direction of her own vineyard.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;To be lucky enough to have lived one passion -- tennis -- is great but to learn many things and meet new people in a completely different area, atmosphere and world, why not?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>she tells CNN&amp;apost;s Open Court show.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;I have a high passion that is wine; I am a wine lover, I have a big wine cellar.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;I read a lot of things about wine from around the world and different regions in France.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>I check sometimes with friends of mine about the wine chateaus that are for sale.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>A world away from the tranquil vines associated with France&amp;apost;s verdant valleys is the slog of the professional tennis circuit -- Mauresmo&amp;apost;s home for well over a decade.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>As well as clinching those two major championships in 2006 -- the Australian Open and Wimbledon crowns -- she attained the coveted world No. 1 spot on several occasions and won a silver medal the 2004 Olympics.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>But when injuries began to mount in 2009 and Mauresmo took the decision to quit the court, a whole new world presented itself to her.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;It was the pressure,&amp;quot; she explains.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;The pressure that came out of my shoulders was huge.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>I was finally able to live a normal life, let&amp;apost;s say, to enjoy the things that I could not enjoy before.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;I also felt that I achieved as a tennis player everything that I could have done, so I think it made it quite easy for me to take the step out of it and to do other things.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;Honestly I was scared.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>(I thought) &amp;apost;What am I going to do?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Is it going to be exciting enough?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>How exactly is it going to be?&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;You are going into something and you have no clue what it is ... and I am really happy, I don&amp;apost;t regret anything.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Fast forward five years and Mauresmo is still intrinsically linked with tennis.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>In 2011 she was named tournament director of the GDF Suez Open in Paris, a competition she won three times as a player, before accepting the role of captain of France&amp;apost;s national women&amp;apost;s team in July 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Mauresmo has a special place in her heart for the Fed Cup -- the female equivalent of the Davis Cup -- having won it in 2003, triumphing in all eight of her singles rubbers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Alize Cornet, one of those involved in France&amp;apost;s Group II win over Switzerland last month, says Mauresmo is the best captain she has ever played for.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>She has also had success in her short coaching career, helping propel Marion Bartoli to the 2013 Wimbledon title before her compatriot&amp;apost;s shock decision to quit the sport.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>With 25 career singles titles to her name, and over $15 million accrued in prize money, Mauresmo&amp;apost;s name was, and still is, indelibly marked into the fabric of the women&amp;apost;s game.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;Tennis was all my life for 20 years,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;I owe so much to tennis as a person also because I really grew up and learned many things, I was talking earlier about the relationships with people and the strong connections that you get.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;I love that also to go on this journey but not alone -- really having people next to me, beside me, guiding me, learning from them, listening to them and giving them some things -- the exchange and the connection you have is quite interesting.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;And on the sports side you develop the competitiveness that you have inside of you, you really let it out.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s an obsessive thing to be a professional athlete, it&amp;apost;s something you think about all the time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s everything you do, how you eat, how you sleep, what time you go to bed, the activities you do outside.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s all related with your tennis and it&amp;apost;s something that is really taking all your life, and I also enjoyed it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;It was a relief when it stopped but throughout your career it was really fulfilling you, and it&amp;apost;s quite interesting.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Given the knowledge and experience she has, tennis will miss Mauresmo when she departs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>And when she does, what memory from her playing days will she treasure most?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;Wimbledon in 2006,&amp;quot; she replies, recalling a final in which she rallied from a set down to beat Justine Henin -- who had denied her Olympic gold in Athens -- and become the first Frenchwoman to win the prestigious title since Suzanne Lenglen in 1925.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;It was really the emotion, the exhilaration the relief, being so proud of what I did,&amp;quot; Mauresmo adds.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;It was a feeling you really keep in yourself, you are not thinking about it every day in your life but it&amp;apost;s something that belongs to you and you cherish.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;Getting a medal in the Olympics is huge, winning the Fed Cup for my country, being number one in the world also is an amazing achievement, all those things but yes I would put Wimbledon on top.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Follow us at @WorldSportCNN and like us on Facebook.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>