<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1511" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/06/25/sport/saudia-arabia-olympic-women/index.html" date_published="2012-06-25 06:34:06" category="sport" author="the CNN Wire Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Saudi Arabia to let women compete in Olympics for first time</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="15">One Saudi athlete praises the decision as &amp;quot;a dream come true&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="20">Saudi Arabian schools don&amp;apost;t have physical ed classes for girls.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="24">Qatar and Brunei will also send women for the first time.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="7">The decision is a rare concession for a kingdom where women cannot drive or vote.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-27 17:20:37" annotation_time="19.122">
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="4">The decision is a rare concession for a kingdom where women are banned from driving.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="1">Dalma Rushdi Malhas, who became the first Saudi woman to compete in the Youth Olympics, praised the decision, calling it &amp;quot;a dream come true.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="2">In 2009 and 2010, the country closed private gyms for women, and its schools&amp;apost; curriculum does not include physical education classes for women, the rights group said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="3">For its part, Qatar will send three women to London this year: a shooter, a swimmer and a runner.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Saudi Arabia will let its female athletes compete in the Olympics for the first time, its embassy in London said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Until now, Saudi Arabia was one of three countries that did not allow women to participate in the games.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The other two -- Qatar and Brunei -- also reversed course this year and said they will send female athletes to the London games, which begin July 27.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Kingdom of Saudi Arabia wishes to reaffirm its support for the sublime meanings reflected by Olympic Games and the cherished values of excellence, friendship and respect that they represent,&amp;quot; the Saudi Embassy in London said in a statement announcing the decision.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The International Olympic Committee had been pressing Saudi Arabia to allow women to compete and act as officials, and said in March that talks were going well.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;IOC is confident that Saudi Arabia is working to include women athletes and officials at the Olympic Games in London in accordance with the International Federations&amp;apost; rules,&amp;quot; the committee said March 19.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The decision is a rare concession for a kingdom where women are banned from driving.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>They also cannot vote or hold public office, though that will change in 2015.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Women in Saudi Arabia also cannot marry, leave the country, go to school or open bank accounts without permission from a male guardian, who usually is the father or husband.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Much of public life is segregated by gender.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>When it came to sports, female athletes were barred from the Olympic Games because they would be participating in front of a mixed-gender crowd.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The Saudi Embassy did not say what prompted the kingdom to change its mind.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Officials in Saudi Arabia could not immediately be reached for comment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The embassy statement added that women who qualify for the Games will be allowed to participate, raising questions how many female athletes will be ready at such short notice.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Dalma Rushdi Malhas, who became the first Saudi woman to compete in the Youth Olympics, praised the decision, calling it &amp;quot;a dream come true.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;This just opens so many doors for women,&amp;quot; Malhas, an equestrian, told CNN International.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Malhas said she won&amp;apost;t be competing in London games this year because her horse suffered a minor injury, but didn&amp;apost;t rule out future competitions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;I look forward to giving my best and I&amp;apost;m determined to keep on trying for the next Games, hopefully,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Earlier this year, Human Rights Watch issued a report in which it said the Saudi government&amp;apost;s policy of banning women&amp;apost;s participation in national competitive sports reflects the &amp;quot;predominant conservative view that opening sports to women and girls will lead to immorality: &amp;apost;steps of the devil,&amp;apost; as one prominent religious scholar put it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>In 2009 and 2010, the country closed private gyms for women, and its schools&amp;apost; curriculum does not include physical education classes for women, the rights group said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>And while the Saudi National Olympic Committee selects athletes to represent it in competition, the committee does not have a women&amp;apost;s section.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Saudi Arabia&amp;apost;s 153 official sports club are also closed to women, Human Rights Watch said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The only exception is the female basketball section of Jeddah United, a private sports company that is not among the official sports clubs, the group said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>For its part, Qatar will send three women to London this year: a shooter, a swimmer and a runner.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Brunei will send a woman who will compete in hurdling.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
