<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1472" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/07/04/world/asia/first-chinese-cyclist-tour-de-france/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-07-04 05:08:07" category="sport" author="Casey Tolan, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Ji Cheng: first Chinese cyclist in Tour de France</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">26-year-old Ji Cheng will become the first rider from China to compete in cycling&amp;apost;s most prestigious race.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Ji, who is part of the Giant-Shimano team, has also competed in two of the sport&amp;apost;s other two highest profile races.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="32, 27">International road cycling hasn&amp;apost;t gained much traction in China, and some bicycles have been replaced by vehicles.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="7">As a growing middle class starts cycling for recreation, some think China could be the next frontier for competitive cycling.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-22 16:53:33" annotation_time="108.70801" mapping_time_divergence="54.354004">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Chinese fans will have a new reason to cheer when the 101st Tour de France kicks off on Saturday: 26-year-old Ji Cheng will become the first rider from China to compete for competitive cycling&amp;apost;s highest honor.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">Ji, who will be riding with the Netherlands-based Giant-Shimano team, has competed in professional European cycling since 2007 and has already completed other top races.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="4">As Ji qualifies for one of the most famous races in the world, his example could help kickstart China&amp;apost;s nascent competitive cycling scene.</sentence>
      <sentence id="27" ids_highlights="3">But overall, international road cycling hasn&amp;apost;t gained much traction in the country.</sentence>
      <sentence id="32" ids_highlights="3">Now, as more people have moved into the middle class, mopeds and automobiles have started to replace bikes on the streets of Beijing and other cities, although there are still more than 8 million bikes in the capital city.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Chinese fans will have a new reason to cheer when the 101st Tour de France kicks off on Saturday: 26-year-old Ji Cheng will become the first rider from China to compete for competitive cycling&amp;apost;s highest honor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Ji, who will be riding with the Netherlands-based Giant-Shimano team, has competed in professional European cycling since 2007 and has already completed other top races.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am just really happy to race for my country in the Tour de France, I&amp;apost;m really excited,&amp;quot; Ji, who comes from the northern Chinese city of Harbin, told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s dreamed of competing in the Tour since he began racing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;When I started cycling in China, the Tour de France was the only race they showed on the TV,&amp;quot; Ji said from Leeds, England, where the tour will begin.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s happy that his friends and family will get to watch him compete.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>As Ji qualifies for one of the most famous races in the world, his example could help kickstart China&amp;apost;s nascent competitive cycling scene.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;apost;Breakaway killer&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Ji started his athletic career as a runner in school, but shifted to cycling soon after in part because of the cold weather in Harbin, where winter temperatures get below -4°F (-20°C) and cycling gave him the opportunity to train indoors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>He started with track cycling -- in which racers do laps around a velodrome track on specialized bikes -- and then moved to longer distance road cycling.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>After training with a Hong Kong team for a year, he was signed by Shimano and moved to Europe in 2007.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The Tour de France won&amp;apost;t be the first milestone Ji has passed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s also competed in the other two highest profile races in competitive cycling: the Vuelta a Espana, in which he raced in 2012 and the Giro d&amp;apost;Italia the following year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The three races collectively are known as Grand Tours, and he is the first Chinese cyclist to participate in each of them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Ji is known as a &amp;quot;breakaway killer,&amp;quot; which means he catches up with cyclists who try to get away from the pack of riders.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s not the flashiest role, but it helps position his teammates on the nine-man squad to win races.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>He says he doesn&amp;apost;t have a strategy going into the Tour.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;My goal is to try my hardest for my team, and I hope I finish the whole three weeks.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Giant-Shimano coach Rudi Kemna said in a statement that Ji played an important factor in the team&amp;apost;s formations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>His participation in the Tour &amp;quot;will be huge for him and his country and we look forward to seeing the impact this has on the globalization of the sport,&amp;quot; Kemna said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Kingdom of Bicycles?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Advocates hope that Ji&amp;apost;s participation in the Tour could help competitive cycling gain attention in China.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;The fact that there is a Chinese racer in the race means the media and the public will focus on it much more,&amp;quot; said Alain Rumpf, the director of Global Cycling Promotions, an organization affiliated with cycling&amp;apost;s governing body, that promotes the sport around the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;Ji Cheng is a pioneer.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>International teams currently compete in events like the Tour of Beijing, a top-level annual race that will have its fourth edition in October.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Ji and several of his Shimano teammates competed in the race in 2013.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>But overall, international road cycling hasn&amp;apost;t gained much traction in the country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>China won three medals in women&amp;apost;s track cycling at the 2012 London Olympics -- two silvers and a bronze -- but has lagged behind in road cycling.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Some cyclists aim instead for China&amp;apost;s National Games, where athletes represent their regions or cities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Cycling in general is also not as prevalent as it once was.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>China was known as the &amp;quot;Kingdom of Bicycles&amp;quot; in the 70&amp;apost;s and 80&amp;apost;s, when a bike was the main form of transportation for many.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Now, as more people have moved into the middle class, mopeds and automobiles have started to replace bikes on the streets of Beijing and other cities, although there are still more than 8 million bikes in the capital city.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Poor air quality is also an obstacle for cyclists, who can face health problems from riding in smoggy urban centers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Cycling renaissance.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Recently, however, members of a growing middle class are picking up their bikes again.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>For these people, cycling is recreation, not a way to get to work.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;There&amp;apost;s now more and more people who will strap an expensive road bike to the top of their BMW and head to the hills around Beijing,&amp;quot; said David Culbert, a spokesperson for the Tour of Beijing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>In the suburbs, the roads are smooth and the air is clean.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;You will see literally hundreds, if not thousands, of people out there on the weekends riding their bikes,&amp;quot; said Shannon Bufton, the co-founder of Serk Cycling, a Beijing NGO promoting cycling culture.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>This cycling renaissance has even gotten support from the headline-grabbing billionaire Chen Guangbiao, who celebrated China&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;National Urban Car-Free Day&amp;quot; in 2011 by smashing a Mercedes-Benz and giving his employees free bicycles.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s also attracting the attention of professional cycling teams eager to find untapped talent, and cycling sponsors eying China&amp;apost;s potential as a lucrative market.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>And Beijing is looking to build a more competitive road cycling program for the 2016 Olympics in Rio de Janeiro.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Ji&amp;apost;s example could give more people a reason to get back in the saddle.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;What Chinese cycling needs is a national hero who performs well at an international level,&amp;quot; Bufton said -- and that could be Ji.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>For now, Ji is focused on the Tour, in which 198 cyclists, divided among 22 teams, will ride a total of 2,272 miles before the July 27 finish line.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>But he&amp;apost;s already thinking ahead.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>&amp;quot;I hope for the future we will send more and more riders to European pro races,&amp;quot; Ji said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>&amp;quot;I hope they can use my experience to see that European cycling is possible.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
