<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1494" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/01/30/sport/football/qatar-workers-rights-fifa-football" date_published="2014-01-30 19:56:02" category="sport" author="" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Qatar set deadline by FIFA over conditions for migrant workers</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Qatar given deadline over conditions for migrant workers on 2022 World Cup.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">FIFA want detailed report by February 12 .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">Amnesty International report last year highlighted the situation .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="5">FIFA president Sepp Blatter said at time it was &amp;quot;unacceptable&amp;quot;.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-27 17:06:26" annotation_time="19.522">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Organizers of the 2022 World Cup in Qatar have been set a tight deadline by FIFA to explain how conditions are improving for migrant workers on the various building projects associated with the hosting of football&amp;apost;s showpiece competition.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">The world governing body are demanding a &amp;quot;detailed report&amp;quot; by February 12 with &amp;quot;information on specific steps&amp;quot; being taken to improve the situation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">Concerns over the welfare of migrant workers in Qatar was highlighted by an Amnesty International report last year, which reported on widespread abuse.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="4">It prompted FIFA president Sepp Blatter to describe the conditions as &amp;quot;unacceptable&amp;quot; and he raised the issue with the Emir of Qatar on a visit to Doha last November.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Organizers of the 2022 World Cup in Qatar have been set a tight deadline by FIFA to explain how conditions are improving for migrant workers on the various building projects associated with the hosting of football&amp;apost;s showpiece competition.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The world governing body are demanding a &amp;quot;detailed report&amp;quot; by February 12 with &amp;quot;information on specific steps&amp;quot; being taken to improve the situation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>FIFA secretary-general Jerome Valcke wrote to Qatar&amp;apost;s Supreme Committee for Delivery and Legacy Thursday to request the assurances.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Concerns over the welfare of migrant workers in Qatar was highlighted by an Amnesty International report last year, which reported on widespread abuse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>It prompted FIFA president Sepp Blatter to describe the conditions as &amp;quot;unacceptable&amp;quot; and he raised the issue with the Emir of Qatar on a visit to Doha last November.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>FIFA executive committee member Theo Zwanziger has been given the responsibility to monitor any progress and has held a series of meeting with human rights and labor organizations, including Amnesty and the International Labor Organization (ILO).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are currently in the middle of an intensive process, which is exclusively aimed at improving the situation of workers in Qatar,&amp;quot; Zwanziger said in a statement released by FIFA.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;Ultimately, what we need are clear rules and steps that will build trust and ensure that the situation, which is unacceptable at the moment, improves in a sustainable manner.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The Qatar World Cup 2022 Committee was not immediately available for comment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Zwanziger is due before the European Parliament on February 13, the day after the deadline for Qatar to report, in a hearing over workers&amp;apost; rights in the Arab emirate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The executive committee will also receive an update at its March 20 and 21 meeting.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;FIFA firmly believes in the power of the World Cup in triggering positive social change in Qatar, including improving the labor rights and conditions of migrant workers,&amp;quot; it added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Since Qatar was awarded the 2022 World Cup it has been dogged by various controversies, with FIFA still to decide on an actual date for the competition.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Acute summer temperatures in Qatar have led to fears over safety for players and spectators and Valcke told a French radio station earlier this month that he favored a winter World Cup with a November start.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>FIFA&amp;apost;s official position is that a final decision will be made in December 2014.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
