<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1576" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/03/17/tech/innovation/big-bang-gravitational-waves/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-03-17 22:08:26" category="tech" author="Elizabeth Landau, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Big Bang breakthrough announced; gravitational waves detected</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6">Gravitational waves were predicted by Albert Einstein.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12">New results from BICEP2 are &amp;apost;smoking gun for inflation&amp;apost; .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="19">During inflation, the universe expanded faster than the speed of light.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-26 11:14:08" annotation_time="29.044">
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">What&amp;apost;s more, researchers discovered direct evidence for the first time of what Albert Einstein predicted in his general theory of relativity: Gravitational waves.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">The BICEP2 results are the &amp;quot;smoking gun for inflation,&amp;quot; Marc Kamionkowski, professor of physics and astronomy, said at a news conference.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;And then it expanded during inflation at faster than the speed of light.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>There&amp;apost;s no way for us to know exactly what happened some 13.8 billion years ago, when our universe burst onto the scene.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But scientists announced Monday a breakthrough in understanding how our world as we know it came to be.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>If the discovery holds up to scrutiny, it&amp;apost;s evidence of how the universe rapidly expanded less than a trillionth of a second after the Big Bang.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;It teaches us something crucial about how our universe began,&amp;quot; said Sean Carroll, a physicist at California Institute of Technology, who was not involved in the study.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s an amazing achievement that we humans, doing science systematically for just a few hundred years, can extend our understanding that far.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>What&amp;apost;s more, researchers discovered direct evidence for the first time of what Albert Einstein predicted in his general theory of relativity: Gravitational waves.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>These are essentially ripples in space-time, which have been thought of as the &amp;quot;first tremors of the Big Bang,&amp;quot; according to the Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>A telescope at the South Pole called BICEP2 -- Background Imaging of Cosmic Extragalactic Polarization 2 -- was critical to the discovery.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The telescope allowed scientists to analyze the polarization of light left over from the early universe, leading to Monday&amp;apost;s landmark announcement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>How inflation works.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Scientists use the word &amp;quot;inflation&amp;quot; to describe how the universe rapidly expanded after the Big Bang in a ripping-apart of space.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The BICEP2 results are the &amp;quot;smoking gun for inflation,&amp;quot; Marc Kamionkowski, professor of physics and astronomy, said at a news conference.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Kamionkowski also was not involved in the project.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;Inflation is the theory about the &amp;apost;bang&amp;apost; of Big Bang,&amp;quot; said Chao-Lin Kuo, an assistant professor of physics at Stanford and SLAC National Accelerator Laboratory, and a co-leader of the BICEP2 collaboration, in a Stanford video.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;It explains why we have all this stuff in the universe.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Imagine that you are making a raisin bun, said Stanford physicist Kent Irwin, who worked on sensors and readout systems used in the experiment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>As the dough bakes and expands, the distance from any given raisin to another increases.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Certainly everything in the universe that we see now, at one time before inflation, was smaller than an electron,&amp;quot; Irwin said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;And then it expanded during inflation at faster than the speed of light.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>You may have learned in physics class that light sets the universe&amp;apost;s speed limit, but space-time is an exception; it can stretch faster than the speed of light, Irwin said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Stanford University professor Andrei Linde, who helped develop the current inflation theory, said the new results are something he had hoped to see for 30 years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;If this is true, this is a moment of understanding of nature of such a magnitude that it just overwhelms and let&amp;apost;s just hope that it&amp;apost;s not a trick,&amp;quot; Linde said in a university video interview.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Another cool tidbit: Inflation can be used in theories that suggest the existence of multiple universes, Irwin said, although these results do not directly address such theories.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>What are gravitational waves?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Scientists believe that in the fabric of space-time, there are tiny ripples called quantum fluctuations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>If you could look at space-time on the smallest scale possible, you would, in theory, see them, even today.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Unfortunately, no microscope is capable of seeing something that small.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Such fluctuations also existed at the beginning of the universe.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Inflation blew them up much larger, launching gravitational waves that we now see imprinted on the cosmic microwave background.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;These gravitational waves are an aftershock of the Big Bang,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The BICEP2 study is the first to image them directly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have for the first time a detection for the mythical gravity wave signal that people have been searching for so hard, for so long,&amp;quot; said Clem Pryke, associate professor at the University of Minnesota, at a press conference Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Other experiments such as LIGO -- Caltech&amp;apost;s Laser Interferometer Gravitational Wave Observatory -- are also looking for proof of gravitational waves, but in the context of energetic cosmic phenomena such as coalescing black holes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The gravitational waves suggested by the BICEP2 results would have expanded across the entire universe at that time, Irwin said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The length of one of these waves -- the distance between peaks and troughs -- would have been billions of light years across.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Light from the early universe, called cosmic microwave background radiation, reveals these telltale signs of our universe&amp;apost;s history.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Last year, scientists from the European Space Agency&amp;apost;s Planck space telescope released a detailed map of temperature variations in this light, which came from from about 380,000 years after the Big Bang.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Instead of temperature, BICEP2 scientists were looking specifically at the polarization of the cosmic microwave background -- that is, the direction the electric field is pointing across the sky.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Researchers were looking for a specific type of polarization called &amp;quot;B-modes,&amp;quot; which signify a curling pattern in the polarized orientations of light from the ancient universe, said Jamie Bock, co-leader of the BICEP2 collaboration and professor of physics at California Institute of Technology.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>In theory, this swirling polarization pattern could only be created from gravitational waves.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>And that is what BICEP2 found.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s a very clean signature of those gravity waves,&amp;quot; Irwin said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Is it for real?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Because of how potentially important these results are, they must be viewed with skepticism, said David Spergel, professor of astrophysics at Princeton University.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>The measurement is a very difficult one to make and could easily be contaminated.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>There are, as it stands, some &amp;quot;oddities&amp;quot; in the results that could be concerning, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am looking forward to seeing these results confirmed or refuted by other experiments in the next year or two,&amp;quot; Spergel said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>The Planck space telescope collaboration is expected to release results on polarization of the cosmic microwave background as well, Irwin said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Other experiments are working toward similar goals, which could support or go against BICEP2.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Regardless, Monday&amp;apost;s announcement is making big waves in the scientific community.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
