<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1645" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/09/18/tech/china-mobile-internet-migrants/index.html" date_published="2012-09-18 11:16:50" category="tech" author="Lara Farrar for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Smartphone explosion liberating China&amp;apost;s migrants</title>
  <keywords>China,migrants,mobiles,smartphones,microblogs,tech,internet,access,data</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="12">Smartphone use on the rise in China amid falling handset prices and cheaper call plans.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12">China set to overtake the United States as the largest market for smartphones.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="16">Analyst: Such technology helping to &amp;quot;restructure the social identity&amp;quot; of migrants.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="32">Workers also connecting with broader segments of Chinese society via micro-blogs.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-28 12:30:00" annotation_time="71.85">
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="1, 2">Falling prices of handsets made by foreign brands paired with domestic manufacturers churning out cheaper and cheaper devices, combined with faster and more affordable data plans, means China will overtake the United States as the largest market for smartphones this year, according to market intelligence firm IDC.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="3">For migrant populations, such technology has served to &amp;quot;liberate workers culturally&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;restructure the social identity&amp;quot; of migrants, according to Pui-lam Law, editor of &amp;quot;New Connectivities in China: Virtual, Actual and Local Interactions.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="32" ids_highlights="4">Some migrants are garnering thousands of fans on microblogs where they share personal experiences and feelings that have rarely been voiced outside their immediate social circles - if at all.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Shanghai One recent afternoon, two 17-year-old migrant workers from the nearby province of Anhui came to an electronics market in this Chinese metropolis with one goal in mind: To purchase a smartphone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>They browsed a couple of different models, before settling on a Samsung Galaxy Ace for 1,200 yuan (about $180).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>They traded in their old cell phones, good for nothing much more than making calls, sending text messages and maybe playing a few games.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>One of the migrants said he looked forward to watching movies on his new device.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The other said he did not really know how to use such a gadget.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Wang Shenyong, manager of the cell phone stall, said nearly all of his customers who have migrated to Shanghai from elsewhere for work are opting to purchase smartphones rather than low-budget fake phones that have long been a staple technology of China&amp;apost;s marginalized populations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;The migrant workers are different than before,&amp;quot; Wang said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;They are more advanced now.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>They want a better life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>They use these [smartphones] because they can know news very fast and share information with others.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>China is on the verge of a smartphone revolution.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Falling prices of handsets made by foreign brands paired with domestic manufacturers churning out cheaper and cheaper devices, combined with faster and more affordable data plans, means China will overtake the United States as the largest market for smartphones this year, according to market intelligence firm IDC.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Analysts expect the growth of the mobile Internet on the mainland to be game changing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Countless entrepreneurs are working to create applications and other software for the coming mobile web explosion that will be fueled by widespread smartphone adoption.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Even simple handsets have enabled China&amp;apost;s migrant workers to find jobs, communicate with family back home, organize into groups and access information.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>For migrant populations, such technology has served to &amp;quot;liberate workers culturally&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;restructure the social identity&amp;quot; of migrants, according to Pui-lam Law, editor of &amp;quot;New Connectivities in China: Virtual, Actual and Local Interactions.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>It is hard to say how many migrants now have smartphones.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Anecdotal evidence suggests their uptake, especially among younger migrants in urban areas, is quickly becoming widespread and that the technology is enabling them to connect with broader segments of Chinese society in ways they never have before.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;China has long had a very active, even militant, working class,&amp;quot; said Jack Linchuan Qiu, an assistant professor at the Chinese University of Hong Kong&amp;apost;s communication and journalism school, who researches information and communication technologies and their impact on labor movements in China.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;They have always been socially engaged but usually they stay under the radar, but now there is a new window for us to see what is going on.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>That new window is specifically Sina Weibo, China&amp;apost;s largest microblog, most commonly referred to as a mainstream social media channel for the middle class.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Now migrant workers are starting to take part, and in some instances people are paying attention.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>This summer, for example, a migrant NGO successfully stopped the closure of a school for migrant children in Beijing after posting their grievances on Sina Weibo.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Public intellectuals, television hosts, even state-run media, became involved in supporting their cause.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is all possible because they have smartphones,&amp;quot; Qiu said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;But the most essential ingredient is the workers want to have their voices heard, and they are facing existential issues.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Technology is of no use if no one has the political will.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Qiu said similar efforts to stop recent government crackdowns on workers&amp;apost; rights groups in the southern province of Guangzhou have not been as successful.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Beijing case -- that was a rare case,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;It was almost like a little miracle.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Nevertheless, more migrants, particularly those in factories, are creating what Qiu calls &amp;quot;worker generated content&amp;quot; about their working conditions and sharing it with wider audiences.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Some migrants are garnering thousands of fans on microblogs where they share personal experiences and feelings that have rarely been voiced outside their immediate social circles - if at all.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;Am going to bed now,&amp;quot; posted one migrant who writes under the name &amp;quot;Blue Piano&amp;quot; on Sina Weibo.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;Good night to this hypocritical, pretentious, two-faced world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Step on another&amp;apost;s head in order to get to the top.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Keep on fighting tomorrow.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;Stay home.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Marry.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Farming.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Raise pigs,&amp;quot; wrote another migrant called &amp;quot;Red Peasant&amp;quot; online.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;Leave home.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Roaming.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Working.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Make money.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Where is the road?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>&amp;quot;There are more and more stories like this, of migrants trying to vent their grievances through smartphones,&amp;quot; said Tai Zixue, author of &amp;quot;The Internet in China: Cyberspace and Civil Society.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is not a dramatic change yet in that sense.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>They are still marginalized.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>It is only under particular circumstances they get the spotlight, but what we are seeing is a big sign of what could happen further down the road.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
