<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1666" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/01/10/tech/gaming-gadgets/tv-trends-ces/index.html" date_published="2012-01-10 20:58:28" category="tech" author="Brandon Griggs, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>TVs in 2012 will get brighter, thinner, more social</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">HDTV debuted at CES in 1998, but it was six years before HD was common.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">No evidence yet that the average person wants all these new features, analyst says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">Biggest buzz at CES has surrounded TVs with OLED screens.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-12 14:23:56" annotation_time="1077.7461">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">HDTV debuted at CES in 1998, but it was another five or six years before HD sets became common in living rooms.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">But there&amp;apost;s no evidence that the average person wants all these new features when shopping for a TV, said Andrew Eisner, a gadget analyst with Retrevo, an electronics shopping site.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">The biggest buzz at CES has surrounded TVs with OLED screens instead of plasma or liquid crystals.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Las Vegas When it comes to TVs -- often the flashiest, most buzzed-about gadgets at the International Consumer Electronics Show -- it takes several years for reality to catch up to the hype.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>HDTV debuted at CES in 1998, but it was another five or six years before HD sets became common in living rooms.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>3-D TV arrived at CES in 2009 amid massive hoopla but has yet to catch on with mainstream consumers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>So judging from the variety of next-generation products being unveiled at this year&amp;apost;s show, TV manufacturers are still scrambling to find the next killer feature that will entice buyers to ditch their flat-panel plasmas for something better.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The buzz surrounding 3-D has subsided, but television makers here are pushing other enhancements in the hopes something will stick: TVs that connect seamlessly with the Internet, TVs that interact wirelessly with your tablet device, TVs with built-in social features so you can post to Twitter about the show you&amp;apost;re watching and TVs you control by speaking or waving your arms.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>But there&amp;apost;s no evidence that the average person wants all these new features when shopping for a TV, said Andrew Eisner, a gadget analyst with Retrevo, an electronics shopping site.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;Do consumers really care?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>I don&amp;apost;t know,&amp;quot; Eisner said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;As long as it looks decent and it won&amp;apost;t break down and it&amp;apost;s within their budget, that&amp;apost;s what&amp;apost;s important to most people.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The biggest buzz at CES has surrounded TVs with OLED screens instead of plasma or liquid crystals.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>OLEDs, or organic light-emitting diodes, produce a crisp picture and deep, saturated colors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>They appear in some high-end smartphone displays but until now have been difficult to manufacture in larger screens.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>At a CES press event Monday morning, LG Electronics introduced what it called &amp;quot;the world&amp;apost;s thinnest, largest and lightest&amp;quot; OLED TV: a 55-inch model with a remarkable picture.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>There was an audible gasp in the room when it was unveiled, and a throng of photographers crowded around the set afterward like paparazzi around a starlet.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Not to be outdone, Samsung unveiled its own 55-inch OLED TV that afternoon, calling it &amp;quot;the ultimate in picture quality.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Both LG and Samsung say their OLED sets will hit the market in 2012, although neither would talk about price.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The TVs won&amp;apost;t be cheap; Eisner, the Retrevo analyst, expects them to sell initially for at least $8,000.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>OLED &amp;quot;is beyond the reach of most consumers at this point,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;But it looks gorgeous.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>To confuse matters further, Sony unveiled a 55-inch prototype TV that uses an eye-opening 6 million LEDs in place of pixels.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>But these impressive-looking TVs won&amp;apost;t be mainstream products anytime soon.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Based on CES press announcements and interviews with analysts, here are some TV features that may be on display at your neighborhood electronics store within the next 12 months:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Voice and motion controls.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The remote control may be an endangered species.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Some TV makers are following the lead of Apple&amp;apost;s Siri, the iPhone 4S &amp;quot;virtual assistant,&amp;quot; and Microsoft&amp;apost;s Kinect gaming system, which allows players to operate their TVs and manipulate onscreen avatars by moving their bodies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Samsung on Monday announced its flagship ES8000 LED model, whose built-in cameras, microphones and software let users speak commands like &amp;quot;channel 7&amp;quot; to control the TV.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Users also will be able to use gesture controls for Web browsing, adjusting the volume and more.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>LG also is adding voice control to the Magic Remote interface that comes with all its high-end Cinema Screen TVs in 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>And don&amp;apost;t forget Apple, which may add Siri voice-recognition functions to the TV set it is rumored to be building this year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>More social features.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s been documented that more people are watching TV with a phone or tablet nearby so they can check Facebook during commercials or chat with their friends about what they&amp;apost;re watching.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Now, manufacturers want to help you do all that through your television.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>On Monday, Panasonic announced a series of Web-connected &amp;quot;Smart Viera&amp;quot; TVs that will flash your social-networking updates on the screen.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The company also unveiled a split-screen feature that lets you launch Skype and chat with friends while you&amp;apost;re watching TV.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Panasonic also announced it&amp;apost;s partnering with flagging social network Myspace for a new service called Myspace TV.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Pop star Justin Timberlake, a Myspace investor, appeared onstage Monday to help promote the product, which will let viewers use a connected tablet to share music and TV shows with friends.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Bigger, thinner, lighter screens.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>TV sets can&amp;apost;t get much thinner, but that hasn&amp;apost;t stopped manufacturers -- always looking for a design edge over a competitor -- from trying.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;ve gone to great lengths to reduce the thinness of our TVs without sacrificing picture quality,&amp;quot; said Wayne Park, president of LG Electronics USA, whose 55-inch OLED TV is just 4 millimeters thick (or thin).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Sharp Electronics, on the other hand, spent much of its press event Monday emphasizing its push toward massive screens.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>The company showed a video encouraging consumers to fit larger TVs into smaller spaces in their homes and handed out special glasses to demo what it claims is the world&amp;apost;s first 80-inch 3-D LED TV, coming in April (price not announced).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Better sound.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s not all about bigger, brighter screens.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>There&amp;apost;s been some chatter, but few specifics, at CES about the next generation of home-theater audio, including 3-D sound systems that create &amp;quot;sound fields&amp;quot; around the TV viewer.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Expect to see more of this by the end of the year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>&amp;quot;Sound is always the unappreciated element of TVs,&amp;quot; Eisner said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>&amp;quot;People don&amp;apost;t pay much attention to it, and they probably should, because surveys have shown that good sound can make the picture look better.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
