<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1672" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/01/17/tech/rosetta-comet-chaser" date_published="2014-01-17 10:37:52" category="tech" author="Dave Gilbert, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Wake up ESA&amp;apost;s Rosetta space probe, you have a comet to meet</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6">Rosetta will be the first spacecraft to orbit a comet and to place a lander on the surface.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">ESA says the mission objective is to help understand the evolution of the solar system.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="11">After mapping the comet a lander will be deployed to the surface.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="25">Some believe Earth may have received its water from comets.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-09 14:16:29" annotation_time="9.253">
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">Rosetta will be the first spacecraft to orbit a comet and to place a lander on the surface as it approaches and then swings around the sun.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">ESA says the mission&amp;apost;s objective is to help understand the origin and evolution of the solar system and investigate the role that comets may have played in seeding Earth with water.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="3">After mapping the comet&amp;apost;s surface it will release the lander Philae in November and monitor changes as it gets closer to the sun.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="4">Some think that Earth may have received its water from comets, or even the chemicals that make up the building blocks of life on our planet.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>London Scientists are inviting you to take part in &amp;quot;waking up&amp;quot; a comet-chasing probe that has been in hibernation in space for nearly three years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The spacecraft is due to reactivate itself from an internal alarm clock on Monday but to celebrate the event the European Space Agency (ESA) is asking people to film themselves shouting &amp;quot;Wake up, Rosetta!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>and then share their video clips on a dedicated Facebook page.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Visitors to the page can vote for their favorites and the top 10 will be transmitted towards Rosetta and out into the universe beyond.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Behind the fun lies a ground-breaking mission, which, if successful, will notch up a series of notable firsts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Rosetta will be the first spacecraft to orbit a comet and to place a lander on the surface as it approaches and then swings around the sun.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>ESA says the mission&amp;apost;s objective is to help understand the origin and evolution of the solar system and investigate the role that comets may have played in seeding Earth with water.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Named after the Rosetta stone --- a block carved with ancient scripts that led to Egyptian hieroglyphs being deciphered -- the €1 billion ($1.36 billion) space mission was launched in 2004.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Since then, ESA says it has been around the sun five times as controllers line it up to meet comet 67P/Churyumov-Gerasimenko in August this year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>For the last 31 months it has been in hibernation for the coldest part of the journey that took it close to the orbit of Jupiter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>After mapping the comet&amp;apost;s surface it will release the lander Philae in November and monitor changes as it gets closer to the sun.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>ESA project scientist Matt Taylor said if the project is successful it will advance the knowledge about comets.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s the first time we&amp;apost;ve made a rendezvous with a comet -- that&amp;apost;s never been done before -- and it&amp;apost;s going to be the first time we&amp;apost;ve escorted a comet past its closest approach to the Sun,&amp;quot; he told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;The cherry on the cake is that we also deploy the lander to probe the surface of the comet.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;With these firsts it will enable us to make a quantum leap in our understanding of comets -- where they come from, their consistencies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;Previous missions have only flown past comets at high speed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Rosetta will get within 5km (3.1 miles) when we deploy the lander and will be in pace with the comet -- we will be really up close and personal with it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Taylor explained that the spacecraft was designed to be put in hibernation because even with massive solar panels the size of a basketball court, Rosetta would not have enough power to complete its mission without this energy-saving strategy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The lander is equipped with harpoons to attach itself to the comet, which is about 4km (2.5 miles) long, and then drill about 20cm (8 inches) into the surface to analyze the chemical components.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Often described as &amp;quot;dirty snowballs,&amp;quot; comets are known to contain a lot of ice but scientists want to learn more about their exact composition.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Barry Kellett, an astronomer and research scientist at the UK&amp;apost;s Rutherford Appleton Laboratory, explained that when comets approach the sun, the ice melts and is turned into an ionized gas tail.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The dust produces a separate, curving tail.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;Astronomers believe comets are made of pristine solar system material before the solar system was formed,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;They are the left over bits that never became a planet.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Some think that Earth may have received its water from comets, or even the chemicals that make up the building blocks of life on our planet.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;When Earth and Mars formed it would have been very hot so they would have formed dry,&amp;quot; said Kellett.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;And it was certainly very hot when Earth was hit by something that made the Moon.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The only things we know that have a large amount of water on them are comets.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>He said if Rosetta can establish the composition of this comet then &amp;quot;the question of where life came from might be better answered than before.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Rosetta&amp;apost;s target comet 67P/Churyumov-Gerasimenko is known as a short-period comet.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>It reappears every six years as its orbit brings it close to the Sun.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Halley&amp;apost;s comet has a period of about 76 years and is not due to return close enough to Earth to be visible until 2061.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Others only return after thousands of years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Recently, comet ISON was mostly destroyed in its close encounter with the sun in November last year but it did provide scientists with fresh data in the process.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
