<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1630" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/04/10/tech/innovation/navy-new-technology/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-04-10 14:44:57" category="tech" author="Brad Lendon, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Navy&amp;apost;s future: Electric guns, lasers, water as fuel</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="20, 19">Railgun prototype fires missiles at 7.5 times the speed of sound.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="18">Laser weapon costs about $1 a shot.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="29">Lab says it can make fuel from seawater.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="5">High-tech destroyer to be christened Saturday.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 14:44:53" annotation_time="34.930332" mapping_time_divergence="8.732583">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="4">Saturday, the Navy will christen its most advanced warship ever, the destroyer USS Zumwalt, which may one day be using these new technologies.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;Spending about $1 per shot of a directed-energy source that never runs out gives us an alternative to firing costly munitions at inexpensive threats,&amp;quot; Klunder said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="1">The Navy thinks the other weapon prototype it discussed this week, the electromagnetic railgun, will save money while providing a more potent force.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="1">The gun uses electromagnetic force to send a missile to a range of 125 miles at 7.5 times the speed of sound, according to the Navy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="29" ids_highlights="3">Researchers at the U.S. Naval Research Laboratory, Materials Science and Technology Division, said this week they have demonstrated proof-of-concept on the ability to draw carbon dioxide and hydrogen from seawater and turn it into forms of gasoline.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Imagine ships that fire missiles at seven times the speed of sound without using explosives, or that use lasers to destroy threats at the cost of about a dollar a shot, and vessels making fuel from the very seawater in which they&amp;apost;re floating.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s the glimpse of the high-tech future the U.S. Navy gave this week.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>And these aren&amp;apost;t just ideas.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>They&amp;apost;ve all been shown to work to some degree.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Saturday, the Navy will christen its most advanced warship ever, the destroyer USS Zumwalt, which may one day be using these new technologies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The Zumwalt, which was launched last year and is to be christened at Bath Iron Works in Maine, is the Navy&amp;apost;s first stealth destroyer.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>At 610 feet long and 80 feet wide, it&amp;apost;s about 100 feet longer and 20 feet wider than ships in the Navy&amp;apost;s current fleet of Arleigh Burke class destroyers, but the canopy and the rest of the Zumwalt is built on angles that help make it 50 times harder to spot on radar than an ordinary destroyer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;It has the radar cross-section of a fishing boat,&amp;quot; Chris Johnson, a spokesman for Naval Sea Systems Command, told CNN when the ship was launched last year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>In its current configuration, the Zumwalt will carry a considerable arsenal of weapons, including two Advanced Gun Systems (AGS), which can fire rocket-powered, computer-guided shells that can destroy targets 63 miles away.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s three times farther than ordinary destroyer guns can fire.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>But in the future, it could be fitted with the even more advanced systems the Navy talked about this week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>One, a laser weapon prototype, will be tested aboard the amphibious transport dock USS Ponce in the Persian Gulf this summer, the Navy said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is a revolutionary capability,&amp;quot; Rear Adm. Matthew Klunder, chief of Naval Research, said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;This very affordable technology is going to change the way we fight and save lives.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The laser weapon is design to take on aircraft or small surface vessels that may pose threats to Navy ships.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Tests in 2011 and 2012 showed it can accomplish that mission.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The laser can be fired by one sailor using a video game-like console and do it at little cost, the Navy said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Spending about $1 per shot of a directed-energy source that never runs out gives us an alternative to firing costly munitions at inexpensive threats,&amp;quot; Klunder said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The Navy thinks the other weapon prototype it discussed this week, the electromagnetic railgun, will save money while providing a more potent force.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The gun uses electromagnetic force to send a missile to a range of 125 miles at 7.5 times the speed of sound, according to the Navy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>When it hits its target, the projectile does its damage with sheer speed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>It does not have an explosive warhead.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;The electromagnetic railgun represents an incredible new offensive capability for the U.S. Navy,&amp;quot; Rear Adm. Bryant Fuller, the Navy&amp;apost;s chief engineer, said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;This capability will allow us to effectively counter a wide range of threats at a relatively low cost, while keeping our ships and sailors safer by removing the need to carry as many high-explosive weapons.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The railgun projectiles could cost about 1/100th the price of current missiles, according to Klunder.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The Navy said the railgun will be tested at sea aboard the USS Millinocket, a non-combat ship known as a joint high-speed vessel, in 2016.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>No decision has been made on which combat ships might eventually be deployed with a railgun.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>No matter what ships are chosen, other Navy scientists said this week those vessels may someday draw their fuel from the oceans they&amp;apost;re crossing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Researchers at the U.S. Naval Research Laboratory, Materials Science and Technology Division, said this week they have demonstrated proof-of-concept on the ability to draw carbon dioxide and hydrogen from seawater and turn it into forms of gasoline.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Heather Willauer, a Naval Research Laboratory chemist, called the technology &amp;quot;game changing.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is the first time technology of this nature has been demonstrated with the potential for transition, from the laboratory, to full-scale commercial implementation,&amp;quot; she said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The lab&amp;apost;s researchers used &amp;quot;an innovative and proprietary NRL electrolytic cation exchange module&amp;quot; to remove the carbon dioxide from the water and produce hydrogen gas in the process.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;The gases are then converted to liquid hydrocarbons by a metal catalyst in a reactor system,&amp;quot; the research lab&amp;apost;s statement said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The fuel produced was used to power the engine of a small model aircraft, the researchers said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The process could be ramped up to produce a replacement for jet fuel at a cost of $3 to $6 per gallon within a decade, the researchers said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>That step would come on land, with versions to be used on ships coming later, they said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Writing on the Navy&amp;apost;s official blog this week, Vice Adm. Phil Cullom, deputy chief of Naval Operations for Fleet Readiness and Logistics, also called the new technology &amp;quot;game changing&amp;quot; and potentially life saving.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;After more than a decade of war, our adversaries have found certain soft underbellies to our operations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>They know that when you go after the logistics and resupply of fuel, that&amp;apost;s an easier target than confronting our frontline forces.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>What if we removed that from the equation?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Can you imagine a time when an aircraft carrier doesn&amp;apost;t have to wait for the oiler to come steaming alongside it to deliver jet fuel?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>It truly does change things.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>It prevents what could one day be our &amp;apost;maritime IED moment,&amp;apost;&amp;quot; Cullom wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
