<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1652" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/05/22/tech/social-media/pew-teens-facebook/index.html" date_published="2013-05-22 18:52:16" category="tech" author="Brandon Griggs, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Survey: Teens&amp;apost; enthusiasm for Facebook is waning</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="8">A new Pew survey of U.S. teens finds &amp;quot;waning enthusiasm&amp;quot; for Facebook.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">Teens report feeling annoyed by frequent &amp;quot;drama&amp;quot; they encounter on the site.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="14">Facebook remains the most popular social network among U.S. teens. .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="16">Facebook exec: We continue have high penetration rates among young users.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 14:28:15" annotation_time="115.621">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">They complain about their friends&amp;apost; oversharing, and about too much &amp;quot;drama&amp;quot; on the site.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="1">According to Pew, focus-group discussions with teens revealed &amp;quot;waning enthusiasm&amp;quot; for Facebook for the reasons cited, including feeling &amp;quot;drained by the &amp;apost;drama&amp;apost; that they described as happening frequently&amp;quot; on the site.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="3">Facebook has 1.1 billion users worldwide and remains the most popular social network among U.S. teens.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="4">&amp;quot;We continue to have really high penetration rates among that age group, both in the U.S. and globally, and ... younger users remain among the most active and engaged users,&amp;quot; Ebersman said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>There&amp;apost;s fresh evidence that American teenagers may be growing weary of Facebook.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>They don&amp;apost;t like the fact that their parents, grandparents and other adults are also there, diluting Facebook&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;cool&amp;quot; factor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>They complain about their friends&amp;apost; oversharing, and about too much &amp;quot;drama&amp;quot; on the site.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>And they&amp;apost;re increasingly flocking to other social platforms, such as Twitter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>These are some of the findings of a new Pew Research Center survey of U.S. teens&amp;apost; social media use.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Released Tuesday, the survey finds that teens are sharing more personal information on social media, but are also taking a variety of steps to manage their privacy online.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>But it was the Facebook stuff that generated the most headlines.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>According to Pew, focus-group discussions with teens revealed &amp;quot;waning enthusiasm&amp;quot; for Facebook for the reasons cited, including feeling &amp;quot;drained by the &amp;apost;drama&amp;apost; that they described as happening frequently&amp;quot; on the site.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;The stress of needing to manage their reputation on Facebook also contributes to the lack of enthusiasm,&amp;quot; the survey said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The Pew survey found that 24% of online teens now use Twitter, up from 16% in 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Other social platforms such as Tumblr, Instagram (which is owned by Facebook), YouTube and Snapchat also have seen big growth among young users in the past year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Those teens who used sites like Twitter and Instagram reported feeling like they could better express themselves on these platforms, where they felt freed from the social expectations and constraints of Facebook,&amp;quot; the Pew survey said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;Nevertheless, the site is still where a large amount of socializing takes place, and teens feel they need to stay on Facebook in order to not miss out.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Facebook has 1.1 billion users worldwide and remains the most popular social network among U.S. teens.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>A Facebook spokesperson declined to comment specifically Wednesday on the Pew report but pointed to statements by CFO David Ebersman in a recent conference call about quarterly earnings, in which he emphasized Facebook&amp;apost;s popularity among users under 25.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;We continue to have really high penetration rates among that age group, both in the U.S. and globally, and ... younger users remain among the most active and engaged users,&amp;quot; Ebersman said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;Younger users are extremely active users of Instagram as well.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Facebook executives maintain that teen use of their social network has remained steady.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>They argue that Facebook is not losing users to other platforms -- instead, they say, more users are visiting other social media sites in addition to Facebook.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;The urban legend (that Facebook is losing younger users) flows more often than not from surveys people have done of younger users that indicate that they&amp;apost;re using other social services ... much of the concern stems from the assumption that this is a zero-sum game, and that&amp;apost;s not how we see it,&amp;quot; Ebersman said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;We think the overall amount of time spent on services that enable you to connect and share is growing and will continue to grow.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Jeff Hancock, a professor of communication at Cornell University and a frequent social media analyst, mostly agrees.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;Facebook&amp;apost;s attraction to youth is based in part on being connected, but also on being an &amp;apost;ingroup&amp;apost; and &amp;apost;cool&amp;apost; thing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>To the degree that the cool of Facebook wears off, we should see some migration of teens to other platforms,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;People are unlikely to fully leave Facebook but simply to diversify their tools for accomplishing social interaction.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Instead of Facebook being the Walmart of social media, it will become just one platform in a big ecology, including photo sharing with Instragram, broadcasting with Twitter, etc.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Pew&amp;apost;s findings are based on a nationally representative phone survey, run by its Internet &amp;amp; American Life Project, of 802 teens ages 12-17.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>It was conducted between July 26 and September 30, 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Pew also conducted two online focus groups of teenagers ages 12-17 in June 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Pew found that the typical (median) teen Facebook user has 300 friends, while the typical teen Twitter user has 79 followers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
