<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1589" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/04/05/tech/gaming-gadgets/e-reader-survey-pew-gahran/index.html" date_published="2012-04-05 05:30:03" category="tech" author="Amy Gahran, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>E-books spur reading among Americans, survey shows</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">E-book users tend to read more often than people who read only print material, a survey finds.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8">A third of people who read e-content say they now spend more time reading than before.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="13">Currently 28% of Americans age 18 and older own at least one tablet or e-reader.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-24 09:58:50" annotation_time="21.848333">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">E-book users tend to read more often than people who read only print material, Pew found.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">Also, a third of people who read e-content say they now spend more time reading than they did before e-books.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="3">Currently 28% of Americans age 18 and older own at least one tablet or an e-book reader.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>E-books aren&amp;apost;t just becoming increasingly popular.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>They also appear to be promoting reading habits among American adults.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>So says new research from the Pew Internet and American Life Project, which states that about one-fifth of U.S. adults have read an e-book in the past year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>And if you expand that to include Americans over 16 who have used an e-reader device or app to read news articles or magazine-style features, the figure jumps to 43%.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>E-book users tend to read more often than people who read only print material, Pew found.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>In particular, they read more books.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>A typical e-book user read 24 books in the past year, compared with the 15 books reported by typical non-e-book users.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Also, a third of people who read e-content say they now spend more time reading than they did before e-books.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>This is especially true for people who own tablets and e-book readers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>This might be good for the economy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>According to Pew, e-book users are &amp;quot;also more likely than others to have bought their most recent book, rather than borrowed it, and they are more likely than others to say they prefer to purchase books in general.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>E-readers and tablets (including Amazon&amp;apost;s Kindle Fire e-reader, which is a modified Android tablet) were a popular holiday gift item last year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Currently 28% of Americans age 18 and older own at least one tablet or an e-book reader.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>And that&amp;apost;s not even counting the people who read books on a smartphone or iPod Touch app.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Then again, Pew also noted that e-book users often start searching for books online -- which isn&amp;apost;t great news for people who run brick-and-mortar bookstores.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>For now, print reading material still rules the consumer market, however.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Pew found that nearly three-fourths of U.S. adults read a printed book in 2011, and 11% listened to an audiobook.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Print books are especially popular when people read to children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Print books are also the most popular choice when people want to borrow or lend a book.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s not surprising -- recently author Dave Taylor explained step-by-step how to borrow a Kindle book from a public library.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s not too difficult, but is still considerably more complicated than walking into the library and pulling a book off the shelf.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The survey also found that just slightly more people prefer e-books over print for reading in bed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>On the flip side, Pew noted that nearly 20% of U.S. adults said they had not read a single book in the past year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In general, people who don&amp;apost;t own electronic reading devices are more likely not to read much at all.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>In addition, nearly 20% of Americans 16 and older said they had &amp;quot;physical or health conditions that made reading difficult or challenging.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Most of these people are older (25% of those over age 50), unemployed or low-income.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>But an interesting aspect of e-book and audiobook technology is its potential to improve the accessibility of written content.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Most e-reading devices allow the reader to adjust the font, font size, contrast, column width, and other factors to compensate for impaired vision.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Plus, they often include text-to-speech technology that can read books or articles aloud -- maybe not with thrilling delivery, but still a useful option.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>This can also be helpful to people with limited literacy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The cost of e-reading devices keeps dropping, and it&amp;apost;s likely that in the next year or two companies like Amazon may be giving away basic e-readers for free (on the principle that you can make more money selling &amp;quot;blades&amp;quot; than &amp;quot;razors&amp;quot;).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>As the price of e-readers approaches zero, it opens up more opportunities for people who have been left on the wrong side of the digital divide to access the same wealth of information, entertainment and education as people with normal vision and average-or-better income.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Since the invention of writing, the written word has always disrupted the balance of power in societies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>While e-books might have started out as a high-tech novelty for early adopters, they may ultimately prove to be a great equalizer across boundaries of ability, resources and education.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The opinions expressed in this post are solely those of Amy Gahran.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
