<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1671" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/03/19/tech/gaming-gadgets/sony-morpheus-virtual-reality/index.html" date_published="2014-03-19 19:14:32" category="tech" author="Doug Gross, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Virtual reality gets a new player with Sony&amp;apost;s &amp;apost;Project Morpheus&amp;apost;</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Sony announces &amp;quot;Project Morpheus,&amp;quot; a virtual-reality gaming system.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">The headset will immerse players in the game&amp;apost;s virtual world.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">Morpheus joins Oculus Rift as emerging VR leaders.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="22">Microsoft also rumored to be working on virtual reality.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-10 17:12:09" annotation_time="39.689">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1, 2">Sony, makers of the top-selling PlayStation 4, has rolled out &amp;quot;Project Morpheus,&amp;quot; a virtual reality system it says will pair with its top-selling gaming console to immerse players in the virtual worlds in which they&amp;apost;re playing.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">The system, announced Tuesday at the annual Game Developers Conference in San Francisco, joins Oculus Rift, a similar full-immersion VR system that has captured the imaginations of gamers since its $2.4 million debut on Kickstarter in 2012.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="4">With Xbox-maker Microsoft also rumored to be working on its own headset, will the independent shop get squeezed by gaming&amp;apost;s big names before it even hits the market?</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Virtual reality, the emerging 3D technology many expect to be the next quantum leap in the video gaming world, just got a little more real.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Sony, makers of the top-selling PlayStation 4, has rolled out &amp;quot;Project Morpheus,&amp;quot; a virtual reality system it says will pair with its top-selling gaming console to immerse players in the virtual worlds in which they&amp;apost;re playing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The system, announced Tuesday at the annual Game Developers Conference in San Francisco, joins Oculus Rift, a similar full-immersion VR system that has captured the imaginations of gamers since its $2.4 million debut on Kickstarter in 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;At (Sony Computer Entertainment), we view innovation as an opportunity to build on our mission to push the boundaries of play,&amp;quot; said Shuhei Yoshida, president of SCE Worldwide Studios, at the conference.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;Project Morpheus is the latest example of innovation from SCE, and we&amp;apost;re looking forward to its continued development and the games that will be created as development kits get into the hands of content creators.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Virtual reality utilizes a headset that gives the wearer a 360-degree field of vision, allowing them to interact with their surroundings as if they were really there.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Morpheus will feature a visor-style headset and interact with the camera on the Playstation 4 using sensors that track the player&amp;apost;s head movements.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Despite a multitude of other dramatic changes through the decades, the way console gamers have interacted with visuals has remained virtually unchanged.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The prospect of replacing the static, two-dimensional screen has many in the gaming world anxiously contemplating the possibilities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;VR is exciting because it thoroughly immerses players in ways not possible on a regular TV set,&amp;quot; said Dan &amp;quot;Shoe&amp;quot; Hsu, a longtime gaming journalist and editor-in-chief of GamesBeat.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;Wherever you turn your head, that&amp;apost;s where you&amp;apost;ll look, even if it&amp;apost;s physically behind you.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>That sort of 360-degree immersion has never been done in a believable manner in the past, but the technology has caught up.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>We can now experience the same high graphical fidelity that we see on HDTVs within virtual reality now.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Sony did not announce a specific timetable or price details for Morpheus, saying models that will be made available to developers are prototypes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>It all raises the question of whether top-tier game developers will be willing to make the considerable investment of time and resources it will take to create games for a new, untested system that will only be owned by some gamers who own one particular console.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Hsu thinks Sony is in a good position, though.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>In just three-and-a-half months, the PlayStation 4 has sold more than 6 million units worldwide.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Not every PS4 owner will buy it, of course,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;But because Project Morpheus is essentially a new platform on its own, there will be plenty of developers who will want to be first or early on it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>This is a chance for developers to plant their flags in a new market.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>So, what does the arrival of Morpheus mean for Oculus?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>With Xbox-maker Microsoft also rumored to be working on its own headset, will the independent shop get squeezed by gaming&amp;apost;s big names before it even hits the market?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Don&amp;apost;t count on it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>For one, the Oculus Rift is designed to work, primarily, with PCs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>So, even if the console makers each develop their own systems, there&amp;apost;s plenty of space for the system to thrive despite the competition.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>And it&amp;apost;s got plenty of momentum itself.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Oculus has drummed up more than $90 million in funding and, in August, brought in legendary gaming developer John Carmack, the lead programmer behind classic games like &amp;quot;Doom,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Quake&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Wolfenstein 3D,&amp;quot; as chief technology officer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;Oculus is still in a great position with its head start in development, both in hardware and software,&amp;quot; Hsu said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;Third-party games have been in the works for the Oculus Rift for quite some time now, so the company is in a good spot for when the headset releases.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The system got a profile boost at this month&amp;apost;s South by Southwest Interactive festival, when it was used for a popular exhibit promoting HBO&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;Game of Thrones.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;Competition is always, always good,&amp;quot; Hsu said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;If Sony&amp;apost;s announcement forces Oculus to be even more aggressive in creating a top-notch VR unit and getting it to market more quickly, then the consumers will benefit.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
