<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1574" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/03/10/tech/social-media/social-media-north-korea/index.html" date_published="2013-03-10 05:23:56" category="tech" author="Brandon Griggs, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Beyond the DMZ: Tweeting from North Korea</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Jean H. Lee may have been the first person to send a mobile tweet from North Korea.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="11">The country last month launched a new 3G wireless network, available only to foreigners.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">Lee, of the AP, is the only U.S. reporter granted regular access to the secretive nation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="7">She spoke Saturday at the South by Southwest Interactive festival in Texas.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-06 19:32:31" annotation_time="1369.277">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">But on February 25, Jean H. Lee of the Associated Press became perhaps the first person to send a mobile tweet from North Korea when she posted a message on the country&amp;apost;s new 3G wireless network, available only to foreigners.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">As the AP&amp;apost;s bureau chief for both South and North Korea, Lee is the only American news reporter granted regular access to the secretive nation, which she has visited more than 20 times.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="4">She offered a rare glimpse of digital life beyond the DMZ -- the strip of land separating North Korea from its more open rival to the south -- during an onstage chat here Saturday at the South by Southwest Interactive festival.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="2">The new Koryolink 3G network -- jointly owned by the North Korean government and an Egyptian company -- that launched last month marks a shift in policy for Kim Jong Un&amp;apost;s regime, which also has recently begun to allow foreigners to bring their cellphones into the country.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Austin, Texas &amp;quot;North Korean social media.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>In the famously restrictive country, where people have almost no Internet contact with the outside world, it sounds like an oxymoron.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>But on February 25, Jean H. Lee of the Associated Press became perhaps the first person to send a mobile tweet from North Korea when she posted a message on the country&amp;apost;s new 3G wireless network, available only to foreigners.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;Hello world from comms center in #Pyongyang,&amp;quot; she wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Lee has been active from North Korea on Instagram as well, posting snapshots of street scenes, food and government propaganda posters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>As the AP&amp;apost;s bureau chief for both South and North Korea, Lee is the only American news reporter granted regular access to the secretive nation, which she has visited more than 20 times.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>She offered a rare glimpse of digital life beyond the DMZ -- the strip of land separating North Korea from its more open rival to the south -- during an onstage chat here Saturday at the South by Southwest Interactive festival.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>At a time when North Korea is responding to tougher sanctions from the U.N. Security Council with angry rhetoric and threats, Lee described a country with two parallel digital worlds -- one for residents and another for foreign visitors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>While foreigners now have access to fast broadband Internet, with no firewall blocking certain sites, North Koreans can only use a state-controlled intranet service.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The country lags behind much of the world when it comes to digital adoption, but there are signs that North Korea is trying to catch up, Lee said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The new Koryolink 3G network -- jointly owned by the North Korean government and an Egyptian company -- that launched last month marks a shift in policy for Kim Jong Un&amp;apost;s regime, which also has recently begun to allow foreigners to bring their cellphones into the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are starting to see more openness,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re talking baby steps.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>They&amp;apost;re a long way from being a free and open society.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>When Lee first visited Pyongyang in 2008, security officers confiscated her iPhone at the airport, she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;I freaked out,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;I tried to hide it in my pocket.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Lee is joined in her social media updates from Pyongyang by AP photographer David Guttenfelder, who posts images often to his 71,000 Instagram followers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>His photos offer a fascinating peek at North Korean life and culture: Teens skating on a roller track, a woman braving a snowstorm, photos of his in-flight meal on Air Koryo, North Korea&amp;apost;s airline.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Lee said that North Korea, a country of about 25 million people, has only about 1 million cellphones, although the devices are gaining in popularity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>North Koreans can&amp;apost;t access Facebook or Twitter, although they have primitive social networks -- sort of like online bulletin boards -- where users share thoughts about innocuous topics such as pop music, she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Everything North Koreans do online is tied to their identity, Lee said, so it&amp;apost;s easy for the government to monitor users&amp;apost; intranet behavior.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Lee said she has spent a little time on the country&amp;apost;s limited web but hasn&amp;apost;t seen any evidence of people using underground networks to talk more freely.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;I would like to (see that).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>But it would be very dangerous, I imagine,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;They have a culture of fear in North Korea that still exists.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s something that isn&amp;apost;t going to change right away.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>When former NBA star Dennis Rodman made a bizarre visit to Pyongyang last month, Lee said she encouraged the unlikely ambassador to take advantage of the nation&amp;apost;s new 3G cellular network.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>He took her advice, later tweeting, &amp;quot;I come in peace.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>I love the people of North Korea!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Lee said the North Korean government has never tried to censor what she reports.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>But she is mindful that authorities may be monitoring her Web use.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;In any situation where I&amp;apost;m accessing their broadband, they can probably see everything I&amp;apost;m doing,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>