<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1588" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/06/26/tech/web/ebook-lending-pew/index.html" date_published="2012-06-26 22:24:24" category="tech" author="Amy Gahran, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>E-book lending: Your public library&amp;apost;s best kept secret?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Many Americans don&amp;apost;t know whether their public library has e-books, a new Pew report says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">Those who use e-books read 30% more books per year than those who don&amp;apost;t.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="8">If e-books encourage people to read more, that&amp;apost;s good for public libraries.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="25">However, library e-book acquisition has been complicated by higher publisher prices.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-31 16:18:20" annotation_time="105.731995">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Still, well over half of U.S. library card holders don&amp;apost;t know whether their local public library lends e-books, according to a new Pew report.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">Earlier this year, Pew research found that about one in five U.S. adults have read an e-book in the past year, and that e-book users tend to read over 30% more books per year than people who only read printed material.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="3">If e-books encourage people to read more, that&amp;apost;s good for public libraries -- which have a core mission to foster literacy and community engagement with information, culture and civic life.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="4">But evidence indicates that publishers may not have much to fear from library e-book lending -- just like they haven&amp;apost;t been hurt by library lending of print editions of current bestsellers.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>About three quarters of American public libraries currently lend out e-books, and in the past year libraries have seen a sharp growth in e-book borrowing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Still, well over half of U.S. library card holders don&amp;apost;t know whether their local public library lends e-books, according to a new Pew report.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Pew also found that 12% of all Americans age 16 and older who read e-books have borrowed an e-book from a library in the past year -- and they&amp;apost;re generally pretty happy with the experience.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Two thirds of them characterized their library&amp;apost;s selection of e-book titles as &amp;quot;excellent,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;very good&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;good.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Of course, there are occasional hitches.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Some library patrons reported waiting lists for popular e-books, or that the library e-book wasn&amp;apost;t offered in a format compatible with their device.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Earlier this year, Pew research found that about one in five U.S. adults have read an e-book in the past year, and that e-book users tend to read over 30% more books per year than people who only read printed material.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>If e-books encourage people to read more, that&amp;apost;s good for public libraries -- which have a core mission to foster literacy and community engagement with information, culture and civic life.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Also, lending e-books allows libraries to potentially serve more patrons beyond the hours and walls of their branches.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Eventually this might lead to smaller collections of printed books on library shelves, but it also could free up space to meet growing community needs for meeting rooms and computer labs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Money is a top concern for public libraries.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Lately most have been facing an especially severe budget crunch.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>This is motivating some libraries to making acquiring e-books a higher priority.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>According to Pew: &amp;quot;A number of librarians report that some funds for purchasing printed books have been shifted to e-book purchases.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Others&amp;apost; libraries have cut back on other media purchases, such as CD audiobooks, to free up funds for purchases of e-books.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Even though libraries have options to get many e-books for free, lending out many of the most popular titles definitely costs money.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>And this recently got considerably more expensive for libraries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Publishers have historically sold e-books to libraries (or to distributors such as Overdrive) at prices roughly equivalent to the retail hardcover price.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>However, in March, one of the largest U.S. publishers, Random House, suddenly increased its library pricing for e-books by as much as 300%.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>This was a big blow to libraries, which consider lending current bestsellers to be a critical service.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Random House is the only major publisher to make e-books of its entire catalog available to any public library for unrestricted lending.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The other &amp;quot;Big Six&amp;quot; publishers either refuse to allow libraries to lend out their e-books (at least their &amp;quot;front list&amp;quot; of current bestsellers), or they require libraries to periodically pay to re-license e-books.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Publishers have largely resisted e-book library lending because they&amp;apost;re concerned it might undermine their own e-book sales.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Why would consumers buy e-books if they can get them for free at the library?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>But evidence indicates that publishers may not have much to fear from library e-book lending -- just like they haven&amp;apost;t been hurt by library lending of print editions of current bestsellers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Pew found that nearly half of all Americans who have read a book in the previous year purchased their most recent book.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Only one fourth borrowed their most recent book from a friend; 14% borrowed it from a library.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Furthermore over half of e-book users who also hold library cards told Pew that they prefer to buy -- not borrow -- their e-books.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Among the library patrons who are currently borrowing e-books, only one-third say they generally prefer to buy e-books; 57% generally prefer to borrow them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>But, interestingly, slightly more library e-books borrowers told Pew that when they want to find an e-book, the first place they look is an online bookstore -- not the library.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>At least one major publisher is warming up to library e-book lending.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Last week, Penguin announced a pilot program to allow public libraries in New York City and Brooklyn to lend out its e-books via 3M&amp;apost;s Cloud Drive service.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>This is notable because last November Penguin pulled its books from Overdrive.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The community role of public libraries is evolving, and libraries are seeking ways to better meet the needs of people who are especially in need of their services.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Pew found that people who live in households with an annual income of less than $30,000, rural dwellers, and seniors are least likely to have a library card.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Pew asked people who don&amp;apost;t already borrow library e-books whether they might avail themselves of library programs that would prepare them for using e-books.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Nearly half said they would be &amp;quot;very&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;somewhat&amp;quot; likely to borrow an e-reading device that came loaded with a book they wanted.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>About a third would be at least somewhat likely to take library classes on how to download e-books onto handheld devices (including smartphones), or classes on how to use an e-reader or tablet computer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Pew also noted: &amp;quot;Those most interested in these services include some groups that librarians are especially eager to reach.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>African-Americans, Hispanics, and those who live in lower-income households are more likely than others to say they would be interested in borrowing pre-loaded e-reading devices and take classes about how to use the devices and download books.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Clearly, public libraries have more work to do with spreading the word that they have e-books to lend.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>It also wouldn&amp;apost;t hurt if the process of borrowing a e-book were less clunky at many libraries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>To find out whether your public library lends out e-books, check their website or ask a librarian.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Or conduct a library search on Overdrive.com.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>You&amp;apost;ll need a library card, of course -- so if you don&amp;apost;t already have one (more than 40% of Americans don&amp;apost;t), borrowing free e-books might be a good reason to finally visit your public library and get a library card.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
