<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1614" link="http://cnn.com/2013/09/10/tech/innovation/iphone-fingerprint-scanner/index.html" date_published="2013-09-10 22:04:23" category="tech" author="Doug Gross, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>iPhone 5S makes your finger into a password</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2, 1">On the iPhone 5S, Touch ID uses your fingerprint for security.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8">Fingerprint data is encrypted, stored on phone, not Apple servers.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="27">Some experts say Apple&amp;apost;s tech is nice, but won&amp;apost;t be game-changer.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-28 12:25:00" annotation_time="191.631">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">The most impressive feature of the new iPhone 5S may be its ability to turn your finger into a password.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Touch ID is Apple&amp;apost;s name for a new fingerprint scanner that would act as a security tool for log-ins and for making purchases from iTunes and other Apple stores.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">The fingerprint data is encrypted, Riccio said, and stored internally on the phone.</sentence>
      <sentence id="27" ids_highlights="3">David Rogers, director of the Columbia Business School&amp;apost;s Digital Marketing program and executive director of its Center for Global Brand Leadership, called Touch ID one of several &amp;quot;nice,&amp;quot; but ultimately underwhelming, features on the iPhone 5S.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The most impressive feature of the new iPhone 5S may be its ability to turn your finger into a password.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Touch ID is Apple&amp;apost;s name for a new fingerprint scanner that would act as a security tool for log-ins and for making purchases from iTunes and other Apple stores.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;Your fingerprint is one of the best passwords in the world,&amp;quot; said Dan Riccio, a senior vice president for hardware design at Apple, in a promotional video.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s always with you and no two are exactly alike.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Apple unveiled the iPhone 5S, along with a cheaper, simpler iPhone 5C, at an event Tuesday at the company&amp;apost;s California headquarters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>On the new 5S, the Home button will be made of sapphire crystal and act as a reader.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>According to Apple a fingerprint -- up to five prints from different users, depending on who else shares your phone -- can be read by the sensor from any angle to give access the same way a password does currently.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The fingerprint data is encrypted, Riccio said, and stored internally on the phone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s never available to other software and it&amp;apost;s never stored on Apple&amp;apost;s servers or backed up to iCloud,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The iPhone isn&amp;apost;t the first phone to have a fingerprint sensor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>In 2011, the Motorola ATRIX 4G included one, though adoption among users wasn&amp;apost;t particularly high and the company eventually discontinued the feature.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>And at least one Android phone to be released this year also will have the technology, according to a Wall Street Journal report.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Some laptops and PCs have had fingerprint readers for several years now.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>But the technology has never really caught on, with users often complaining about them being balky and unreliable.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Maybe Apple can change that.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;Fingerprint sensors have come a long way,&amp;quot; said Michael Barrett, president of the Fast Identity Online Alliance, an industry group advocating for universal security authentication tools.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;They are by and large much better quality now and very readily able to detect &amp;apost;Is this just an image of a finger or a real-life finger?&amp;apost;&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>But while he called Touch ID &amp;quot;an exciting announcement,&amp;quot; Barrett still sees some problems.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>First, he said, fingerprint scanning still isn&amp;apost;t perfect.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>He mentioned his wife, an artist, who has trouble accessing her PC with a fingerprint scanner when she&amp;apost;s been working with plaster, which dries out her hands.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;Like many biometrics, it falls slightly into &amp;apost;your mileage may vary,&amp;apost;&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;If it works for you, great.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>But it may not work for you all the time.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The former chief information security officer at PayPal, Barrett also sees limitations to using the system for online purchases.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>While it may work fine on iTunes or in the App Store, it&amp;apost;s not likely other Web retailers are going to spend millions of dollars to make their systems accommodate an Apple feature used on fewer than 17 percent of the world&amp;apost;s smartphones.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>That means iPhone 5S owners who used Touch ID for purchases inside Apple&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;walled garden&amp;quot; would still need to use other security tools to shop elsewhere with the same phone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>David Rogers, director of the Columbia Business School&amp;apost;s Digital Marketing program and executive director of its Center for Global Brand Leadership, called Touch ID one of several &amp;quot;nice,&amp;quot; but ultimately underwhelming, features on the iPhone 5S.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;Touch ID ... could have been that killer app.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>But so far, it&amp;apost;s just a feature that saves you a couple seconds logging in,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;If they can manage to link it to multiple profiles on a device, like the new Google Nexus tablets, or make it a password to controlling smart devices in the home -- your stereo, thermostat, etc. -- that could make for a truly killer feature.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>But they just didn&amp;apost;t get there today.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Paco Hope, principal consultant at software security firm Cigital, said that, if nothing else, Apple will widely expand the public&amp;apost;s understanding of the use of biometrics in the digital world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;People&amp;apost;s ideas about biometrics were as informed by Hollywood as they were by real products and experiences,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;Now, when someone asks the value of a fingerprint scanner, we can point to the iPhone and use it as a reference, for better or worse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;Esoteric and academic theories of usability, reliability, false positives, false negatives, and so on will suddenly be tested by millions of real users in real situations.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
