<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1669" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/06/04/tech/gaming-gadgets/parenting-digital-devices-study/index.html" date_published="2013-06-04 21:14:46" category="tech" author="Brandon Griggs, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>U.S. parents not worried about kids&amp;apost; digital-media use</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7">Study: Most parents in the U.S. are not concerned about their young children&amp;apost;s media use.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">Almost 60% say they&amp;apost;re not worried about their kids becoming addicted to digital devices.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">The Northwestern University survey of 2,300 parents was released Tuesday.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 16:24:24" annotation_time="27.053665" mapping_time_divergence="9.017888">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">Based on a nationally representative survey of more than 2,300 parents of children up to 8 years old, the study &amp;quot;reveals a generational shift in parental attitudes about technology&amp;apost;s role in young children&amp;apost;s lives,&amp;quot; said Ellen Wartella, director of Northwestern&amp;apost;s Center on Media and Human Development and lead author of the report.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">An overwhelming majority (78%) of parents say their children&amp;apost;s media use is not a source of family conflict, while 59% say they are not worried about their children becoming addicted to phones, tablet computers or gaming devices.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">The study found that 55% of parents are &amp;quot;not too&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;not at all&amp;quot; concerned about their children&amp;apost;s media use, compared to 30% who are concerned.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>With seemingly every kid in America glued most waking hours to a glowing digital device, you might expect their parents to be worried about the potentially harmful effects of all that screen time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Turns out, not so much.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The majority of parents in the United States are largely unconcerned about their young children&amp;apost;s media use, according to a Northwestern University study released Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>This despite 70% of parents saying that smartphones and tablets -- so-called &amp;quot;digital babysitters&amp;quot; used to appease bored or fussy kids -- don&amp;apost;t make parenting any easier.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Based on a nationally representative survey of more than 2,300 parents of children up to 8 years old, the study &amp;quot;reveals a generational shift in parental attitudes about technology&amp;apost;s role in young children&amp;apost;s lives,&amp;quot; said Ellen Wartella, director of Northwestern&amp;apost;s Center on Media and Human Development and lead author of the report.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>An overwhelming majority (78%) of parents say their children&amp;apost;s media use is not a source of family conflict, while 59% say they are not worried about their children becoming addicted to phones, tablet computers or gaming devices.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The study found that 55% of parents are &amp;quot;not too&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;not at all&amp;quot; concerned about their children&amp;apost;s media use, compared to 30% who are concerned.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The study, &amp;quot;Parenting in the Age of Digital Technology,&amp;quot; also challenges two key assumptions about media and parenting: First, that smartphones and tablets have become today&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;go-to&amp;quot; parenting tools.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Instead, parents say they are more likely to turn to toys or activities (88%), books (79%), or TV (78%) when trying to keep their children occupied.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Of those with smartphones or tablets, 37% say they are very or somewhat likely to turn to those devices.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Even when trying to calm an upset child, parents say they are still more likely to turn to a toy or activity (65%) or to a book (58%) than to a media device.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Second, the survey challenged the notion that the dominant pattern in most households is children pleading for screen time while parents try to limit it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;Today&amp;apost;s parents (of young children) grew up with technology as a central part of their lives, so they think about it differently than earlier generations of parents,&amp;quot; said Northwestern&amp;apost;s Wartella in a press release.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;Instead of a battle with kids on one side and parents on the other, the use of media and technology has become a family affair.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The impact of heavy media and technology use on kids&amp;apost; social, emotional and cognitive development is only beginning to be studied, although some early research suggests the Internet may actually be changing how our brains work.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Among the other findings of the report:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>-- With the exception of video games, parents think more positively than negatively about the impact of media (TV, computers and mobile devices) on children&amp;apost;s reading and math skills and their creativity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>-- Parents&amp;apost; most consistent concern about digital media is their negative impact on children&amp;apost;s physical activity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>-- Parents view video games more negatively than TV, computers or mobile devices.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Parents rated video games as more likely to have a negative effect on children&amp;apost;s academic skills, attention span, creativity, social skills, behavior and sleep than any other medium.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>-- Parents view computers as less harmful to their kids than TV or mobile devices.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The study was presented Tuesday at a conference on &amp;quot;Parenting in the Age of Digital Technology: How Families Use Media and Technology in Their Daily Lives,&amp;quot; at the Pew Charitable Trusts Conference Center in Washington.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
