<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1620" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/03/28/tech/mobile/commentary-windows-8/index.html" date_published="2012-03-28 14:06:23" category="tech" author="Steve Kovach, Business Insider" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Mac user: Why I love Windows 8</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">This fall, Microsoft will launch Windows 8, a radical redesign from the Windows of old.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">The classic Start menu is gone, replaced by a tile layout full of your favorite apps and files.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="13">In an un-Microsoft move, firm created the most radical desktop redesign in more than a decade.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 14:25:51" annotation_time="29.206">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">This fall, Microsoft will launch Windows 8, a radical redesign from the Windows you&amp;apost;ve grown accustomed to since Windows 95 made its debut 17 years ago.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">At first glance, you&amp;apost;ll notice the classic Start menu is gone, replaced by a gorgeous tile layout full of your favorite apps and files.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="3">In a very un-Microsoft move, the company created the most radical redesign of the desktop in well over a decade.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>I&amp;apost;ve been a Mac user for about 11 years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>And since I made the switch, I never thought the day would come when I&amp;apost;d say this:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>I&amp;apost;m excited for the next version of Windows.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>This fall, Microsoft will launch Windows 8, a radical redesign from the Windows you&amp;apost;ve grown accustomed to since Windows 95 made its debut 17 years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Windows 8 has been reimagined from the ground up, and it&amp;apost;s built to run on both the traditional desktop and touchscreen tablets.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>At first glance, you&amp;apost;ll notice the classic Start menu is gone, replaced by a gorgeous tile layout full of your favorite apps and files.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Microsoft calls this the &amp;quot;Metro&amp;quot; interface.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Imagine it as a blown-up version of the Windows Phone 7 interface used on several smartphones now.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Those little tiles provide live updates with news, sports, weather, Twitter mentions and Facebook updates without you even having to open the app.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>In one quick glance, you can get all the information you need.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s not the same old Windows.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>And that&amp;apost;s what makes me so excited to try the final version of Windows 8 this fall.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>In a very un-Microsoft move, the company created the most radical redesign of the desktop in well over a decade.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s incredibly functional, too.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>A beta version Windows 8 is available as a free consumer preview, and I&amp;apost;ve been using it for the last few weeks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Right now, there are only a handful of prototype tablets that run Windows 8, so I&amp;apost;ve been using it on a laptop instead.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>However, since the Metro interface is designed more for touch than a mouse cursor, there&amp;apost;s a bit of a learning curve with Windows 8.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Scrolling through the Start screen can get confusing on a keyboard until you learn all the shortcuts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>But once you do, the experience is incredible, unlike any operating system I&amp;apost;ve ever used.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s the perfect hybrid of old and new.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>While Apple attempts slowly to merge its mobile operating system into the desktop with new iPhone-like features, Microsoft made a bold move and jumped ahead to the future where most computing takes place on touch-friendly smartphones and tablets.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s enough to make an Apple fan like me drool.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>But what if you&amp;apost;re worried you won&amp;apost;t be able to catch on to the new look in Windows 8?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The classic Windows is still there in Windows 8.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Microsoft hid it behind the Metro interface.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>That means you get the same old taskbar, Start menu and desktop full of icons for your favorite apps.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a great way to ease the transition.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Plus, some apps such as Excel and Powerpoint just work better on the classic desktop.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Of course, it&amp;apost;s far too early to tell if Microsoft&amp;apost;s gamble with Windows 8 will pay off.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Consumers have been slow to adopt Windows Phones, and Windows 8 is essentially just a blown-up version of that.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>But if Microsoft can get me this pumped up over a new product, then it must be doing something right.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
