<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1635" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/06/04/tech/innovation/cousteau-mission-31" date_published="2014-06-04 20:47:20" category="tech" author="Katie Linendoll, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>One month under the sea with Fabien Cousteau</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Fabien Cousteau is living in a marine lab 63 feet beneath the ocean&amp;apost;s surface near Florida.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">Cousteau is a grandson of underwater explorer Jacques-Yves Cousteau.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">Mission 31 is named for the number of days his team will live underwater.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="4">They will study how climate change and pollution affect ocean life.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-25 21:11:12" annotation_time="24.928001">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1, 2">Cousteau, grandson of underwater explorer Jacques-Yves Cousteau, is spending the rest of June in Aquarius, the world&amp;apost;s only underwater marine lab, 63 feet beneath the ocean&amp;apost;s surface near Key Largo, Florida.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="4">Cousteau and a small team of researchers -- they like the term &amp;quot;aquanauts&amp;quot; -- will spend the month living together in cramped quarters while studying how climate change and pollution affect ocean life.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">The monthlong operation is called Mission 31, named for the number of days they will live underwater.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Could we one day live underwater?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Ask Fabien Cousteau -- a month from now.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Cousteau, grandson of underwater explorer Jacques-Yves Cousteau, is spending the rest of June in Aquarius, the world&amp;apost;s only underwater marine lab, 63 feet beneath the ocean&amp;apost;s surface near Key Largo, Florida.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Cousteau and a small team of researchers -- they like the term &amp;quot;aquanauts&amp;quot; -- will spend the month living together in cramped quarters while studying how climate change and pollution affect ocean life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The monthlong operation is called Mission 31, named for the number of days they will live underwater.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;I hope this will spawn a new focus on ocean exploration, whether it&amp;apost;s living in a habitat or beyond,&amp;quot; said Cousteau.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>He&amp;apost;ll be assisted by more than 30 support staff, including filmmakers and researchers from Florida International University, which operates the Aquarius lab.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;It takes 24 people topside just to have six people down below for 31 days, just like NASA does for the International Space Station,&amp;quot; Cousteau said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Some 50 years ago, Jacques Cousteau and a team of underwater researchers lived for a record 30 days in an ocean lab known as Conshelf II at the bottom of the Red Sea.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>With Mission 31, Fabien Cousteau hopes to honor his grandfather&amp;apost;s legacy while beating his record by one day.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The project also marks the first opportunity for fans to follow an underwater Cousteau expedition in real time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Thanks to Internet connectivity inside Aquarius, Fabien Cousteau hopes to reach millions of people through Skype, Instagram, Twitter chats and classroom sessions via streaming video at mission-31.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>com.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>We had a rare opportunity to visit Cousteau as he was undertaking his mission and get a glimpse of Aquarius, a lab that has been used by NASA astronauts in pre-mission training.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The 81-ton lab sits on stilts and resembles some kind of underwater machinery that&amp;apost;s covered with algae, barnacles and other growths.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Schools of fish, a stingray, tarpons, a nurse shark and a 300-pound grouper cruise by as we descend the 63 feet to the lab.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>We enter through something called a moon pool, a small chamber that leads to the entrance of Aquarius.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Going quickly from underwater to inside, we begin breathing normal air, but our bodies are still pressurized, so they&amp;apost;re reacting to dive-like conditions underwater.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Because of that, our time is limited before we have to go to the surface.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>At 400 square feet, the lab is the size of a small studio apartment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The air conditioning is broken, and you can feel the humidity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;You might find this to be a little weird and trippy, but I actually feel at home down here,&amp;quot; Cousteau said upon greeting us.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is amazing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>I couldn&amp;apost;t imagine a better house than one under sea.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Looking around, we see packets of dehydrated food and chips, which will feed the crew, who can&amp;apost;t cook anything.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>To heat a pan could cause a spark, which is too risky with all the flammable oxygen around.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>But while the meals are basic, the technology is advanced.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The lab and control room are equipped with Wi-Fi, which lets Cousteau use Skype and remain in contact with the world above.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>There are 4K cameras and dozens of GoPros, along with numerous computers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>There&amp;apost;s also a refrigerator and a half-dozen bunk beds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>A few personal mementos, like family snapshots, are sprinkled around.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>There are many things scientists already know about what happens when humans spend a lot of time underwater.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Weird things.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>After about 10 days, for example, you start to lose your sense of taste.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Your hair grows faster, your voice is higher -- due to atmospheric pressure -- and for some reason you can&amp;apost;t whistle (try and you will fail).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>After scuba diving for six to eight hours a day, you sleep like a baby.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>That may be helpful, considering Cousteau&amp;apost;s team is conducting the longest underwater sleep study to date.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Their sleep cycles are monitored constantly with smartwatches.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>While all this research is important, there&amp;apost;s one question that still lingers: What is the point of a mission like this?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Cousteau said it&amp;apost;s about more than just breaking records.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;I hope I am a firestarter, because at the end of the day, who wouldn&amp;apost;t want to be an aquanaut?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>&amp;quot;I mean, this is just an amazing place.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s our final frontier.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>We&amp;apost;ve explored less than 5% of our oceans, so there&amp;apost;s a lot left to do out there.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
