<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="22717" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/08/19/tech/innovation/city-of-tomorrow-lusail/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-08-19 13:41:29" category="tech" author="Brandon Griggs, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>2022 World Cup city rises in the desert - CNN.com</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Lusail is an ambitious planned city rising along the Persian Gulf in Qatar.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">Its infrastructure will be run by computers, making Lusail a &amp;quot;smart&amp;quot; city .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">A Lusail stadium is expected to host the final game of the 2022 World Cup.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="17">But FIFA is under pressure to move the event to another country.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 14:30:08" annotation_time="102.15">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">That&amp;apost;s essentially what the government of Qatar and its developers are trying with Lusail, an ambitious planned city on 28 square miles of waterfront desert along the Persian Gulf.</sentence>
	  <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">It also will feature an 86,000-seat soccer stadium, surrounded by a moat, that&amp;apost;s expected to host the final game of the 2022 FIFA World Cup.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">And all the energy, communications and transportation systems will be run with the help of computers from a single command center, making Lusail a &amp;quot;smart&amp;quot; city that can automatically adapt to changing traffic and weather conditions.</sentence>
	  <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="4">Some activists have been pressuring FIFA, soccer&amp;apost;s international governing body, to reconsider Qatar for a variety of reasons: allegations of bribery, the country&amp;apost;s condemnation of homosexuality and the blistering summer heat, which can reach 120 degrees Fahrenheit.</sentence>
	</gold_standard>
  </summaries>	
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>If you&amp;apost;re trying to create the perfect 21st-century city, it helps to start with a blank slate.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Even if that slate is a sweltering strip of sand.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s essentially what the government of Qatar and its developers are trying with Lusail, an ambitious planned city on 28 square miles of waterfront desert along the Persian Gulf.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Now under construction, the compact city will contain a commercial district, a lagoon, four islands, two marinas, an upscale shopping mall, a hospital, a zoo, two golf courses and housing for some 250,000 people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>It also will feature an 86,000-seat soccer stadium, surrounded by a moat, that&amp;apost;s expected to host the final game of the 2022 FIFA World Cup.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Residents and visitors will get around via a light-rail network, a water-taxi system and a network of underground pedestrian tunnels.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>And all the energy, communications and transportation systems will be run with the help of computers from a single command center, making Lusail a &amp;quot;smart&amp;quot; city that can automatically adapt to changing traffic and weather conditions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s very much an opportunity to build a vision of the future,&amp;quot; said Barry Hughes, senior vice president at HOK, the global architectural firm that designed Lusail&amp;apost;s Marina Mall shopping center.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Funded by the oil-rich Qatari government, Lusail can offer innovative solutions to urban problems because it&amp;apost;s being built from the ground up.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>For example, the city&amp;apost;s gas, electric and water lines are being laid out in an underground network of tunnels, allowing for maintenance work that won&amp;apost;t disrupt buildings, roads or people above.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The city will be fitted with a network of surveillance cameras, monitored around the clock, to keep streets safe.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Buildings will be cooled by solar power and chilled water pumped through a vast network of pipes, which the city&amp;apost;s developers say is cheaper and more energy efficient than electrical air conditioning.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Human waste will be disposed not through sewer lines but a more efficient network of pneumatic, or vacuum tubes, not unlike the ones at your bank&amp;apost;s drive-up window.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Some 20,000 workers -- a small city unto itself -- are building Lusail at an estimated cost of $45 billion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Developers hope to complete the city by 2019, three years before Qatar is scheduled to become the first Arab country to host the World Cup.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>But all the city&amp;apost;s sparkling features will lose some of their luster if soccer&amp;apost;s big global tournament gets moved to another locale.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Some activists have been pressuring FIFA, soccer&amp;apost;s international governing body, to reconsider Qatar for a variety of reasons: allegations of bribery, the country&amp;apost;s condemnation of homosexuality and the blistering summer heat, which can reach 120 degrees Fahrenheit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>There also have been allegations that Qatar has used slave labor -- mostly migrant workers from Nepal -- to build Lusail&amp;apost;s infrastructure.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>A report last year by the Guardian, the UK newspaper, said at least 44 construction workers had died of heart attacks and other ailments in a two-month period of 2013 amid grueling conditions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The state-run Lusail Real Estate Development Company, which is spearheading construction of the city, has said it&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;extremely concerned&amp;quot; about the slave-labor allegations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>In a statement on its website, the company added that it&amp;apost;s investigating the charges, which involve one of its subcontractors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;Lusail City will not tolerate breaches of labor or health and safety law,&amp;quot; the company said in the statement, posted in response to the Guardian article.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>It declined to respond to CNN&amp;apost;s requests for comment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In response to criticisms, Qatar in May announced reforms to its labor laws, which had bound workers to a single employer and left them open to exploitation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>This appeared to satisfy FIFA President Sepp Blatter, who called the changes &amp;quot;a significant step in the right direction.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>As for the brutal heat, Qatar says its stadiums will contain advanced, open-air cooling systems that will keep World Cup players and fans comfortable.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Meanwhile, Lusail continues to rise slowly in the Qatar desert.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Anchoring the city&amp;apost;s skyline will be four commercial towers, up to 75 stories each.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>These will be surrounded by five-star hotels, an entertainment district and the Marina Mall, a retail palace measuring more than 600,000 square feet.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Scheduled to open in 2017, the mall is a cluster of five interconnected pods, shaped like giant boulders, with cantilevered white roofs to repel the heat.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Its architects want the space to evoke desert canyons.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>A canal runs through it, and waterfalls splash throughout.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The scope and design of the mall echoes the grand, futuristic vision for Lusail itself.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is a very ambitious and optimistic plan,&amp;quot; said Daniel Hajjar, a senior vice president in HOK&amp;apost;s Dubai office.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a plan that has helped land Qatar the World Cup.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>But Hajjar said Lusail will be completed even if FIFA has a change of heart and finds a new host for the event.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;Qatar has a path ... they&amp;apost;re pursuing,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;It won&amp;apost;t affect their decision to move forward and get it built.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
