<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1586" link="http://www.cnn.com/2011/09/02/tech/mobile/cell-phone-emergency" date_published="2011-09-02 20:25:49" category="tech" author="Amy Gahran, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Does your emergency kit have a cell phone?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7">In emergency, expect you might not have cell service immediately, be prepared .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12">Keep contacts updated across platforms, including phone, e-mail and social media.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="26">If you have little or no cell signal, it might be a good idea to turn your phone off .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="47">A hand-crank charger is a must-have part of your emergency kit.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-12 14:17:16" annotation_time="42.6155">
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">So in those emergencies, expect that you might not have cell service immediately -- and be prepared with information, supplies, and skills to get you through that crucial time.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;Keep your contacts updated across all of your channels, including phone, e-mail and social media.</sentence>
      <sentence id="26" ids_highlights="3">So if you see that you have little or no cell signal, it might be a good idea to turn your phone off most of the time and just check in occasionally to see if better signal has returned.</sentence>
      <sentence id="47" ids_highlights="4">A hand-crank charger is a must-have part of your emergency kit.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>September is National Preparedness Month -- do you know where your cell phone is, and how to use it during an emergency?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>According to The New York Times, U.S. wireless networks proved fairly resilient when Hurricane Irene recently swept the eastern seaboard.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Many people who lost power or landlines were still able to communicate via cell phones using voice calls, text or multimedia messaging, e-mail, and social media.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Of course, in this case wireless network operators had days to prepare for the storm.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>As CNET reported, they were able to get generators and backup equipment in place to keep their cell towers functioning.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>This would not be possible for sudden kinds of emergencies, such as tornadoes or earthquakes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>So in those emergencies, expect that you might not have cell service immediately -- and be prepared with information, supplies, and skills to get you through that crucial time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Soon after an emergency strikes (within hours or days), carriers usually bring in extra cell phone towers on wheels -- and generators or solar cells -- to compensate for damaged towers or to supplement coverage in areas where evacuees or emergency responders are located.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>So after an emergency cell networks are among the first pieces of infrastructure to come back online -- often before power, landlines, and drinking-water systems.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The Federal Emergency Management Administration&amp;apost;s Get Tech Ready page offers some handy tips for getting your phone ready to use during an emergency.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Here are some of the basics:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Keep your contacts updated across all of your channels, including phone, e-mail and social media.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>This will make it easy to reach out to the right people quickly to get information and supply updates.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Consider creating a group list serve of your top contacts.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;Learn how to send updates via text and Internet from your mobile phone to your contacts and social channels in case voice communications are not available.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Text messages and the Internet often have the ability to work in the event of a phone service disruption.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;Keep extra batteries for your phone in a safe place or purchase a solar-powered or hand crank charger.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>These chargers are good emergency tools to keep your laptop and other small electronics working in the event of a power outage.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>This part may be a little more challenging than you&amp;apost;d expect.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Power is a key challenge.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>While smartphones offer the most mobile-communication options, they&amp;apost;re also notorious energy hogs with batteries that tend to last less than a day with average use.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>So if, like 35% of Americans, you own a smartphone, it&amp;apost;s a good idea to know how to trim your power consumption so you can extend your battery life in an emergency.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Lifehacker published a great guide to saving your smartphone&amp;apost;s battery.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>It might be worth printing that out and storing it in your emergency kit -- but also read it over and try out the measures it recommends now, when you&amp;apost;re not in a rush, to figure out what works best for you and your phone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Low cell signals can drain your battery quickly because your phone can expend considerable energy searching for towers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>So if you see that you have little or no cell signal, it might be a good idea to turn your phone off most of the time and just check in occasionally to see if better signal has returned.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>If the signal is low, turn off your 3G or 4G data connection if possible most of the time and stick to low-bandwidth uses like text messaging.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Although FEMA recommends keeping your contacts updated across all your channels, that can be a challenge.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>While contact syncing works fairly well on some phones, on others it&amp;apost;s confusing and unreliable.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>(I&amp;apost;ve definitely found that to be a challenge with my Android phone.).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>So don&amp;apost;t underestimate the low-tech fallback: paper.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Personally, I maintain a text file that lists all important phone numbers, e-mail addresses, URLs, Twitter IDs, and shortcodes that I&amp;apost;ll want to have in an emergency.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>I print that out every time I update it, and store the latest copy in my emergency kit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Make sure your local office for emergency management is on that list -- as well as the local offices for places where your loved ones live or work.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Find out which of these offices offer text-messaging alerts, or have numbers where you can send text messages in an emergency.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Also, learn to do as much as you can with text messaging.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>For instance, you can update Twitter via text message, and interact with many other online services (such as your bank, or some insurance companies -- so make sure all relevant account numbers are in your emergency kit, too).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Text messaging is a clunky interactive interface, so practice this skill in advance.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Don&amp;apost;t try to learn it during an emergency.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>It may also be a good to have a simple second cell phone as an emergency.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>You don&amp;apost;t need to pay a monthly bill on it, just get some prepaid minutes or text messages.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Very simple phones tend to hold a charge much longer than smartphones or even many feature phones.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>The Motorola Motofone F3 is the phone I keep on hand for emergencies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>It holds a standby charge for months, and can operate for weeks on a single charge.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>I keep my important phone numbers and shortcodes programmed in it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>The catch is, prepaid minutes expire -- so if you go this route, mark your calendar to use your minutes before they expire, and recharge the SIM card with the carrier as needed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>A hand-crank charger is a must-have part of your emergency kit.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>A solar charger may also help, but hand-crank chargers can be used day or night and tend to charge phones faster.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Many emergency radios include a hand-crank charger and mini or micro USB ports.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>So keep a couple of extra cables in your emergency kit to charge your phone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>If you use Dropbox (a cloud-based file storage service) or Evernote (a free service for taking, storing, and sharing notes), it may be a good idea to post your important documents and contact info in a private folder there, install the associated apps on your smartphone, and practice using it on the go.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Both services also offer the ability to share folders with selected individuals -- so in advance you might want to share an &amp;quot;emergency info&amp;quot; folder to some people you trust who live in other parts of the country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>They could use these services to send you the text of news stories and Web pages, maps, e-mails, and more to help you get through the emergency -- and you can access this in one place, whenever you have time or connectivity (whether on your phone, or maybe a computer in a shelter).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>You can also use your mobile phone to assist emergency responders locally or elsewhere by gathering important information to coordinate relief efforts.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>This can range from knowing how to tweet usefully, to adding information to crowdsourced crisis maps, to supplying photos or videos of affected areas.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>But the most important points are to keep a cell phone and charger in your emergency kit, know how to keep it charged, program in the numbers and info you&amp;apost;ll need, keep that information up to date, know how to use it to send text messages, and (if prepaid) make sure the minutes aren&amp;apost;t expired.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>More emergency preparedness tips and tools can be found here: Ready.gov.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>The opinions expressed in this post are solely those of Amy Gahran.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
