<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1682" link="http://www.cnn.com/2011/09/26/tech/social-media/facebook-users-will-revolt-cashmore/index.html" date_published="2011-09-26 21:03:38" category="tech" author="Pete Cashmore, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>You&amp;apost;ll freak when you see the new Facebook</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Facebook is about to completely change the way its profile pages look .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="15">Cashmore: I thrive on new things, but this change was radical even for me.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="19">Your profile will become a scrapbook documenting your entire life, all the way back to birth.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-12 15:10:41" annotation_time="42.532997">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Facebook is about to completely change the way its profile pages look as part of the website&amp;apost;s biggest redesign so far, and only a fraction of the website&amp;apost;s 800 million users seem to have the slightest clue.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="2">I&amp;apost;m someone who thrives on trying new things, but this change was radical even for me.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="3">Rather than just displaying your most recent activities, your profile will become a scrapbook documenting your entire life, all the way back to your birth.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Facebook users, mark my words: You&amp;apost;ll revolt when the site rolls out its new features in the coming weeks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Facebook is about to completely change the way its profile pages look as part of the website&amp;apost;s biggest redesign so far, and only a fraction of the website&amp;apost;s 800 million users seem to have the slightest clue.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>I&amp;apost;m not talking about the new real-time &amp;quot;Ticker&amp;quot; at the top right of your Facebook profile.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>I&amp;apost;m not even talking about the &amp;quot;Top Stories&amp;quot; that now appear at the top of your Facebook news feed -- those are tiny, insignificant changes compared to what&amp;apost;s just around the corner.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>But boy, did some people react badly to even those minuscule improvements.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Among my Facebook friends, more than half said they disliked the changes and some threatened to quit.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Of course, they did no such thing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>How will they react when Facebook throws away the old profiles and replaces them with something completely new?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>If you use Facebook, chances are you&amp;apost;re unaware of the major changes that are slated to begin rolling out by the end of this month (full disclosure: Mashable is one of several news organizations partnering with Facebook on a social news app).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Only geeks like me are obsessed enough to have watched Facebook&amp;apost;s 90-minute announcement of the new profile pages last week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>And an even smaller percentage of Facebook users have discovered, like I did, that you can enable the new &amp;quot;Facebook Timeline&amp;quot; profile page right now so you&amp;apost;re prepared for the launch.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>So what&amp;apost;s the big change?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Facebook will be switching profile pages, perhaps optionally at first, to a new format called &amp;quot;Facebook Timeline.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>I switched my profile over last week and boy was it a shock -- I immediately wanted to switch it back to the old format.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>I&amp;apost;m someone who thrives on trying new things, but this change was radical even for me.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Yet I could find no way to switch my profile back, so I stuck with it for a few days.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>I&amp;apost;m so glad I did: Facebook Timeline is the best change Facebook has ever made.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Here&amp;apost;s what&amp;apost;ll happen once the Timeline profiles are launched: Your Facebook profile will go from having one central column to two, with boxes of text, photos, videos and even maps of your favorite locations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Rather than just displaying your most recent activities, your profile will become a scrapbook documenting your entire life, all the way back to your birth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Facebook will become a record of your existence: All your memories, your victories and your defeats, your loves, your losses and everything in between.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>You&amp;apost;ll be shocked, as I was, when this change is made.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Suddenly your life is laid out before you, the highs and lows somehow pinpointed by Facebook&amp;apost;s algorithms.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>You&amp;apost;ll wonder why the status update box is so tiny now, and where all your most recent updates went.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>You&amp;apost;ll add a big, new &amp;quot;Cover photo&amp;quot; to your page and waste a few hours preening your Timeline, choosing to feature your happiest memories, hide the inconsequential ones, and lingering awhile on the most bittersweet of moments.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>And you&amp;apost;ll realize, as I did, that Facebook knows you better than you know yourself.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Through this process, you&amp;apost;ll realize that Facebook Timeline is much more than a way to post the minutiae of your existence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>While a typical social networking profile might highlight what you ate this morning, or what time you left for work, or where you had lunch, Facebook Timeline takes these thousands of seemingly inconsequential events, discards the irrelevant ones, finds the most emotive, the most visual, the most striking and emotionally touching moments and pulls them into sharp focus.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Much like our memories, Facebook Timeline understands that some moments have resonance that lasts through the years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a marvel of computer programming: An algorithm that comes eerily close to emulating human memory; perhaps the first algorithm to spark such a deep emotional response.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>So yes, you will hate the new Facebook profile when it launches in the coming weeks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Then, like me, you&amp;apost;ll realize that Facebook has unleashed something so remarkable that you didn&amp;apost;t even recognize it at first: A meaningful social network.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>And like any other groundbreaking technology -- the PC, the smartphone, the iPad -- you&amp;apost;ll wonder why life wasn&amp;apost;t always this way, and how you got by without it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
