<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1641" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/07/14/tech/nasa-search-for-life/index.html?hpt=hp_mid" date_published="2014-07-15 03:17:28" category="tech" author="Suzanne Presto, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Scientists: We&amp;apost;re &amp;apost;very close&amp;apost; to finding another Earth</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">NASA convenes panel on search for life in the universe.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">Scientist says technological advancements have increased likelihood of finding Earth&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;twin&amp;apost;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="24">New space telescopes will allow scientists to find multitude of new planets, panel says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-11 10:23:13" annotation_time="51.312" mapping_time_divergence="34.208">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">That was the consensus of a panel on the search for life in the universe held at NASA headquarters Monday in Washington.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;We believe we&amp;apost;re very, very close in terms of technology and science to actually finding the other Earth and our chance to find signs of life on another world,&amp;quot; said Sara Seager, a MacArthur Fellow and professor of planetary science and physics at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="3">NASA&amp;apost;s assembled panelists said, if they follow this map of stars, they&amp;apost;re certain to find a multitude of new planets.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Scientists looking for signs of life in the universe -- as well as another planet like our own -- are a lot closer to their goal than people realize.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>That was the consensus of a panel on the search for life in the universe held at NASA headquarters Monday in Washington.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The discussion focused not only on the philosophical question of whether we&amp;apost;re alone in the universe but also on the technological advances made in an effort to answer that question.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;We believe we&amp;apost;re very, very close in terms of technology and science to actually finding the other Earth and our chance to find signs of life on another world,&amp;quot; said Sara Seager, a MacArthur Fellow and professor of planetary science and physics at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;Finding Earth&amp;apost;s twin, that&amp;apost;s kind of the holy grail,&amp;quot; said John Grunsfeld, an astronaut who helped repair the Hubble Space Telescope in 2009 and is now an associate administrator at NASA.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Strides in the search for life.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Scientists have made stellar strides in the past few years alone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;We already know that our galaxy has at least 100 billion planets, and we didn&amp;apost;t know that five years ago,&amp;quot; said Matt Mountain, director of the Space Telescope Science Institute in Maryland.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>He credited the work of the Kepler Space Telescope for these new discoveries.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The planet-hunting Kepler probe, launched in 2009, finds planets by looking for dips in the brightness of a star as a planet transits, or crosses, in front of that star.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Kepler also found the first Earth-size planet that orbits in a star&amp;apost;s habitable zone, the area around a star where a planet could exist with liquid water on its surface.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The Kepler mission builds upon the stalwart Hubble Space Telescope, which launched in 1990 and was the first of its kind to be placed in space.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>As Hubble orbits the Earth, it allows scientists to peer back in time, into distant galaxies, and yields stunning images of the cosmos.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Hubble has helped shape our awareness of our planet&amp;apost;s place in an ever-changing universe.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The Earth, though 4.5 billion years old, is a newcomer, said John Mather, senior project scientist on NASA&amp;apost;s next-generation James Webb Space Telescope.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s only about one-third of the age of the universe.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>And our galaxy is ever-evolving, with &amp;quot;about five or 10 new stars being born per year in our Milky Way,&amp;quot; Mather said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Planet hunters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Hubble&amp;apost;s astounding views come from a vantage point only 353 miles above our Earth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>In comparison, the James Webb telescope will be a whopping 930,000 miles from our planet.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s close to four times the distance between the Earth and the moon.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Webb is set to launch in 2018.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Mountain, who is the telescope scientist for Webb, said scientists now know where every single star is within 200 light years of the Sun.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>NASA&amp;apost;s assembled panelists said, if they follow this map of stars, they&amp;apost;re certain to find a multitude of new planets.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;Every star in the sky is a sun, and if our sun has planets, we naturally expect those other stars to have planets also, and they do,&amp;quot; said Seager.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>She said if someone looked up at a starry sky and wondered how many of the stars have planets, the answer would be &amp;quot;basically every single one.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Some of a star&amp;apost;s light will shine through the atmosphere, said Seager, and the Webb telescope should be able to pick up gases from the planet that are imprinted on the atmosphere.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>While the Webb telescope wasn&amp;apost;t designed to find signs of life on another planet, it can spot biosignature gases -- gases in the atmosphere produced by life.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Seager said, with the James Webb telescope, &amp;quot;we have our first chance, our first capability of finding signs of life on another planet.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Now nature just has to provide for us.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Spotting Earths.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Finding small planets, ones the size of Earth, is challenging, in part because they produce fainter signals, said Dave Gallagher, director for astronomy and physics at NASA&amp;apost;s Jet Propulsion Laboratory, who likened it to spotting a firefly beside a searchlight.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>That difficulty doesn&amp;apost;t dull the hunt for another Earth or signs of life.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>NASA administrator Charles Bolden said he counts himself among the people who &amp;quot;are probably convinced that it&amp;apost;s highly improbable in the limitless vastness of the universe that we humans stand alone.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
