<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1643" link="http://www.cnn.com/2011/10/25/tech/gaming-gadgets/smaller-cheaper-tablets/index.html" date_published="2011-10-25 14:34:59" category="tech" author="Amy Gahran, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Smaller, cheaper tablets could become a big deal</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="10">Tablets let people do what can be done on a laptop in an easier way.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="17">In the last year Android tablets grew from 2% in the global market to 27%.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="37">Gadgets that are more complex or open-ended tend to frustrate most consumers.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-01 17:10:25" annotation_time="25.775335">
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="1">The grand vision of tablet computers is that, ideally, they&amp;apost;ll allow the average, non-geeky person to do most of what can be done with a laptop computer -- in a way that&amp;apost;s much easier to learn, use and carry around.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="2">According to a new report from Strategy Analytics, in the last year Android tablets grew from 2% of the global tablet market to 27%.</sentence>
      <sentence id="37" ids_highlights="3">Gadgets that are more complex or open-ended tend to confuse or frustrate average consumers -- which generally isn&amp;apost;t good for sales.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Smaller tablet computers that are significantly more affordable and portable than the iPad are finally starting to hit the United States -- and they could hit a crucial sweet spot in the consumer market.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Recently Kobo announced the new Kobo Vox, which costs $200.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s the same price as Amazon&amp;apost;s recently announced Kindle Fire.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The Kobo Vox starts shipping Friday, while the Kindle Fire won&amp;apost;t start shipping until November 15.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The Barnes &amp;amp; Noble Nook Color, which costs about $250, is already available in stores and online.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Although marketed mainly as e-book readers, all three of these consumer devices are actually small tablet computers (7 inches) that run the Android mobile operating system and use Wi-Fi -- no carrier data plan or contract required.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>So theoretically, they can do much more than just let you buy and read e-books.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>This makes them potentially powerful tools for people who want access to the Web, apps and more -- especially people who face economic or other barriers to using smartphones or computers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Small, inexpensive, easy-to-use tablets could become an important bridge to help people cross the digital divide and gain expanded access to education, jobs, community, and other resources.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The grand vision of tablet computers is that, ideally, they&amp;apost;ll allow the average, non-geeky person to do most of what can be done with a laptop computer -- in a way that&amp;apost;s much easier to learn, use and carry around.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Certainly this is the case with Apple&amp;apost;s iPad, which sold 11 million units in the last quarter alone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>But at this point, iPads start at $500 -- about what you might pay for a brand new 32-inch flat-screen TV at Best Buy, and twice or more what PC netbooks cost at most retail stores.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>From the perspective of typical consumers, especially given the current economy, that&amp;apost;s a significant luxury investment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>This month there are fresh rumors that Apple may be planning to introduce a smaller and less costly &amp;quot;iPad mini.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>But nothing is confirmed, so don&amp;apost;t hold your breath.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The tablet market is growing fast, and its dynamics are shifting quickly.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>According to a new report from Strategy Analytics, in the last year Android tablets grew from 2% of the global tablet market to 27%.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Meanwhile, the iPad&amp;apost;s global tablet market share has dropped from 96% to 67%.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>That doesn&amp;apost;t reflect a decrease in the iPad&amp;apost;s popularity, but rather that consumer demand for tablets is not one-size-fits-all.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>In fact, size is a key issue for people shopping for tablets.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The iPad measures roughly 7-by-10 inches -- too big for a typical pocket or purse, and nearly twice the size of the basic Kobo Vox, Nook Color and Kindle Fire models.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Digital devices that aren&amp;apost;t as easy to carry around tend to mainly get used only at certain times of day, in certain settings.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>For this reason it&amp;apost;s questionable how &amp;quot;mobile&amp;quot; larger tablets like the iPad really are.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Aside from the Vox, Fire, and Nook Color, there are lots of other small Android tablets available.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>But so far these products have faced various challenges in the consumer market:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Cost: The Wi-Fi-only version of Samsung&amp;apost;s 7-inch Galaxy Tab costs about $350, which is on the pricier side.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The carrier-branded versions cost much less to buy up front if you agree to a two-year contract.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>For instance, Verizon currently sells the 7-inch Galaxy Tab for just $200, but data plans cost $30-$80 per month, and there&amp;apost;s a $350 early termination fee.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Philadelphia Newspapers Inc., publisher of the Philadelphia Inquirer and Daily News, is selling a small Android tablet by Arnova for just $99-$129 in a small pilot program -- but for that bargain-basement price you have to agree to a one- or two-year newspaper subscription, costing up to $13 per month.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Device quality: This is an issue for the cheapest tablets.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>For instance, one reviewer noted that the touchscreen performance on the Philly.com tablet is less than stellar.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>In contrast, the Nook Color has been getting generally favorable reviews for device quality.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The advance Kindle Fire reviews are also mostly positive.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Android&amp;apost;s learning curve: This can be an obstacle for some.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The straightforward Android experience that comes with tablets by Samsung, Motorola, Lenovo, and other manufacturers can be daunting to typical consumers -- especially the majority of U.S. consumers who don&amp;apost;t yet own a smartphone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>A more constrained but dependable out-of-the-box user experience can be simpler to learn and can make the average consumer happier, at least initially.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Gadgets that are more complex or open-ended tend to confuse or frustrate average consumers -- which generally isn&amp;apost;t good for sales.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Despite the high relative cost of Apple devices, and the fairly closed nature of the Apple ecosystem, there&amp;apost;s a lot to be said for &amp;quot;It just works.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>However, most &amp;quot;pure&amp;quot; Android tablets do offer one key advantage over constrained e-reader tablets: direct access to Google&amp;apost;s Android Market, where there&amp;apost;s a virtually unlimited choice of apps.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The Fire, Nook Color, and Philly.com tablets only offer apps through their own markets, not the Android Market, which means they can block the installation of competing apps, such those from other e-book vendors or publishers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Also, even though Kobo touts that its Vox will offer access to &amp;quot;over 15,000 apps,&amp;quot; the company has not clarified whether that will be through the Android Market or its own app store.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Which means it&amp;apost;s possible that you may not be able to install the Kindle e-reader app on the Kobo Vox -- at least, not without &amp;quot;rooting&amp;quot; the tablet to remove vendor controls, which can be a formidable technical hurdle.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>The coming year -- especially the 2011 holiday season -- will probably indicate whether smaller tablets will play a leading role in the U.S. digital media landscape.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>If these devices start becoming as commonplace as iPhones and Kindles, they may become popular and powerful tools for the delivery of mobile services for health, education, jobs, and more.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Sure, you can use a small, cheap tablet to read books, watch YouTube, and play &amp;quot;Angry Birds.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>But maybe someday lots of people will be using these devices to get a college degree -- or perhaps to learn to read in the first place.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>The opinions expressed in this post are solely those of Amy Gahran.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
