<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1785" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/06/30/travel/holographic-staff-and-no-lost-luggage/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-06-30 13:18:51" category="travel" author="Teo Kermeliotis, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Holographic staff and no lost luggage: Future of travel</title>
  <keywords>skyscanner,airport,flight,future of travel,technology,2024,future of travel report skyscanner,skyscanner report 2024,future of travel,travel skyscanner,future of travel 2024,skyscanner cnn</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="9">Skyscanner released Monday the second part of its &amp;quot;Future of Travel&amp;quot; report.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="10">It predicts that journeys in 2024 &amp;quot;will be almost unrecognizable&amp;quot; from today&amp;apost;s stressful experience.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="11">The report says airports will become smart spaces that will allow travelers to enjoy an automated journey.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-31 23:07:31" annotation_time="33.367">
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="1">The travel booking site released Monday the second part of its &amp;quot;Future of Travel&amp;quot; report which looks at what travel journeys will look like in 2024.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="2">Compiled by a team of 56 experts and futurologists from the travel and tech industries, the study predicts that future travel journey &amp;quot;will be almost unrecognizable from the often time consuming and stressful experience of 2014.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="3">In 10 years&amp;apost; time airports will be intelligent spaces that will allow travelers to enjoy an automated and stress free journey.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A driverless taxi is waiting for you outside your house.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Cruising through the city, you arrive safely at the airport where you drop off your luggage while ordering a coffee.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Check-in is then a matter of just a few seconds, thanks to facial recognition software, while distant biometric scanning allows you to avoid long security queues.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Walking past interactive shopping windows, yoga studios and outdoor green terraces, you arrive at the departure hall, a bright uplifting space dotted with paintings by the French impressionist masters.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>After having a look around, holographic airport staff guide you to your boarding gate.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>You soon find yourself aboard sitting in your body morphing seat that is fully-equipped with all the movies from your favorite director.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>No, this is not science fiction.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Instead, this is how your airport travel experience will be in just 10 years from now-- according to Skyscanner.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The travel booking site released Monday the second part of its &amp;quot;Future of Travel&amp;quot; report which looks at what travel journeys will look like in 2024.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Compiled by a team of 56 experts and futurologists from the travel and tech industries, the study predicts that future travel journey &amp;quot;will be almost unrecognizable from the often time consuming and stressful experience of 2014.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>In 10 years&amp;apost; time airports will be intelligent spaces that will allow travelers to enjoy an automated and stress free journey.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Emerging technologies will transform airlines into virtual hubs where passengers will be able to create their own havens to suit their personal preferences.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;Airports and flights will no longer be the price we pay to travel but instead will signify the start of our holidays where travelers can relax and create the perfect space to suit their needs whether they&amp;apost;re flying for business or leisure,&amp;quot; says Filip Filipov, Skyscanner&amp;apost;s Head of B2B.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Here, based on Skyscanner&amp;apost;s predictions, CNN&amp;apost;s On The Move presents the top three things you can expect to experience at the airport and while flying in 2024.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>1.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Self-service check-in, scanning sensors and digital bag tags.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Future travelers will take complete control of their journey, which will be free of check-in desks and long queues.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Biometric check-in software will eliminate the need for boarding passes and passport checks, while X-ray machines will also become a thing of the past thanks to sensors capable of scanning big groups from a large distance.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Digital luggage tags pre-set with flight details and destination information will allow passengers to track their bags in real time throughout their trip.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;You&amp;apost;d be able to see where your bag is at all time,&amp;quot; says Filipov, &amp;quot;and when it is arriving.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>2.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Art, yoga and waterfalls.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Once past security, out go the blunt and dull and in come the cool and splendor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The soulless departure lounges and mundane transit areas of today will be replaced by uplifting, comfortable lounges filled with paintings and sculptures.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>If you don&amp;apost;t feel like delving into the world of art, amenities ranging from rooftop swimming pools and 3D cinemas to gyms and open-air parks will offer a pleasant distraction before boarding your flight.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Similarly, virtual shopping walls will replace duty free stores, with passengers able to order goods with a simple verbal command.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;You will be able to select the goods that you&amp;apost;d like to buy and have them delivered to your home potentially when you&amp;apost;re back from vacation,&amp;quot; says Filipov.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>3.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;apost;Your home in the air&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>In cabin smart lighting will make jetlag a thing of the past, while seats that mold to the passengers&amp;apost; body shape will come with pre-loaded films and music according to their tastes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>A mix between a mobile living room and a virtual office, the seating will also allow travelers to hold 3D chats with their family, friends or business contacts through Skype hologram systems.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;That seat will become your home, in a way, in the air,&amp;quot; says Filipov.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;It will actually be tailored to you, not in terms of how it looks and how it feels but rather the multimedia that goes with it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>