<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1764" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/01/24/travel/concordia-victim-compensation/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2012-01-24 21:28:19" category="travel" author="Marnie Hunter, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Costa denies &amp;apost;unfounded&amp;apost; reports of survivor discounts</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Cruise line denies offering discounts on future cruises to survivors.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="10">Costa did offer discounts to passengers set to sail January 14 and beyond.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="13">Concordia passengers will be reimbursed for all expenses, Costa announced.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="15">Indemnity for hardship suffered has not been determined.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-24 13:36:34" annotation_time="47.908337">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">The cruise line issued a statement Tuesday denying that it offered discounts on future cruises to passengers who were aboard Concordia when it ran aground.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="2">The cruise line did offer 30% off on future cruises to guests who were scheduled to sail on the Concordia from January 14 and beyond, which Askin called &amp;quot;perfectly ordinary&amp;quot; compensation for people booked on cruises canceled because of an incapacitated ship.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="3">All costs associated with travel to the port of embarkation and the return home, including transfer arrangements made independently of the cruise line, will be reimbursed, as will medical expenses, cash deposits and any expenses incurred on board.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="4">The company has been following up on the emotional and physical well-being of affected passengers, the statement said, and talking with tourism trade associations and consumer protection groups to determine indemnity for passengers for the hardship endured.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Costa Cruises is on the defensive again.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The cruise line issued a statement Tuesday denying that it offered discounts on future cruises to passengers who were aboard Concordia when it ran aground.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The statement was in response to news reports that the cruise line offered 30% off on future travel to some survivors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;The company has never offered any discount on future cruises to our guests who were on board Costa Concordia for the cruise of Jan. 13 and involved in the tragic accident,&amp;quot; Costa&amp;apost;s statement said, calling reports published by various news outlets &amp;quot;unfounded.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>An internal investigation into the reports that surfaced over the weekend revealed no evidence of discounts being offered to disaster survivors, said Buck Banks, Costa&amp;apost;s North American spokesman.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;There&amp;apost;s probably no way to know for sure as confused as things were in the hours just following the accident,&amp;quot; Banks said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m not going to say mistakes couldn&amp;apost;t have been made,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Banks said he was certain no discount offers were made to North American passengers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>It must have been a mistake or miscommunication if any discounts were offered to survivors, said Dan Askin, an editor at cruising website CruiseCritic.com, noting that there&amp;apost;s no confirmation that such offers were made.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The cruise line did offer 30% off on future cruises to guests who were scheduled to sail on the Concordia from January 14 and beyond, which Askin called &amp;quot;perfectly ordinary&amp;quot; compensation for people booked on cruises canceled because of an incapacitated ship.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Costa is offering cancellation without penalty by February 7 to concerned passengers booked on other ships, the company&amp;apost;s statement said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Passengers involved in the Concordia disaster will receive full refunds for the cruise and all related expenses, Costa said Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>All costs associated with travel to the port of embarkation and the return home, including transfer arrangements made independently of the cruise line, will be reimbursed, as will medical expenses, cash deposits and any expenses incurred on board.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Costa said it will update passengers on the return of personal belongings and try to return valuables stored in cabin safes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The company has been following up on the emotional and physical well-being of affected passengers, the statement said, and talking with tourism trade associations and consumer protection groups to determine indemnity for passengers for the hardship endured.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Costa had no comment on a class-action lawsuit against the cruise line and its parent company, Carnival Corp., that Italian consumer group Codacons and two U.S. law firms plan to file in Miami.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;ve been contacted by hundreds of victims and the numbers are growing moment by moment,&amp;quot; said Mitchell Proner, senior partner at Proner &amp;amp; Proner, one of two firms involved.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The suit is seeking at least 125,000 euros (about $160,000) per passenger, Proner said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
