<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1730" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/01/29/travel/900-year-stone-great-zimbabwe/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-01-29 11:17:09" category="travel" author="Teo Kermeliotis and Stefanie Blendis, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>900-year-old stone kingdom: The breathtaking ruins of Great Zimbabwe</title>
  <keywords>great zimbabwe,zimbabwe,zimbabwe city,ancient city zimbabwe</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7">Great Zimbabwe is an ancient city that flourished between 11th and 15th centuries.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">The site contains the largest single pre-colonial structure in sub-Saharan Africa.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="20">Zimbabwe, which translates to &amp;quot;big houses of stone,&amp;quot; was named for the city.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-23 09:06:40" annotation_time="41.2965">
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">Central to their prosperity was the ancient town of Great Zimbabwe, the capital of a booming trading empire that flourished between the 11th and 15th centuries, extending over the gold-rich plateau in southern Africa.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">A UNESCO World Heritage site since 1986, the archeological remains contain the largest ancient structure in sub-Saharan Africa.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="3">In fact, Great Zimbabwe became such an important part of the national identity that the country itself was named for this ancient city -- &amp;quot;Zimbabwe&amp;quot; derives from the Shona name for the historic town -- meaning &amp;quot;big houses of stone.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Legend has it that this was once a playground for the giants -- and for visitors gazing over this steep hill in southern Zimbabwe it&amp;apost;s easy to understand why.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Spread around in every direction, great jumbled blocks of granite rise from the ground to create spectacular rock formations, their fantastical shapes fashioned by centuries of wind and rain, of heat and cold.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Stacked upon one another, such boulders are scattered haphazardly across the southern African country -- Zimbabwe is indeed home to one of Africa&amp;apost;s most breathtaking landscapes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Living here amongst the boulders, in the hills of Masvingo province, the Zimbabwean people are largely Shona.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Sometimes known as Bantu, they form three quarters of the country&amp;apost;s population.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Shona people first settled in the region more than 1,000 years ago and for centuries flourished in the region&amp;apost;s lush green savannah plains.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Central to their prosperity was the ancient town of Great Zimbabwe, the capital of a booming trading empire that flourished between the 11th and 15th centuries, extending over the gold-rich plateau in southern Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Located some 30 kilometers from the modern Zimbabwean town of Masvingo, the stone ruins of Great Zimbabwe are today one of the continent&amp;apost;s most impressive monuments, linking the present with the past.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>A UNESCO World Heritage site since 1986, the archeological remains contain the largest ancient structure in sub-Saharan Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>According to UNESCO, the method of construction in Great Zimbabwe is unique in the continent&amp;apost;s architecture and although there are cases of similar work elsewhere, none are as exceptional and imposing as here.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The first thing that draws the visitor&amp;apost;s eye is the high level of craftmanship that went into the construction of the site.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Skillful stonemasons built massive dry-stone walls, incorporating large natural boulders into some of the structures.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Walls extend between rocky outcrops and massive rocks, forming a maze of narrow passageways and the enclosures.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The site extends over about 800 hectares and it can be divided into three main architectural zones.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The Hill Complex is generally considered a royal site, and the Valley Ruins are a series of living spaces.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>But most impressive is the Great Enclosure, a spectacular circular monument made of cut granite blocks that was entirely built in curves.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Its outer wall extends some 250 meters and it has a maximum height of 11 meters, making it the largest single pre-colonial structure in Africa south of the Sahara.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>While trade kept the community prosperous, religious life was also rich at Great Zimbabwe, which had an estimated population of about 18,000 people in its heyday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Although the stone city was largely abandoned around the 1450s, its cultural and historical significance didn&amp;apost;t wane with the passing of centuries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>In fact, Great Zimbabwe became such an important part of the national identity that the country itself was named for this ancient city -- &amp;quot;Zimbabwe&amp;quot; derives from the Shona name for the historic town -- meaning &amp;quot;big houses of stone.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Click through the gallery above to take our tour through the ruins of the stone kingdom of Great Zimbabwe.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>