<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1797" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/03/31/travel/kowloon-walled-city/index.html" date_published="2014-03-31 04:46:30" category="travel" author="Wilfred Chan, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Life inside the densest place on earth: Photos of Kowloon Walled City</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Kowloon Walled City was once considered the densest settlement on earth.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">33,000 people lived within the space of one city block, with little government regulation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">Photographer Greg Girard spent years documenting the Walled City before its demolition.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-11 22:00:36" annotation_time="380.22766">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">Now picture 33,000 people living there, within the space of one city block.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">That was Kowloon Walled City, once considered the densest settlement on earth.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">Before it was demolished twenty years ago, photographer Greg Girard spent years with collaborator Ian Lambot documenting this unique Hong Kong phenomenon, and remembers being amazed when he first saw it.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>(CNN)Picture a colossal empire of little houses stacked on top of each other.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Visualize them connected by staircases snaking under dangling wires, through corridors so dark even police were rumored to be afraid of them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Now picture 33,000 people living there, within the space of one city block.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>That was Kowloon Walled City, once considered the densest settlement on earth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;A huge monstrosity of buildings&amp;quot;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Before it was demolished twenty years ago, photographer Greg Girard spent years with collaborator Ian Lambot documenting this unique Hong Kong phenomenon, and remembers being amazed when he first saw it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;It was a huge monstrosity of buildings,&amp;quot; recalls Girard.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;It didn&amp;apost;t look like anything else.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>After all, the Walled City was a kind of historical accident.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>A former Qing dynasty fortress, it never fully came under the regulation of the British colonial government in Hong Kong.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>As a result, its residents were free to build their dwellings as they wished, ignoring safety codes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Quite often houses were built by building onto the next building, punching out walls to use their staircases,&amp;quot; said Girard.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;A lot of them didn&amp;apost;t have access to air or open space, because they were enclosed in the center of the structure.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Deep within the building&amp;apost;s darkness, a variety of small businesses flourished.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;The places that stuck out were the meat factories,&amp;quot; says Girard.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;There were pig carcasses laying splayed out on the floor; they&amp;apost;d burn the hair off with a blowtorch, it was all pretty open and of course there were no health laws governing the place.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>But despite the City&amp;apost;s wild appearance, the photographer found that the people inside lived just like people anywhere else.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;People were doing very ordinary things,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s just that all these ordinary things were happening in an extraordinary place.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>An ingenious community.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The complexity of the Walled City also fascinated local architect Aaron Tan, now the director of Hong Kong firm Research Architecture Design.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>A graduate student then, he wrote his thesis on the Walled City as it was being torn down.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;I was fascinated -- it was like a piece of machinery that worked very well.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The demolition was like taking the machine apart -- the first time you could see what was inside.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;It was a really humbling process for me as a designer -- when we met this Walled City, we started to see that people could be more intelligent than us, the designers -- that they could think of ways to solve problems that are outside the traditional academic world.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Tan was especially impressed by Kowloon Walled City&amp;apost;s water system.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>To support its dense population, residents dug extra wells and built thousands of pipes that twisted through the building.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>But since pumping water to the City&amp;apost;s roof tanks required plenty of power, the people would take turns conserving electricity so that water could be shared successfully.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;It revealed the community inside -- that no matter the challenges, they would find some intelligent way to solve it,&amp;quot; says Tan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Despite the ingenuity of the Walled City, by 1994 it was completely torn down by the city government, which was eager to replace the chaotic and unregulated community with a public park.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;Seeing the Walled City fall into disuse was sort of melancholic,&amp;quot; says Girard.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;Every city realizes too late to start caring about their architectural heritage -- it&amp;apost;s a mistake that gets repeated everywhere.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>By the time you start caring about it, it&amp;apost;s too late to save it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Today, visitors to the site of the old Walled City will find a placid garden with swaying trees and cloudy ponds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>In the park there is a small museum in honor of Kowloon Walled City.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>But when you look to the sky and imagine the colossus of Hong Kong life that once stood, it&amp;apost;s easy to see that something significant has been lost.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>The City is not dead.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Even today, the City&amp;apost;s legacy lives on.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>A walled neighborhood called the Narrows in the 2005 film &amp;quot;Batman Begins&amp;quot; was based on Kowloon Walled City.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The City is even a level in the video game &amp;quot;Call of Duty: Black Ops.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Because of the continued interest, Greg Girard is working with his fellow Kowloon Walled City photographer Ian Lambot to finish a new book of their stunning photographs, entitled &amp;quot;City of Darkness: Revisited.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>(Click here to visit the book&amp;apost;&amp;apost;s crowd-funding campaign).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>&amp;quot;You don&amp;apost;t want to romanticize a slum, you know.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Because it was that.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>But it was much more than that.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>The Walled City was a kind of architectural touchstone in terms of what a city can be -- unplanned, self-generated, unregulated.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>It was vital and vibrant and every part of it was being used.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Tan believes the spirit of the Walled City continues to pulse through the heart of Hong Kong itself.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>&amp;quot;Go to The Peak and look down upon this amazing collection of buildings coming together -- it&amp;apost;s almost like a blown up version of the Walled City, right?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Each building is related to the next building.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>New programs evolve because of the connections.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>This organic chaos, he says, has been an inspiration for his own work.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>&amp;quot;Many architects and urban planners like control,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>&amp;quot;But people like to get lost in the city.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>In my design process, I always consciously try to allow accidents, to allow others to participate, to surprise me.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
