<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1829" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/05/23/travel/national-parks-great-smoky/index.html?hpt=tr_c2" date_published="2013-05-23 12:11:07" category="travel" author="Katia Hetter, CNN" highlights_mapped="false" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Summer in the park: Great Smoky Mountains</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Great Smoky Mountains National Park divides North Carolina and Tennessee.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="34">Visitors to the park can spot bear, elk and spring bird migrations.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="30, 28">There are day hikes for the novice and longer hikes that will make you sweat.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_time="39.319668">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">The boundary between Tennessee and North Carolina might be one of the loveliest border crossings ever: It&amp;apost;s the crest of the Great Smoky Mountains National Park.</sentence>
      <sentence id="28" ids_highlights="3">Favorite less-traveled spot: The hike to the Mount Cammerer Fire Tower is Worth&amp;apost;s favorite hike to see spring wildflowers and changing fall colors.</sentence>
      <sentence id="30" ids_highlights="3">It&amp;apost;s a long hike -- about 11 miles round trip or 17 miles in a loop -- and it&amp;apost;s not flat.</sentence>
      <sentence id="34" ids_highlights="2">Favorite spot to view wildlife: While Cades Cove is filled with people wanting to see bears, Worth loves to spot elk and spring bird migrations in the Oconaluftee Valley.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The boundary between Tennessee and North Carolina might be one of the loveliest border crossings ever: It&amp;apost;s the crest of the Great Smoky Mountains National Park.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Hikers on the Appalachian Trail walk the line between the two states for most of the trail&amp;apost;s path through the park.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Incredible biological diversity is one of the Smokies&amp;apost; standout features.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Animals and plants typically found in the northern United States are found at the park&amp;apost;s higher elevations, while at lower elevations, the flora and fauna of the Southern states are represented.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Elevations reach 6,643 feet in the Smokies, which are among the oldest mountains in the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Park stats: Great Smoky Mountains National Park is the most visited National Park in the country with 9.7 million visitors last year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>It occupies 800 square miles in the Southern Appalachian Mountains.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>More than 17,000 species have been found in the park.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The location: Great Smoky Mountains National Park is in North Carolina and Tennessee.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>If you go: Entry to the park is free.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Camping costs range from $14 to $23 per night.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Meet our ranger: A second-generation park ranger, Caitlin Worth knows her national parks well.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Her father and mother met working for the Park Service at Washington&amp;apost;s National Mall.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The family followed her father to his postings at Acadia National Park in Maine and the Great Smokies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>(Her father retired as head of the Great Smokies&amp;apost; public affairs office last year.).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Worth did summer internships at the park while in college and graduate school, and she was hired permanently three years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Now Worth, her husband and new baby live just a mile from the park.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;I fell in love with this park when I worked here (as a seasonal intern) and couldn&amp;apost;t figure out why I&amp;apost;d ever want to be anywhere else,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;There are so many historical resources here.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>There are so many places you could close your eyes and open them again and you&amp;apost;re in the past.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>For a day trip, don&amp;apost;t miss: Cades Cove right after sunup (especially in the summer) to see the misty valley waking up and the wildlife at its most active.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>You might spend a few hours there.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;One of biggest mistakes people make, if they have only one day, is to start at 10 a.m. You&amp;apost;ve already missed the best hours.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s hot and busy, and they don&amp;apost;t see it the way they should.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>If you have a little more time, drive up and over the mountain to Clingmans Dome, the park&amp;apost;s highest point.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>You can walk up to the observation tower and even walk a little bit of the Appalachian Trail.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Southern Appalachian mountains are pretty spectacular.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Favorite less-traveled spot: The hike to the Mount Cammerer Fire Tower is Worth&amp;apost;s favorite hike to see spring wildflowers and changing fall colors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>But it&amp;apost;s not for novices.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a long hike -- about 11 miles round trip or 17 miles in a loop -- and it&amp;apost;s not flat.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;I like a hike that makes me feel like I worked for it,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s a good challenge hike if you&amp;apost;re up for one.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>And it&amp;apost;s quiet, which is sometimes hard to find in the park.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Favorite spot to view wildlife: While Cades Cove is filled with people wanting to see bears, Worth loves to spot elk and spring bird migrations in the Oconaluftee Valley.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The Oconaluftee River Trail runs through the valley, as does the road (in case you&amp;apost;re worn out at this point).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;There&amp;apost;s something about that valley in the morning that&amp;apost;s spectacular,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;There&amp;apost;s an ethereal quality.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Most magical moment: Leading a group of second-graders to see Mingus Mill, Worth suggested the children pretend they saddle up on their imaginary horses with their imaginary bags to collect corn from the mill.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Then everyone galloped up the hill to the mill.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;You can imagine a ranger galloping up the hill in full uniform?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>says Worth, laughing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;The class wanted to ride their horses all day.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>And they asked if the horses could look like whatever they wanted.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Yes, of course, she told them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Her horse had purple stripes and sparkles.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>&amp;quot;By the end of the day, the kids really fell in love with their horses.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>One girl came up to me and said, &amp;apost;Thank you for letting us come to the park.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Can we take our horses home with us?&amp;apost; &amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Another favorite national park: The Florida side of the Gulf Islands National Seashore (it also skips a state as part of it is also in Mississippi) was Worth&amp;apost;s annual beach trip as a child, and it&amp;apost;s the place she credits with making her want to be a park ranger.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>&amp;quot;I saw my dad going to work in a uniform but I didn&amp;apost;t get it,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>&amp;quot;It was the junior ranger program (at Gulf Island) where I fell in love with the idea of being a park ranger (when I was 6).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>I just loved it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>Gulf Islands is an &amp;quot;amazing untouched beach park, where I feel like I&amp;apost;m on a real Florida beach that hasn&amp;apost;t been manufactured or plowed flat,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s also a neat historical park with fortifications on the islands&amp;quot; dating back nearly 150 years to the Spanish.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>What&amp;apost;s your favorite national park and why?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>Please tell us in the comments section below.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>