<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1809" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/06/05/world/europe/polands-mini-sahara-desert/index.html" date_published="2014-06-05 09:34:53" category="travel" author="Paula Newton and Laura Chubb, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>No, its not a mirage, Poland does have a mini Sahara desert</title>
  <keywords>The Bledow desert ,Poland</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="16">The Bledow desert was created by humankind&amp;apost;s destruction and natural deposits of sand.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">Multi-million dollar financing has been provided to help safeguard the Polish desert.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="23">During World War II, it was used to train occupying German troops before they went to Africa.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-01 14:04:33" annotation_time="20.318335">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">Multi-million dollar financing has been provided to help safeguard the Polish desert, through deforestation and the eradication of native plant life.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="1">Humankind&amp;apost;s destruction of native plant life, in league with the natural deposit of sand, created the desert.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="3">During World War II, it was used to train occupying German troops before they went to the North African front.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>No, it&amp;apost;s not a mirage: there really is a desert in the middle of Poland.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The Bledow desert -- or, as some prefer to call it, the Polish Sahara -- has been flummoxing visitors for centuries.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Its sprawling sands are entirely at odds with an otherwise verdant country that boasts four lush lake districts, and 30% of which is covered by thick forest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>More bizarre still is the conservation project funded by the EU to preserve this barren anomaly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Multi-million dollar financing has been provided to help safeguard the Polish desert, through deforestation and the eradication of native plant life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The desert is shrinking, thanks to the return of native fauna, such as pine and fir trees.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Money from Natura 2000, a European Union-wide initiative to preserve fragile ecosystems, is trying to stop it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;Some people would say why bother?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Just let it grown green, let the vegetation grow, let the trees grow.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Why not?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>says Magdalena Moroń of the Desert Rejuvenation Program.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a good question.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>But far from being man made, the Bledow first came to be via a combination of natural and unnatural factors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>In the 13th century, the forest here was felled to foster silver and lead mining.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>It revealed a hitherto hidden deep layer of sand, deposited by waters flowing from melting glaciers perhaps a century before.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Humankind&amp;apost;s destruction of native plant life, in league with the natural deposit of sand, created the desert.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>In the beginning, this dusty expanse measured 150 square kilometers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Today, thanks to the encroaching trees planted in the 1950s by neighboring locals fed up of sweeping sand from their villages, it now commands a dinky 32 square kilometers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>But while it might not quite be the bona fide Sahara, Moroń insists: &amp;quot;This place is worth fighting for.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s worth working on it to make sure it doesn&amp;apost;t disappear off the map.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s true that Bledow has carved a unique place in its home country&amp;apost;s history.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The desert&amp;apost;s eerie emptiness on the fringes of Chechlo village, southern Poland, has long fascinated passers-by (in 1924, a tourist even reported seeing a mirage here).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>During World War II, it was used to train occupying German troops before they went to the North African front.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>For Moroń the desert&amp;apost;s future rests on it remaining a unique part of Poland.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s the only natural desert in our area, (so it&amp;apost;s) a very big attraction for Poland and Europe,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are planning to have a lot of tourism here.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The conservation project&amp;apost;s objectives are to stabilize the desert, establish nature trails, produce a guidebook and attract 1,000 visitors to this sandy oddity a year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>But, unlike the camels that this desert doesn&amp;apost;t have, it remains to be seen whether the idea of the Polish Sahara as a major tourist attraction will hold water.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
