<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1737" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/02/12/travel/air-new-zealand-safety-video/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-02-12 09:58:10" category="travel" author="CNN staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Air New Zealand&amp;apost;s swimsuit safety video: Fun or offensive?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="36">&amp;apost;Safety in Paradise&amp;apost; released February 11, already has 120,000+ YouTube views.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8">It features models Ariel Meredith, Chrissy Teigen, Hannah Davis and Jessica Gomes.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="13">Air New Zealand says it has been done &amp;quot;tastefully&amp;quot;.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-08 10:37:42" annotation_time="48.980335">
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">The models include Ariel Meredith, Chrissy Teigen, Hannah Davis and Jessica Gomes.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="3">From the negative corner, while some commented they were appalled Air New Zealand would be so sexist, others said the Sports Illustrated version just isn&amp;apost;t all that clever -- a disappointing follow up to the airline&amp;apost;s creative safety videos of the past.</sentence>
      <sentence id="36" ids_highlights="1">The &amp;quot;making of&amp;quot; video already has 540,000 views on YouTube, while the &amp;quot;Safety in Paradies&amp;quot; video, released Tuesday, has more than 120,000 at the time of writing.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Air New Zealand&amp;apost;s latest in-flight safety video, released Tuesday, is already another viral hit but is encountering some turbulence over its use of several bikini-clad Sports Illustrated models.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>View the video here.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Previous versions of the video -- starring anything from Hobbits to Bear Grylls to New Zealand&amp;apost;s all conquering All Blacks rugby team -- have revolutionized the on-board safety message airlines deliver to passengers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The most recent effort though is being criticized by some as neither ground-breaking nor as creative, after the airline teamed up with Sports Illustrated magazine to produce what it&amp;apost;s calling &amp;quot;the world&amp;apost;s most beautiful safety video.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The &amp;quot;Safety in Paradise&amp;quot; video, which rolls out on Air New Zealand flights at the end of February, is beautifully shot and certainly cheerful and fun.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>It was filmed in the Cook Islands -- home to several stunning beaches -- and coincides with the 50th anniversary of Sports Illustrated&amp;apost;s Swimsuit franchise.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Earlier videos have been witty, clever and quirky but the paradise video combines a far less subtle use of eye-catching material -- using four of the planet&amp;apost;s most beautiful, and scantily clad women, to deliver information to passengers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The models include Ariel Meredith, Chrissy Teigen, Hannah Davis and Jessica Gomes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Christie Brinkley makes a cameo.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;It seems that suddenly they are saying that my sexuality is all that matters about me,&amp;quot; one critic, Massey University lecturer and feminist commentator Deborah Russell told the Sydney Morning Herald.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Social media reaction to the video was predictably mixed, though the majority of commenters on Facebook and Twitter appeared to support the video -- and the women in it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Many praised Air New Zealand for using beautiful women to promote the Cook Islands and complimented the airline on its marketing prowess, given the mass of media attention now being given to the safety video.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>From the negative corner, while some commented they were appalled Air New Zealand would be so sexist, others said the Sports Illustrated version just isn&amp;apost;t all that clever -- a disappointing follow up to the airline&amp;apost;s creative safety videos of the past.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;No no no no no!</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>What a giant step backwards for the representation of women by NZ,&amp;quot; commented Facebook user Claire Jongenelen on Air New Zealand&amp;apost;s official page.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am so embarrassed and disappointed, as a young NZ woman who travels for business and leisure with Air NZ.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>This isn&amp;apost;t the beauty of the Cook Islands.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The beauty of the Cook Islands is the scenery and its (truly) beautiful inhabitants.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>I&amp;apost;m actually a little disgusted.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>(We&amp;apost;ve posted several comments from social media at the base of this story).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Air New Zealand spokesperson Andrew Aitken refuted those comments.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have been careful to ensure &amp;apost;Safety in Paradise&amp;apost; has been produced in a way that is tasteful,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The carrier, taking fun seriously, quickly established a reputation for edgy safety videos -- part of the company strategy, Air New Zealand CEO Christopher Luxon told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;We know that we actually get our customers watching and interpreting and internalizing our safety messages, better than I would argue anyone else, because we get their attention with the video ... We&amp;apost;ve had 12 million people watch our Hobbit safety video on YouTube and you sit there and go, that&amp;apost;s quite an incredible thing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>But it&amp;apost;s another small example of just how we think that we can deliver the table stakes of a great airline but actually do it with a twist and with some personality along the way,&amp;quot; Luxon told CNN in an interview recorded late January for CNN&amp;apost;s business feature series, Executive Innovator.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>That interview was conducted before the safety video was released.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;ll have inflight safety videos that people love or people hate.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>But at the end of the day it&amp;apost;s about taking risk and embracing risk intelligently.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>And that&amp;apost;s what we&amp;apost;ve trying to do across the whole of the business as a result.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Previous safety video &amp;quot;episodes&amp;quot; include &amp;quot;Safety Old School Style,&amp;quot; featuring Betty White and other octogenarians, &amp;quot;The Bear Essential of Safety,&amp;quot; with Bear Grylls and &amp;quot;Mile High Madness with Richard Simmons,&amp;quot; in which a sequin-shirted, short-shorted Simmons gaily encourages passengers to &amp;quot;grab, click and pull!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The latter has racked up nearly 3 million views on YouTube.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The latest &amp;quot;Safety in Paradise: video includes:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>- Ariel Meredith checking herself in a mirror having donned her oxygen mask.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>- Local men sneaking a look at a pouting, frolicking Jessica Gomes while demonstrating how to &amp;quot;brace.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>- A three-second glimpse of a muscly male pool cleaner (seemingly in case the ladies were feeling neglected).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>The &amp;quot;making of&amp;quot; video already has 540,000 views on YouTube, while the &amp;quot;Safety in Paradies&amp;quot; video, released Tuesday, has more than 120,000 at the time of writing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Below are some of the reactions sourced from social media.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Tell us what you think of the video in the comments -- fun, or sexist?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>