<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1784" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/01/16/travel/gulf-airlines-alliances/index.html" date_published="2013-01-16 11:28:12" category="travel" author="Ayesha Durgahee, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Gulf airlines shake up aviation alliances</title>
  <keywords>etihad emirates qatar airways gulf alliance</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7">Qatar Airways was the first Gulf carrier to join one of the three big alliances.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">&amp;quot;Alliances competing for members,&amp;quot; says Oneworld CEO Bruce Ashby.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="15">Gulf carriers&amp;apost; location and capacity make them important players in aviation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="28">But Star Alliance has &amp;quot;no aspirations&amp;quot; to have a Gulf carrier as a member, says CEO.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-11 21:43:30" annotation_time="47.603333">
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">Oneworld has marked a milestone in airline alliance history with its newest member Qatar Airways being the first Gulf carrier to join an alliance.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;As more airlines are aligned and more consolidation occurs, alliances actually end up competing for members in some ways,&amp;quot; said Bruce Ashby, CEO of the Oneworld alliance.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;These Gulf carriers have developed substantial capacity with high transfer capabilities, making these airlines and their hubs relevant players in aviation today, both in terms of industry developments and possible further consolidation,&amp;quot; he added.</sentence>
      <sentence id="28" ids_highlights="4">&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re the only global alliance that flies to all of the countries in the Middle East and we really have no aspirations to have one of the carriers in the Gulf join our alliance,&amp;quot; says Mark Schwab, CEO for Star Alliance, which has 27 members.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>When it comes to airline alliances, there is safety and profitability in numbers -- even more so as the industry tries to stave off the worst effects of the Great Recession and sluggish recovery, where we have seen mergers and code share agreements.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>All the major European airlines are part of one of the three big alliances.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>There is Star (the biggest) based around Lufthansa and United Airlines; Skyteam based around Air France/KLM and Delta; and Oneworld based around BA and American Airlines.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Alliances are a key part of the aviation industry.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>According to Oneworld CEO Bruce Ashby, 86% of the revenue from travel between the world&amp;apost;s top 100 cities business is booked with alliances.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;Passengers who travel for business are heavily invested in alliances carriers,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Oneworld has marked a milestone in airline alliance history with its newest member Qatar Airways being the first Gulf carrier to join an alliance.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Competition between the &amp;quot;Big Three&amp;quot; (Emirates, Etihad and Qatar Airways) is rife and now that Qatar has made this bold step to join Oneworld, the impact of Gulf carriers on the industry and the relationships they choose to forge are being followed more closely than ever before, to see how airlines and alliances will respond.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;As more airlines are aligned and more consolidation occurs, alliances actually end up competing for members in some ways,&amp;quot; said Bruce Ashby, CEO of the Oneworld alliance.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;Now that more and more airlines belong, the tension between them has grown.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>For other Gulf carriers, a cosy codeshare with different alliances is as far as they&amp;apost;ll go.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Emirates has codeshare agreements with Oneworld carrier Qantas and, most recently, with Star Alliance member TAP Portugal.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Skyteam welcomes Air France&amp;apost;s partnership with Etihad and Air Berlin, where Etihad owns 29% of the German airline.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;Gulf carriers and their hubs are well-positioned geographically for a number of major traffic flows, both within the Gulf region itself and between other continents&amp;quot; said Michael Wisburn, CEO of Skyteam.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;These Gulf carriers have developed substantial capacity with high transfer capabilities, making these airlines and their hubs relevant players in aviation today, both in terms of industry developments and possible further consolidation,&amp;quot; he added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Although Etihad has not joined an alliance, Skyteam member Air France says it&amp;apost;s a case of &amp;quot;if you can&amp;apost;t beat&amp;apost;em, join&amp;apost;em.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;When you see geographically the way the world is built, Gulf carriers bring significant improvement to the alliances,&amp;quot; said Alexandre de Juniac, president and CEO of Air France in an exclusive interview with CNN -- his first international television appearance since being appointed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>When asked about doing business with Air Berlin -- which is a member of a rival alliance Oneworld -- Juniac candidly said: &amp;quot;In the future if our ties with Etihad and Air Berlin become closer, Air Berlin will have to make a decision about which alliance they want to belong to.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The decision is in their hands.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Air Berlin, Germany&amp;apost;s second largest carrier after Lufthansa, has only been a member of Oneworld since March last year and if it were ever to leave, the alliance wouldn&amp;apost;t let it go quietly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;We would regret it very deeply if Air Berlin left Oneworld,&amp;quot; says Ashby.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;We like Air Berlin and they add a lot of value to us and we think we add a lot of value to them, by the way.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;It would be easier if we had exclusive clubs and we said &amp;apost;if you join my club you can&amp;apost;t use any other club,&amp;apost; but this is the airline business and it&amp;apost;s completely impractical.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>We would be sad to see them leave.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>I would definitely put up a fight if I thought it were necessary.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Star Alliance is monitoring this relationship closely, especially because its chief member, Lufthansa, is the only major European airline that hasn&amp;apost;t teamed up with a Gulf carrier.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Even so, Star Alliance says it doesn&amp;apost;t feel left out or threatened.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re the only global alliance that flies to all of the countries in the Middle East and we really have no aspirations to have one of the carriers in the Gulf join our alliance,&amp;quot; says Mark Schwab, CEO for Star Alliance, which has 27 members.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>He adds: &amp;quot;Fifteen years of Star Alliance, 21,900 flights a day, 192 countries, 1,330 cities we fly to -- we have Turkish Airlines in the vicinity, also EgyptAir, so we&amp;apost;re not feeling any kind of commercial pressure.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>And for airlines like south-east Asia&amp;apost;s Royal Brunei, which are too small for it to be worth their while joining an alliance, the best way to compete is not to compete.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think you have to cut your cloth in this industry,&amp;quot; says Royal Brunei deputy chairman Dermot Mannion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Gulf carriers have put a lot of capacity into the region over the last five-six years and that&amp;apost;s had an impact on all the airlines, especially the kangaroo traffic between the UK, Australia and New Zealand.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;ve cut capacity, we closed routes to Brisbane, Perth and Auckland.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>We are backing off competing against the Gulf carriers and focusing on what we do best -- ASEAN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>That way we can happily co-exist with the Gulf carriers.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>According to the International Air transport Association, airlines were expected to return a profit of $6.7 billion at the end of 2012, only slightly improving to $8.4 billion in 2013.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Adding capacity and connecting continents, Gulf carriers will continue to play a crucial role in helping airlines and alliances expand their networks, filling their geographical gaps.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Ayesha Durgahee is the resident reporter on CNN&amp;apost;s Business Traveller.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Follow Ayesha on Twitter at @AyeshaCNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>