<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1760" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/28/travel/chicago-ohare-midway-flights-stopped/index.html?hpt=travel_hp_row1left" date_published="2014-09-28 17:32:02" category="travel" author="Chandrika Narayan, Ted Rowlands and Ralph Ellis, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Chicago flight cancellations continue after fire</title>
  <keywords>Chicago air traffic control</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="26">NEW: FAA administrator will urge review of security protocols.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">NEW: O&amp;apost;Hare International Airport is still operating at 60% capacity.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">Police say fire was set by an employee before he apparently tried to kill himself.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="8">FAA hopes to return Chicago air traffic center to full service by October 13 .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-27 17:27:53" annotation_time="12.874">
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">O&amp;apost;Hare was operating at 60% of its capacity Monday, according to the Chicago Department of Aviation, while Midway International Airport was at 75%.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="4">The FAA hopes to have the center in Aurora, Illinois, repaired and returned to full service by October 13, the agency said Sunday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">Police say Friday&amp;apost;s blaze was set intentionally by Brian Howard, a contract employee at the facility, before he apparently attempted to kill himself.</sentence>
      <sentence id="26" ids_highlights="1">The FAA will launch an internal review of security protocols at its facilities, its administrator said Monday.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>If you are traveling today, you may want to check with your airline.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Thousands of flights into and out of Chicago&amp;apost;s two airports have been delayed or canceled since a fire damaged a key Chicago air traffic control center Friday, creating flight problems that rippled across the nation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Aviation authorities say it will take at least two weeks to get the center back to normal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>One airport affected, O&amp;apost;Hare International, is the world&amp;apost;s second-busiest airport.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Long lines of stranded passengers have been clogging Chicago airports all weekend.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>O&amp;apost;Hare was operating at 60% of its capacity Monday, according to the Chicago Department of Aviation, while Midway International Airport was at 75%.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>As of Monday morning, at least 300 flights had been canceled at O&amp;apost;Hare.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The FAA hopes to have the center in Aurora, Illinois, repaired and returned to full service by October 13, the agency said Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Other control centers have handled many of the Chicago flights while repairs are made.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Police say Friday&amp;apost;s blaze was set intentionally by Brian Howard, a contract employee at the facility, before he apparently attempted to kill himself.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>According to an affidavit, first responders found smoke when they arrived in the basement of the control center after a 911 call about 5:40 a.m. Friday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>They also found blood on the floor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>They followed the trail and found two knives and a lighter and then Howard himself, who was in the process of cutting his throat, according to the affidavit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The paramedics took the knife from him and began to treat Howard, who told them to leave him alone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Howard was taken to a hospital in Aurora.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Howard remained hospitalized Monday, according to Randall Samborn, spokesman for the U.S. Attorney&amp;apost;s Office in Chicago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s charged with one count of destruction of aircraft or aircraft facilities, a felony that could bring a 20-year prison sentence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>No court date has been set.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Howard, 36, had worked at the center for eight years but was facing a transfer to Hawaii, according to an affidavit filed in U.S. district court in Illinois, obtained by CNN affiliate WLS.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The affidavit quoted a Facebook post&amp;apost;s of Howard&amp;apost;s: &amp;quot;Take a hard look at the mirror, I have.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>And this is why I am about to take out... and my life... I am sorry.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Leaving you with a big mess.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Do your best to move on quickly from me please.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Feel like I give a shit for the first time in a long time again... but not for too long (haha!).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>So I&amp;apost;m gonna smoke this blunt and move on, take care everyone.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The FAA will launch an internal review of security protocols at its facilities, its administrator said Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;If we need to make changes as a result of what happened on Friday to improve the system, we will not hesitate to do so,&amp;quot; Michael Huerta said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Sen. Dick Durbin of Illinois is calling for an investigation into whether security was breached.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The suspect was able to enter the facility with a black suitcase without raising any red flags, officials have said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>CNN aviation analyst Mary Schiavo said the FAA has to take a second look at who has access to critical facilities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;You have to make sure you have a system in place to evaluate your contract employees, because remember, the Federal Aviation Administration ... huge percent of their employees are contract employees,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Most of the air traffic controllers are FAA employees, she added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>After the fire, air traffic controllers initially had to transfer flight data manually rather than by computer, said Doug Church, spokesman for the National Air Traffic Controllers Association.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Church said the fire damaged the telecom line that transfers flight plans from the airlines to the O&amp;apost;Hare control tower and then to the Aurora control center.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Airlines had to fax flight plans to the control tower, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Because so much information had to be manually transferred, two controllers were needed for each position.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>The effects of the fire were immediate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>O&amp;apost;Hare International is a hub for United Airlines and other major carriers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>When controllers stop flights scheduled to land or depart from there, it has the potential to trigger a line of falling air-traffic dominoes that will ruin travel plans for countless would-be passengers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The FAA says it&amp;apost;s bringing in extra technicians to replace the damaged communications network in the building, officially called the Chicago En Route Center.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>The first shipment of replacement equipment was scheduled to arrive late Sunday night, and additional deliveries were scheduled over the next few days.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;Teams will be working around the clock to install equipment, run cable and restore network connections at the facility,&amp;quot; the FAA said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>The FAA said over the weekend that it was managing the air traffic into and out of Chicago &amp;quot;through other large Terminal Radar Approach Control (TRACON) facilities in Illinois, Indiana and Wisconsin with additional help from high-altitude centers in Minnesota, Kansas, Indiana and Ohio.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
