<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1830" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/10/05/travel/007-james-bond-destinations/index.html" date_published="2012-10-05 12:00:39" category="travel" author="Leslie Gilbert Elman, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Tailing James Bond: 007 destinations</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">No film series has provided more travel inspiration than James Bond.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="21">His cinematic stops have included the Bahamas, Paris and Swiss mountains.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">&amp;quot;We are always looking to offer the audience the &amp;apost;wow&amp;apost; experience,&amp;quot; producers said.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 14:55:47" annotation_time="286.934" mapping_time_divergence="95.64466">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">Film after film, no one has given us more inspiration to travel the world than James Bond.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;We are always looking to offer the audience the &amp;apost;wow&amp;apost; experience of something amazing and different,&amp;quot; said Callum McDougall, executive producer of the upcoming &amp;quot;Skyfall,&amp;quot; the 23rd film in the James Bond franchise.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="2">Other scenes shot in the area include a car chase on Seven Mile Bridge, the segmented concrete (to make it hurricane-resistant) span you&amp;apost;ll cross if you&amp;apost;re driving to Key West, and a scene at the Ernest Hemingway Home in which M (Robert Brown) demands that Bond relinquish his &amp;quot;license to kill.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>We love James Bond films for so many reasons: the handsome men and beautiful women, the cool gadgets and outrageous villains, the amazing chases and death-defying stunts.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>And, of course, the travel tips.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Film after film, no one has given us more inspiration to travel the world than James Bond.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are always looking to offer the audience the &amp;apost;wow&amp;apost; experience of something amazing and different,&amp;quot; said Callum McDougall, executive producer of the upcoming &amp;quot;Skyfall,&amp;quot; the 23rd film in the James Bond franchise.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think everyone who goes to see a Bond movie expects to be impressed by the look and the locations chosen.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Certainly I was when I grew up watching them, and I don&amp;apost;t think that&amp;apost;s changed in the last 50 years.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>There are two reasons to celebrate Mr. Bond in style: Global James Bond Day was October 5, commemorating the 50th anniversary of the theatrical release of &amp;quot;Dr. No,&amp;quot; starring Sean Connery as Agent 007.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>And November 9 is the U.S. premiere of &amp;quot;Skyfall,&amp;quot; starring the latest Bond, Daniel Craig.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>In celebration of all things Bond, we give you (00)7 destinations where you can experience the world James Bond-style.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Turkey.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Several locations in Turkey are featured in &amp;quot;Skyfall.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is where East meets West, and the colors and vibrancy of Istanbul provided us with a great backdrop and such amazing locations as the Grand Bazaar,&amp;quot; McDougall said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Istanbul&amp;apost;s Grand Bazaar has been a must-see since 1461.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>More than 550 years later, it attracts nearly a half-million visitors daily.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Presumably few of them other than &amp;quot;Skyfall&amp;quot; director Sam Mendes envision its narrow, crowded aisles as a location for a high-speed chase.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>It is, however, an excellent place to purchase local handicrafts and to engage all your senses as you immerse yourself in the city.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Railway scenes for &amp;quot;Skyfall&amp;quot; were shot on and around Adana&amp;apost;s dizzying Varda Railway Bridge in southern Turkey, and beach scenes -- including one that was meant to be in the Far East -- were shot near Fethiye on the Mediterranean coast.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Turkey actually allowed us to combine our needs of four different looks in one country, quite remarkable,&amp;quot; McDougall added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Key West, Florida.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;Licence to Kill&amp;quot; (1989) kicks off with Timothy Dalton as Bond, parachuting in with his CIA pal Felix Leiter (David Hedison) to Felix&amp;apost;s wedding at St. Mary&amp;apost;s Star of the Sea Church in Key West after some insane aerial maneuvers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Other scenes shot in the area include a car chase on Seven Mile Bridge, the segmented concrete (to make it hurricane-resistant) span you&amp;apost;ll cross if you&amp;apost;re driving to Key West, and a scene at the Ernest Hemingway Home in which M (Robert Brown) demands that Bond relinquish his &amp;quot;license to kill.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Hemingway, also no slouch in the adventure department, moved to the 907 Whitehead St. house in 1931.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>A guided tour shows you his writing studio and introduces you to the descendants of Hemingway&amp;apost;s famous six-toed cats, who have unlimited license to roam the house and grounds.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The Bahamas.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Of Bond&amp;apost;s many visits to the Bahamas, the most memorable is Sean Connery&amp;apost;s 1965 &amp;quot;Thunderball&amp;quot; battle in the underwater caves of the Exuma Cays.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>They&amp;apost;ve been known ever since as the Thunderball Grotto.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>(Connery returned there in 1983 for &amp;quot;Never Say Never Again.&amp;quot;).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Several charter companies, including Four C&amp;apost;s Adventures and the Island Routes 007 Thunderball Luxury Tour, will take you out to the grotto by boat and guide you on a snorkeling route to the inside of the caves, where light seems to stream in directly from heaven and colorful fish dart about below the water&amp;apost;s surface.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Some tours also include a visit to the nearby Exuma Cays Land and Sea Park and a stop at the Staniel Cay Yacht Club, where you can dine or spend the night.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Paris.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>With an &amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m too old for this stuff&amp;quot; look on his face, Roger Moore as Bond chased Grace Jones as May Day up the steps of the Eiffel Tower in &amp;quot;A View to a Kill&amp;quot; (1985), only to watch her parachute off the top in one of the film&amp;apost;s more memorable scenes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>(It was almost as unforgettable as Duran Duran&amp;apost;s video for the film&amp;apost;s theme song.).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>On a tour of the tower, you&amp;apost;ll learn about Franz Reichfelt&amp;apost;s tragic demonstration of his &amp;quot;parachute suit&amp;quot; in 1912, which should convince you that parachuting is not the thing to do here.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>However, if you&amp;apost;re feeling fit, you can climb the 704 steps from the ground to the second floor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>From there, you can catch the lift to the top, where you&amp;apost;ll find a Champagne bar with killer views of its own.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Schilthorn, Switzerland.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;On Her Majesty&amp;apost;s Secret Service&amp;quot; (1969) took us to the mountaintop: the 2,970-meter-high Schilthorn in Switzerland&amp;apost;s Bernese Alps, which George Lazenby as Bond skied down at breathtaking speed, with Telly Savalas as Blofeld in pursuit.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s one of the great movie ski chase scenes, now documented in an exhibit at Piz Gloria, the world&amp;apost;s first revolving restaurant, which doubled as the Bleuchamp Institute for Allergy Research in the film.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Organized Bond-themed excursions that include a James Bond breakfast at Piz Gloria start from the car-free town of Mürren, or you can glide up the mountain yourself on a 32-minute aerial cable car trip that originates in Stechelberg.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>For more Bond-style adventure, ski the mountain&amp;apost;s 15.8 km mixed-terrain Inferno course.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Experienced skiers usually cover it in about 45 minutes; competitors in the annual Inferno Race -- the largest amateur ski race in the world -- can do it in 15.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Bregenz, Austria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>The James Bond producers were so impressed by the 2007 production of Tosca at the open-air Seebühne floating stage on Lake Constance (or Bodensee), they knew they had to work it into a film.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s why in &amp;quot;Quantum of Solace&amp;quot; (2008), Daniel Craig finds himself chasing bad guys under the startling open-eye backdrop of the &amp;quot;Tosca&amp;quot; set designed by Johannes Leiacker.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>The annual Bregenz Festival, approaching its 67th season, are only slightly less exciting.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>The next Opera on the Lake will be Mozart&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;The Magic Flute,&amp;quot; which opens July 17 and runs through the summer.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Bregenz itself, in western Austria, is known for its contemporary architecture, such as the Festival House concert hall adjacent to the floating stage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Guided tours of both are conducted year-round.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Auyuittuq National Park, Canada.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>&amp;quot;Nobody Does it Better&amp;quot; than the opening sequence of &amp;quot;The Spy Who Loved Me&amp;quot; (1977), in which Roger Moore BASE jumps off the edge of a mountain and ... whoosh!</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>A Union Jack parachute opens and wafts him to safety.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>&amp;quot;No effects, all done in camera for real,&amp;quot; McDougall points out.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>(BASE is an acronym for Buildings, Antennas, Spans and Earth, the four things you can jump from.).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>The mountain, with its distinctive twin flat-topped peaks at 6,598 feet, is Mount Asgard in Auyuittuq National Park on Baffin Island, Canada.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>Serious outdoors people find the 7,370-square-mile arctic park a haven of pristine beauty offering 24-hour daylight in summer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>Accessible via the Inuit hamlets of Pangnirtung and Qikiqtarjuaq, which can be reached only by small plane, the park requires that all visitors attend a safety orientation before they embark on their travels.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>For this level of adventure, only experienced wilderness travelers -- and MI-6 agents -- need apply.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
