<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1718" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/06/13/travel/brazilian-barbecue-guide" date_published="2013-06-13 11:38:32" category="travel" author="Joe Robinson, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>5-minute guide to Brazilian barbecue</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6">At a Brazilian churrascaria there can be more than 20 types of meat to choose from.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="16">The star of the Brazilian barbecue is picanha, a top prime sirloin.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="46">Lombo is pork loin on a skewer dressed in a Parmesan cheese coating.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-11 21:11:18" annotation_time="9.7386675">
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">There can be more than 20 different types of meat to choose from in the course of a meal at one of the big churrascarias.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="2">The star of this meatapalooza is picanha, a top prime sirloin that melts in your mouth.</sentence>
      <sentence id="46" ids_highlights="3">The loin is sliced into slabs for the skewer dressed in a Parmesan cheese coating.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Brazil may be the only country in the world where the food comes in bigger portions than on American plates.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s particularly true when it comes to the carnivorous side of things.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s meat by the wheelbarrow in the barbecue tradition known as churrascaria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The Brazilian barbecue tradition hails from the southern part of the country, from a gaucho technique of cooking meat in the wide-open country after a long day wrangling cattle.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>These days the wranglers come to you at the churrascaria, wielding skewers of meat from all manner of beast and bringing the cuts to your table one by one.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>There can be more than 20 different types of meat to choose from in the course of a meal at one of the big churrascarias.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Each skewer-toting server approaches with a particular cut.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>You inspect and nod, as if it was a bottle of wine, and the waiter then slices off a chunk for you to savor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>When a couple of waiters vie for your taste buds, it looks like a fencing match will break out.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>It can get hectic on the churrascaria floor, but it&amp;apost;s worth it, because the slow-grilling Brazilian barbecue style known as rodizio produces some amazingly tasty food.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>It starts with a fanatical devotion to high-quality meat and special cuts.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The hunks of meat are stabbed onto the skewer and then slow-roasted rotisserie-style over charcoal to lock in the juiciness and flavor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>When the top layer of the meat is browned, it&amp;apost;s sliced off fresh to serve.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The barbecuing is tailored to your individual tastes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>You get not only a wide selection of cuts, but also styles: rare (mal passado), medium rare (a ponto para mal), medium (a ponto), medium well (a ponto para bem) and well done (bem passado).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The star of this meatapalooza is picanha, a top prime sirloin that melts in your mouth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>But there&amp;apost;s a big supporting cast -- alcatra (top sirloin), baby beef, filet mignon, file com alho (filet mignon with garlic), maminha (rump steak), costela de Ripa (beef short ribs), and pork loin, sausage, chicken and plenty more.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Top 5 Brazilian barbecue cuts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Picanha.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The hands-down favorite for Brazilians is picanha, a rump cut that&amp;apost;s sliced in thin sheets and eaten with rice and beans.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>For anyone who wants to experience the Brazilian barbecue tradition, picanha is a must.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The meat comes from the top of the rump, the rump cap, which has two sides, one that&amp;apost;s better known as tri-tip and the other smaller side, which is picanha.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Brazilians grill slabs of picanha with the fat on, and slice it off before serving.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Good picanha is juicy, tender and triggers taste buds to demand more.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a premium cut, juicy, tender and out of the normal steak experience.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Keep the slices modest and you&amp;apost;ll be able to get up from the chair after the feast.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Baby beef.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Known by the American handle (pronounced &amp;quot;bebe beefey&amp;quot;), baby beef is the second most popular cut in Brazil, just back of picanha.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s seen as a delicacy and is priced accordingly, the most expensive of the churrascaria cuts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Baby beef, as the name implies, comes from younger cows, though not as young as veal cows.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The savory meat comes from the tenderloin section and is more tender and lean than that of mature cows, which is a big attraction for Brazilian palates.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a super-tasty cut, but will set your wallet back a bit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Alcatra (top sirloin).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Alcatra is a top sirloin cut that&amp;apost;s a traditional dish in Portuguese homes, served as a kind of pot roast, but the Brazilians reinvented it on the grill to create a flavorful style of sirloin.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The right seasoning, grilling and smoky flavoring gives this tender cut a flavor and tenderness you won&amp;apost;t be able to stop thinking about.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a whole new slice of sirloin.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Filet mignon.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>The king of the steaks is part of a pantheon in the Brazilian barbecue universe.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s still a favorite, but has competition from picanha and baby beef.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The great thing about the churrascaria style, though, is that you&amp;apost;re not restricted to one slab of meat.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>You can have a couple slices of picanha, filet mignon and more, depending on how many extra belt loops you have.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Known for its lack of fat and tenderness, filet mignon can be exquisite in the hands of a great churrascaria chef.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Lombo (pork loin).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s not all beef at the churrascaria, where pork, lamb, chicken and even fish are also on the menu.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Lombo is a pork cut worth sampling.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>The loin is sliced into slabs for the skewer dressed in a Parmesan cheese coating.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>As is done with the beef, only the best cuts of loin make it to the grill, so the pork is as juicy and tender as the high-end beef cuts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Got your own churrascaria tips?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Favorite cuts of meat?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Share them in the comments section below.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
