<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1852" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/03/25/travel/would-you-pay-to-cut-in-flight/index.html" date_published="2014-03-26 02:09:40" category="travel" author="Daisy Carrington, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Would you pay to cut in line for the toilets on a flight?</title>
  <keywords>airline fees,checked baggage fees,carry on fees,carry-on fees,fly.com,wi-fi on planes,free wi-fi on planes,in-flight catering,food on planes,free food on planes</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">A Fly.com survey reveals which airline fees passengers are willing to pay for.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="31">4% of those polled would pay to skip the line for the bathrooms.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="31">13% said they&amp;apost;d splurge for control of the armrest.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="11">20% said they&amp;apost;d spend extra for first class meals in coach.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-26 17:15:32" annotation_time="32.1735">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">According to a recent survey by Fly.com, there are actually some luxuries passengers are willing to shell out for -- they&amp;apost;re just not always in line with what airlines actually charge.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="4">Fly.com also found that 20% of respondents would pay for a first class meal in coach class, a service that few carriers offer.</sentence>
      <sentence id="31" ids_highlights="2, 3">Some of the perks respondents wanted would be a challenge for airlines to implement: 13% of those polled said they&amp;apost;d pay to have control of their armrests, 4% said they&amp;apost;d shell out for the right to control the window shade, and 4% said they&amp;apost;d pay to be first in line for the restrooms.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>We live in an era of airline fees.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Where once ticket prices included checked baggage, inflight meals and seat selection, increasingly, those items are add-ons geared towards generating extra income for carriers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>According to a recent survey by Fly.com, there are actually some luxuries passengers are willing to shell out for -- they&amp;apost;re just not always in line with what airlines actually charge.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;Overall, fees are here to stay, and as we continue to see a debundling of fares, passengers will increasingly be asked to pay for various services that previously they didn&amp;apost;t,&amp;quot; says Warren Chang, vice president and general manager of Fly.com.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;There&amp;apost;s an overall perception that consumers feel they&amp;apost;re being nickel and dimed, and it&amp;apost;s important for airlines to express what value they are presenting.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Give passengers what they want.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>According to Fly.com&amp;apost;s survey, the most widespread fees are also some of the least popular.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>While U.S. airlines collected $2.5 billion from checked baggage fees between January and September 2013, 89% of respondent said it&amp;apost;s important for them to be able to check their bag for free.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Also, with the exception of Hawaiian Airlines, all U.S. carriers now charge for in-flight meals on domestic flights, even though nearly half of those surveyed classified free food as an important perk.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>If airlines dropped these fees, they could recoup in other areas.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Fly.com also found that 20% of respondents would pay for a first class meal in coach class, a service that few carriers offer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;In my view, that&amp;apost;s something that would be a real win-win for the airlines.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>It doesn&amp;apost;t devalue first class, as people aren&amp;apost;t just paying for the meal, but for the exclusivity, for more space, for better service and amenities.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>First-class meals would enhance the flying experience in coach without detracting from the experience in first,&amp;quot; he adds.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Put it in the bin.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Cramped storage space is not only a headache for passengers, it&amp;apost;s poses a financial loss for carriers as well.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>While customers malaise through the aisles, holding up boarding in an attempt to fit their carry-ons on the plane, airlines are losing money (slow boarding costs them approximately $10 million yearly).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Increasingly, airlines have started charging for carry-on luggage, a fee that is, understandably, not popular with passengers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Frequent flyers have another solution in mind.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Rather than pay to bring luggage on-board, they&amp;apost;d rather spend extra for roomier overhead bins.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Of those surveyed, 42% said this is a service they would happily splurge on.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;No airline allows you to buy designated overhead bin space, but based on our findings, it&amp;apost;s definitely something they should consider,&amp;quot; says Chang.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Why wi-fi?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>While airlines are investing heavily in upgrading their systems to offer passengers wi-fi, many of those surveyed expressed it&amp;apost;s not really a feature that matters to them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Only 30% said they would pay extra for wi-fi, a number that surprised Chang.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;With large populations having their own smart phones, I would have thought they&amp;apost;d want to bring their own entertainment systems on board, but that wasn&amp;apost;t something our survey found,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>A little extra for comfort.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>As plane seats continue to shrink, it&amp;apost;s probably no surprise that most fliers are willing to pay for a little extra room.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Nearly 90% of passengers said they wanted more comfortable seats, and 45% said they&amp;apost;d pay for extra legroom.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>A good chunk were willing to go even further; 34% of travelers would pay to prevent the seat in front of them from reclining and 26% would pay to have an empty middle seat next to them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Some of the perks respondents wanted would be a challenge for airlines to implement: 13% of those polled said they&amp;apost;d pay to have control of their armrests, 4% said they&amp;apost;d shell out for the right to control the window shade, and 4% said they&amp;apost;d pay to be first in line for the restrooms.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
