<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1773" link="http://www.cnn.com/2011/12/21/travel/pilot-fatigue-rule/index.html" date_published="2011-12-21 14:17:09" category="travel" author="Jim Barnett, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>FAA announces pilot fatigue rule</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Rule governs how much time off commercial passenger pilots must have between work shifts.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">The new rule sets a 10-hour minimum rest period prior to a flight duty period.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">The final rule will take effect in two years.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="15">FAA chief: Pilots have a personal responsibility to arrive at work fit for duty.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-23 09:09:29" annotation_time="67.574">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Washington The U.S. Department of Transportation and the Federal Aviation Administration announced Wednesday a sweeping final pilot fatigue rule governing how much time off commercial passenger pilots must have between work shifts, ensuring they have a longer opportunity for rest before they enter the cockpit.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">The new rule sets a 10-hour minimum rest period prior to a flight duty period, a two-hour increase over the old rules.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">The final rule will take effect in two years, according to the FAA, to allow commercial passenger airline operators time to transition, rearrange schedules and indoctrinate pilots.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="4">&amp;quot;Every pilot has a personal responsibility to arrive at work fit for duty.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington The U.S. Department of Transportation and the Federal Aviation Administration announced Wednesday a sweeping final pilot fatigue rule governing how much time off commercial passenger pilots must have between work shifts, ensuring they have a longer opportunity for rest before they enter the cockpit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The new rule sets a 10-hour minimum rest period prior to a flight duty period, a two-hour increase over the old rules.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The new rule also mandates that a pilot must have an opportunity for eight hours of uninterrupted sleep within the 10-hour rest period.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The DOT said the proposal was science based, and would significantly increase public safety.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The final rule will take effect in two years, according to the FAA, to allow commercial passenger airline operators time to transition, rearrange schedules and indoctrinate pilots.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is a major safety achievement,&amp;quot; said Transportation Secretary Ray LaHood.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;We made a promise to the traveling public that we would do everything possible to make sure pilots are rested when they get in the cockpit.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>This new rule raises the safety bar to prevent fatigue.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>LaHood disputed criticism the changes in the rule took a long time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;We wanted to make sure we got it right.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>We took time to listen to people.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Every voice was heard,&amp;quot; LaHood said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;You can&amp;apost;t implement overnight.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>It takes time.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;Every pilot has a personal responsibility to arrive at work fit for duty.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>This new rule gives pilots enough time to get the rest they really need to safely get passengers to their destinations,&amp;quot; said FAA Acting Administrator Michael Huerta.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>It was a point echoed by Transportation and Infrastructure Committee Chairman John Mica, R-Florida, who released a statement saying, &amp;quot;While the final rule provides improvement for aviation safety, pilots must take personal responsibility for coming to work rested and fit for duty.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The government cannot put a chocolate on every one of their pillows and tuck them in at night.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The FAA said it &amp;quot;expects pilots and airlines to take joint responsibility when considering if a pilot is fit for duty, including fatigue resulting from pre-duty activities such as commuting.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>At the beginning of each flight segment, a pilot is required to affirmatively state his or her fitness for duty.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>If a pilot reports he or she is fatigued and unfit for duty, the airline must remove that pilot from duty immediately.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The rule has been a long time in coming.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>In the mid 1990s, the FAA tried to update its flight and duty time regulations, but withdrew its rule under opposition from airlines.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>But momentum for change increased following the February 12, 2009, crash of Continental flight 3407 near Buffalo, New York, which killed 50 people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The National Transportation Safety Board concluded pilot fatigue contributed to the crash, although it said it could not be attributed solely to fatigue.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The hearing, though, spotlighted the practice among some pilots to commute lengthy distances to their jobs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The pilot of Colgan Air 3407 commuted from Tampa, Florida, and the co-pilot commuted from Seattle, Washington, to their base in Newark, New Jersey.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The new rule addresses potential cumulative fatigue by placing weekly and 28-day limits on the amount of time a pilot may be assigned any type of flight duty, according to the FAA.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The rule also places 28-day and annual limits on actual flight time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>It also requires that pilots have at least 30 consecutive hours free from duty on a weekly basis, a 25 percent increase over the old rules.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The FAA said the rule also incorporates the latest fatigue science to set different requirements for pilot flight time, duty period and rest based on the time of day pilots begin their first flight, the number of scheduled flight segments and the number of time zones they cross.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The previous rules included different rest requirements for domestic, international and unscheduled flights.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Those differences were not necessarily consistent across different types of passenger flights, and they did not take into account factors such as start time and time zone crossings.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Another component of the rule includes when a pilot&amp;apost;s day begins.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The FAA said, &amp;quot;The allowable length of a flight duty period depends on when the pilot&amp;apost;s day begins and the number of flight segments he or she is expected to fly, and ranges from 9-14 hours for single crew operations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>The flight duty period begins when a flight crew member is required to report for duty, with the intention of conducting a flight and ends when the aircraft is parked after the last flight.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>It includes the period of time before a flight or between flights that a pilot is working without an intervening rest period.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>The Air Line Pilots Association expressed its support for the new rule covering passenger flights.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;Today&amp;apost;s pilot fatigue rule release marks historic progress in what must be an unrelenting commitment to ensuring the highest safety standards throughout the airline industry.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The Air Line Pilots Association, Int&amp;apost;l (ALPA), is gratified that the Department of Transportation and the Federal Aviation Administration have delivered on their pledge, and a Congressional mandate, to issue new flight- and duty-time regulations and minimum rest requirements for airline pilots,&amp;quot; said Capt. Lee Moak, president of the Air Line Pilots Association, an independent aviation safety organization.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Moak said while the new rule brings &amp;quot;much-needed science improvements to flight and duty regulations,&amp;quot; he expressed disappointment that cargo operations &amp;quot;are being held to a lesser standard.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
