<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1803" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/07/18/travel/move-over-abramovich-azzam" date_published="2013-07-18 10:40:29" category="travel" author="Arion McNicoll, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Meet the Azzam, the world&amp;apost;s largest superyacht</title>
  <keywords>azzam,largest,super yacht,billionaire,sailing,mainsail,largest superyacht,world&amp;apost;s largest superyacht,superyacht,azzam worlds largest yacht,worlds largest yacht,superyacht</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">590-foot Azzam becomes world&amp;apost;s largest superyacht.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">The yacht is 57-feet longer than Russian billionaire Roman Abramovich&amp;apost;s Eclipse.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="19">With a top speed of 30-knots, the Azzam is also the fastest superyacht on the waves.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-11 10:51:31" annotation_time="32.375668" mapping_time_divergence="10.791889">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">With the launch of the gleaming new Azzam, Russian billionaire Roman Abramovich can no longer lay claim to being the owner of the world&amp;apost;s largest superyacht.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">At 590- feet long, the Azzam is 57-feet longer than Abramovich&amp;apost;s mighty Eclipse -- previously the largest yacht on the waves.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="3">With a top speed of over 30 knots (around 34 mph), the Azzam is considered to be the fastest superyacht on the sea.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>With the launch of the gleaming new Azzam, Russian billionaire Roman Abramovich can no longer lay claim to being the owner of the world&amp;apost;s largest superyacht.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>At 590- feet long, the Azzam is 57-feet longer than Abramovich&amp;apost;s mighty Eclipse -- previously the largest yacht on the waves.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The hulking superyacht is significantly longer than a football field, larger than the US Navy&amp;apost;s Arleigh Burke-class destroyer and more capacious than many popular cruise ships.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Last month, the behemoth eased cautiously out of its shipyard in Bremen, Germany, ushered by a team of powerful tugboats which were dwarfed by its enormous scale.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The yacht has been kept under wraps throughout its construction for the past three years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The identity of the huge boat&amp;apost;s owner remains a mystery, but some speculate that it belongs to a powerful Middle Eastern billionaire.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Just building the yacht cost a staggering $605 million -- a fee which doesn&amp;apost;t even begin to take into account the sky-high costs of its annual upkeep.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>In his book on the Lady Linda superyacht, author G. Bruce Knecht said that, &amp;quot;operating and maintaining a yacht is at least 10% of what the thing cost.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>By which estimation, just keeping the Azzam on the water could cost as much as $60 million every year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The project was brought to fruition by Mubarak Saad al Ahbabi, who assembled a triumvirate of yacht-building super stars: the Azzam&amp;apost;s engineering was done by premier German shipbuilding company Lürssen, the exterior design was by Nauta Yachts and the interior was composed by Christophe Leoni.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>At present, very little is known about the interior detailing of the vessel.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>A spokesperson for Lürssen said &amp;quot;the yacht is still under construction, and I doubt that we will get permission to shoot her even when she is ready.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Experts suggest that the interior could match or even surpass the opulence of Abramovich&amp;apost;s yacht which is equipped with two helipads, two swimming pools, a cinema, a disco and a mini-submarine that can dive to 150-feet to explore the ocean floor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Bullet-proof glass and armor plating lines Abramovich&amp;apost;s master bedroom, and the boat has its own missile defence system.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The Azzam is described as having a &amp;quot;sophisticated and luxurious interior in a turn of the century Empire style.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Although his primary work is not in yachting, French interior decorator Christophe Leoni says he is &amp;quot;confident that the final yacht is everything and more the owner expects.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>TheYachtPhoto&amp;apost;s Peter Seyfferth commented: &amp;quot;For a yacht of this size, I think that she looks amazingly elegant and sleek.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>As well as its prodigious length, the yacht also travels at a record-breaking pace.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>With a top speed of over 30 knots (around 34 mph), the Azzam is considered to be the fastest superyacht on the sea.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The Azzam is the latest in a line of vessels to have held the mantle of world&amp;apost;s largest yacht.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Prior to the Eclipse, the 482-foot Prince Abdulaziz, owned by the Saudi royal family, held the record for 22 years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>And before it, the Rising Sun was briefly the record-holder.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Built by American businessman Larry Ellison, The Rising Sun came in at 454-feet and cost $200 million.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>With many more billionaires around the world eager to inscribe their names into the history books, it is anyone&amp;apost;s guess quite how long the Azzam will remain at the top.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>For now, its mystery owner can revel in the knowledge that his or her boat is at the very pinnacle of the yachting pecking order.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
