<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1763" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/10/07/travel/best-motoring-museum/index.html?hpt=travel_hp_herobox" date_published="2014-10-07 06:25:45" category="travel" author="Geoff Hiscock, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>City of Cars: Is this the world&amp;apost;s best auto museum?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="8">Cite de l&amp;apost;Automobile in Mulhouse, France, is home to the world&amp;apost;s biggest Bugatti collection.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="29, 2">Most of the luxury performance cars were collected by brothers Fritz and Hans Schlumpf.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="9">The collection includes the fabulous 1929 Type 41 Royale Coupe Napoleon, Ettore Bugatti&amp;apost;s personal car.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-02 10:39:23" annotation_time="73.35333" mapping_time_divergence="24.45111">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">Anyone who&amp;apost;s ever been lured by the siren call of a powerful engine can take comfort in the fact that, though they may be consumed by automotive obsession, they have nothing on the Schlumpf brothers.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="1">Known as the Cite de l&amp;apost;Automobile, or the French National Automobile Museum - Schlumpf Collection, it&amp;apost;s certainly the biggest Bugatti collection in the world.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="3">Among the vehicles is the absolute must-see of the Mulhouse collection: Bugatti founder Ettore Bugatti&amp;apost;s personal car, the fabulous 1929 Type 41 Royale Coupe Napoleon.</sentence>
      <sentence id="29" ids_highlights="2">Just how the Schlumpfs acquired their massive collection of Bugattis and other cars is a story of obsession, deception and loss that puts ordinary midlife crises to shame.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a well driven path for the motoring male: as middle age approaches, thoughts turn to acquiring a shiny sports car as wives, female friends and relatives shake their heads with despair.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Anyone who&amp;apost;s ever been lured by the siren call of a powerful engine can take comfort in the fact that, though they may be consumed by automotive obsession, they have nothing on the Schlumpf brothers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Fritz and Hans Schlumpf made a fortune in textiles during the last century.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>When it came to spending it, Fritz&amp;apost;s thoughts naturally turned to the sumptuous style and classic panache of the Bugatti sports car.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Not just one Bugatti, not even two, but 122 of them, amassed in secret alongside hundreds of other rare and expensive cars in their textile mill warehouses between 1957 and 1976.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The secret didn&amp;apost;t last and the collection is now housed in what could well be the world&amp;apost;s most fascinating car museum.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The museum lies in the French provincial town of Mulhouse, a three-hour ride from Paris by France&amp;apost;s fast TGV trains -- or, if it was possible to drive the full 480 kilometers at the car&amp;apost;s top speed, just over an hour in a Bugatti Veyron 16.4 Super Sport.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Known as the Cite de l&amp;apost;Automobile, or the French National Automobile Museum - Schlumpf Collection, it&amp;apost;s certainly the biggest Bugatti collection in the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Among the vehicles is the absolute must-see of the Mulhouse collection: Bugatti founder Ettore Bugatti&amp;apost;s personal car, the fabulous 1929 Type 41 Royale Coupe Napoleon.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>This imposing 6.4-meter, 3-ton black and blue chauffeur coupe has a massive 14.7-liter engine that produced 300 horsepower and could propel the car to 200 kilometers an hour (124 mph).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>It has an equally imposing value -- somewhere north of $15 million, based on past sales of other Bugatti Royales.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Bugatti&amp;apost;s challenge to Mercedes-Benz and Rolls-Royce.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Ettore&amp;apost;s son, Jean, who was killed in 1939 at the age of 30 while testing a Bugatti race car, designed the Napoleon, while the silver elephant mascot that graces its long bonnet was sculpted by Ettore&amp;apost;s younger brother Rembrandt.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Italian-born Ettore conceived the Royale as a vehicle that would supplant Rolls-Royce and Mercedes-Benz as the choice of European royalty.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>His dream foundered when the Great Depression killed the market for super-expensive luxury limousines.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>In the end only six Royales were built by Bugatti between 1929 and 1933 -- hence their astronomical value today.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The museum has two examples, the Coupe Napoleon and the Limousine Park Ward, plus a 1990 replica known as the Royale Esders.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Of the other four Royales, one is with the Volkswagen group -- which now owns the Bugatti brand, a couple are with U.S. museums and one is in private hands.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>A 1988 replica of the Coupe Napoleon sits in the Sinsheim Auto Museum in Germany.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>While Cite de l&amp;apost;Automobile is known as a Bugatti heaven, it caters to other interests.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The current collection of 430-plus vehicles includes early French examples of the horseless carriage (Panhard-Levassor and De Dion-Bouton) through to early high-end limousines such as Isotta-Fraschini and Hispano-Suiza and classic prewar sports coupes such as the Alfa Romeo 8C 2900A Pinin Farina Berlinetta.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>An oddity is the 1942 Paul Arzens-designed aluminum and Plexiglass bubble car known as &amp;quot;The Egg.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The postwar sports car lineup includes Ferrari, Maserati, Porsche, Gordini and an exceptional 1955 gullwing Mercedes-Benz 300 SL that was one of Fritz Schlumpf&amp;apost;s drive cars.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>A section of the Mulhouse collection is devoted to a full grid of F1 racing cars, including the rear-engine Bugatti 251 racer that made its debut at the 1956 French Grand Prix.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Naturally, there&amp;apost;s also a modern Bugatti Veyron, housed in its own room.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Secret treasure trove.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Still, pride of place goes to the Royale Coupe Napoleon, which Ettore Bugatti used as his personal car until the family&amp;apost;s financial difficulties forced his daughter L&amp;apost;Ebe to sell it in 1963.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The ultimate buyers were the Schlumpf brothers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Just how the Schlumpfs acquired their massive collection of Bugattis and other cars is a story of obsession, deception and loss that puts ordinary midlife crises to shame.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Using money from their textile business, former Bugatti racer Fritz snapped up every model of the car that came on the market, including in 1963 a 30-car collection from the U.S. auto enthusiast John Shakespeare that included a second Royale.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>By the late 1960s, Fritz decided he would put his secret treasure trove on public display.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Over the next decade he began restoring and preparing the vehicles for showing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Then economic circumstances turned against the Schlumpfs as the European textile business began to decline in the face of cheaper Asian products.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Having spent so much of their revenues on motoring masterpieces, their business began to falter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Encumbered by debt, the Schlumpf brothers sought exile in Switzerland, where they remained until they died -- Hans in 1989, followed by Fritz in 1992.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>The Schlumpfs&amp;apost; workers put the vehicles on show between 1977-79, until the French government made the collection a listed monument, ensuring it wouldn&amp;apost;t be broken up or taken abroad.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="37">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>A consortium that included the local municipal authority was created to run the collection and in 1982 the museum officially opened.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="38">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>By court order, the words &amp;quot;Schlumpf Collection&amp;quot; were added to its name in 1989, in honor of the men whose hunger for horsepower may never be surpassed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="39">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Cite de l&amp;apost;Automobile (French National Car Museum - Schlumpf Collection), 192 Avenue de Colmar, Mulhouse; +33 3 89 33 23 23.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Open daily from 10 a.m.-5 p.m. (10 a.m.-6 p.m. April-October).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Admission 14.50 euros for adults, 11 euros for children/concession.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Price includes on-track show.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="40">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Getting there: From Paris, it&amp;apost;s about three hours by high-speed TGV service to Mulhouse main station.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>About 25 minutes by train from Basel SBB in Switzerland.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="41">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>From the tram terminus near Mulhouse station, take Tram Line 1 to the &amp;quot;Musee de l&amp;apost;Auto&amp;quot; stop, about two kilometers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="42">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Accommodation: Hotel brands in Mulhouse include Holiday Inn (34 Rue Paul Cezanne, +33 3 89 60 44 44), Best Western (Bourse Hotel, 14 Rue de la Bourse; +33 3 8956 1844) Mercure (4 Place du General de Gaulle; +33 3 8936 2939) and Ibis (53 Rue de Bale; +33 3 8946 4141).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="43">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Among the best-ranked independent hotels are The Bristol (8 Avenue de Colmar; +33 3 8942 1231) and Hotel du Parc (26 Rue de la Sinne; +33 3 89 66 12 22).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="44">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>ResidHotel Mulhouse Centre (49 Rue de la Sinne; +33 3 8945 2114) has three-star studio apartments from 65 euros ($83).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
