<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1964" link="http://us.cnn.com/2014/09/03/us/philadelphia-drug-bust-house-seizure/index.html?hpt=hp_t4" date_published="2014-09-03 18:13:14" category="us" author="Pamela Brown, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Parents&amp;apost; house seized after son&amp;apost;s drug bust</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="47">Sourovelis family ousted from their house.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">They were not convicted of any wrongdoing.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="48">Son pleaded no contest to drug charges, leading to house forfeiture.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-11 09:29:40" annotation_time="34.23967">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">One day this past March, without warning, the government took his house away, even though he and his wife, Markella, have never been charged with a crime or accused of any wrongdoing.</sentence>
      <sentence id="47" ids_highlights="1">After eight days of sleeping on a family member&amp;apost;s couch, the Sourvelises were let back into their house, but only on the guarantee they would ban their son from the house -- a heartbreaking decision, they say.</sentence>
      <sentence id="48" ids_highlights="3">(Their son pleaded no contest to the drug charges.).</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The rare moments Christos Sourovelis can take a break from running his own painting business, he can be found toiling away on his family&amp;apost;s dream house in the suburbs of Philadelphia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m a working guy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>I work every day, six days a week, even seven if I have to,&amp;quot; Sourovelis says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>One day this past March, without warning, the government took his house away, even though he and his wife, Markella, have never been charged with a crime or accused of any wrongdoing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;I was so upset thinking somebody&amp;apost;s going to take my house for nothing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>That makes me crazy,&amp;quot; Sourovelis says, shaking his head.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The nightmare began when police showed up at the house and arrested their 22-year-old son, Yianni, on drug charges -- $40 worth of heroin.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Authorities say he was selling drugs out of the home.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The Sourvelises say they had no knowledge of any involvement their son might have had with drugs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>A month-and-a-half later police came back -- this time to seize their house, forcing the Sourvelises and their children out on the street that day.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Authorities came with the electric company in tow to turn off the power and even began locking the doors with screws, the Sourvelises say.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Authorities won&amp;apost;t comment on the exact circumstances because of pending litigation regarding the case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Police and prosecutors came armed with a lawsuit against the house itself.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>It was being forfeited and transferred to the custody of the Philadelphia District Attorney.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Authorities said the house was tied to illegal drugs and therefore subject to civil forfeiture.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>In two years, nearly 500 families in Philadelphia had their homes or cars taken away by city officials, according to records from Pennsylvania&amp;apost;s attorney general.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Authorities use a civil forfeiture law that allows them to seize people&amp;apost;s property when that property is connected to the sale of illegal drugs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>CNN legal analyst and consumer attorney, Brian Kabateck, says the law is intended to protect the public.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;It discourages crime and it takes the ill-gotten gains away from the bad people.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>But not all people who have their property taken away are charged with a crime.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Unlike criminal forfeiture, the civil law allows authorities to seize property without the owner ever being convicted or even charged.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>In North Carolina property can be forfeited only if the property owner is actually convicted of a crime.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>This is not so in other states.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Civil liberties attorneys with the Institute for Justice, who recently filed a class action lawsuit against Philadelphia authorities for abusing the law, say, &amp;quot;Civil forfeiture is something that is an assault upon fundamental notions of private property ownership and due process.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>But Kabateck disagrees, &amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s a good law.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>It works.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>That doesn&amp;apost;t mean that it doesn&amp;apost;t sometimes have issues that need to be corrected.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The system constantly has to change.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>In Pennsylvania, the City of Brotherly Love is far and away the most aggressive in the state when it comes to people&amp;apost;s property.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Over a four-year period, Allegheny County, the second largest county in Pennsylvania, filed about 200 petitions for civil forfeiture.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Philadelphia filed nearly 7,000 petitions in one year alone, according to the class action lawsuit, in which the Sourvelises are plaintiffs, along with other Philadelphia citizens.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Philadelphia officials seized more than 1,000 houses, about 3,300 vehicles and $44 million in cash, totaling $64 million in civil forfeitures over a 10-year period, according to the lawsuit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The very authorities taking the property appear to be profiting from it, according to Pennsylvania state records.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The Pennsylvania Attorney General&amp;apost;s office says about $7 million went straight to the salaries for the Philadelphia District Attorney&amp;apost;s office and the police department in just three years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>In that same time period, records show the D.A.&amp;apost;s office spent no money on community-based drug and crime-fighting programs, according to the Philadelphia AG&amp;apost;s office.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>The Philadelphia District Attorney&amp;apost;s office told CNN it seizes property only as a last resort, and added that it is limited in what it can currently say because of the pending litigation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;In most cases the Public Nuisance Task Force doesn&amp;apost;t pursue forfeiture because the underlying issue with the real estate is resolved when a settlement agreement is reached with the property owner in which he or she agrees to take reasonable efforts to prevent future narcotics dealing from the property.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>The DA&amp;apost;s office also says it works directly with citizens, the police, government agencies, and community groups in an effort to abate or close drug properties.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Civil forfeiture can be used on the federal or state level.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Only eight states -- Maine, Maryland, Missouri, Indiana, Vermont, North Carolina, Ohio and North Dakota -- require seized funds be placed in a neutral account.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Other states allow law enforcement to directly profit from the civil forfeitures or put proceeds into a special crime fighting fund.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>In some states, like Pennsylvania, the burden is on the property owner to prove their innocence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>The Sourvelises say they had to go to a courtroom and fight to get their home back where, instead of facing a judge, they faced a prosecutor from the DA&amp;apost;s office.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>There was no courtroom or judge, Christos Sourvelis says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>&amp;quot;There&amp;apost;s just one guy telling us to sign these papers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>After eight days of sleeping on a family member&amp;apost;s couch, the Sourvelises were let back into their house, but only on the guarantee they would ban their son from the house -- a heartbreaking decision, they say.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>(Their son pleaded no contest to the drug charges.).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Still fighting the city to resolve their case and stay in their home permanently, Markella Sourovelis says: &amp;quot;To me I&amp;apost;m home, but I feel violated at this point.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>I&amp;apost;m doing things in my house, but I worry is it always going to be my house?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>Are they going to take it one day like that?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>The Philadelphia District Attorney&amp;apost;s office told CNN it strictly follows the state law in an effort to crack down on drug abuse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>&amp;quot;In these efforts we will follow applicable law to protect the rights of those involved -- not only drug dealers and those associated with them -- but the law-abiding citizens who are negatively affected by them.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
