<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1986" link="http://cnn.com/2013/11/23/us/new-jersey-smart-gun-law" date_published="2013-11-23 16:10:32" category="us" author="Chris Boyette, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Smart gun technology could trigger New Jersey law</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">New Jersey law could take hold with new smart gun technology.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">&amp;quot;Personalized&amp;quot; guns only fire with signal from watch, ring or the right grip .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">The law, the only one of its kind, has become part of national gun debate.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-08 23:58:34" annotation_time="89.34701" mapping_time_divergence="29.782335">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">The idea behind this firearms technology is to create &amp;quot;personalized&amp;quot; guns that only fire in the right hands -- whether by recognizing a certain signal from a watch, a ring or even just the right grip.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">The New Jersey law is the only one of its kind in the United States.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">The new technology has become one more point of contention in the gun debate, with gun-control supporters expecting it to lead to fewer injuries and deaths and the pro-gun side arguing that it will take away options from gun owners.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>New York A gun law passed by the New Jersey legislature more than a decade ago may be set into motion as tech savvy gun makers get closer to being able to sell so-called smart guns in the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The idea behind this firearms technology is to create &amp;quot;personalized&amp;quot; guns that only fire in the right hands -- whether by recognizing a certain signal from a watch, a ring or even just the right grip.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The New Jersey law is the only one of its kind in the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>It requires that within three years of the technology being available, only smart guns be sold in the state.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The new technology has become one more point of contention in the gun debate, with gun-control supporters expecting it to lead to fewer injuries and deaths and the pro-gun side arguing that it will take away options from gun owners.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;The problem is you have an industry that is totally reluctant to embrace any changes to make their products safer,&amp;quot; said Ladd Everitt, communications director of the Washington D.C.-based Coalition to Stop Gun Violence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;The benefits of this technology should be obvious to anyone,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;The key is implementation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>It is going to take some political will.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Will you have a state government in New Jersey with the political will to see this through?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The country&amp;apost;s largest gun advocacy organization, the National Rifle Association, did not respond to requests for comment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;New Jersey&amp;apost;s smart-gun law is as dumb as it gets,&amp;quot; said Scott Bach, executive director of the Association of New Jersey Rifle &amp;amp; Pistol Clubs, a group affiliated with the NRA.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;It forces you to use an unproven technology to defend your life, and then exempts the state from liability when the gun goes &amp;apost;click&amp;apost; instead of &amp;apost;bang,&amp;apost;&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;If it&amp;apost;s such a great idea, then law enforcement shouldn&amp;apost;t be exempt, and the free market should be allowed to determine its viability.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>One Germany-based company, Armatix, which already sells personalized guns in Europe, expects to have its Armatix iP1 digital pistol available on the nation&amp;apost;s shelves &amp;quot;within weeks,&amp;quot; according to Belinda Padilla, president and CEO.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Armatix uses radio frequency technology in its .22-caliber digital pistol, which unlocks with a digital watch and a PIN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>If someone who isn&amp;apost;t wearing the watch grabs the gun, it immediately deactivates.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Our digital pistol is the first of its kind and has gone through rigorous testing in Germany -- some of the highest standards -- and in the U.S,&amp;quot; Padilla told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;Anybody who picks up the handgun, whether it&amp;apost;s a child or it&amp;apost;s actively stolen, they can&amp;apost;t activate the watch.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Another firm, Kodiak Industries of Utah, markets an &amp;quot;Intelligun,&amp;quot; which uses a fingerprint-based locking system.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Bill Gentry, president of Kodiak, said the company began taking preorders in January.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The personalized weapon will be in full production by the end of December.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Armatix, Kodiak and other smart-gun makers are poised to force acting New Jersey Attorney General John Jay Hoffman, a Republican, to decide how to implement the law.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>For more than a decade, researchers at the New Jersey Institute of Technology have been working on a grip-recognizing gun that measures the pressure applied and the size and shape of the hand holding the gun.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Triggersmart, which was founded by Irish entrepreneur Robert McNamara, also uses radio frequency technology to enable -- and disable -- guns.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The chip that activates the gun can be placed in a ring, bracelet or potentially even embedded in the owner&amp;apost;s hand.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>So what does this mean for the law?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The state Attorney General&amp;apost;s office declined to comment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Under the law, Hoffman must determine whether the smart guns meet industry standards and are available for retail sale.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The law says &amp;quot;personalized handguns shall be deemed to be available for retail sales purposes if at least one manufacturer has delivered at least one model of a personalized handgun to a registered or licensed wholesale or retail dealer in New Jersey or any other state.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The New Jersey State Police then will issue a list of firearms that meet the technological standard.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Within three years of the guns hitting the market, they will be the only kinds of firearms sold in New Jersey.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>In New Jersey, 2013 firearms background checks -- needed to obtain permits required to purchase handguns -- increased by more than 50% through October, compared with the same period in 2012, according to the FBI.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>In the first 10 months of 2013, 100,922 background checks were conducted, compared to 66,912 during the same period the year before.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>According to the latest data available from the Centers for Disease Control&amp;apost;s National Center for Health Statistics, there were 456 firearm related deaths in New Jersey in 2010.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>In August, New Jersey Gov. Chris Christie vetoed a bill that would ban certain long-range rifles and sent several gun-related bills back to the state legislature for changes, according to his office.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
