<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1972" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/02/01/us/aaron-hernandez-investigation/index.html" date_published="2014-02-01 20:56:29" category="us" author="Laura Dolan and Ray Sanchez, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Prosecutors say Aaron Hernandez discussed killing in jailhouse calls</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">NEW: Defense attorneys move to block request for Aaron Hernandez&amp;apost;s jailhouse calls.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">The former NFL star is being held on first-degree murder charge in death of Odin Lloyd.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">Prosecutor says Hernandez used &amp;quot;coded messages&amp;quot; while discussing killing during calls.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="3">He has pleaded not guilty to the charge stemming from the June killing.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-08 23:57:42" annotation_time="137.30267" mapping_time_divergence="34.32567">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">Hernandez, 24, is being held on first-degree murder and weapons charges in the shooting death last year of his friend Lloyd.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="4">Hernandez has pleaded not guilty.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">In court papers filed Thursday, the Bristol County District Attorney&amp;apost;s Office asked a state court to order the Sheriff&amp;apost;s Office to turn over recordings of jailhouse calls and records of the people who visited Hernandez since the former tight end was arrested in Lloyd&amp;apost;s killing in June.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">Prosecutors said Hernandez used coded messages when discussing with friends allegations that he planned the June 17 killing of Lloyd in a North Attleborough, Massachusetts, industrial park, where Lloyd was found shot to death.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Former New England Patriots star Aaron Hernandez used &amp;quot;coded messages&amp;quot; in jailhouse calls to discuss the killing of Odin Lloyd, Massachusetts prosecutors said in court papers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Hernandez, 24, is being held on first-degree murder and weapons charges in the shooting death last year of his friend Lloyd.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Hernandez has pleaded not guilty.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>In court papers filed Thursday, the Bristol County District Attorney&amp;apost;s Office asked a state court to order the Sheriff&amp;apost;s Office to turn over recordings of jailhouse calls and records of the people who visited Hernandez since the former tight end was arrested in Lloyd&amp;apost;s killing in June.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Prosecutors said Hernandez used coded messages when discussing with friends allegations that he planned the June 17 killing of Lloyd in a North Attleborough, Massachusetts, industrial park, where Lloyd was found shot to death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Hernandez&amp;apost;s lawyers moved to quash the request, calling it a &amp;quot;fishing expedition.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;There is absolutely no basis to provide the Commonwealth with access to all of the defendant&amp;apost;s recorded phone calls, past, present, and future,&amp;quot; his attorneys, Michael Fee and Jamie Sultan, said in their court filing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Those who have visited Hernandez included his fiancee, Shayanna Jenkins, and cousin, Tanya Cummings Singleton, both of whom face charges in connection with the Lloyd homicide, the court papers said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;Both of these co-defendants have been charged as accessories in the underlying offense of murder on the theory that they provided assistance to the defendant after the commission of that offense,&amp;quot; Bristol Assistant District Attorney Roger L. Michel Jr. wrote in a court papers requesting the tapes and records.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Michel wrote that in jailhouse phone conversations Hernandez discussed &amp;quot;matters directly relevant to the circumstances surrounding the murder of Odin Lloyd; viz: the defendant&amp;apost;s subjective belief about his criminal liability; his use of coded messages to communicate with persons outside of jail; related prior offenses; inculpatory denials of ownership of a vehicle connected with the investigation; the extent of his control over persons charged as accessories; other matters relating to his codefendants, including their whereabouts and likely criminal liability.&amp;apost;&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Both detainees and people they call are warned by the jail that their conversations are recorded.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Authorities have said that Hernandez and two other men picked Lloyd up from his Boston apartment in a rental car shortly before he was found shot to death June 17.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Surveillance cameras then captured the rental car leaving the crime scene and Hernandez carrying a gun as he returned to his home minutes later.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
