<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1949" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/02/09/us/sport-football-michael-sam-comes-out" date_published="2014-02-10 02:23:01" category="us" author="Ralph Ellis, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Michael Sam, college football star and top NFL prospect, says he&amp;apost;s gay</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="16">NEW: His agent says Sam&amp;apost;s revelation will not hurt his draft prospects.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Michael Sam was an All-American lineman at the University of Missouri.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="14">With his skills, he could be drafted by the NFL in May.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="1">He&amp;apost;d be the first openly gay draftee in pro football.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-12 06:42:04" annotation_time="19.993334">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2, 4">Michael Sam, an All-American defensive lineman from the University of Missouri, publicly revealed that he&amp;apost;s gay Sunday, creating the possibility he&amp;apost;ll be the first openly gay player drafted by the National Football League.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="3">With those credentials, he&amp;apost;s expected to be picked in the NFL draft in May.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="1">His agent said Monday that he does not think Sam&amp;apost;s decision to acknowledge his sexual orientation will hurt his draft prospects.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Michael Sam, an All-American defensive lineman from the University of Missouri, publicly revealed that he&amp;apost;s gay Sunday, creating the possibility he&amp;apost;ll be the first openly gay player drafted by the National Football League.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;I came to tell the world I&amp;apost;m an openly proud gay man,&amp;quot; he said in an interview with ESPN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>He said he told his Missouri teammates in August and suffered no repercussions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>He said he was surprised to discover many people in the media already knew he was gay.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;I understand how big this is,&amp;quot; Sam said in the ESPN interview.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s a big deal.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>No one has done this before.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>And it&amp;apost;s kind of a nervous process, but I know what I want to be ... I want to be a football player in the NFL.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Sam also spoke about his sexual orientation Sunday to The New York Times, saying: &amp;quot;I just want to make sure I could tell my story the way I want to tell it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>I just want to own my truth.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Sam, at 6-foot-2 and 260 pounds, starred in college football last season.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Besides being first team All-American, he was named the top defensive player in the Southeastern Conference, considered the nation&amp;apost;s best league.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Teammates named him the team&amp;apost;s most valuable player.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>With those credentials, he&amp;apost;s expected to be picked in the NFL draft in May.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The Bleacher Report mock draft projected him to go in the late rounds because &amp;quot;athletic limitations including a lack of flexibility and a lack of optimal size are concerning.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>His agent said Monday that he does not think Sam&amp;apost;s decision to acknowledge his sexual orientation will hurt his draft prospects.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think, if anything, teams will look at it and see a guy who was honest and upfront instead of waiting until after the draft to potentially make his announcement,&amp;quot; Joe Barkett told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Mike was forward, and he wants the team who drafts him to accept him for who he is.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The NFL issued a statement on Twitter on Sunday: &amp;quot;We admire Michael Sam&amp;apost;s honesty and courage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Michael is a football player.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Any player with ability and determination can succeed in the NFL.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>We look forward to welcoming and supporting Michael Sam in 2014.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>However, the NFL has made headlines on the issue of sexual orientation in the past.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Last year, a University of Colorado player said an NFL team asked him if he liked girls and had a girlfriend.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The NFL quickly said, &amp;quot;Any team or employee that inquires about impermissible subjects or makes an employment decision based on such factors is subject to league discipline.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Sam issued his own Tweet: &amp;quot;I want to thank everybody for their support and encouragement, especially @espn, @nytimes and @nfl.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>I am proud to tell my story to the world!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Sam&amp;apost;s announcement comes as the federal government expands its recognition of same-sex marriages.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Attorney General Eric Holder said the Justice Department will issue a memo Monday that extends the federal government&amp;apost;s recognition of same-sex marriages, even in the 34 states that don&amp;apost;t consider it legal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Other athletes have come out as gay, but they didn&amp;apost;t have Sam&amp;apost;s profile.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>GLAAD, a lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender media advocacy group, said Sam is &amp;quot;the latest high-profile athlete to come out as LGBT.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Others include the NBA&amp;apost;s Jason Collins, the WNBA&amp;apost;s Brittney Griner, WWE&amp;apost;s Darren Young, UFC&amp;apost;s Liz Carmouche, MMA&amp;apost;s Fallon Fox and Major League Soccer&amp;apost;s Robbie Rogers.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Of those athletes, Collins made the biggest media splash.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s not playing in the NBA this season.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Praise poured in for Sam, who overcame a rough childhood in which one of his brothers was killed and others ended up in prison.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Sam&amp;apost;s head football coach at Missouri, Gary Pinkel, said: &amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re really happy for Michael that he&amp;apost;s made the decision to announce this, and we&amp;apost;re proud of him and how he represents Mizzou.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Michael is a great example of just how important it is to be respectful of others, he&amp;apost;s taught a lot of people here first-hand that it doesn&amp;apost;t matter what your background is, or your personal orientation, we&amp;apost;re all on the same team and we all support each other.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>GLAAD President Sarah Kate Ellis said in a prepared statement: &amp;quot;By rewriting the script for countless young athletes, Michael has demonstrated the leadership that, along with his impressive skills on the field, makes him a natural fit for the NFL.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>With acceptance of LGBT people rising across our coasts -- in our schools, churches, and workplaces -- it&amp;apost;s clear that America is ready for an openly gay football star.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
