<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1873" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/05/09/us/arkansas-same-sex-ban-overturned/?hpt=po_c2" date_published="2014-05-09 22:23:41" category="us" author="Bill Mears, CNN Supreme Court Producer" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Arkansas ban on same-sex marriage struck down by state judge</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">&amp;quot;Our country has evolved as a beacon of liberty,&amp;quot; judge writes.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">&amp;quot;It is time to let that beacon of freedom shine brighter on all our brothers and sisters&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">Seventeen states and the District of Columbia already allow same-sex marriage.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="11">Just a decade ago, there were none.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-07-26 17:16:02" annotation_time="22.26">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;Our freedoms are often acquired slowly, but our country has evolved as a beacon of liberty in what is sometimes a dark world.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;It is time to let that beacon of freedom shine brighter on all our brothers and sisters.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">Seventeen states and the District of Columbia allow same-sex marriage within its borders: California, Connecticut, Delaware, Hawaii, Illinois, Iowa, Maine, Maryland, Massachusetts, Minnesota, New Hampshire, New Jersey, New Mexico, New York, Rhode Island, Vermont, and Washington.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="4">Just a decade ago, there were none.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Arkansas became the latest state to have its ban on same-sex marriage overturned, after a state judge Friday declared the voter-approved measure to be unconstitutional.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Twenty-one gay and lesbian couples were part of a group of plaintiffs challenging Amendment 83 to the Arkansas constitution, saying it violated their federal and state rights of equal protection and privacy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>There was no indication from the court the decision would be temporarily put on hold pending appeal, leaving unclear whether some same-sex couples could begin getting married immediately.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The state has the option of asking for a stay on enforcement, and the legal fight is now likely headed to the state supreme court.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;Our freedoms are often acquired slowly, but our country has evolved as a beacon of liberty in what is sometimes a dark world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>These freedoms include a right to privacy,&amp;quot; said Pulaski County Circuit Judge Chris Piazza.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is time to let that beacon of freedom shine brighter on all our brothers and sisters.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>We will be stronger for it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The ruling continues a near-unbroken string of state and federal court victories nationwide in the past year, giving marriage-equality supporters unbridled encouragement that their ultimate goal will be achieved: eliminating all laws limiting the rights of homosexuals to wed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Seventeen states and the District of Columbia allow same-sex marriage within its borders: California, Connecticut, Delaware, Hawaii, Illinois, Iowa, Maine, Maryland, Massachusetts, Minnesota, New Hampshire, New Jersey, New Mexico, New York, Rhode Island, Vermont, and Washington.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Just a decade ago, there were none.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Friday also marks the two-year anniversary of President Barack Obama voicing his public support for the first time of same-sex marriage, citing his own &amp;quot;evolution&amp;quot; on the issue.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;At a certain point, I&amp;apost;ve just concluded that for me personally it is important for me to go ahead and affirm that I think same-sex couples should be able to get married,&amp;quot; said Obama at the time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Groups supporting same-sex marriage applauded the Arkansas ruling.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;Judge Piazza held that there is no good reason for discriminating against couples and their loved ones just because they are gay,&amp;quot; said Evan Wolfson, president of Freedom to Marry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;With nearly 70 marriage cases now making their way through the courts, and five federal appellate courts now hearing arguments and soon to rule, today&amp;apost;s decision out of Arkansas underscores that all of America is ready for the freedom to marry.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>A federal appeals court last month heard challenges to same-sex marriage bans in Utah and Oklahoma.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Appeals courts in coming weeks and months will hear similar challenges over current bans in Nevada, Texas, Kentucky, Ohio, and Michigan, including Virginia next Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>In June, the U.S. Supreme Court cleared the way for same-sex marriages in California to resume after it ruled private parties did not have &amp;quot;standing&amp;quot; to defend a voter-approved ballot measure barring gay and lesbian couples from state-sanctioned wedlock.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>More importantly, the high court also rejected parts of the federal Defense of Marriage Act in its 5-4 &amp;quot;Windsor&amp;quot; decision, citing equal protection guarantees to conclude same-sex spouses legally married in a state may receive federal benefits such as tax breaks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Judge Piazza cited the Windsor case in tossing out the Arkansas statute.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;The strength of our nation is in our freedom which includes, among others, freedom of expression, freedom of religion, the right to marry, the right to bear arms, the right to be free of unreasonable searches and seizures, the right of privacy, the right of due process and equal protection, and the right to vote regardless of race or sex,&amp;quot; he wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The state&amp;apost;s attorney general, Dustin McDaniel, earlier this week said he personally backs the same-sex marriage right, but that his duties require him to defend the current ban in all court challenges.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The case is Wright v. State of Arkansas (60CV-13-2662).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
