<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1860" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/06/28/us/georgia-toddler-death-questions/index.html" date_published="2014-06-28 16:00:35" category="us" author="Michael Pearson, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>5 key questions about Georgia toddler&amp;apost;s hot-car death</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="14, 7">Cooper Harris died on June 18; his death was consistent with hyperthermia or overheating.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">Police have charged his father, Justin Ross Harris, with murder.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="24">Court documents state Harris researched child deaths in cars.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="27">Harris spoke to the crowd at Cooper&amp;apost;s funeral, via speakerphone.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-11 10:52:47" annotation_time="168.59532" mapping_time_divergence="84.29766">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">He&amp;apost;s been charged with felony murder and second-degree child cruelty.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">On the morning of June 18, Cooper and his father stopped for breakfast at a Chick-fil-A restaurant near his office in suburban Atlanta.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="1">It&amp;apost;s a condition called hyperthermia.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="3">The document states that when investigators interviewed Justin Harris, &amp;quot;he stated that he recently researched, through the Internet, child deaths inside vehicles and what temperature it needs to be for that to occur.</sentence>
      <sentence id="27" ids_highlights="4">Leanna Harris spoke in defense of her husband during Cooper&amp;apost;s funeral Saturday in Tuscaloosa, Alabama, Justin Harris&amp;apost; hometown.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s hard to imagine a young child, strapped into a car seat under a baking sun, slowly succumbing to a hellish death.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s even harder to imagine that it could have been anything other than a terrible accident.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>But that&amp;apost;s what police in Cobb County, Georgia, say happened last week when 33-year-old Justin Ross Harris left his 22-month-old son, Cooper Mills Harris, strapped into a car seat while he went to work.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s been charged with felony murder and second-degree child cruelty.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Here are the key elements about this disturbing case:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>What happened?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>On the morning of June 18, Cooper and his father stopped for breakfast at a Chick-fil-A restaurant near his office in suburban Atlanta.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Afterward, Harris put his son into the rear-facing car seat for the half-mile drive to the office.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Instead of taking Cooper inside to the day care at his office, police say Harris left the boy strapped into his car seat and went inside to work.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>According to police, he came out and opened the driver side door and put something inside at lunchtime.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>He left the office at 4:16 p.m., stopping a few miles later in a shopping center parking lot, where he called for help, screaming, &amp;quot;What have I done?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>How did Cooper die?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Although final autopsy reports aren&amp;apost;t yet in, it appears he died the same way at least 619 other children have died since 1998, according to a study by a San Francisco State University researcher: his body got too hot and there wasn&amp;apost;t anyone there to cool him down.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a condition called hyperthermia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;Essentially what happens is that the body temperature gets so high that it begins to kill the cells,&amp;quot; forensic pathologist and former medical examiner Vincent DiMaio told HLN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s like you&amp;apost;re cooking something.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>While hyperthermia can strike anyone with enough exposure to heat, babies and small children strapped into rear-facing car seats are at particular risk, if a parent or caregiver forgets they are there.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>On an 80-degree day, a car can heat to an unsafe temperature in just two minutes, according to the National Weather Service, and the temperature can rise to 123 degrees in just one hour.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>On the day Cooper died, the temperature peaked at 88 degrees.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>So why is the father charged with murder?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Police at first seemed sympathetic to what seemed like a tragic accident, but later said there was more to the case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;The chain of events that occurred in this case does not point toward simple negligence and evidence will be presented to support this allegation,&amp;quot; Cobb County police Chief John R. Houser said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>A subsequent affidavit released by the Magistrate Court of Cobb County may indeed support the allegation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The document states that when investigators interviewed Justin Harris, &amp;quot;he stated that he recently researched, through the Internet, child deaths inside vehicles and what temperature it needs to be for that to occur.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Justin stated that he was fearful this could happen.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>What are his family and friends saying?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Leanna Harris spoke in defense of her husband during Cooper&amp;apost;s funeral Saturday in Tuscaloosa, Alabama, Justin Harris&amp;apost; hometown.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Justin Harris spoke as well, by phone from jail, thanking attendees &amp;quot;for everything you&amp;apost;ve done for my boy.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The family has not answered questions from the media.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Neither has anyone close to the family.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Of the numerous family and friends of Harris contacted by CNN, none would speak.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Most said they had been advised not to.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Cooper&amp;apost;s obituary says the boy was &amp;quot;loved and cherished and protected by both parents and all family members for his short 22 months of life.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>And on a now-closed change.org petition calling on authorities to drop the charges, several posts from people who said they know Harris spoke well of him.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;He has been nothing but a caring father and supporting husband,&amp;quot; wrote one poster, identified as Michael Gordon of Northport, Alabama.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>What&amp;apost;s next?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Justin Harris is being held without bond at the Cobb County jail after pleading not guilty last week.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s scheduled for a preliminary appearance on July 3.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Because he&amp;apost;s charged with murder, a grand jury will also have to review his case if the magistrate in an upcoming hearing finds probable cause for the charge to stand.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
