<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1911" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/09/13/us/benghazi-victims/index.html " date_published="2012-09-13 21:37:30" category="us" author="Matt Smith, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Ex-SEALs, online gaming maven among Benghazi dead</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6">NEW: Tyrone Woods&amp;apost; friends and family called him &amp;quot;Rone,&amp;quot; Clinton says .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="11">Security officer Glen Doherty was searching for anti-aircraft missiles, source says: .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">Computer expert Sean Smith was renowned in a gamer&amp;apost;s universe.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="3">Both died in Benghazi with Chris Stevens, the U.S. ambassador to Libya.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-08 23:55:29" annotation_time="50.871334" mapping_time_divergence="25.435667">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="3">Sean Smith was a computer expert with an online alter-ego legendary in the gaming world.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="4">The three men and U.S. Ambassador Chris Stevens died in the assault on the American consulate in the Libyan city of Benghazi.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;Tyrone&amp;apost;s friends and colleagues called him &amp;apost;Rone,&amp;apost; and they relied on his courage and skill, honed over two decades as a Navy SEAL,&amp;quot; said Secretary of State Hillary Clinton in a statement.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="2">A diplomatic source told CNN that Doherty was in Libya to search for shoulder-fired anti-aircraft missiles -- a mission given high priority after the fall of longtime Libyan strongman Moammar Gadhafi.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Tyrone Woods and Glen Doherty were former Navy SEAL commandos working as diplomatic security officers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Sean Smith was a computer expert with an online alter-ego legendary in the gaming world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The three men and U.S. Ambassador Chris Stevens died in the assault on the American consulate in the Libyan city of Benghazi.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Details of how they met their fates in the Mediterranean city that had been the cradle of Libya&amp;apost;s 2011 revolution were just beginning to emerge Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>On Thursday, a U.S. official confirmed Woods as among the dead.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;Tyrone&amp;apost;s friends and colleagues called him &amp;apost;Rone,&amp;apost; and they relied on his courage and skill, honed over two decades as a Navy SEAL,&amp;quot; said Secretary of State Hillary Clinton in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;In uniform, he served multiple tours in Iraq and Afghanistan.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Since 2010, he protected American diplomatic personnel in dangerous posts from Central America to the Middle East.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>He had the hands of a healer as well as the arm of a warrior, earning distinction as a registered nurse and certified paramedic.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>All our hearts go out to Tyrone&amp;apost;s wife Dorothy and his three sons, Tyrone Jr., Hunter, and Kai, who was born just a few months ago.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>A diplomatic source told CNN that Doherty was in Libya to search for shoulder-fired anti-aircraft missiles -- a mission given high priority after the fall of longtime Libyan strongman Moammar Gadhafi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Doherty grew up in Massachusetts with a passion for the outdoors, particularly the mountain West, his family said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Outside the family&amp;apost;s home in Woburn, near Boston, his sister remembered him as &amp;quot;our American hero.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;Glen lived his life to the fullest,&amp;quot; Katie Quigley told reporters.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;He was my brother, but if you ask his friends, he was their brother as well.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The 42-year-old graduated from high school in 1988 in neighboring Winchester, where flags were displayed at half-staff on Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>He played on the varsity tennis and wrestling teams, school officials said in an announcement marking his death.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>His junior-year English teacher, Judy Hession, recalled him as &amp;quot;bursting with life.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;Every day his huge smile and his happy-go-lucky optimism filled my classroom,&amp;quot; Hession said in a statement released by the school district.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;He got along with all types of people, was a class leader and, from the perspective of 30 years of teaching, one of my most memorable students.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>After college in Arizona and stints as a &amp;quot;ski bum&amp;quot; and raft guide in Utah, Doherty joined the Navy and became a member of the elite Navy SEAL commandos in 1995, his family said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>He had planned to leave the service after knee surgery in 2001, but after the al Qaeda attacks on New York and Washington, he &amp;quot;was not allowed to to leave and didn&amp;apost;t want to,&amp;quot; his family said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Doherty served two tours of duty in Iraq, starting with the U.S. invasion in 2003, before leaving the military in 2005.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>He then became a private security contractor, working in Afghanistan, Pakistan and Yemen -- a job that took a toll on his home life and contributed to a divorce, his family said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>He also joined the advisory board of the Military Religious Freedom Foundation, a group that has battled religious intolerance in the U.S. armed forces.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Its president, former Air Force officer Michael &amp;quot;Mikey&amp;quot; Weinstein, said he was &amp;quot;in a state of shock&amp;quot; after learning of Doherty&amp;apost;s death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;He was one of our most active advisory board members,&amp;quot; Weinstein said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;I was surprised he was willing to come on and lend the gravitas that comes with being a Navy SEAL to our cause.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Doherty&amp;apost;s involvement &amp;quot;made it easier for others to come to us,&amp;quot; Weinstein added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>He said Doherty believed the kind of violent jihadists American troops faced were &amp;quot;a very small percentage of the overall mosaic of the Muslim faith,&amp;quot; and saw anti-Muslim sentiment in the United States and in the ranks as something that hurt U.S. national security.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;He went back to the Middle East because he cared deeply about the Muslim people, and because he cared about bringing freedom and democracy and human rights to the Middle East,&amp;quot; Weinstein said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Doherty &amp;quot;was a kind and caring person, and I&amp;apost;m sure that he gave every last bit of his courage and strength&amp;quot; to defend the consulate and Stevens, he added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;All this is going to do is light a further fire under us in Glen&amp;apost;s name and memory to continue to fight for religious freedom and respect and tolerance.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>He also co-authored a 2010 book, &amp;quot;The 21st-Century Sniper: A Complete Practical Guide,&amp;quot; with former comrade Brandon Webb.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>In a statement accompanying the family&amp;apost;s, Webb said, &amp;quot;Don&amp;apost;t feel sorry for him, he wouldn&amp;apost;t have it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;He died serving with men he respected, protecting the freedoms we enjoy as Americans and doing something he loved,&amp;quot; Webb said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>In her statement, Clinton said Doherty, a paramedic, was referred to as &amp;quot;Bub&amp;quot; by his friends and family.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;In the end, he died the way he lived -- with selfless honor and unstinting valor,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Smith&amp;apost;s death was among the first reported in the Benghazi fracas.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Clinton eulogized him Wednesday as a 10-year veteran of the Foreign Service, an information management officer who had served in Iraq, South Africa, Canada and the Netherlands.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>In real life, he was an Air Force veteran with a wife, a son and a daughter.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>But in the virtual universe of the computer game EVE Online, Smith was &amp;quot;Vile Rat&amp;quot; -- one of the leaders of a gamer&amp;apost;s alliance renowned for his diplomatic skill in the multi-player space warfare simulation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>&amp;quot;If you play this stupid game, you may not realize it, but you play in a galaxy created in large part by Vile Rat&amp;apost;s talent as a diplomat.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>No one focused as relentlessly on using diplomacy as a strategic tool as VR,&amp;quot; Smith&amp;apost;s friend Alex Gianturco wrote in a tribute posted on his website.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Gianturco wrote that Smith had been under fire before, while posted to Baghdad.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>When that occurred, he usually broke off his messaging.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;d freak out and he&amp;apost;d come back OK after a bit,&amp;quot; Gianturco wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>But Tuesday night, after reporting &amp;quot;GUNFIRE,&amp;quot; Smith &amp;quot;disconnected and never returned,&amp;quot; he added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>A few hours earlier, Smith had posted, &amp;quot;assuming we don&amp;apost;t die tonight.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>We saw one of our &amp;apost;police&amp;apost; that guard the compound taking pictures,&amp;quot; he recounted.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m clearly in shock as I write this as everything is buzzing around my head funnily and I feel kind of dead inside,&amp;quot; Gianturco wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
