<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1857" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/02/08/us/northeast-blizzard/index.html" date_published="2013-02-08 08:19:02" category="us" author="CNN Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>1 dead, 600,000 without power from ongoing blizzard</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="21">NEW: One person confirmed dead in storm-related vehicle accident.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="24">NEW: More than 600,000 customers are without power in the area.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">Connecticut warns 4 to 5 inches of snow an hour may fall in the state.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="5">Parts of Rhode Island, Connecticut and Massachusetts already have 1-plus feet of snow.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-08 14:07:15" annotation_time="31.479334">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">At one point Friday night, for instance, Connecticut&amp;apost;s emergency management agency warned on Twitter that &amp;quot;a wide ban of extremely heavy snow&amp;quot; was moving through the central and eastern parts of the Nutmeg State, dropping snow at a staggering rate of 4 to 5 inches an hour.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="4">Smithfield, Rhode Island, had 14 inches of snow by 9 p.m. Friday, one of several towns in that state, Connecticut and Massachusetts to be buried under more than a foot of snow -- with much more, potentially, on the way.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="1">Police in Poughkeepsie, New York, said one person died in a storm-related vehicle accident there, the first fatality that CNN has confirmed from the blizzard.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="2">By early Saturday, more than 600,000 customers -- most in Massachusetts, Rhode Island and Connecticut -- were without electricity, a number that could grow.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A monster blizzard has left at least one person dead and hundreds of thousands of New Englanders in the dark and in the cold Friday night, thanks to a storm that&amp;apost;s already delivered whipping winds and more than a foot of snow in some parts, with prospects of even double that by the time it&amp;apost;s done.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The storm -- actually the convergence of two powerful systems -- began in earnest Friday morning in parts of New York and is expected to continue well into Saturday in Rhode Island, eastern Massachusetts and Maine.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Snow was more or less continuous for much of the region all day, with some lulls as well as times when it picked up considerably.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>At one point Friday night, for instance, Connecticut&amp;apost;s emergency management agency warned on Twitter that &amp;quot;a wide ban of extremely heavy snow&amp;quot; was moving through the central and eastern parts of the Nutmeg State, dropping snow at a staggering rate of 4 to 5 inches an hour.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Smithfield, Rhode Island, had 14 inches of snow by 9 p.m. Friday, one of several towns in that state, Connecticut and Massachusetts to be buried under more than a foot of snow -- with much more, potentially, on the way.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;I couldn&amp;apost;t believe the amount of snow that had piled up, as well as the many fallen branches,&amp;quot; said CNN iReporter Molly Schulson in Providence, Rhode Island.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>She was among the tens of millions of people stranded in the blizzard&amp;apost;s path.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Many were prohibited by authorities from driving as a preemptive measure while other roads were closed in the thick of the bad weather, as was the case late Friday for New York&amp;apost;s Long Island Expressway and Sunrise Highway, according to the Suffolk County Police Department.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Others saw their travel plans squashed when more than 5,000 flights from some 60 airports were canceled.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>And Amtrak nixed several of its scheduled runs, citing the weather, while commuter rail service in and out of New York and other locales were also impacted.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>That helped transform several New England communities into ghost towns, as streets that typically would be choked with traffic were quiet, except for whistling winds; and empty, except for a blanket of thick, sticky snow.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>CNN iReporters sent in photos and video from Boston, for instance, that showed sheets of white on the ground -- except when whipping winds made for near whiteout conditions on camera -- and little movement on the streets.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;Boston is kind of eerie at the moment,&amp;quot; said Chris Moran, a veteran snowplow driver doing his best to keep the roads clear.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;People are off the streets, and it looks like it could be 3 o&amp;apost;clock in the morning.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Strong winds made this storm especially biting.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>By Friday night, the National Weather Service reported wind gusts around 70 mph along the Massachusetts coast and through greater Boston, including a 74-mph gust in Buzzards Bay on Cape Cod.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;The wind is just pounding,&amp;quot; CNN iReporter Jordana Fleischut said from Nantucket, off Massachusetts&amp;apost; southern coast.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s currently moving the Jeep that we&amp;apost;re in -- that&amp;apost;s how powerful it is.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Such strong winds threatened to rustle up flooding along the coast at high tide Saturday morning.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>In the seaside Massachusetts town of Marshfield, for instance, the emergency management agency noted there may be a storm surge of between two to three feet and forecast a &amp;quot;serious event with moderate to major impact&amp;quot; around 10 a.m. Saturday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Police in Poughkeepsie, New York, said one person died in a storm-related vehicle accident there, the first fatality that CNN has confirmed from the blizzard.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The storm also damage for those not living directly on the coast, as evidenced by extensive power outages around the region.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>For many more people, the storm&amp;apost;s impact will be in the form of widespread power outages.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>By early Saturday, more than 600,000 customers -- most in Massachusetts, Rhode Island and Connecticut -- were without electricity, a number that could grow.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>For some, it all evoked memories of the &amp;quot;Blizzard of &amp;apost;78&amp;quot; and the &amp;quot;Presidents Day Storm of 2003&amp;quot; -- two of dozens of winter storms in Massachusetts that Moran has been out on the streets.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The Framingham resident bundled up to brave the bitter cold and clear snow off the roads.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>But with a storm this powerful, it sometimes seems like a losing battle.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;I just finished plowing a 40-car parking lot,&amp;quot; said Moran.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;But if you were to look at it now, you never would have guessed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s completely covered.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Alarms raised, events canceled ahead of the storm.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Authorities have been sounding the alarm about the coming storm for days, urging people to stock up and stay off the roads.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The worries were especially pronounced in places slammed by Sandy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>That late October storm tore through Nick Camerada&amp;apost;s Staten Island home, leaving him personally &amp;quot;destroyed&amp;quot; and cognizant that there may be more hits coming.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;You can&amp;apost;t mess with Mother Nature,&amp;quot; an emotional Camerada said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Lines of customers snaked around storefronts as many braced for the worst.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>When Reading, Massachusetts, resident Elizabeth Frazier arrived at a grocery store late Thursday night, shoppers were already buying up the store.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s a zoo in there,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;There&amp;apost;s nothing left on the shelves,&amp;quot; she told CNN affiliate WHDH.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Governors across New England and New York have declared states of emergency, and all cars and trucks -- except emergency vehicles -- must now be off Massachusetts and Connecticut roadways.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>A similar ban in Rhode Island took effect at 5 p.m.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Violating that ban could incur a penalty of up to a year in jail and a $500 fine.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>By Friday night, the storm had already led to hundreds of cancellations of public school classes to sporting events.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>The storm even prompted the cancellation of ACT tests, for would-be college students, around the Northeast.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Utility companies tried to get a head start on the storm, by having additional crews ready to respond to outages caused by downed power lines.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>The fear is that, as happened after Sandy, such outages could persist for days.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Still, for all the alarms being raised, the mayor of Boston -- which forecasters expected would be the city hardest hit by the storm -- said he expected residents of his community and others to hunker down and weather the storm.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Said Mayor Thomas Menino, &amp;quot;We are hardy New Englanders.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
