<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1959" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/02/09/us/north-korea-trip-cancelled/index.html" date_published="2014-02-10 02:10:53" category="us" author="Ralph Ellis and Jethro Mullen, CNN" highlights_mapped="false" mapping_error="false">
  <title>North Korea cancels U.S. envoy&amp;apost;s visit to discuss Kenneth Bae</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="13">NEW: The Rev. Jesse Jackson has offered to go to Pyongyang.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">Ambassador Robert King was scheduled to visit and discuss Bae&amp;apost;s case.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">North Korea has held Bae, a Korean-American, since November 2012.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="14">Annual U.S.-South Korean military drills, which anger Pyongyang, begin later this month.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_time="312.017">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="3">Bae, of Lynwood, Washington, was arrested in November 2012 in Rason, along North Korea&amp;apost;s northeastern coast.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">State Department spokeswoman Jen Psaki expressed disappointment that Ambassador Robert King&amp;apost;s visit was called off and noted North Korea had said it wouldn&amp;apost;t use Bae as a &amp;quot;political bargaining trip.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="1">The Rev. Jesse Jackson, the U.S. civil rights leader, has offered, at the request of Bae&amp;apost;s family, to &amp;quot;travel to Pyongyang on a humanitarian mission focused on Bae&amp;apost;s release,&amp;quot; Psaki added.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="4">She said that annual joint military exercises by U.S. and South Korean forces, due to begin later this month, are &amp;quot;in no way linked to Mr. Bae&amp;apost;s case.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>North Korea has rescinded its invitation for a U.S. envoy to visit the secretive nation to discuss the fate of Kenneth Bae, a Korean-American man who is being held there, a State Department official said Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Bae, of Lynwood, Washington, was arrested in November 2012 in Rason, along North Korea&amp;apost;s northeastern coast.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Pyongyang sentenced him last year to 15 years of hard labor, accusing him of planning to bring down the government through religious activities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>He is widely reported to have been carrying out Christian missionary work in North Korea.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Bae, 45, operated a China-based company specializing in tours of North Korea, according to his family, who have described him as a devout Christian.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>No reason was given for the trip cancellation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>State Department spokeswoman Jen Psaki expressed disappointment that Ambassador Robert King&amp;apost;s visit was called off and noted North Korea had said it wouldn&amp;apost;t use Bae as a &amp;quot;political bargaining trip.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>This is the second time North Korea has canceled a planned visit by King.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Bae was moved to a hospital last year after his health deteriorated.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>But last week the United States said he had been moved back to a labor camp, a development his family described as &amp;quot;devastating.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;We again call on the DPRK to grant Bae special amnesty and immediate release as a humanitarian gesture so he may reunite with his family and seek medical care,&amp;quot; Psaki said Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;We will continue to work actively to secure Mr. Bae&amp;apost;s release.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The Rev. Jesse Jackson, the U.S. civil rights leader, has offered, at the request of Bae&amp;apost;s family, to &amp;quot;travel to Pyongyang on a humanitarian mission focused on Bae&amp;apost;s release,&amp;quot; Psaki added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>She said that annual joint military exercises by U.S. and South Korean forces, due to begin later this month, are &amp;quot;in no way linked to Mr. Bae&amp;apost;s case.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Tensions over exercises.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The large military drills anger the nuclear-armed North Korean regime, which says it views them as a prelude to an invasion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Last year, Pyongyang&amp;apost;s threatening rhetoric reached alarming levels during the exercises, heightening tensions in the region.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>North Korea has been urging the South not to take part in the drills -- a call that Seoul and Washington have rejected.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>This year&amp;apost;s exercises, involving thousands of U.S. and South Korean troops, will begin February 24, United States Forces Korea said Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>One of the exercises, Key Resolve, in which about 5,200 U.S. troops will participate, will run until March 6.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The U.S. military says Key Resolve makes sure forces are prepared to defend South Korea and trains them to &amp;quot;respond to any potential event on the peninsula.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The other exercise, Foal Eagle, in which about 7,500 U.S. troops will take part, continues until April 18.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Foal Eagle, according to the U.S. military, is &amp;quot;a series of joint and combined field training exercises&amp;quot; that combine ground, air, naval, expeditionary and special operations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>United States Forces Korea said the North&amp;apost;s Korean People&amp;apost;s Army had been informed of the dates of the exercises and of &amp;quot;the non-provocative nature of this training.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The dates of the drills overlap with planned reunions of families in North and South Korea who were separated by the Korean War in the 1950s.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The reunions of about 200 people -- 100 from each country -- are scheduled to take place between February 20 and 25 at a resort on the North&amp;apost;s side of the heavily militarized border.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>But Pyongyang said last week it may back out of the arrangement -- as it has in the past -- if South Korea goes ahead with the joint military drills with the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
