<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1863" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/07/14/us/twa-flight-800-five-things/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-07-14 16:56:59" category="us" author="Chuck Hadad, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>5 things you didn&amp;apost;t know about the crash of TWA 800</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="42">230 people were on board TWA Flight 800 from 13 countries.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">The government spent four years and millions of dollars in the investigation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="49">The FBI said the disaster was not caused by a terrorist act .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-01 17:18:05" annotation_time="20.894333">
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">The government spent four years and millions of dollars in that investigation and 18 years later, many still question whether they got it right.</sentence>
      <sentence id="42" ids_highlights="1">There were 230 people on board TWA Flight 800 from 13 countries.</sentence>
      <sentence id="49" ids_highlights="3">In November 1997, more than a year after the crash, the FBI announced that a criminal act did not bring down the ill-fated plane.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>On July 17, 1996, TWA Flight 800 took off from JFK Airport headed for Paris.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Just 12 minutes later, it exploded over the shores of Long Island, New York.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>There were 230 people on board, and no one survived.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Many eyewitnesses described seeing something heading toward the plane before it exploded, and the suspicion of terrorism was almost instant.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The biggest investigation in aviation history, at that time, ensued.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The government spent four years and millions of dollars in that investigation and 18 years later, many still question whether they got it right.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>With that in mind, here are five surprising things you probably didn&amp;apost;t know about the investigation, including one big thing the investigators themselves still don&amp;apost;t know:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>1.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The FBI interviewed at least 755 witnesses.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>TWA Flight 800 crashed eight miles off the coast of Long Island at dusk on a clear summer night.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Hundreds of witnesses saw the plane explode from either on shore, on a boat, in a plane or in at least one case, a helicopter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Of the 755 witness reports that the FBI have made public, accounts vary widely but hundreds describe what they thought was either a flare or fireworks heading up toward the plane before it exploded.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>A few witnesses even used the words &amp;quot;missile&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;rocket.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>2.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>America was in a high state of alert when TWA 800 crashed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>A series of terrorism-related events in the years, months and weeks before the flight went down, and even one incident just days afterward, led many to suspect terrorism was to blame.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>-- December 21, 1988: Pan Am Flight 103 explodes over Lockerbie, Scotland, killing all 270 people on board.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Eventually Libyan national Abdel Baset Ali Mohmed al Megrah is tried and found guilty of 270 counts of murder.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>-- February 26, 1993: A bomb explodes at the World Trade Center, killing six people and injuring more than 1000.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Two years later, Ramzi Yousef, the mastermind of that attack, is arrested in Pakistan by the FBI and the State Department and put on trial.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am a terrorist and proud of it,&amp;quot; he told the court.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>-- April 19, 1995: The Alfred P. Murrah building in Oklahoma City is bombed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The blast destroys large parts of the building and kills 168 people, including 19 children.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Two Americans, Timothy J. McVeigh and Terry L. Nichols, are eventually convicted for the attack.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>-- May 29, 1996: Yousef goes on trial in New York City.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The trial continues through the crash of TWA Flight 800, leading many to question if the two were related.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>-- June 25, 1996: The Khobar Towers are attacked.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>A powerful truck bomb explodes on the perimeter of a U.S. military complex in eastern Saudi Arabia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Nineteen U.S. Air Force personnel are killed, and several hundred are wounded, in the deadliest attack against the American military since a 1983 bombing of the Marine headquarters in Beirut, Lebanon.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>-- July 17, 1996: TWA Flight 800 explodes over the shores of Long Island.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>-- July 27, 1996: A bomb explodes at the Olympic Games in Atlanta, killing one person and injuring over 100.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>More than two years later, Eric Robert Rudolph, a suspect in bombings at abortion clinics in Alabama, is charged in the Olympic Park bombing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>3.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Moammar Gadhafi and Saddam Hussein were suspects.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Beyond terrorist groups being suspected, state-sponsored terrorism was also cause for concern inside the White House.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Leon Panetta, former secretary of Defense and former CIA director, was chief of staff for President Bill Clinton at the time of the crash.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;The investigation was looking at almost every possibility, including state actors, because we&amp;apost;d known that Libya had been involved with regards to bringing down the airliner over Scotland (Pam Am Flight 103)&amp;quot;, said Panetta.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;We were looking at Iraq and Saddam Hussein.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>We were looking at, you know, the possibility of even Iran might have played a role in this,&amp;quot; added Panetta.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>4.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>It took close to a year, but all 230 victims were eventually recovered.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>There were 230 people on board TWA Flight 800 from 13 countries.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>When the plane crashed into the water, much of what was left sunk 130 feet below the surface in the Atlantic Ocean.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>While it took authorities more than 10 months, remains of every victim were recovered.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>All of their names are etched into the TWA Flight 800 International Memorial at Smith Point County Park on Long Island, New York.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>The memorial was dedicated on July 14, 2004, and it includes flags from the 13 countries of the victims.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>5.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>The NTSB said a spark in a fuel tank led to the explosion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>In November 1997, more than a year after the crash, the FBI announced that a criminal act did not bring down the ill-fated plane.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>At that point, it was up to the National Transportation Safety Board to figure out the cause of the explosion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>A full four years after the crash of TWA Flight 800, the NTSB released its official report: It found the probable cause of the accident was a spark in the center fuel tank that eventually led to the explosion that brought down the aircraft.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>While they offered their best theory on where the spark came from, they never found a definitive answer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
