<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2005" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/12/26/us/utah-same-sex-marriage" date_published="2013-12-26 21:20:01" category="us" author="Michael Martinez, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Utah to appeal same-sex marriage ruling to U.S. Supreme Court</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6">NEW: Sotomayor is likely to refer Utah request to entire court, expert says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Utah attorney general will appeal a lower-court ruling to nation&amp;apost;s highest court.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">Utah will file appeal after consulting with outside attorneys over the next few days.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="9">A lower federal court struck down Utah&amp;apost;s ban on same-sex marriage.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-09 14:19:20" annotation_time="34.886">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2">Utah officials will appeal to the U.S. Supreme Court a lower-court ruling allowing same-sex marriage in the state, the state attorney general&amp;apost;s office said Thursday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="3">Newly appointed Utah Attorney General Sean Reyes will seek a stay of the federal judge&amp;apost;s ruling after state officials consult first with outside attorneys over the next few days.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">Sotomayor is likely to refer the Utah request to the entire court, as is tradition with high-profile traditional cases, said Carl Tobias, a professor of constitutional law at the University of Richmond.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="4">Last week, U.S. District Judge Robert J. Shelby struck down Utah&amp;apost;s ban on same-sex marriage, saying the law &amp;quot;conflicts with the United States Constitution&amp;apost;s guarantees of equal protection and due process under the law.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Utah officials will appeal to the U.S. Supreme Court a lower-court ruling allowing same-sex marriage in the state, the state attorney general&amp;apost;s office said Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Newly appointed Utah Attorney General Sean Reyes will seek a stay of the federal judge&amp;apost;s ruling after state officials consult first with outside attorneys over the next few days.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is the intent of the Attorney General&amp;apost;s Office to file with the Supreme Court as soon as possible,&amp;quot; the attorney general&amp;apost;s office said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The emergency appeal, when filed, would go to Justice Sonia Sotomayor because she has jurisdiction over appeals from Utah and nearby states.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>She could rule on the state&amp;apost;s application herself or ask the entire nine-member court to weigh in.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Sotomayor is likely to refer the Utah request to the entire court, as is tradition with high-profile traditional cases, said Carl Tobias, a professor of constitutional law at the University of Richmond.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The Utah announcement comes two days after state officials lost their case in a federal appeals court, which said the state&amp;apost;s request for a stay wasn&amp;apost;t warranted and ordered the appeal process be expedited.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The appeals court&amp;apost;s ruling allows same-sex marriages to continue in Utah while appeals continue.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Last week, U.S. District Judge Robert J. Shelby struck down Utah&amp;apost;s ban on same-sex marriage, saying the law &amp;quot;conflicts with the United States Constitution&amp;apost;s guarantees of equal protection and due process under the law.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Utah voters approved a law banning same-sex marriage in 2004.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Judge Shelby&amp;apost;s ruling drew national attention partly because Utah is viewed as among the more conservative states and because the U.S. Supreme Court just ruled this summer on same-sex marriage.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>In June, the nation&amp;apost;s highest court cleared the way for same-sex marriages in California to resume after it ruled private parties did not have &amp;quot;standing&amp;quot; to defend California&amp;apost;s voter-approved ballot measure barring gay and lesbian couples from state-sanctioned wedlock.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The U.S. Supreme Court also rejected parts of the federal Defense of Marriage Act (DOMA) in a 5-4 decision, dismissing an appeal over same-sex marriage on jurisdictional grounds and ruling same-sex spouses legally married in a state may receive federal benefits.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>In the Utah case, the state argues that the &amp;quot;federal district court&amp;apost;s ruling that same-sex marriage is a fundamental right has never been established in any previous case in the 10th Circuit&amp;quot; Court of Appeals, the attorney general&amp;apost;s office said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The federal judge&amp;apost;s ruling, nonetheless, prompted a rush of same-sex couples to courthouses in Utah where they obtained marriage licenses, despite the state&amp;apost;s ongoing legal challenge.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Some jurisdictions such as Piute and San Juan Counties are issuing marriage licenses to same-sex couples, but there haven&amp;apost;t been requests for them there, officials said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Utah Gov. Gary R. Herbert has criticized Judge Shelby&amp;apost;s ruling of last week, calling him &amp;quot;an activist federal judge.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Shelby said the state&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;current laws deny its gay and lesbian citizens their fundamental right to marry and, in so doing, demean the dignity of these same-sex couples for no rational reason.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;Accordingly, the court finds that these laws are unconstitutional,&amp;quot; the judge said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Same-sex marriage is banned by constitutional amendment or state law in: Alabama, Alaska, Arizona, Arkansas, Colorado, Florida, Georgia, Idaho, Indiana, Kansas, Kentucky, Louisiana, Michigan, Mississippi, Missouri, Montana, Nebraska, Nevada, North Carolina, North Dakota, Ohio, Oklahoma, Oregon, Pennsylvania, South Carolina, South Dakota, Tennessee, Texas, Virginia, West Virginia, Wisconsin and Wyoming.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>It is legal in 17 other U.S states and the District of Columbia: California, Connecticut, Delaware, Hawaii, Illinois, Iowa, Maine, Maryland, Massachusetts, Minnesota, New Hampshire, New Jersey, New Mexico, New York, Rhode Island, Vermont and Washington.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
