<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1864" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/05/01/us/colleges-sex-complaint-investigations" date_published="2014-05-01 16:34:53" category="us" author="Jason Hanna, Emanuella Grinberg and Eliott C. McLaughlin, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>55 colleges investigated over handling of sexual violence complaints</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">List includes colleges and universities from 27 states and Washington, D.C.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">Education Department: &amp;quot;We hope this increased transparency will spur community dialogue&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="26">Rape is a longstanding issue on campuses, but activists are now casting it as a cultural problem.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="38">Any federally funded school not complying with Title IX risks losing funding.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-28 12:54:01" annotation_time="46.091">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">The list includes colleges and universities in 27 states and in the District of Columbia.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;We hope this increased transparency will spur community dialogue about this important issue.</sentence>
      <sentence id="26" ids_highlights="3">Rape is a longstanding issue on college campuses, but the latest movement, led by student activists, survivors and faculty, recasts sexual violence as a cultural problem on campuses nationwide -- not just a series of isolated incidents.</sentence>
      <sentence id="38" ids_highlights="4">All schools -- from K-12 to universities -- must comply with Title IX or risk losing funding and Justice Department action.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Federal investigators are checking whether 55 colleges and universities illegally handled sexual violence and harassment complaints, the U.S. Department of Education said Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Such investigations have long been known, but this is the first time that the department has released a list of all probes currently under way.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The list includes colleges and universities in 27 states and in the District of Columbia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are making this list available in an effort to bring more transparency to our enforcement work and to foster better public awareness of civil rights,&amp;quot; said Catherine E. Lhamon, the department&amp;apost;s assistant secretary for civil rights.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;We hope this increased transparency will spur community dialogue about this important issue.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>I also want to make it clear that a college or university&amp;apost;s appearance on this list and being the subject of a Title IX investigation in no way indicates at this stage that the college or university is violating or has violated the law.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Five schools promptly responded to CNN&amp;apost;s request for response.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The University of California, Berkeley said it will cooperate with the investigation and added that its chancellor had sent out a letter to campus saying sexual assault would not be tolerated.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;Much has been done to strengthen the campus&amp;apost; handling of these issues, but we understand that there is always room for improvement,&amp;quot; the university statement said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Washington State University, meanwhile, said it was notified in January 2013 that a federal complaint had been filed and volunteered to work with the Department of Education&amp;apost;s Office of Civil Rights to improve its policies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>In February, the university said, federal representatives visited Pullman and engaged in student focus groups as well as student and employee interviews.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;There has been no finding of any wrongdoing on the part of WSU.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>We are still waiting to hear from OCR regarding participation in the voluntary resolution process,&amp;quot; a university statement said, adding that there&amp;apost;s no tolerance for sexual harassment, assault or misconduct on its campus.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The University of Wisconsin-Whitewater said it could not comment on specifics because of the ongoing investigation but said it, too, took sexual violence seriously and provides all victims with resources and assistance.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The University of Chicago said it had &amp;quot;made every effort to comply with the spirit and letter of this inquiry&amp;quot; and is committed to ensuring that its programs and work environment are discrimination free.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The University of Colorado Boulder said it wasn&amp;apost;t surprised by its inclusion as it knew of the probe in July, and it has since hired a law firm to conduct an external review of its policies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>It also expects to a name a specially designated Title IX director by the end of the summer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The investigations center on Title IX, under which a school must ensure that students are not denied or limited in the ability to participate in or benefit from its educational programs or activities on the basis of sex.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The list, which reflects open investigations as of Thursday, does not disclose any details about the cases, other than when the investigation was opened.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The list will be updated regularly and available to the public upon request.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>In February, CNN profiled student and faculty activists from six schools in a report on how sexual violence complaints to the Department of Education&amp;apost;s Office of Civil Rights had almost tripled since 2009.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Thursday&amp;apost;s numbers come on the heels of a marked year-to-year increase in complaints the department received, from 17 in 2012 to 30 in 2013.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Five of those six students&amp;apost; universities were included in Thursday&amp;apost;s report: the University of Texas-Pan American; Vanderbilt University; the University of California, Berkeley; Occidental College; and Emory University.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In the story, Joanna Espinosa, a student at UTPA who has since graduated, told CNN she would not have come forward without the help of a nationwide network that has been a driving force in bringing attention to the way schools handle sexual misconduct reports.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>President Barack Obama recently called the nationwide, student-led movement a catalyst for a federal task force to protect college students from sexual violence on campus.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Rape is a longstanding issue on college campuses, but the latest movement, led by student activists, survivors and faculty, recasts sexual violence as a cultural problem on campuses nationwide -- not just a series of isolated incidents.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Students are taking matters into their own hands, filing complaints en masse and speaking out publicly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>They&amp;apost;ve flocked to advocacy groups such as End Rape on Campus and Know Your IX, which sprang from grassroots activism around university handling -- or mishandling -- of sexual violence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Leslie Gomez, a Pennsylvania attorney and former prosecutor who has worked as a sexual assault policy consultant for Occidental College, Grinnell College and other schools, told CNN that from one campus to the next, the concerns are mostly the same: lack of clarity, students being mistreated, complex procedures and insufficient training among those leading the processes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>After she grew displeased with how campus and local authorities handled her case, Espinosa reached out to End Rape on Campus, and a member of the group helped her file a complaint with the federal Office of Civil Rights.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m not sure I would&amp;apost;ve come forward if all these people hadn&amp;apost;t done it before me,&amp;quot; Espinosa said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;I needed the validation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>I needed someone to confirm, &amp;apost;You&amp;apost;re right.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>You&amp;apost;re not blowing things out of proportion.&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>... It was a relief to hear someone tell me, &amp;apost;You have a case, and they shouldn&amp;apost;t treat you this way.&amp;apost; &amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>In Thursday&amp;apost;s announcement, the Department of Education said releasing its list &amp;quot;advances a key goal of President Obama&amp;apost;s White House Task Force to Protect Students from Sexual Assault to bring more transparency to the federal government&amp;apost;s enforcement activities around this issue.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>The department also released new guidance this week outlining federally funded schools&amp;apost; responsibilities to address sexual violence and other forms of discrimination.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>All schools -- from K-12 to universities -- must comply with Title IX or risk losing funding and Justice Department action.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;Under federal law, sexual violence refers to physical sexual acts perpetrated against a person&amp;apost;s will or where a person is incapable of giving consent -- including rape, sexual assault, sexual battery, sexual abuse and sexual coercion,&amp;quot; the statement said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>