<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1979" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/08/31/us/oregon-beach-collapse/index.html?hpt=hp_t2&amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;imw=Y" date_published="2014-08-31 04:36:47" category="us" author="Mark Morgenstein and Faith Karimi, CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Sand collapse kills 9-year-old girl at Oregon beach</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Isabel Grace Franks, 9, died Friday, buried in sand at an Oregon beach.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">&amp;quot;We heard screaming,&amp;quot; a witness says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">Franks is at least the third person to die in beach sand in the United States this summer.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-12 13:54:11" annotation_time="25.132">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">But that unexpected killer has now claimed at least three lives in the United States this summer.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">Nine-year-old Isabel Grace Franks died at a Lincoln City, Oregon, beach on Friday, when a hole she was digging in the sand caved in and buried her, authorities said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;We heard screaming,&amp;quot; Tracey Dudley, who was staying at a nearby hotel, told CNN affiliate KATU.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>When you think of potentially fatal threats at the beach, you probably think of sharks or riptides.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>You probably don&amp;apost;t worry about the sand.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>But that unexpected killer has now claimed at least three lives in the United States this summer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Nine-year-old Isabel Grace Franks died at a Lincoln City, Oregon, beach on Friday, when a hole she was digging in the sand caved in and buried her, authorities said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;We heard screaming,&amp;quot; Tracey Dudley, who was staying at a nearby hotel, told CNN affiliate KATU.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;At first we thought, you know, it was just kids.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>But it was like screaming and screaming and screaming.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;Her and her siblings were digging a big hole in the sand,&amp;quot; Lincoln City police Sgt. Brian Eskridge said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;She was sitting inside, and the hole collapsed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>We believe she was under the sand around five minutes.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Franks, her family and friends were visiting the beach from Sandy, Oregon.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Police and firefighters dug her out.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>She was unconscious and not breathing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Emergency crews performed CPR on her and transported her to a hospital, where she was declared dead.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Mourners left flowers, candles and notes near where she died.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Before the emergency workers arrived, beachgoers had frantically tried to dig her out, but the sand kept collapsing back into the hole, Eskridge said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s a common problem when someone gets buried at the beach, Tom Gill of the United States Lifesaving Association said Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Once the sand starts collapsing, digging out becomes a technical rescue,&amp;quot; Gill said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s difficult because the sand keeps collapsing back into the hole, and the more people gathering around, the more difficult it is.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s not unusual for kids to build holes and sandcastles in the sand, but a lot of people don&amp;apost;t understand it can collapse,&amp;quot; Eskridge said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s difficult for people to understand how hard it is to get people out.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Dry sand weighs 100 pounds per square foot, and wet sand weighs 120 pounds per square foot, according to a 2004 study from the Mayo Clinic, entitled &amp;quot;Accidental Burials in Sand: A Potentially Fatal Summertime Hazard.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;Dry sand burial can totally engulf and compress a person... with no air pocket for breathing,&amp;quot; the report said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;Depending on the age and strength of the child, just 1 foot of sand may overwhelm respiratory and diaphragmatic force,&amp;quot;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>But according to the Mayo study, airway obstruction is an even bigger concern than sand stifling lung and diaphragm expansion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;Although accidental sand burial has its own set of clinical problems, clearing the airway is the main focus of treatment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Airway management at the scene of the incident may be crucial and lifesaving,&amp;quot; the Mayo report said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The hole containing Franks was big enough for a crouching adult to fit in, witnesses told KATU.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Gill said no national standards exist to restrict the depth of holes, though local jurisdictions often set their own rules.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>For example, in Virginia Beach, Virginia, the USLA&amp;apost;s home base, beach visitors aren&amp;apost;t supposed to dig holes deeper than knee-level, even for small children, Gill said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>There&amp;apost;s also no national database of fatal sand collapses, Gill said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>They don&amp;apost;t happen often, Gill said, &amp;quot;but often enough that we try to make people aware.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Articles in scholarly journals over the past decade, including the Mayo report, have called for public health and safety officials to be more aware of sand dangers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>In June 2007, the New England Journal of Medicine published a letter to the editor entitled &amp;quot;Sudden Death from Collapsing Sand Holes,&amp;quot; from Dr. Bradley Maron of Harvard Medical School.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Maron counted &amp;quot;52 documented fatal and nonfatal cases, occurring primarily in the past 10 years, in which persons were submerged after the collapse of a dry-sand hole excavated for recreational purposes.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>He said 31 of those 52 people died, and &amp;quot;the other 21 survived by virtue of timely rescue involving extrication from the sand; many of them required cardiopulmonary resuscitation, performed by a bystander.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Maron&amp;apost;s study concluded that collapses were inadvertently triggered by a variety of circumstances, including digging, tunneling, jumping, or falling into the hole.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Young children like Isabel Franks aren&amp;apost;t the only age group at risk.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>The two sand-related fatalities earlier this summer were both grown men.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>A 49-year-old Virginia man died on the beach at North Carolina&amp;apost;s Outer Banks on June 23, according to CNN affiliate WTVR.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>David Frasier of Fredericksburg, Virginia, had to be extracted from a hole approximately 5 to 6 feet deep.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>A bystander was unable to revive him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>And on July 21, in Half Moon Bay, California, Adam Jay Pye was buried alive while tunneling under the sand, CNN affiliate KRON reported.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Fire officials said Pye was standing in a 10-foot-deep pit when the sand rushed in around him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
