<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1938" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/06/05/justice/california-proposition-8/index.html " date_published="2012-06-05 13:24:13" category="us" author="Bill Mears, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Judges open door for Supreme Court showdown over same-sex marriage</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="8">The parties now have 90 days to appeal to the U.S. Supreme Court.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">A stay on same-sex marriage in California will remain in place.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">Supporters of Proposition 8 had asked for a rehearing of the case.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="4">A three-judge panel in February ruled the proposition illegal.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-21 23:02:06" annotation_time="44.13933">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">A stay on same-sex marriages in California remains in place until the issue is exhausted in the courts.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="4">In February, a three-judge panel of that court ruled the measure unconstitutional.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">Backers of the proposition had asked for a larger panel of judges to rehear the case.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="1">The parties now have 90 days to ask the U.S. Supreme Court to intervene.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The divisive issue of same-sex marriage in California may become another landmark case taken up by the U.S. Supreme Court after federal appeals court judges refused Tuesday to revisit an earlier ruling.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The 9th Circuit U.S. Court of Appeals in San Francisco denied a request to re-examine the issue, months after judges gave gay and lesbian couples constitutional blessing to wed in the state.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>A stay on same-sex marriages in California remains in place until the issue is exhausted in the courts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>In February, a three-judge panel of that court ruled the measure unconstitutional.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>In its split decision, the panel found that Proposition 8 &amp;quot;works a meaningful harm to gays and lesbians&amp;quot; by denying their right to civil marriage in violation of the 14th Amendment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Backers of the proposition had asked for a larger panel of judges to rehear the case.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>In a seven-page order Tuesday, the court refused.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The parties now have 90 days to ask the U.S. Supreme Court to intervene.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Supporters of Proposition 8 vowed to appeal to the nation&amp;apost;s highest court.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;Marriage is a universal good that has been honored by diverse cultures and faiths for the entire history of Western civilization,&amp;quot; said Brian Raum, senior counsel for the Alliance Defense Fund.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The organization is part of the legal defense team for ProtectMarriage.com, the banner organization for proponents of the measure.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;The ProtectMarriage.com legal team looks forward to standing before the U.S. Supreme Court on behalf of the people&amp;apost;s right to preserve the fundamental building block of civilization, especially since the dissents accompanying today&amp;apost;s decision strongly support our arguments.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The democratic process and the most important human institution -- marriage -- shouldn&amp;apost;t be overthrown based on the demands of Hollywood activists.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;Millions of Californians who gave their time and treasure to protect marriage deserve better,&amp;quot; said Brian Brown, president of the National Organization for Marriage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are calling on the U.S. Supreme Court to preserve our democratic rights and overturn this action of judicial arrogance.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Gay-rights advocates, meanwhile, hailed the court&amp;apost;s action.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;Today&amp;apost;s refusal by the 9th Circuit to grant further review is a testament to the meticulous and well-reasoned opinion originally issued by the court,&amp;quot; said Kate Kendell, executive director of the National Center for Lesbian Rights.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;While the supporters of Proposition 8 will now seek review by the U.S. Supreme Court, there is no doubt that they are on the wrong side of history.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Excluding same-sex couples from the right to marry runs counter to our highest ideals of equality and fairness.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;Today&amp;apost;s decision by the Ninth Circuit ... brings committed same-sex couples in California one step closer to being able to marry,&amp;quot; said Evan Wolfson, president of the group Freedom to Marry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s now been three and a half years since the freedom to marry was stripped from loving and committed same-sex couples.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>It is long past time for this &amp;apost;gay exception&amp;apost; to marriage in California to come to an end.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The three-judge panel&amp;apost;s ruling in February upheld a 2010 decision by a U.S. district judge in San Francisco.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>However, in the appeals court decision, Judges Stephen Reinhardt and Michael Daly Hawkins said that they were speaking only about Proposition 8 and that states would have to decide the marriage issue themselves.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>California&amp;apost;s Supreme Court ruled that same-sex marriages were legal in 2008, before Proposition 8 went before voters.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>After the measure passed with 52% of the vote that year, its passage put an end to the practice.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Last month, a federal appeals court in Massachusetts struck down a key part of the Defense of Marriage Act -- the law banning federal recognition of same-sex marriage -- as unconstitutional.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The issue before the 1st U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals was whether the federal government could deny tax, health and pension benefits to same-sex couples in states where they can legally marry.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The Massachusetts case could also soon be appealed to the U.S. Supreme Court.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Currently, same-sex marriage is legal in six states: Massachusetts, Connecticut, Iowa, Vermont, New Hampshire and New York, along with the District of Columbia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Washington and Maryland voted earlier this year to allow same-sex marriages, but the laws have not yet taken effect.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Another five states -- Delaware, Hawaii, Illinois, New Jersey and Rhode Island -- allow civil unions, providing state-level spousal rights to same-sex couples.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Last month, President Barack Obama, who previously opposed same-sex marriage, said that he now supports it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;When I think about those soldiers or airmen or Marines or sailors who are out there fighting on my behalf and yet feel constrained, even now that &amp;apost;don&amp;apost;t ask, don&amp;apost;t tell&amp;apost; is gone, because they are not able to commit themselves in a marriage, at a certain point I&amp;apost;ve just concluded that for me personally, it is important for me to go ahead and affirm that I think same-sex couples should be able to get married,&amp;quot; the president told ABC.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The National Association for the Advancement of Colored People also announced last month that it supports same-sex marriage.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>The California cases are Perry v. Brown and Coleman v. Brown.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
