<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1869" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/01/11/us/alex-rodriguez-suspended/index.html" date_published="2014-01-11 18:50:40" category="us" author="Ray Sanchez, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Alex Rodriguez suspended for entire 2014 season</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="11">NEW: The New York Yankees say they &amp;quot;respect&amp;quot; the decision .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Alex Rodriguez suspended for 2014 regular season and postseason.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">Decision will cost slugger $25 million .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="17">Rodriguez plans to appeal.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-14 13:30:17" annotation_time="125.70734">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2">New York An arbitrator Saturday upheld most of New York Yankees slugger Alex Rodriguez&amp;apost;s 211-game doping suspension, keeping him out of the 162-game 2014 regular season and the postseason.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="3">The ruling by Major League Baseball arbitrator Fredric Horowitz will not only cost Rodriguez $25 million in salary, it also further clouds the groundbreaking career of a player who will turn 40 during the 2015 season.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="1">The Yankees said in a statement that they &amp;quot;respect Major League Baseball&amp;apost;s Joint Drug Prevention and Treatment Program, the arbitration process, as well as the decision released today by the arbitration panel.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="4">Rodriguez, who has claimed he was the target of a MLB &amp;quot;witch hunt,&amp;quot; probably will appeal Horowitz&amp;apost;s decision in the courts or to seek to delay the suspension.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>New York An arbitrator Saturday upheld most of New York Yankees slugger Alex Rodriguez&amp;apost;s 211-game doping suspension, keeping him out of the 162-game 2014 regular season and the postseason.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The ruling by Major League Baseball arbitrator Fredric Horowitz will not only cost Rodriguez $25 million in salary, it also further clouds the groundbreaking career of a player who will turn 40 during the 2015 season.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The 162-game suspension -- which is the most severe punishment in baseball history for doping -- highlights baseball Commissioner Bud Selig&amp;apost;s recent high-profile crackdown on performance-enhancing drugs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Rodriguez, one of the best players of his generation who was once considered an automatic Hall of Fame candidate, was defiant in a statement released Saturday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>He will likely appeal in federal court.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;The number of games sadly comes as no surprise, as the deck has been stacked against me from day one,&amp;quot; said Rodriguez, who has struggled with hip injuries in recent years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The former Seattle Mariner, Texas Ranger and now New York Yankee player then took a swipe at Selig, whom he has claimed in the past had an unjustified vendetta against him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is one man&amp;apost;s decision that was not put before a fair and impartial jury,&amp;quot; Rodriguez said, &amp;quot;does not involve me having failed a single drug test, is at odds with the facts and is inconsistent with the terms of the Joint Drug Agreement and the Basic Agreement, and relies on testimony and documents that would never have been allowed in any court in the United States because they are false and wholly unreliable.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>When the suspension ends in 2015, Rodriguez will be owed $61 million in a contract that runs through 2017.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Major League Baseball did not release details of the arbitrator&amp;apost;s decision, which the players union said it &amp;quot;strongly disagrees&amp;quot; with.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The Yankees said in a statement that they &amp;quot;respect Major League Baseball&amp;apost;s Joint Drug Prevention and Treatment Program, the arbitration process, as well as the decision released today by the arbitration panel.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Saturday&amp;apost;s ruling stemmed from Rodriguez&amp;apost;s appeal of a his suspension by MLB, which accused him of taking performance-enhancing drugs and having ties to the now-shuttered Biogenesis clinic in South Florida.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Biogenesis was a former anti-aging clinic that MLB said supplied steroids to at least a dozen baseball players.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Rodriguez, one of 14 players suspended in the Biogenesis scandal, was the only one who appealed his suspension.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Though he was suspended in August, Rodriguez played out the 2013 season because of the appeal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Rodriguez, 38, is fifth on MLB&amp;apost;s list of all-time home run leaders, just six behind Willie Mays.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Rodriguez, who has claimed he was the target of a MLB &amp;quot;witch hunt,&amp;quot; probably will appeal Horowitz&amp;apost;s decision in the courts or to seek to delay the suspension.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;No player should have to go through what I have been dealing with, and I am exhausting all options to ensure not only that I get justice, but that players&amp;apost; contracts and rights are protected through the next round of bargaining, and that the MLB investigation and arbitration process cannot be used against others in the future the way it is currently being used to unjustly punish me,&amp;quot; Rodriguez said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
