<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1968" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/08/27/us/ferguson-police-protests/index.html" date_published="2014-08-27 23:17:16" category="us" author="Catherine E. Shoichet, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Police scale back in Ferguson as tensions ease</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Authorities are scaling back police presence in Ferguson, Missouri.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="11">Capt. Ron Johnson says there&amp;apost;s been a notable change: Police are listening.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">Protests followed deadly police shooting of unarmed teen this month.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="25">St. Louis County police chief defends the use of tear gas, military equipment.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-28 14:27:58" annotation_time="39.79">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Police are scaling back their presence in Ferguson, Missouri.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">Protests erupted in Ferguson this month after a police officer shot and killed 18-year-old Michael Brown, who was unarmed.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="2">There&amp;apost;s been a notable change on the ground, Johnson said: Law enforcement is listening as protests continue.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="4">St. Louis County Police Chief Jon Belmar said he didn&amp;apost;t regret his agency&amp;apost;s decisions to fire tear gas at protesters.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Police are scaling back their presence in Ferguson, Missouri.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But that doesn&amp;apost;t mean their jobs are done.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;There&amp;apost;s a lot of work to do,&amp;quot; said Missouri State Highway Patrol Capt. Ron Johnson, who was chosen by the state&amp;apost;s governor to head up security as tensions between police and protesters boiled over in the St. Louis suburb.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Protests erupted in Ferguson this month after a police officer shot and killed 18-year-old Michael Brown, who was unarmed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Police have said Brown was trying to grab the officer&amp;apost;s gun.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Witnesses say the teen was holding his hands in the air when he was fatally shot.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>As a grand jury and federal civil rights investigators carry out investigations into the controversial case, tensions have been running high in the town of 21,000, where there&amp;apost;s a history of distrust between the predominately black community and the largely white police force.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Brown was African-American.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Darren Wilson, the Ferguson police officer who shot him, is white.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Now that the situation has cooled, St. Louis city police officers are heading back to their normal duties, the Missouri National Guard is no longer part of the operation, and some state troopers have pulled out, Johnson said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>There&amp;apost;s been a notable change on the ground, Johnson said: Law enforcement is listening as protests continue.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>And officers must keep trying to build better relationships with the community going forward, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;When this first started ... I wondered if there would be a day that law enforcement and the community would see peace together,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;And I&amp;apost;ve seen that.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>I&amp;apost;ve seen hands being held.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>I&amp;apost;ve seen adults laughing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>I&amp;apost;ve seen kids taking pictures.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>I&amp;apost;ve seen policemen listening.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>I&amp;apost;ve seen arms come unfolded.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>As he announced that the command center that authorities had been using to coordinate responses to the protests was shutting down, Johnson steered clear of giving details about the police response over the past two weeks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>He said he couldn&amp;apost;t provide the total number of arrests made during the protests or reveal operational plans going forward.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Asked how authorities handled allegations of police misconduct, Johnson said, &amp;quot;any officer that we were notified about or we identified that&amp;apost;s conduct was inappropriate, the proper actions were taken.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Police tactics to calm the crowds drew sharp criticism, including a rebuke from Attorney General Eric Holder.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;At a time when we must seek to rebuild trust between law enforcement and the local community, I am deeply concerned that the deployment of military equipment and vehicles sends a conflicting message,&amp;quot; Holder said as the protests unfolded.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>St. Louis County Police Chief Jon Belmar said he didn&amp;apost;t regret his agency&amp;apost;s decisions to fire tear gas at protesters.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>That approach, he said, was much better than using nightsticks or dogs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Even though President Barack Obama has called for a review of military equipment sales to police in light of the clashes between police and protesters in Ferguson, Belmar said that such equipment is often necessary.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;I never envisioned a day that we would ever see that kind of equipment used against protesters,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;But I also never imagined a day in 28 years when we would see that kind of criminal activity spin out of peaceful demonstrations.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
