<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1865" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/11/05/us/iyw-simple-ways-to-honor-veterans/index.html" date_published="2013-11-05 17:52:26" category="us" author="Betsy Anderson, CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>9 simple ways you can help veterans</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">Simple things can make a difference for the more than 23 million American veterans.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="46, 45">Donate frequent flier miles, give a veteran a ride, write a letter or send a care package .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">Let your actions speak to veterans, thanking them for their service to their country.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard>
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="3">Most Americans will never serve in the military or fight for their country.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">Here are nine simple things you can do to make a difference on Memorial Day-- or any day -- for the more than 23 million American veterans:.</sentence>
      <sentence id="45" ids_highlights="2">It also has a letter writing campaign encouraging everyone to write handwritten letters of gratitude to veterans.</sentence>
      <sentence id="46" ids_highlights="2">Over the next two years, Operation Gratitude hopes to provide a care package to every Vietnam veteran ahead of the 40th anniversary of the end of the Vietnam War.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Most Americans will never serve in the military or fight for their country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Yet there are countless ways that everyone can help these veterans, who often return home from war to face their most difficult battles.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Those severely injured may need to learn how to live with the loss of a limb or limited mobility.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>For others, brain injuries or post-traumatic stress disorder can make the return to civilian life a struggle.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Here are nine simple things you can do to make a difference on Memorial Day-- or any day -- for the more than 23 million American veterans:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>1.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Give a veteran a ride.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Medical care may be needed for some veterans for the rest of their lives.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Disabled American Veterans provides free transportation to men and women who can&amp;apost;t travel to Veterans Affairs medical facilities on their own.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>You can volunteer to drive a van for those who need a lift.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>2.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Donate frequent flier miles.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The Fisher House Foundation has a network of homes on the grounds of military and VA hospitals around the country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>These homes help family members be close during the hospitalization of a loved one for a combat injury, illness or disease.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Fisher House operates the Hero Miles Program, using donated frequent flier miles to bring family members to the bedside of injured service members.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>You can also volunteer or donate household items.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>3.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Buy veteran-friendly holiday cards.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>More than a third of all Iraq and Afghanistan veterans have or will experience post-traumatic stress disorder.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>And veterans of past wars are still dealing with the ghosts of their time in the service.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Coping with PTSD can put stress on not just veterans but also their families and friends.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Your holiday card purchase this year can help veterans dealing with PTSD and other similar issues.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Puppies Behind Bars is a program in which prisoners train companion dogs for veterans with PTSD, and these canines are featured in holiday cards sold to support the program.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>(If you know a veteran dealing with PTSD, the VA offers the PTSD Coach Online to help veterans learn to manage symptoms, come up with ways to cope and find professional help.).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>4.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Help build a home for severely injured vets.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Severely injured veterans often come home needing a place to live that better accommodates their physical disabilities.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Homes for our Troops builds specially modified homes for veterans that help them live independently.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>These homes are provided by Homes for Our Troops at no cost to the veterans.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The group is able to do so through fund-raisers and donations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>5.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Keep veterans off the streets.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>In times of war, exhausted combat units were removed from the battlefield to &amp;quot;stand down&amp;quot; in a place of relative security to rest.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The Department of Veterans Affairs&amp;apost; Stand Down program is designed to help homeless veterans &amp;quot;combat&amp;quot; life on the streets.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Stand Downs are usually one- to three-day events to provide food, shelter, clothing and health screenings to homeless and unemployed veterans.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>To find a Stand Down program in your community, contact your local VA hospital in the VA Medical Center Directory.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>A phone call can also make difference in the life of a veteran who is homeless or at risk of becoming homeless.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Call 877-4AID-VET, or 877-424-3838, to be connected 24 hours a day, seven days a week with help at the VA.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>The VA has set a goal of eliminating homelessness among veterans by 2015.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>6.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Send a care package or a letter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Operation Gratitude is about to send its 1 millionth individually addressed care package to the military community.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>The packages are sent to current military members as well as veterans, wounded warriors and their caregivers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>As more American troops return to civilian life, the Operation Gratitude veterans program has been growing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>It also has a letter writing campaign encouraging everyone to write handwritten letters of gratitude to veterans.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Over the next two years, Operation Gratitude hopes to provide a care package to every Vietnam veteran ahead of the 40th anniversary of the end of the Vietnam War.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>7.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Help them take flight.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>According to the Department of Veterans Affairs, an estimated 640 World War II veterans die every day.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>The Honor Flight Network helps veterans of the &amp;quot;greatest generation&amp;quot; make a free pilgrimage to the World War II Memorial on the National Mall in Washington.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>You can volunteer to escort these men and women on the flight to see this memorial.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Honor Flight also plans to help Korean and Vietnam War veterans visit memorials to those wars in Washington as well.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>8.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>Share their stories.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>So many veterans&amp;apost; stories have been left untold, but the Library of Congress is collecting the tales of veterans of every war with the Veterans History Project.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>If you are related to a veteran or know one who has a story to tell, the Library of Congress wants to hear it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>Help veterans share their stories before it&amp;apost;s too late.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>For directions on how to get involved, check out the Veterans History Project.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="59">
          <content>9.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="60">
          <content>Say thank you.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="61">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s simple, but it can make an impact.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="62">
          <content>And so many veterans have never heard the words &amp;quot;thank you.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="63">
          <content>If you know a veteran or see someone in a military uniform, say something.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="64">
          <content>It may make his or her day and yours.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
