<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="1978" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/09/27/us/new-jersey-same-sex-marriage/index.html" date_published="2013-09-27 19:35:17" category="us" author="Jason Hanna. Laura Ly and Andy Rose, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Same-sex marriages must be allowed in New Jersey, judge rules</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="10, 9">NEW: &amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s an amazingly strong decision,&amp;quot; says leader of a group that sued.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Judge: New Jersey must allow same-sex marriages starting October 21.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">Ruling says civil unions insufficient because they hinder federal benefits.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="15">New Jersey has allowed same-sex civil unions since 2007.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-09 18:38:31" annotation_time="215.03731" mapping_time_divergence="53.759327">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">The judge ordered that same-sex marriages be allowed starting October 21.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;If the trend of federal agencies deeming civil union partners ineligible for benefits continues, plaintiffs will suffer even more, while their opposite-sex New Jersey counterparts continue to receive federal marital benefits for no reason other than the label placed upon their relationship by the state,&amp;quot; Jacobson wrote.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="1">The group&amp;apost;s executive director, Troy Stevenson, said the ruling is &amp;quot;amazing news.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s an amazingly strong decision.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="4">New Jersey has recognized civil unions between same-sex couples since 2007, after the New Jersey Supreme Court ruled that the state must allow same-sex couples all the rights and benefits of marriage.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Same-sex couples must be permitted to marry in New Jersey, a state judge ruled Friday, arguing that the parallel label &amp;quot;civil unions,&amp;quot; which the state already allows gay couples, is illegally preventing them from getting federal benefits.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The judge ordered that same-sex marriages be allowed starting October 21.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>But the date could be delayed on appeal, and the office of Gov. Chris Christie indicated the case would be appealed to the New Jersey Supreme Court.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The ruling cites the U.S. Supreme Court&amp;apost;s June rejection of part of the federal Defense of Marriage Act, a move that ensured same-sex spouses legally married in a state may receive federal benefits.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>After the DOMA ruling, some federal agencies are extending benefits to legally married same-sex couples, but denying them to same-sex couples in &amp;quot;civil unions,&amp;quot; Judge Mary Jacobson of Mercer County Superior Court wrote in her ruling Friday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;If the trend of federal agencies deeming civil union partners ineligible for benefits continues, plaintiffs will suffer even more, while their opposite-sex New Jersey counterparts continue to receive federal marital benefits for no reason other than the label placed upon their relationship by the state,&amp;quot; Jacobson wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;This unequal treatment requires that New Jersey extend civil marriage to same-sex couples to satisfy the equal protection guarantees of the New Jersey Constitution,&amp;quot; she continued.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Jacobson ruled on a lawsuit that six same-sex couples and their children, as well as gay-rights group Garden State Equality, filed against the state.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The group&amp;apost;s executive director, Troy Stevenson, said the ruling is &amp;quot;amazing news.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s an amazingly strong decision.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>We&amp;apost;re very excited,&amp;quot; Stevenson said Friday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;ve been saying for months that we were going to win marriage equality for New Jersey, and this was a total victory.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>An attorney who represented the plaintiffs also hailed the &amp;quot;thrilling&amp;quot; ruling.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;We argued that limiting lesbians and gay men to civil union is unfair and unconstitutional, and now the court has agreed,&amp;quot; said Hayley Gorenberg, deputy legal director of Lambda Legal, a gay rights organization.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>New Jersey has recognized civil unions between same-sex couples since 2007, after the New Jersey Supreme Court ruled that the state must allow same-sex couples all the rights and benefits of marriage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>As far as state rights and benefits went, civil unions and marriages differed only in label, Jacobson noted.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Friday&amp;apost;s ruling came more than a year after Christie vetoed a bill that would have legalized same-sex marriage in the state.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>On Friday afternoon, Christie&amp;apost;s office said it had wanted the &amp;quot;issue of marriage equality&amp;quot; to be on the ballot this November, but said the Legislature scuttled the effort.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>It also indicated that Jacobson&amp;apost;s ruling would be appealed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;Since the Legislature refused to allow the people to decide expeditiously, we will let the Supreme Court make this constitutional determination,&amp;quot; read a Friday statement from Christie&amp;apost;s office, which later clarified that it meant the state&amp;apost;s high court.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The New Jersey attorney general&amp;apost;s office, which was one of the suit&amp;apost;s defendants, deferred CNN&amp;apost;s questions about Friday&amp;apost;s ruling to the governor&amp;apost;s office.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>New Jersey is one of four states that offer civil unions, but not marriage, to same-sex couples.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The others are Colorado, Hawaii and Illinois.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Same-sex marriage is legal in 13 U.S states and the District of Columbia: California, Connecticut, Delaware, Iowa, Maine, Maryland, Massachusetts, Minnesota, New Hampshire, New York, Rhode Island, Vermont and Washington.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Same-sex marriage is banned in every state not mentioned above, except for New Mexico, which has no laws banning or allowing it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
