<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2009" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/03/20/us/westboro-church-founder-dead/index.html" date_published="2014-03-20 16:35:38" category="us" author="Daniel Burke, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Westboro church founder Fred Phelps dies</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Church spokesman says Phelps died late Wednesday of natural causes .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">Phelps founded Westboro Baptist Church in Topeka, Kansas.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">The church is known for its virulently anti-gay protests, including at military funerals.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-08 23:12:28" annotation_time="24.643667">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="3">Fred Phelps -- the founding pastor of a Kansas church known for its virulently anti-gay protests at public events, including military funerals -- has died, the church said Thursday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">The 84-year-old died of natural causes at 11:15 p.m. Wednesday, according to church spokesman Steve Drain.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">Phelps founded Westboro Baptist Church of Topeka, Kansas, in 1955 and molded it in his fire-and-brimstone image.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Fred Phelps -- the founding pastor of a Kansas church known for its virulently anti-gay protests at public events, including military funerals -- has died, the church said Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The 84-year-old died of natural causes at 11:15 p.m. Wednesday, according to church spokesman Steve Drain.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Phelps founded Westboro Baptist Church of Topeka, Kansas, in 1955 and molded it in his fire-and-brimstone image.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Many members of the small congregation are related to Phelps through blood or marriage.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>In a statement Thursday, the church chided the &amp;quot;world-wide media&amp;quot; for &amp;quot;gleefully anticipating the death.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;God forbid, if every little soul at the Westboro Baptist Church were to die at this instant, or to turn from serving the true and living God, it would not change one thing about the judgments of God that await this deeply corrupted nation and world.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>According to Westboro, the church has picketed more than 53,000 events, ranging from Lady Gaga concerts to funerals for slain U.S. soldiers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Typically, a dozen or so church members -- including small children -- will brandish signs that say &amp;quot;God Hates Fags&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Thank God for Dead Soldiers.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Phelps was often called &amp;quot;the most hated man in America,&amp;quot; a label he seemed to relish.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;If I had nobody mad at me,&amp;quot; he told the Wichita Eagle in 2006, &amp;quot;what right would I have to claim that I was preaching the Gospel?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Under Phelps&amp;apost; leadership, Westboro members have preached that every calamity, from natural disasters to the Sandy Hook Elementary School shooting in Newtown, Connecticut, is God&amp;apost;s punishment for the country&amp;apost;s acceptance of homosexuality.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Phelps had advocated for gays and lesbians to be put to death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;Fred Phelps will not be missed by the LGBT community, people with HIV/AIDS and the millions of decent people across the world who found what he and his followers do deeply hurtful and offensive,&amp;quot; the National Gay and Lesbian Task Force said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Phelps began his anti-gay protests in Wichita in 1991 after complaining that the city refused to stop gay activities in a public park.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>He rose to national notoriety in 1998, when Westboro members picketed at the funeral of Matthew Shepard, a Wyoming man who was tortured and murdered because he was gay.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Phelps and his church carried signs that said Shepard was rotting in hell.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The Southern Poverty Law Center calls Westboro Baptist Church &amp;quot;arguably the most obnoxious and rabid hate group in America.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>In 2011, the Supreme Court upheld Westboro&amp;apost;s right to picket military funerals on free speech grounds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Congress and several states, though, have passed laws aimed at keeping church members at a distance from funerals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>In 2013, more than 367,000 petitioners called on the White House to legally recognize Westboro Baptist Church as a hate group.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The White House called Westboro&amp;apost;s protests &amp;quot;reprehensible&amp;quot; but said that &amp;quot;as a matter of practice, the federal government doesn&amp;apost;t maintain a list of hate groups.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Born in Meridian, Mississippi, on November 29, 1929, Phelps had his sights set on West Point before he attended a Methodist revival.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>He said the sermon inspired him to enter the ministry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;I felt the call, as they say, and it was powerful,&amp;quot; Phelps told the Topeka Capital-Journal in 1994.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;The God of glory appeared.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Later, Phelps was ordained by a Southern Baptist church in Utah.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>He bounced around several Christian colleges as his preaching and his theology took a hard right turn.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>A Time magazine article from 1951 describes Phelps as a &amp;quot;craggy-faced engineering student&amp;quot; who harangued fellow students about the dangers of promiscuity and profanity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Tim Miller, a professor of religious history at the University of Kansas who has studied Westboro Baptist Church, said Phelps liked to consider himself a &amp;quot;primitive Baptist preacher who held to the old ways.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Despite its &amp;quot;Baptist&amp;quot; name, Westboro is not affiliated with any larger church denomination.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Most Christians criticize the congregation&amp;apost;s harsh anti-gay rhetoric and penchant for pursuing the limelight at inappropriate moments.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Phelps married his wife, Marge, who survives him, in 1952.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The couple moved to Topeka on May 14, 1954, the day the Supreme Court handed down its landmark decision Brown v. Board of Education, which desegregated public schools.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Phelps interpreted that as a sign and soon began a law career that centered on civil rights, winning awards for his work and praise from local leaders.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;Most blacks -- that&amp;apost;s who they went to,&amp;quot; the Rev. Ben Scott, president of the NAACP&amp;apost;s Topeka branch, told CNN in 2010.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;I don&amp;apost;t know if he was cheaper or if he had that stick-to-it-ness, but Fred didn&amp;apost;t lose many back then.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Phelps was disbarred from practicing law in state courts, however, after being accused of badgering a witness and making false claims in court affidavits.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>The Kansas Supreme Court said that Phelps &amp;quot;has little regard for the ethics of his profession.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Phelps surrendered his license to practice law in federal courts in 1989, according to the Topeka Capital-Journal, after nine U.S. District Court judges filed disciplinary complaints against him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Most of the members of Phelps&amp;apost; Westboro Baptist Church are members of his large family.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Phelps has 13 children; 11 are attorneys.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>One son, Nathan, is estranged from his father and from organized religion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>He is an atheist.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Nathan Phelps posted a Facebook message March 15 saying that his father had been excommunicated from the church.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Later, though, Nathan Phelps said it was &amp;quot;unclear&amp;quot; whether his father had been expelled from Westboro.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>A church statement issued on March 16 said that &amp;quot;membership issues are private&amp;quot; and that eight unnamed elders lead the congregation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>On Thursday, the church added, &amp;quot;Listen carefully; there are no power struggles in the Westboro Baptist Church, and there is no human intercessor -- we serve no man, and no hierarchy, only the Lord Jesus Christ.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>For years, Phelps joked about the possibility that his own funeral would draw protests.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>During a sermon in 2006, he said a CNN reporter once asked how he would feel if that occurred.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;d love it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>I&amp;apost;d invite them,&amp;quot; Phelps told the reporter, according to the Wichita Eagle.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>&amp;quot;I said: &amp;apost;I&amp;apost;ll put in my will to pay your way.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>But not first class.&amp;apost; &amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>But Shirley Phelps-Roper, Phelps&amp;apost; daughter, said Westboro will not hold a funeral for its patriarch.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>&amp;quot;We do not worship the dead,&amp;quot; Phelps-Roper told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>