<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2556" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/03/08/world/meast/bin-laden-relative-captured/index.html" date_published="2013-03-08 05:57:10" category="world" author="Michael Pearson and Susan Candiotti, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Osama bin Laden&amp;apost;s son-in-law denies terror charges</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="23">NEW: Sulaiman Abu Ghaith gave investigators a 22-page statement, prosecutors say.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="24">NEW: They say evidence in the case has been sealed.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">Abu Ghaith is accused of conspiracy to kill U.S. nationals.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="10">After 9/11 attacks, he warned that &amp;quot;the storms shall not stop, especially, the airplane storms&amp;quot; .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-26 13:19:03" annotation_time="36.268665">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="3">Prosecutors say Sulaiman Abu Ghaith conspired to kill Americans as part of bin Laden&amp;apost;s al Qaeda terror network, according to a federal indictment unveiled Thursday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="4">He later warned that &amp;quot;the storms shall not stop, especially, the airplane storms,&amp;quot; and warned Muslims and foes of the United States not to board aircraft or live in high-rise buildings, according to the indictment.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="1">According to prosecutors, Abu Ghaith gave investigators a 22-page statement after his arrest, but they didn&amp;apost;t reveal any of what the terror suspect allegedly said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="2">Evidence in the case has been sealed, and prosecutors said they were reviewing classified evidence to see if it would be used in Abu Ghaith&amp;apost;s trial.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>New York Osama bin Laden&amp;apost;s son-in-law, who once sat next to the terror leader and bellicosely threatened the United States, softly answered a judge&amp;apost;s questions Friday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Prosecutors say Sulaiman Abu Ghaith conspired to kill Americans as part of bin Laden&amp;apost;s al Qaeda terror network, according to a federal indictment unveiled Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Through his attorney, the Kuwaiti pleaded not guilty to the charges in a federal courtroom in New York on Friday, nearly a week after his arrest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>A member of bin Laden&amp;apost;s inner circle, Abu Ghaith had spent most of his time since the September 11 terrorist attacks in Iran, according to the federal indictment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Before joining al Qaeda in 2001, he taught high school and preached in his native Kuwait before he was banned from his mosque for using his sermons to attack the government, according to the U.S. government.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>He also fought in Afghanistan and Bosnia-Herzegovina.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>He spent the months before the September 11 attacks recruiting candidates for training in his father-in-law&amp;apost;s terror training camps in Afghanistan, according to the indictment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>After the attacks that destroyed the twin World Trade Center towers in New York and heavily damaged the Pentagon in Washington, Abu Ghaith served as al Qaeda&amp;apost;s official spokesman.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>In a video made the day after the 9/11 attacks, Abu Ghaith sat next to bin Laden and al Qaeda No. 2 Ayman al-Zawahiri -- an AK-47 behind him resting on a rock wall -- urging Muslims to fight &amp;quot;the Jews, the Christians and America.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>He later warned that &amp;quot;the storms shall not stop, especially, the airplane storms,&amp;quot; and warned Muslims and foes of the United States not to board aircraft or live in high-rise buildings, according to the indictment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>U.S. authorities have charged that Abu Ghaith supported a major attack on America and urged people at a Kandahar, Afghanistan, guest house to swear an oath of allegiance to bin Laden.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>While Attorney General Eric Holder said the arrest sends a message to terror suspects that &amp;quot;there is no corner of the world where you can escape from justice,&amp;quot; some analysts said Abu Ghaith is small potatoes in the world of international terrorism.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is overblown,&amp;quot; CNN National Security Analyst Peter Bergen said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;Though he was Osama bin Laden&amp;apost;s son-in-law, Abu Ghaith is far from a big fish in al Qaeda.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>U.S. officials arrested him on February 28 in Jordan, according to a spokesman for U.S. Rep. Peter King, chairman of the House Homeland Security Committee.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Prosecutors have not said where he was arrested.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>According to a report in the Turkish newspaper Hurriyet, Turkish officials detained Abu Ghaith on a tip from the CIA after he had slipped into the country from Iran.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>After deciding he had not committed a crime in Turkey, Turkish officials decided to send him to Kuwait via Jordan.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>While Abu Ghaith was in Jordan, U.S. officials captured him, the newspaper said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The U.S. government has not confirmed the report.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Abu Ghaith -- wearing dark prison-issued clothing, his once dark beard sprinkled with gray -- said little during Friday&amp;apost;s hearing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>He spoke softly through an interpreter, answering &amp;quot;yes&amp;quot; to several questions from the judge.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>According to prosecutors, Abu Ghaith gave investigators a 22-page statement after his arrest, but they didn&amp;apost;t reveal any of what the terror suspect allegedly said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Evidence in the case has been sealed, and prosecutors said they were reviewing classified evidence to see if it would be used in Abu Ghaith&amp;apost;s trial.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>No trial date has yet been set.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The decision to handle Abu Ghaith&amp;apost;s case in civilian court has irked some Republicans, who say the Obama administration is setting a bad precedent and missing an opportunity to get valuable intelligence from someone who had been so close to bin Laden, who died in a 2011 U.S. Navy SEAL raid in Pakistan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;We should treat enemy combatants like the enemy,&amp;quot; said Rep. Mike Rogers, chairman of the House Intelligence Committee.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;The U.S. court system is not the appropriate venue.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
