<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2179" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/08/26/world/meast/mideast-crisis-truce-key-points/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-08-27 00:01:18" category="world" author="Chelsea J. Carter, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>End to fighting in Gaza? What you need to know</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="14">There is little sign that either side in the conflict got what it wanted.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8">Israel agrees to ease the blockade, but not lift it, an official says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">Both sides agree to return to Cairo for further, indirect talks.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="16">The truce looks a lot like the one both sides agreed to in 2012 .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-27 17:31:24" annotation_time="9.017">
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">As part of the negotiated truce, Israel has agreed to &amp;quot;ease&amp;quot; the blockade, opening border crossings to allow humanitarian aid and construction materials into Gaza, a senior Egyptian government official with knowledge of the agreement told CNN.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">Both sides agree to return to Cairo for further, indirect talks -- as Israel and Hamas refuse to meet face to face.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="1">While Hamas spokesman Fawhi Barhoum declared before a cheering crowd in Gaza that the truce was &amp;quot;a day of victories for our people,&amp;quot; there is little sign that either side got what it wanted.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="4">In fact, the truce -- by all accounts -- looks a lot like one agreed to in 2012 to end fighting between Israel and Hamas militants.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Fifty days of fighting.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Thousands of rocket attacks and airstrikes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>And a number of failed cease-fire agreements.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>That all appeared to come to an end on Tuesday, when Israel and Hamas militants agreed to an open-ended truce -- and talks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Here&amp;apost;s what you need to know about the Egyptian-negotiated agreement that appears to have halted the fighting between Israelis and Hamas militants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Who gets what?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>During the fighting, both sides have repeatedly made the same demands: Israel called for the demilitarization of Gaza, and Hamas called for an end to the Israeli and Egyptian blockade of Gaza -- by land, sea and air -- that began in 2007.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>As part of the negotiated truce, Israel has agreed to &amp;quot;ease&amp;quot; the blockade, opening border crossings to allow humanitarian aid and construction materials into Gaza, a senior Egyptian government official with knowledge of the agreement told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>As part of easing the blockade, Israel will also extend the fishing limit off the coast of Gaza to six miles, the official said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Both sides agree to return to Cairo for further, indirect talks -- as Israel and Hamas refuse to meet face to face.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>If the ceasefire holds, the two sides have agreed to begin talks four weeks from now on a broader range of issues, including the Israeli release of Palestinians -- primarily Hamas members -- arrested during the conflict and the construction of a seaport in Gaza, according to published reports in state-run media.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The talks will also address Israel&amp;apost;s demand for the demilitarization of Gaza.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Winner?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>While Hamas spokesman Fawhi Barhoum declared before a cheering crowd in Gaza that the truce was &amp;quot;a day of victories for our people,&amp;quot; there is little sign that either side got what it wanted.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The agreement between Israel and the Palestinians broke no new ground.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>In fact, the truce -- by all accounts -- looks a lot like one agreed to in 2012 to end fighting between Israel and Hamas militants.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>In that agreement, Israel agreed to ease restrictions to allow for humanitarian aid and construction materials with an agreement to engage in talks aimed at easing economic hardships in Gaza.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s very similar.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>There is some moderate easing of the blockade of Gaza as Hamas and most Palestinians really wanted.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>But the big easing has been pushed off to the future,&amp;quot; said Peter Beinart, a contributing editor for the National Journal and The Atlantic.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;And demilitarization of Gaza, which is what Israel said it really wanted, has also been kicked down the road into the future.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>According to Beinart, who has long covered the Israeli-Palestinian conflict: &amp;quot;After all this terrible, terrible bloodshed and trauma on both sides, it looks like we are back to where we were at the beginning.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>What was the cost?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The cost can be measured in lives lost, but also in the economic and political fallout.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>More than 2,100 Palestinians were killed in the conflict.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The United Nations estimates that more than 70% were civilians.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Sixty-seven Israelis -- 64 of them soldiers -- have been killed, the United Nations reports.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>A foreign worker in Israel was killed as well.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The fighting displaced more than 500,000 Palestinians, according to the United Nations, and left thousands of homes damaged.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s not exactly clear how much money the fighting cost both sides, but observers have put the number in the billions of dollars.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Given the toll the conflict has taken, there is also likely to be some kind of political fallout.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The popularity of Hamas has been on the decline since it took control of the Palestinian Parliament in 2006.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Given the length and toll of this conflict, there is a question of whether Palestinians will hold Hamas accountable for it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>At the same time, Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu&amp;apost;s popularity took a severe hit -- going from a high of 82% to 38%, according to The Times of Israel, which cited a poll this week by Israel&amp;apost;s Channel 2.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>What&amp;apost;s next?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>That depends on who&amp;apost;s doing the talking.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>If the ceasefire holds, and the negotiators go back to Cairo, the fact that Israel and Hamas do not talk to one another may prove problematic in trying to bring Israelis together with Palestinian factions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>In any talks, Palestinians are likely to include a demand that Egypt lift its blockade of Gaza dating back to 2007.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Egypt, just like Israel, tightened restrictions on Gaza&amp;apost;s borders after Hamas won political control of Gaza from the Palestinian Authority.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
