<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2902" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/09/15/world/meast/iraq-syria-angelina-jolie/index.html?iref=allsearch" date_published="2012-09-15 14:41:59" category="world" author="Mohammed Tawfeeq, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>U.N. envoy Angelina Jolie visits Syria refugees in Iraq</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Actress Angelina Jolie visits a Syrian refugee camp in Baghdad.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">She discusses Syrian refugees with the Iraqi foreign minster .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="8">The number of Syrian refugees in Iraq has risen to 21,000, the minister says .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="5">Jolie is a special envoy for the U.N.&amp;apost;s refugee agency.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-06 22:54:40" annotation_time="17.539">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">After she met with Kurdish officials at Erbil airport, the actress met with refugees at a Syrian camp in Dohuk province.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="4">Jolie -- a special envoy for the refugee agency -- met Iraqi returnees from Syria and senior government officials Saturday in Baghdad.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">She discussed the situation of Syrian refugees in Iraq with Foreign Minister Hoshyar Zebari at his office in Baghdad, the ministry said in a statement.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="3">Zebari told Jolie that the number of Syrian refugees who have fled the conflict to seek sanctuary in Iraq has risen to 21,000.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Baghdad Hollywood star Angelina Jolie is visiting Iraq&amp;apost;s semi-autonomous Kurdistan region Sunday after cancellation of her flight from Baghdad because of bad weather.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Jolie&amp;apost;s flight to Erbil was canceled Saturday, said Aurvasi Patel, assistant representative of the United Nation&amp;apost;s refugee agency.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>She made it there a day later.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>After she met with Kurdish officials at Erbil airport, the actress met with refugees at a Syrian camp in Dohuk province.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Jolie -- a special envoy for the refugee agency -- met Iraqi returnees from Syria and senior government officials Saturday in Baghdad.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>She discussed the situation of Syrian refugees in Iraq with Foreign Minister Hoshyar Zebari at his office in Baghdad, the ministry said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>They also talked about the Iraqi government&amp;apost;s efforts to meet the daily needs of refugees, the statement said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Zebari told Jolie that the number of Syrian refugees who have fled the conflict to seek sanctuary in Iraq has risen to 21,000.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Many are now living in Iraq&amp;apost;s western Anbar and northern Duhok provinces.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Zebari said nearly 31,000 Iraqis have also fled the war in Syria and returned to their native country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Jolie also met with officials from the Iraqi ministry that deals with displaced people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>She has recently visited refugee camps in Turkey, Lebanon and Jordan to highlight suffering and the need for international humanitarian assistance.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>While at the Zaatari refugee camp in Jordan on Tuesday, Jolie, who is herself raising six children with partner Brad Pitt, spoke of the horrors that children, many of them orphans, have witnessed in Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am grateful to Jordan and the border countries for saving the lives (of those) who are dying in Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s an extraordinary thing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>We encourage the international community to support the people here until one day they go back home,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Jolie, who was appointed a special envoy of U.N. High Commissioner for Refugees Antonio Guterres in April, accompanied Guterres on a visit to the Kilis camp in Turkey on Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>She was previously a goodwill ambassador for the U.N. Refugee Agency, undertaking more than 40 field trips on its behalf.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
