<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2960" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/07/19/world/europe/securing-a-plane-crash-site-mh17-ukraine/index.html?hpt=hp_t1" date_published="2014-07-19 14:15:05" category="world" author="Joshua Berlinger and Laura Smith-Spark, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>What should happen at the MH17 crash site in Ukraine?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Concern is growing that the site has not been sealed off.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="17">The first order of business is to collect the victims&amp;apost; remains.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="9">Keeping the crash site sterile is one of the most important steps that authorities take .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 19:48:44" annotation_time="10.401">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">Concern is growing that the site has not been sealed off as it should have been and that vital evidence is being tampered with.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="3">Keeping the crash site sterile is one of the most important steps that authorities take during the investigation, David Deas, the former spokesman for the U.K. Department of Transport, told CNN&amp;apost;s Hala Gorani.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="2">Although investigators need to survey the crash site to figure out what happened, the first order of business is to collect the victims&amp;apost; remains, according to Fuentes.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Bodies, backpacks, passports and other piles of debris lay splayed across a miles-long area in the remote area in eastern Ukraine where Malaysia Airlines Flight 17 came down.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The crash site is massive -- an international observer called it &amp;quot;one of the biggest -- or the biggest -- crime scenes in the world right now.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Concern is growing that the site has not been sealed off as it should have been and that vital evidence is being tampered with.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Meanwhile, armed rebels have greeted international observers with hostility.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Experts say that this crash investigation is unprecedented due to the site&amp;apost;s immense size and the lack of access given to investigators.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>With so many questions over what happened to MH17 unanswered, experts say it is crucial that the scene is protected.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>What should be being done on the ground?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>How should a crash site be secured?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Keeping the crash site sterile is one of the most important steps that authorities take during the investigation, David Deas, the former spokesman for the U.K. Department of Transport, told CNN&amp;apost;s Hala Gorani.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;It would be sealed off by security forces or law enforcement,&amp;quot; Deas said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>After the site is secured, analyzing and removing the debris is an arduous process.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The investigation &amp;quot;will take hundreds of people several months,&amp;quot; Tom Fuentes, a former assistant director at the FBI, told CNN&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;New Day Saturday.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;They will need a convoy of trucks for the victims.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>They&amp;apost;ll need a convoy of flatbed trucks, cranes to remove the debris.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>They&amp;apost;ll need a location to take the debris to where it can be reassembled, examined and determine what exactly happened to the aircraft.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Why is this important and what will forensics experts look for at a crash site?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Although investigators need to survey the crash site to figure out what happened, the first order of business is to collect the victims&amp;apost; remains, according to Fuentes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Forget about the blame,&amp;quot; Fuentes said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;You want to recover your victims, recover the remains, reunite them with their families.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s first and foremost.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Investigators also say that the proving who and what was responsible for the crash lies among the wreckage.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Seemingly minute details, like the direction in which debris fell, can provide information as to what took down the plane -- that&amp;apost;s why it&amp;apost;s so important to make sure the site is not tampered with.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;The only way that (culpability) is going to be truly determined is by the hard, physical evidence to prove that something did hit the aircraft,&amp;quot; David Soucie, a former accident investigator, told &amp;quot;New Day.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Soucie says that evidence from the crash site can help investigators prove whether something hit the plane, what direction a missile might have come from and how far away the projectile was when it was launched.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>In addition, the wreckage itself can create hazardous conditions for nearby populations, according to the National Transportation Safety Board.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>And the airline industry can also use the information about what exactly took down the Boeing 777 when they construct newer planes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;Lessons can be learned for the future construction of aircraft,&amp;quot; Deas said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Investigators &amp;quot;want to know why it happened, but they also want to learn lessons from it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>What should happen to the bodies of victims?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>As of yesterday, the remains of the victims had not neither been moved nor tampered with, a spokesman for the Organization for Security and Co-Operation in Europe told CNN&amp;apost;s Christian Amanpour.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The bodies still have not been removed, more than two days after the incident, spokesman Michael Bociurkiw said from the crash site.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Observers on the ground say they are starting to decompose and bloat.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>And with the summer heat, there are notable health implications if the bodies remain outside for too long,.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The remains need to be stored in cool temperatures.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>And there are nearby facilities where they could be stored -- like an ice-cream factory, Bociurkiw said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>However, the facilities &amp;quot;are not prepared to receive&amp;quot; the dead, according to Bociurkiw.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>The crash site is large and difficult to access, nearby roads are closed and there is a lack of electricity due to the accident.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>The location of some of the bodies are being marked by white flags.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Civilian emergency workers told Bociurkiw that their job was to mark where the bodies were.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Moving the bodies?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;Well, that&amp;apost;s somebody else&amp;apost;s job,&amp;quot; they told Bociurkiw.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>How are victims&amp;apost; remains identified?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>According to Interpol, the international police agency, it&amp;apost;s very rare that victims can be visually identified.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Interpol uses identifiers such as fingerprints, dental records or DNA samples to confirm who was on board the plane.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>The agency said on Saturday that it will be deploying a team to provide &amp;quot;on-site assistance&amp;quot; within the next two days.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Dutch authorities have sent a team of at least 80 police to visit with families and gather information about the victims -- including DNA, tattoos, dental records and other specifying information.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
