<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2438" link="http://www.cnn.com/2011/12/04/world/americas/mexico-president-speech/index.html" date_published="2011-12-04 17:38:50" category="world" author="the CNN Wire Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Mexico&amp;apost;s president pledges to continue fighting cartels</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">President Felipe Calderon speaks at an event marking five years of his presidency.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">&amp;quot;We are going to continue defending the citizens until the last day of my term,&amp;quot; he says .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="8">The president warns that drug cartels are &amp;quot;threatening democracy&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="9">He says his government has captured or killed 21 of 37 most wanted criminals.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-10 15:15:41" annotation_time="15.252666">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;We have done that, and we are going to continue defending the citizens until the last day of my term.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">Calderon spoke at an event marking five years of his presidency.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="3">In his remarks Sunday, Calderon warned that drug cartels were already &amp;quot;threatening democracy&amp;quot; by attempting to manipulate election results.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="4">Calderon praised his government&amp;apost;s crime-fighting record, noting that 21 of 37 criminals on the nation&amp;apost;s most wanted list earlier in his term had been captured or killed.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Mexico City Mexico&amp;apost;s president defended his drug war strategy Sunday, pledging to continue his fight against organized crime.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;The first obligation of a government is to guarantee the security and the rights of the citizens,&amp;quot; President Felipe Calderon said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have done that, and we are going to continue defending the citizens until the last day of my term.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Calderon spoke at an event marking five years of his presidency.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>He declared a crackdown on cartels shortly after taking office in December 2006, deploying thousands of troops into some parts of the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>With one year left in his term, Calderon&amp;apost;s remarks Sunday came as political campaigns heat up among candidates hoping to be his successor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Mexico&amp;apost;s security situation, and the government&amp;apost;s tactics for dealing with drug cartels, are likely to figure heavily in debates leading up to next year&amp;apost;s elections.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>In his remarks Sunday, Calderon warned that drug cartels were already &amp;quot;threatening democracy&amp;quot; by attempting to manipulate election results.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Calderon praised his government&amp;apost;s crime-fighting record, noting that 21 of 37 criminals on the nation&amp;apost;s most wanted list earlier in his term had been captured or killed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>He vowed to continue efforts to stamp out corruption and strengthen judicial institutions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;The country needs to be able to count on honest, dependable police that are serving the citizens and not the criminals,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Calderon also said his government was committed to human rights, and said he had reacted swiftly when any violations of rights were reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Criticism has mounted over Mexico&amp;apost;s drug war strategy and the country&amp;apost;s human rights record.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Last month, a group of activists filed a 700-page complaint with the International Criminal Court in the Hague, the Netherlands, alleging more than 470 cases of human rights violations against women and children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;What we are denouncing are behaviors that are becoming systematic in the Army and Armed Forces such as rape, forced disappearances, killing of civilians and cover-ups of these killings.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>A series of a disturbing number of violations against international humanitarian laws lead directly to Felipe Calderon&amp;apost;s responsibility,&amp;quot; Netzai Sandoval, a lawyer representing the activist group, told CNNMexico.com.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Calderon&amp;apost;s office released a statement describing the allegations as &amp;quot;false and slanderous.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;In the instances where, unfortunately, it has become known that violations of human rights were committed, the government not only has condemned such actions, but also has judicially proceeded against those responsible before the appropriate tribunals,&amp;quot; the statement said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
