<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2156" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/07/16/world/asia/japan-artist-arrested/index.html?hpt=hp_mid" date_published="2014-07-16 09:34:47" category="world" author="Sophie Brown, Will Ripley and Junko Ogura, CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Does Japanese artist&amp;apost;s arrest prove her point?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Japan detains artist known for creating works inspired by female genitalia.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Megumi Igarashi, 42, is being held on charges of distributing obscene data.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="18">Igarashi says her own insecurities and desire to shatter taboos inspire her work.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-14 00:41:19" annotation_time="80.403">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1, 2">But in Japan, a conceptual artist known for creating works inspired by her genitals is being held by Tokyo police on charges of sharing obscene material electronically.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="3">One of her lawyers, Kazuyuki Minami, acknowledges that not everyone will appreciate Igarashi&amp;apost;s work, but says that her case is about more than artistic expression.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>In a country with a flourishing porn industry and an annual penis festival, it may come as a surprise that an artist with a mission to make female genitalia &amp;quot;more casual and pop&amp;quot; has run afoul of authorities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But in Japan, a conceptual artist known for creating works inspired by her genitals is being held by Tokyo police on charges of sharing obscene material electronically.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Megumi Igarashi, who goes by the pseudonym Rokudenashiko (which means &amp;quot;good-for-nothing kid&amp;quot;), launched a crowd-funding campaign to raise money to build a kayak in the shape of her vagina using a 3-D printer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>In exchange for donations, supporters of the project were given data that would allow them to make their own 3-D prints of her genitals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Police arrested Igarashi Saturday, charging her with &amp;quot;distributing data that could create an obscene shape through a 3-D printer.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The 42-year-old denies the charges, saying that she doesn&amp;apost;t acknowledge that the work is &amp;quot;an obscenity.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>For her, it&amp;apost;s a piece of fine art.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>In fact, Igarashi came up with the the idea for the project based on her own self doubt.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Female genitalia is such a taboo in Japanese society, she explained on her fundraising page, that it has become &amp;quot;overly hidden.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>She did not know what a vagina &amp;quot;should look like,&amp;quot; she said, and worried that her own was &amp;quot;abnormal.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Images of penises, on the other hand, were an acceptable part of pop culture, she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>(And anyone who&amp;apost;s witnessed crowds licking phallic lollipops and sporting penis-shaped glasses at Japan&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;Festival of the Steel Phallus&amp;quot; will find it difficult to argue with her.).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The artist has embarked on a whole series of cutesy works inspired by the female anatomy, from smartphone cases to a giant kawaii mascot.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>She created miniature dioramas, including one of workers toiling away in a vagina-shaped crevice at Fukushima&amp;apost;s damaged nuclear plant.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Many critics of her arrest have pointed out that Japan only banned the possession of child pornography a month ago, and even then, the ban excludes explicit anime and manga cartoons.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Distributing uncensored images of real genitalia is a crime under the country&amp;apost;s obscenity laws.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>More than 17,000 people had signed an online petition calling for Igarashi&amp;apost;s release as of Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>One of her lawyers, Kazuyuki Minami, acknowledges that not everyone will appreciate Igarashi&amp;apost;s work, but says that her case is about more than artistic expression.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;Whether you experience empathy with her works that challenge a taboo will depend on the individual&amp;apost;s sensitivity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>However, all people who believe in freedom and equality of human beings should understand that her arrest and detention was not right thing.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Police are still questioning Igarashi, a spokesperson for the Tokyo Metropolitan Police told CNN Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The earliest the artist can be released is August 8, although police can hold her for up to 20 days in order to gather evidence because she denies the charges, the spokesperson said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>If convicted, she could face up to two years jail time or a fine of as much as 2.5 million yen (around US$24,500), her lawyers say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
