<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2539" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/02/21/world/asia/afghanistan-islamic-books/index.html" date_published="2012-02-21 07:28:46" category="world" author="the CNN Wire Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Official: Burned Islamic religious material had &amp;apost;extremist inscriptions&amp;apost;</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">NEW: Commander of NATO-led force mandates training on handling religious materials.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">Official: Some documents were &amp;quot;extremist in and of themselves&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="17">Commander Gen. John Allen says he has launched an investigation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="19">Muslims regard the Quran as their holy book.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-28 10:03:15" annotation_time="43.022327">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;Additionally, some of the documents were extremist in and of themselves, apparently originating from outside of Afghanistan,&amp;quot; the official said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">The uproar prompted Gen. John Allen, commander of NATO&amp;apost;s International Security Assistance Force, to issue a directive &amp;quot;that all coalition forces in Afghanistan will complete training in the proper handling of religious materials no later than March 3,&amp;quot; the NATO-led force said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="3">Allen said he immediately launched an investigation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="4">Muslims regard the Quran as the absolute word of God.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Kabul, Afghanistan Religious materials -- including Qurans that were burned at Bagram Airfield in Afghanistan, sparking Afghan protests -- were removed from the library of a detainee center &amp;quot;because of extremist inscriptions&amp;quot; on them, a military official said Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>There was &amp;quot;an appearance that these documents were being used to facilitate extremist communications,&amp;quot; a military official said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;Additionally, some of the documents were extremist in and of themselves, apparently originating from outside of Afghanistan,&amp;quot; the official said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The official said the material was burned, but authorities are attempting to determine how much.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The uproar prompted Gen. John Allen, commander of NATO&amp;apost;s International Security Assistance Force, to issue a directive &amp;quot;that all coalition forces in Afghanistan will complete training in the proper handling of religious materials no later than March 3,&amp;quot; the NATO-led force said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The training will include &amp;quot;the identification of religious materials, their significance, correct handling and storage,&amp;quot; according to the statement from coalition forces.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Earlier Tuesday, Allen said the materials were gathered for disposal from the airfield&amp;apost;s Parwan detention facility and inadvertently given to troops for burning.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;This was not a decision that was made because they were religious materials,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;It was not a decision that was made with respect to the faith of Islam.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>It was a mistake.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>It was an error.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The moment we found out about it, we immediately stopped and we intervened.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Hundreds of demonstrators gathered outside the airfield Tuesday, furious over reports of the burning.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Lt. Lauren Rago, a spokeswoman for the coalition forces, told CNN in an e-mail earlier Tuesday that an investigation was under way to determine whether any material was burned before the mistake was discovered and, if so, how much.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are deeply concerned about the report of Qurans or religious materials being damaged, and will get to the bottom of what actually happened,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>But a coalition official acknowledged the materials were improperly burned.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Allen said he immediately launched an investigation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Something like this just cannot happen again,&amp;quot; Allen said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Muslims regard the Quran as the absolute word of God.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>It is so highly revered that many Muslims will not pick up the holy book without ablution, a ritual washing of the hands.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Desecrating the book, such as burning it, is therefore seen as an unforgivable affront -- as an act of intolerance and bigotry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Authorities are looking into the reasons why the material was gathered and why the decision was made &amp;quot;to dispose of them in this manner,&amp;quot; Allen said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Some troops have been questioned, but there have been no arrests or detentions, according to a coalition official.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Afghan officials have been invited to join the investigation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Allen said he has offered &amp;quot;sincere apologies&amp;quot; to Afghan officials, including President Hamid Karzai.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Allen also offered apologies to the Afghan government and &amp;quot;the noble people of Afghanistan.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;This was unintentional,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;There was no intention by any member of ISAF to defame the faith of Islam or to desecrate the precious religious materials of this faith.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;The materials recovered will be properly handled by appropriate religious authorities,&amp;quot; Allen said earlier.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Local citizens who work at the base discovered the material that had been put into a burn pit by NATO personnel and alerted officials.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Soon after, demonstrators massed outside the base, chanting &amp;quot;Death to America!</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Death to the Afghan government!</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Long live Islam!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>As a NATO helicopter circled overhead and black smoke billowed from the ground, men shook their fists in anger.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Several men launched slingshots in the direction of the base.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;The desecration of religious articles is not in keeping with the standards of American tolerance, human rights practices and freedom of religion,&amp;quot; State Department spokeswoman Victoria Nuland said Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;The concern is that some around the world will think that this represents an affirmative statement by the United States, and it does not represent our values or our view of how the Quran ought to be treated,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Allen said, &amp;quot;This is not who we are.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>These are very, very isolated incidents.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>We&amp;apost;ve been here a long time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>We&amp;apost;ve been shoulder to shoulder with the Afghans for a long time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>We&amp;apost;ve been dying alongside the Afghans for a long time because we believe in them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>We believe in their country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>We want to have every opportunity to give them a bright future.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>But &amp;quot;these kinds of incidents, when they do occur, we will move quickly to correct them,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>&amp;quot;We will move quickly to hold people accountable.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Photographs surfaced purporting to show the damaged Qurans.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>A photographer for Agence France-Presse said Afghans who work inside the airfield told him they obtained the Qurans there.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>But the U.S. military said that was unlikely.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>&amp;quot;When it became known that it was religious materials that were brought to the incinerator, the materials were secured by the military authorities in consultation with the local Afghan religious authorities, so it would be highly unlikely that the demonstrators would have any of the material from this incident,&amp;quot; said Col. Gary Kolb, a spokesman for the NATO-led force.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>The U.S. Embassy in Kabul warned on its Twitter feed that protests were possible throughout Afghanistan in the coming days and noted, &amp;quot;Past demonstrations in Afghanistan have escalated into violent attacks on Western targets of opportunity.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Last year, when controversial Florida pastor Terry Jones presided over what he called a trial of the Quran and burned a copy, Afghans took to the streets by the thousands.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>In the northern Afghan city of Mazar-e Sharif, demonstrators stormed a U.N. office and killed 12 people.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>In Kandahar, three people were killed in one demonstration, and nine in another when police and stone-throwing demonstrators clashed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>American officials vociferously condemned the pastor&amp;apost;s act.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>&amp;quot;It was intolerant and it was extremely disrespectful and again, we condemn it in the strongest manner possible,&amp;quot; said Gen. David Petraeus, who headed the U.S.-led international forces in Afghanistan at the time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>In 2010, Afghans protested outside the Forward Operating Base Mirwais in response to an alleged Quran burning inside the base.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>But coalition forces said the suspected burning was a routine burn-pit session in which military documents are destroyed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
