<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2571" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/06/18/world/asia/malaysia-missing-plane/index.html" date_published="2014-06-18 06:57:15" category="world" author="Mike Ahlers, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Outside group tells governments where to search for Flight 370</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Group: 5 computer models all place plane in tight cluster of spots in south Indian Ocean.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">This new potential search area is hundreds of miles southwest of previous search site.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">Malaysia Airlines Flight 370 vanished March 8 while flying from Kuala Lumpur to Beijing.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-11 18:14:26" annotation_time="18.522667">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1, 2">Five separate computer models all place the plane in a tight cluster of spots in the south Indian Ocean - hundreds of miles southwest of the previous search site.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">The plane and its 239 occupants vanished March 8 while flying from Kuala Lumpur to Beijing.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington The doubters have spoken.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>A group of independent experts -- who prodded authorities to release satellite data on Malaysia Airlines Flight 370 -- says it thinks it knows the approximate location of the missing aircraft.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Five separate computer models all place the plane in a tight cluster of spots in the south Indian Ocean - hundreds of miles southwest of the previous search site.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;We recommend that the search for MH370 be focused in this area,&amp;quot; the group said in a statement late Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;While there remain a number of uncertainties and some disagreements as to the interpretation of aspects of the data, our best estimates of a location of the aircraft (is) near 36.02 South 88.57 East,&amp;quot; according to the statement, which was approved by 10 named experts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The group opted to release its statement late Tuesday in advance of a BBC documentary on the missing plane, and ahead of the Australian government&amp;apost;s announcement on the focus of the search, so that there would be no question about the independence of the group&amp;apost;s findings, said one member of the group, American Mobile Satellite Corp. co-founder Mike Exner.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;We wanted to get our best estimate out,&amp;quot; Exner said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The group believes that after the Boeing 777 circumnavigated Indonesia, for reasons that are still unknown, the plane traveled south at an average speed of 470 knots, probably at a consistent altitude and constant heading, Exner said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>All five computer models developed by the experts place the aircraft in a &amp;quot;pretty tight cluster...plus or minus 50 miles of each other,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The plane and its 239 occupants vanished March 8 while flying from Kuala Lumpur to Beijing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>In a blog post, group member Tim Farrar called the recommended search site &amp;quot;our best estimate -- but not the only possible -- location for a potential search.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Meanwhile, a team of government experts and Inmarsat employees is re-evaluating the data before pinpointing where to resume the search.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>On Wednesday the agency overseeing the search said the analysis was &amp;quot;nearly complete&amp;quot; and it expects to announce the new search site by the end of June.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Australian government authorities only recently acknowledged that acoustic pings heard two months ago are now believed to be unrelated to the aircraft&amp;apost;s data recorders, or &amp;quot;black boxes.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The ad hoc group of independent specialists came together through web sites of two experts, Duncan Steel of Wellington, New Zealand, and Tim Farrar of Menlo Park, California.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Several members of the group initially cast doubts on Inmarsat&amp;apost;s conclusions that the plane had flown south, saying the publicly available information from Malaysia and Inmarsat was insufficient to draw that conclusion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The plane could have flown north, landing or crashing along an arc extending from Thailand to Eastern Europe.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>But shortly after Malaysia released raw satellite data on May 27, several of the loose confederation of scientists agreed it provided sufficient data to show the plane had flown south.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The &amp;quot;breakthrough piece of information,&amp;quot; Exner said, was that the satellite terminal on the aircraft had been programmed to use a simplified assumption about the location of the satellite.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The terminal assumed that the satellite was geostationary -- fixed over a spot on the equator -- when, in fact, it drifted to the north and south.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Over the past few weeks, the group continued to exchange information through emails and through postings on the web sites.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The group worked five or six hours Tuesday exchanging some 120 emails in drafting the statement on the possible location of MH370.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Exner said he believes authorities were narrowing in on the correct search site, but were thrown off course when searchers detected acoustic pings northwest of Australia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s my personal opinion that the official search team weighed too heavily&amp;quot; on the acoustic pings, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Exner said the informal group of experts has volunteered to work with the U.S. National Transportation Safety Board and the Australian Transport Safety Bureau.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>But, while the government agencies have been polite, they have been reticent to release additional information that could further help the independent group, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
