<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2461" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/05/17/world/asia/india-leader-transition/index.html" date_published="2014-05-17 08:32:40" category="world" author="Harmeet Shah Singh and Madison Park, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Modi emerges victorious, prepares for transition</title>
  <keywords>Narendra Modi,Indian Prime Minister</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Victory parade held for India&amp;apost;s next Prime Minister, Narendra Modi.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Official results show a clear majority for one party, winning 282 of 543 parliamentary seats.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">Prime Minister Manmohan Singh says goodbye to nation in his last address.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-19 10:52:39" annotation_time="154.53099" mapping_time_divergence="103.02066">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">Modi&amp;apost;s party won 282 of 543 parliamentary seats, according to the country&amp;apost;s election commission, bringing a clear majority and a resounding mandate to a single party to rule the world&amp;apost;s largest democracy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">Modi, 63, is expected to officially be sworn in as India&amp;apost;s new Prime Minister on May 21.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">Meanwhile, outgoing Prime Minister Manmohan Singh submitted his resignation and made his last address to the nation, recalling his background from the subcontinent&amp;apost;s bloody division into India and Pakistan in 1947.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Fresh from a landslide victory, Narendra Modi and his Bharatiya Janata Party celebrated in a parade, as supporters lined the streets in the capital, waving flags of the party and holding balloons.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Modi&amp;apost;s party won 282 of 543 parliamentary seats, according to the country&amp;apost;s election commission, bringing a clear majority and a resounding mandate to a single party to rule the world&amp;apost;s largest democracy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Modi, 63, is expected to officially be sworn in as India&amp;apost;s new Prime Minister on May 21.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>He will have to shoulder great expectations, as voters flocked to his party on his pledge to reform the nation&amp;apost;s slowed economy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Prime Minister says goodbye.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Meanwhile, outgoing Prime Minister Manmohan Singh submitted his resignation and made his last address to the nation, recalling his background from the subcontinent&amp;apost;s bloody division into India and Pakistan in 1947.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;I owe everything to this country, this great land of ours where I, an underprivileged child of (the) partition, was empowered enough to rise and occupy high office.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>It is both a debt that I will never be able to repay and a decoration that I will always wear with pride,&amp;quot; Singh said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Singh, 82, leaves the office with a divided legacy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>While his performance as finance minister in the 1990s has been praised for opening up India&amp;apost;s economy, his recent years as Prime Minister were pockmarked by a spate of high-profile corruption scandals involving his Congress Party, as well as stalled reforms and a drop in growth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;Friends, I am confident about the future of India.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>I firmly believe that the emergence of India as a major powerhouse of the evolving global economy is an idea whose time has come,&amp;quot; Singh said in his TV address.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>He concluded his speech by wishing Modi&amp;apost;s government well and saying he prayed for &amp;quot;even greater successes for our nation.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Modi&amp;apost;s background.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Modi is widely viewed as pro-business and pro-growth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>India&amp;apost;s stock market surged Friday as initial results suggested a huge lead for Modi and his party.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The former tea seller sprang into the national spotlight for his work in the state of Gujarat, where he cultivated an image of a man who gets things done.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Gujarat, which contains 60 million people, has seen China-like rates of growth in recent years, which the rest of the country has eyed enviously.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The &amp;quot;Gujarat model&amp;quot; of development means a focus on infrastructure, urbanization and eradicating red tape.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>His past is not without controversy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Throughout his campaign, his relationship with the country&amp;apost;s huge Muslim minority came under scrutiny.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>In 2002, Gujarat state was wracked with anti-Muslim violence, in which more than 1,000 people, mostly Muslims, were killed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Modi, the state&amp;apost;s chief minister, was criticized for not doing enough to halt the violence, but a Supreme Court-ordered investigation absolved him of blame last year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The United States denied Modi a visa in 2005 over the anti-Muslim violence, but on Friday, President Barack Obama called Modi to congratulate him on winning the election and to invite him to Washington, according to the White House.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The visa issue could add to what has already been a strained relationship between the two nations -- complicated by a case involving an Indian diplomat who was arrested last year in New York.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
