<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2614" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/12/25/world/europe/pope-christmas-message/index.html" date_published="2012-12-25 13:24:52" category="world" author="Mariano Castillo, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Pope expresses hope, calls for peace</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Pope Benedict XVI delivered his Christmas message Tuesday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">He said there&amp;apost;s a hope in this world that can be trusted, &amp;quot;even at the most difficult times&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="9">Benedict called for peace in Syria, Nigeria and other places of tension and strife.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="5">He spoke to a crowd of about 50,000 gathered at St. Peter&amp;apost;s Square in Vatican City.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-11 18:15:16" annotation_time="12.413333">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">On Christmas, Pope Benedict XVI spread a hopeful message to his followers, calling for peace in many of the world&amp;apost;s hot spots.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;Consequently, there is hope in the world; a hope in which we can trust, even at the most difficult times and in the most difficult situations.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="4">Benedict spoke to a crowd of about 50,000 gathered at St. Peter&amp;apost;s Square in Vatican City.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="3">Benedict also asked for dialogue in the Israeli-Palestinian conflict.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>On Christmas, Pope Benedict XVI spread a hopeful message to his followers, calling for peace in many of the world&amp;apost;s hot spots.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>From Syria to northern Nigeria, the leader of the Catholic Church urged dialogue and the protection of civilians.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;In this world, there is a good soil God has prepared,&amp;quot; the pope said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;Consequently, there is hope in the world; a hope in which we can trust, even at the most difficult times and in the most difficult situations.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Benedict spoke to a crowd of about 50,000 gathered at St. Peter&amp;apost;s Square in Vatican City.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>He called for an end to the bloodshed in Syria, where a civil war has claimed more than 40,000 lives.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;May peace spring up for the people of Syria, deeply wounded and divided by a conflict which does not spare even the defenseless and reaps innocent victims,&amp;quot; Benedict said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;Once again, I appeal for an end to the bloodshed, easier access for the relief of refugees and the displaced, and dialogue in the pursuit of a political solution to the conflict.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Benedict also asked for dialogue in the Israeli-Palestinian conflict.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;May peace spring up in the land where the redeemer was born, and may he grant Israelis and Palestinians courage to end long years of conflict and division and embark resolutely on the path of negotiation,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Regarding China, where there have been tensions this year between the Catholic Church and Chinese authorities over the oversight of church leaders there, Benedict called for expanded freedom of religion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Addressing China&amp;apost;s new leaders, he expressed hope that, &amp;quot;in fulfilling this task, they will esteem the contribution of the religions, in respect for each, in such a way that they can help to build a fraternal society for the benefit of that noble people and of the whole world.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Benedict also expressed concern about violence in Mali and Nigeria, &amp;quot;where savage acts of terrorism continue to reap victims, particularly among Christians.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>And he expressed hope that the citizens of Egypt will &amp;quot;build societies founded on justice and respect for the freedom and dignity of every person.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The pontiff added, before delivering Christmas blessings in 65 languages: &amp;quot;May every land become a good earth which receives and brings forth kindness and truth, justice and peace.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Happy Christmas to all of you.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
