<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2245" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/10/08/world/europe/sweden-nobel-prize-physics/index.html" date_published="2013-10-08 06:35:34" category="world" author="Ben Brumfield, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Higgs Boson theorists receive Nobel Prize in physics</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="39">Francois Englert and Peter Higgs are awarded the Nobel Prize in physics.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">The Higgs boson is what gives all matter its mass and is a central part of scientific theory.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="32">The July 2012 discovery of the particle is billed as one of the biggest scientific achievements.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-28 15:55:01" annotation_time="47.909">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">Higgs and Englert&amp;apost;s theories behind the elusive Higgs boson explained what gives matter its mass.</sentence>
      <sentence id="32" ids_highlights="3">The July 2012 discovery of the Higgs boson in the most powerful particle accelerator in the world, the Large Hadron Collider at CERN, has been billed as one of the biggest scientific achievements of the past 50 years.</sentence>
      <sentence id="39" ids_highlights="1">The Nobel Prize in physics makes a nice lifetime achievement award for Englert and Higgs.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The Higgs boson, or the &amp;quot;God particle,&amp;quot; which was discovered last year, garnered two physicists the Nobel Prize in physics on Tuesday, but it didn&amp;apost;t go to the scientists who detected it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Nearly 50 years ago, Francois Englert of Belgium and Peter Higgs of the United Kingdom had the foresight to predict that the particle existed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Now, the octogenarian pair share the Nobel Prize in physics in recognition of a theoretical brilliance that was vindicated by the particle&amp;apost;s discovery last year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences awarded the prize to them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Higgs and Englert&amp;apost;s theories behind the elusive Higgs boson explained what gives matter its mass.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The universe is filled with Higgs bosons.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>As atoms and parts of atoms zoom around, they interact with and attract Higgs bosons, which cluster around them in varying numbers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Certain particles will attract larger clusters of Higgs bosons, and the more of them a particle attracts, the greater its mass will be.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The explanation helped complete scientists&amp;apost; understanding of the nature of all matter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;The awarded theory is a central part of the Standard Model of particle physics that describes how the world is constructed,&amp;quot; the Royal Swedish Academy said in a post on Twitter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>As is tradition, the academy phoned the scientists during the announcement to inform them of their win.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>They were unable to reach Higgs, for whom the particle is named.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The conversation with Englert was short and sweet.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;I feel very well, of course,&amp;quot; he said, when he heard the news.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;Now, I&amp;apost;m very happy.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The discoverers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>When the Nobel announcement came down, the Higgs boson&amp;apost;s discoverers in Geneva, Switzerland, broke out the champagne, said lead physicist Joe Incandela.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;The place erupted into applause.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>There must have been over 100 people in the room at CERN, the European Organization for Nuclear Research, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Many of them were American scientists.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>About one quarter of the physicists involved in the discovery came from the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The researchers felt equally recognized alongside the Nobel recipients.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>They were not expecting to receive the prize themselves.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>That would have been atypical.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>It goes more often to those involved on the theoretical side and not on the experimental side, Incandela said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>But it didn&amp;apost;t matter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re extremely happy with that,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m elated.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>We feel that we&amp;apost;ve been recognized.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The fact that the prize was awarded to the theorists so soon after the particle&amp;apost;s existence was detected by experimenters is a confirmation of the value of their contribution, Incandela said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The discovery.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The July 2012 discovery of the Higgs boson in the most powerful particle accelerator in the world, the Large Hadron Collider at CERN, has been billed as one of the biggest scientific achievements of the past 50 years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>But the Royal Academy passed over the Higgs boson last year, to the surprise of many.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The scientists, in the meantime, have confirmed their discovery and solidified its place in science.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>On March 14, what would have been Albert Einstein&amp;apost;s birthday, they announced that, over time, the particle they found looked even more like the Higgs boson they had been chasing for almost 50 years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>It was a landmark scientific advancement, and it was a first.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Many scientists dislike the term &amp;quot;God particle,&amp;quot; even though it&amp;apost;s become popular in the media.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>The nickname came from the title of a book by Leon Lederman, who reportedly wanted to call it the &amp;quot;Goddamn Particle&amp;quot; since it was so hard to find.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>The Nobel Prize in physics makes a nice lifetime achievement award for Englert and Higgs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Both are professors emeritus: Englert at the Free University of Brussels; Higgs at the University of Edinburgh in Scotland.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Though deserving, they are lucky, as the Royal Academy had a long list of brilliant scientists and achievements to choose from.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>And the field of physics covers a virtually infinite scale, from beyond the smallest sub-atomic particles to the largest, most distant stars and quasars in the vast reaches of the universe.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Last year&amp;apost;s winners.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Last year&amp;apost;s prize to Serge Haroche and David J. Wineland rewarded work in the field of quantum optics.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>It could lead the way to superfast computers and and the most precise clocks ever seen.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>The two approached the same principles from opposite directions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>The American used light particles to measure the properties of matter, while his French colleague focused on tracking light particles by using atoms.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Both Nobel laureates found ways to isolate the subatomic particles and keep their properties intact at the same time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Prior to the breakthrough, such particles quickly interacted with matter, which changed their qualities and rendered them unobservable.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>That left scientists stuck doing a lot of guesswork.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>Past and future Nobels.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="37">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Since 1901, the committee has handed out the Nobel Prize in physics 107 times, including this year&amp;apost;s award.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>The youngest recipient was Lawrence Bragg, who won in 1915 at the age of 25.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>Bragg is not only the youngest physics laureate; he is also the youngest laureate in any Nobel Prize area.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="38">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>The oldest physics laureate was Raymond Davis Jr., who was 88 years old when he was awarded the prize in 2002.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="39">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>John Bardeen was the only physicist to receive the prize twice, for work in semiconductors and superconductivity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="40">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>Two Americans and a German shared the Nobel Prize in physiology or medicine this year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="41">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>Americans James E. Rothman and Randy W. Schekman and German Thomas C. Sudhof were awarded the prize Monday for discoveries of how the body&amp;apost;s cells decide when and where to deliver the molecules they produce.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="42">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="59">
          <content>Disruptions of this delivery system contribute to diabetes, neurological diseases and immunological disorders.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="43">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="60">
          <content>In the coming days, prize committees will announce the laureates in chemistry, literature, peace and economics.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="44">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="61">
          <content>Swedish industrialist Alfred Nobel created the prizes in 1895 to honor work in physics, chemistry, literature and peace.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="62">
          <content>The first economics prize was awarded in 1969.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
