<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2985" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/10/05/world/africa/tanzania-witchcraft/index.html" date_published="2012-10-05 17:09:27" category="world" author="Errol Barnett, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Witchcraft in Tanzania: the good, bad and the persecution</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7">Some 60% of Tanzanians believe sacrifices to spirits or ancestors can protect them from harm.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">Witchcraft serves to explain things that are inexplicable to those in rural villages without education, says anthropology professor.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">Albinos suffer discrimination and sometimes danger because some people believe their body parts bring great wealth.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-11 18:24:09" annotation_time="21.417">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">People with albinism have been dismembered in western parts of the country because so-called witchdoctors perpetuate a belief that albino body parts bring great wealth.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">It says 60% of the Tanzanians interviewed believe that sacrifices to ancestors or spirits can protect them from harm, and that many Christians and Muslims incorporate elements of traditional African beliefs into their daily lives.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">The anthropology professor says for centuries, witchcraft has &amp;quot;served to explain anything inexplicable,&amp;quot; in rural villages like a severely sick child or strange illness.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>It conjures images of cauldrons and pointed hats if you live in the western world or exotic masks and sacred objects if you&amp;apost;re on the African continent.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Around the world a sense of mystery and fear engulfs witchcraft and nowhere is this more evident than in the East African nation of Tanzania.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Here, faith in this specific form of African tradition can turn deadly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>People with albinism have been dismembered in western parts of the country because so-called witchdoctors perpetuate a belief that albino body parts bring great wealth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Those suspected of witchcraft are also targeted; an estimated 600 elderly women were killed in 2011 due to the suspicion they were witches, according to the Legal and Human Rights Center in Tanzania.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>In fact, the Pew Forum on Religious and Public life conducted 25,000 face-to-face interviews in 19 African nations and found that among them, Tanzanians hold the strongest belief in witchcraft.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>It says 60% of the Tanzanians interviewed believe that sacrifices to ancestors or spirits can protect them from harm, and that many Christians and Muslims incorporate elements of traditional African beliefs into their daily lives.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Dark arts flourished in Tanzania partly because, compared to its neighbors, it was &amp;quot;less colonized&amp;quot; by European powers, explains Joachim Mwami of Dar Es Salaam University.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The anthropology professor says for centuries, witchcraft has &amp;quot;served to explain anything inexplicable,&amp;quot; in rural villages like a severely sick child or strange illness.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Professor Mwami admitted that, &amp;quot;even in my own family, I was advised [as a child] not to visit certain relatives considered to be witches,&amp;quot; even though there was no proof.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>He says without access to education, people are more likely to follow the claims of traditional healers and pass down those beliefs to the next generation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Students at Dar Es Salaam University were reluctant to talk to CNN about opinions relating to witchcraft.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Some explained, even if they don&amp;apost;t personally believe in the practice, their relatives take it seriously.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Others feel one must believe in the practice for it to have any power over them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>So even with a university education, some students retain some faith in witchcraft.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Believers seeking healing regularly visit Mama Safi, a self-proclaimed &amp;quot;good witch,&amp;quot; who gained her powers after being visited by spirits, she says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m able to remove evil, stomach sickness, migraines, typhoid and diabetes too,&amp;quot; she boasts.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Safi conducts parts of her ceremonies in Arabic, even though she claims to have never studied it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Her fee ranges anywhere from $20 to $120 depending on the service provided; expensive when you consider most Tanzanians live on less than $2 a day.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Professor Mwami says the charging of any type of fee is not typical among traditional African healers and is more common among con artists capitalizing on the fears of others.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Debunking the claims of other so-called witches is Suleiman Musa, a man with albinism living in fear while trying to raise awareness about his genetic condition.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Albinism reveals itself through a lack of melanin or coloring in the skin, hair and eyes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Musa says many of his albino friends fled their rural homes after being chased out by locals.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>He too experiences prejudice and animosity from strangers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;I bear the pain because I can&amp;apost;t do anything [else],&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>However, in the bustling city of Dar Es Salaam he&amp;apost;s found support through an informal football team made up of people with albinism; Albinos United.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>He relishes the chance to explain to onlookers that he&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;normal, because this is the color God chose for me.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Musa doesn&amp;apost;t believe treatment of albinos will improve if Tanzanians remain uneducated about albinism.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Professor Mwami agrees that education is precisely what&amp;apost;s needed to address issues surrounding witchcraft saying, &amp;quot;the popularization of science is the only answer to these predicaments as far as Tanzania and belief systems are concerned.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>