<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2803" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/04/16/world/meast/iyw-malala-of-zaatari/index.html" date_published="2014-04-16 22:01:56" category="world" author="Abel Alvarado, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Syrian teen is called &amp;apost;the Malala of Za&amp;apost;atari&amp;apost;</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="21">With the help of one teen, 70% of children at Jordanian refugee camp now attend school.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">Mizune has been called &amp;quot;the Malala of Za&amp;apost;atari&amp;quot; for her efforts.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="31">If Za&amp;apost;atari were a city, it would be the fifth largest in Jordan.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-02 10:21:38" annotation_time="13.745999">
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">For her effort, she has been called the &amp;quot;Malala of Za&amp;apost;atari,&amp;quot; in reference to Pakistani education activist Malala Yousafzai.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="1">At this point, about 70% of the children in the camp attend school.</sentence>
      <sentence id="31" ids_highlights="3">If it were a city, it would the fifth-largest in Jordan.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>In the midst of uncertainty, Mizune, 14, one of thousands of refugees who fled Syria since the civil war began, is sure of one thing: &amp;quot;We can help and improve our nation with education.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>These are not just words; she turns them into action.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Despite her young age, she is determined to make it known in the camp that a brighter future begins in the classroom.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Mizune, whose father asked not to use her last name, arrived in Za&amp;apost;atari, Jordan, along with her family when the massive refugee influx began.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>She has spent her time promoting education in the camp, where half of the population is made up of children.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Much of her time in Za&amp;apost;atari has been spent going from tent to tent, from mosque to mosque, talking to children and parents about why getting back in the classroom is important.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s very important to me and important to society that I raise awareness.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>I want to emphasize the importance of education,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>For her effort, she has been called the &amp;quot;Malala of Za&amp;apost;atari,&amp;quot; in reference to Pakistani education activist Malala Yousafzai.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>On October 9, 2012, a gunman shot Malala when she was going home from school.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>She survived and has continued to speak out on the importance of education.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>In fact, Malala and Mizune are friends, having spent many hours together in the Za&amp;apost;atari camp when Malala visted there in February.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Mizune shares the same passion for education.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;We would go to tents and talk to people about their most pressing problems that prevent them from going to school.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>We would try to find solutions and talk about the rights of children to education,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Mizune&amp;apost;s work started when UNICEF began building schools in Za&amp;apost;atari.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Mizune saw this and decided to help.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Children are the most important people in society,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;Parents influence their kids, so the most important thing was educating the parents.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>People listened, and some had different points of view, but we were able to convince a big number to come to school.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>At this point, about 70% of the children in the camp attend school.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>According to Michele Servadei from UNICEF, the children&amp;apost;s parents have been the biggest challenge when it comes to education.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;In many cases, parents think that they&amp;apost;re going to go back (to Syria) soon,&amp;quot; he said, &amp;quot;and it&amp;apost;s not worth sending the children to be educated.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The ongoing Syrian civil war, which started its third year in March, began when protests against President Bashar al-Assad&amp;apost;s regime erupted in Daraa.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Demonstrations and unrest spread to nearly every city in Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The government responded with military action.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Thousands have died, and millions have fled the country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>As of February, there are an estimated 2.6 million Syrian refugees are spread across Iraq, Jordan, Lebanon, Turkey and Egypt.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Back in Za&amp;apost;atari, challenges are infinite, ranging from water supply and mobile home distribution to keeping warm during the winter.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Za&amp;apost;atari has become the second largest refugee camp in the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>If it were a city, it would the fifth-largest in Jordan.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>As many as 150,000 people live in the camp.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>However, that number changes every day as hundreds come or go.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Days go by, and an end to the Syrian crisis does not seem near, but Mizune, who dreams of someday becoming a Journalist, is already thinking of better days for her country&amp;apost;s future.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;A kid will face many challenges in their lives,&amp;quot; she said, &amp;quot;and it&amp;apost;s important to take advantage of education despite the circumstances, because life will go on.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
