<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2736" link="http://www.cnn.com/2011/12/02/world/meast/pol-iran-central-bank" date_published="2011-12-02 09:57:00" category="world" author="Dan Merica, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Senate agrees to sanction Iran&amp;apost;s central bank</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Treasury Secretary Timothy Geithner warned against these sanctions.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="15">The amendment still needs House approval and the president&amp;apost;s signature to become law .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="17">&amp;quot;The time has come to impose crippling sanctions,&amp;quot; a lawmaker says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-26 09:46:37" annotation_time="29.357666">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">Treasury Secretary Timothy Geithner echoed the warnings prior to its passage, stating &amp;quot;strong opposition&amp;quot; to the amendment.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="2">Democratic Sen. Robert Menendez of New Jersey and Republican Sen. Mark Kirk of Illinois sponsored the amendment, which now needs House approval and the president&amp;apost;s signature to become law.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;The time has come to impose crippling sanctions on this terrorist and nuclear-financing institution.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington The U.S. Senate unanimously passed economic sanctions against Iran on Thursday, a move that the Obama administration cautioned against.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Multiple administration officials have said that these sanctions would do more harm than good and both raise the price of oil and have little impact on Iran&amp;apost;s alleged nuclear ambitions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Treasury Secretary Timothy Geithner echoed the warnings prior to its passage, stating &amp;quot;strong opposition&amp;quot; to the amendment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;In its current form,&amp;quot; said Geithner of the amendment, &amp;quot;it threatens to undermine the effective, carefully phased and sustainable approach,&amp;quot; the administration is currently advocating.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The amendment would specifically disallow organizations that do business with financial institutions in Iran, including the countries central bank, from holding financial accounts in the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Waivers though would be provided for companies that deal with national security matters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The amendment also requires that studies be done to better understand how oil prices would be affected in the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;There is absolutely a risk that in fact the price of oil would go up, which would mean that Iran would in fact have more money to fuel its nuclear ambitions, not less,&amp;quot; said Wendy Sherman, the State Department&amp;apost;s undersecretary for political affairs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>EU foreign ministers meeting in Brussels on Thursday also applied more pressure on Iran.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>According to Maja Kocijancic, a spokeswoman for EU foreign policy chief Catherine Ashton, the ministers agreed on new sanctions that apply to 143 entities and 37 individuals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Earlier in the week, Fars News, a semi-official Iranian news agency, reported that Seyed Emad Hossein, head of the Iranian Parliament&amp;apost;s Energy Commission, warned the United States of continuing to sanction the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Sanctions on Iran&amp;apost;s oil, gas and petrochemical industries would be synonymous with a disruption in the world market, which in turn would push up crude prices,&amp;quot; Hossein warned.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is a very, very powerful threat,&amp;quot; said David Cohen, Under Secretary of the Treasury at a congressional hearing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is a threat to essentially the commercial banks to end there ability to transact in the dollar and there ability really to function as major international financial institutions.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Democratic Sen. Robert Menendez of New Jersey and Republican Sen. Mark Kirk of Illinois sponsored the amendment, which now needs House approval and the president&amp;apost;s signature to become law.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Central Bank of Iran is the primary bankroller of Iran&amp;apost;s global terror network, its nuclear program and other illicit activities,&amp;quot; said Kirk.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;The time has come to impose crippling sanctions on this terrorist and nuclear-financing institution.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Passage of the bill was part of a larger defense authorization bill that includes a new policy for detaining and trying suspected al Qaeda terrorists -- a policy that attracted controversy during the debate and may draw a presidential veto.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The bill also passed with little opposition, 93-7.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
