<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2042" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/07/07/world/africa/nigeria-boko-haram-women-escape/index.html" date_published="2014-07-07 06:14:04" category="world" author="Aminu Abubakar and Holly Yan, CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>63 abducted women, girls escape from Boko Haram</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="11">The women and girls escaped while militants left to launch an attack .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">Hundreds of girls abducted in April are still believed held hostage.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="16">Boko Haram has recently increased abductions of females.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="7">Boko Haram is trying to impose strict Sharia law across Nigeria.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-08 23:19:18" annotation_time="33.286">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">Their escape is good news, but the Islamist terrorist group is still believed to be holding about 200 schoolgirls abducted April 14 from their hostels in the town of Chibok -- a case that drew international outrage and prompted a global campaign for their release.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="4">The militant group is trying to impose strict Sharia law across Nigeria, the most populous country in Africa.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="1">The female hostages escaped Friday while their captors left their camp to launch an attack against the military and police in the nearby town of Damboa, said Bukar Kyari, a local vigilante fighting Boko Haram in Maiduguri.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="3">Boko Haram has recently intensified abductions of women in northeastern Borno state, where its five-year insurgency is largely concentrated.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Sixty-three women and girls kidnapped by Boko Haram last month in Nigeria escaped from their captors and have returned to their burnt village, a security source and a local vigilante fighting the militant group said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The hostages were seized from the Kummabza village in northern Borno state on June 18 after a four-day invasion of the village by Boko Haram insurgents.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The militants killed 30 men and burned the entire village.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Their escape is good news, but the Islamist terrorist group is still believed to be holding about 200 schoolgirls abducted April 14 from their hostels in the town of Chibok -- a case that drew international outrage and prompted a global campaign for their release.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Boko Haram has been active as a violent group since 2009 and has killed Nigerians, both Christian and Muslim, at rates frequently exceeding 100 people weekly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The name &amp;quot;Boko Haram&amp;quot; translates to &amp;quot;Western education is sin&amp;quot; in the local Hausa language.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The militant group is trying to impose strict Sharia law across Nigeria, the most populous country in Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The group especially opposes the education of women.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Under its version of Sharia law, women should be at home raising children and looking after their husbands, not at school learning to read and write.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;apost;Rare opportunity to escape&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The female hostages escaped Friday while their captors left their camp to launch an attack against the military and police in the nearby town of Damboa, said Bukar Kyari, a local vigilante fighting Boko Haram in Maiduguri.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Soldiers overwhelmed the insurgents, forcing them to mobilize all their men and leave the abducted women in the camp, Kyari said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;The women seized that rare opportunity to escape when they realized they were alone in the camp,&amp;quot; Kyari said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;But we still have five women, including a nursing mother, missing.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>News of the escape was slow to emerge due to trouble with telecommunication towers in the area damaged by previous Boko Haram attacks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Boko Haram has recently intensified abductions of women in northeastern Borno state, where its five-year insurgency is largely concentrated.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>When a group of women and girls abducted in November was later rescued from Boko Haram, some were pregnant.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Others had been forcibly converted to Islam and married off to their kidnappers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>#BringBackOurGirls.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The April kidnapping galvanized international opinion against Boko Haram and inspired the hashtag #BringBackOurGirls.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The terror group abducted an estimated 276 girls April 14 from a boarding school in Chibok in northeastern Nigeria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Dozens escaped, but more than 200 girls are still missing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Since then the insurgents, seemingly galvanized by the attention, have stepped up the frequency and brazenness of the attacks on villages in the region.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Other girls have been kidnapped, but in lesser numbers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The Nigerian government has come under fire for not doing enough to find the girls.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>About a month ago the government tried to stop organized protests for the abducted girls, then backtracked and allowed the protests.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Deadly battles rage on.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Meanwhile, the group continues battling Nigeria&amp;apost;s military.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Its ambitions have apparently expanded to the destruction of the Nigerian government.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>On Friday, at least six soldiers, five police officers and 53 Boko Haram fighters were killed after the militants launched an attack in the town of Bama, the Nigerian Defense Ministry said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Local residents said half the town was burnt, including the police station.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Many of Boko Haram&amp;apost;s attacks take place in the northern part of the country, despite the fact that Nigeria&amp;apost;s northern half is mainly Muslim and the south is mainly Christian.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>But the radical militant group does not consider all Muslims as supporters and allies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Boko Haram has allegedly killed Muslim clerics who have dared to criticize the group.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>And there have been suggestions that it attacks certain mosques because members have spoken out against it and helped federal officials with their crackdown.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Analysts say attacks are aimed at instilling fear in the local population to prevent cooperation with the government.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Mohammed Yusuf, a charismatic young cleric, founded Boko Haram 12 years ago as part of his push for a pure Islamic state in Nigeria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>He was killed in 2009, but his group lived on.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Boko Haram became more violent after his death as his supporters vowed to strike back.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Human Rights Watch estimates that in the past five years, more than 3,000 people have been killed in the violence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>