<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2722" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/04/17/world/meast/saudi-arabia-to-build-tallest-building-ever/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-04-18 02:18:03" category="world" author="Daisy Carrington, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Saudi Arabia to build world&amp;apost;s tallest building 1-kilometer tower</title>
  <keywords>Kingdom Tower,Saudi Arabia,worlds tallest tower,Dubai,Burj Khalifa,Construction Weekly,Saudi Gazette</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Saudi Arabia is set to start on Kingdom Tower, slated to be the world&amp;apost;s tallest building .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">The Kingdom Tower will reach 3,280 feet, have 200 floors and cost $1.2 billion.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">It would require 5.7 million square feet of concrete and 80,000 tons of steel.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="7">The foundations would be 200 feet (60 meters) deep.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-26 19:15:26" annotation_time="74.608665">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Dubai&amp;apost;s iconic Burj Khalifa, the world&amp;apost;s tallest building, could be stripped of its Guinness title if Saudi Arabia succeeds in its plans to construct the even larger Kingdom Tower in Jeddah -- a prospect looking more likely as work begins next week, according to Construction Weekly.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">The Kingdom Tower, estimated to cost $1.23 billion, would have 200 floors and overlook the Red Sea.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">Building it will require about 5.7 million square feet of concrete and 80,000 tons of steel, according to the Saudi Gazette.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="4">The foundations, which will be 200 feet (60 meters) deep, need to be able to withstand the saltwater of the nearby ocean.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Dubai, long champion of all things biggest, longest and most expensive, will soon have some competition from neighboring Saudi Arabia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Dubai&amp;apost;s iconic Burj Khalifa, the world&amp;apost;s tallest building, could be stripped of its Guinness title if Saudi Arabia succeeds in its plans to construct the even larger Kingdom Tower in Jeddah -- a prospect looking more likely as work begins next week, according to Construction Weekly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Consultants Advanced Construction Technology Services have recently announced testing materials to build the 3,280-feet (1 kilometer) skyscraper (the Burj Khalifa, by comparison, stands at a meeker 2,716 feet, or 827 meters).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The Kingdom Tower, estimated to cost $1.23 billion, would have 200 floors and overlook the Red Sea.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Building it will require about 5.7 million square feet of concrete and 80,000 tons of steel, according to the Saudi Gazette.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Building a structure that tall, particularly on the coast, where saltwater could potentially damage it, is no easy feat.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The foundations, which will be 200 feet (60 meters) deep, need to be able to withstand the saltwater of the nearby ocean.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>As a result, Advanced Construction Technology Services will test the strength of different concretes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Wind load is another issue for buildings of this magnitude.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>To counter this challenge, the tower will change shape regularly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;Because it changes shape every few floors, the wind loads go round the building and won&amp;apost;t be as extreme as on a really solid block,&amp;quot; Gordon Gill explained to Construction Weekly.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Gill is a partner at Adrian Smith + Gordon Gill Architecture, the design architects for the project.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Delivering the concrete to higher floors will also be a challenge.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Possibly, engineers could use similar methods to those employed when building the Burj Khalifa; 6 million cubic feet of concrete was pushed through a single pump, usually at night when temperatures were low enough to ensure that it would set.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Though ambitious, building the Kingdom Tower should be feasible, according to Sang Dae Kim, the director of the Council on Tall Buildings.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;At this point in time we can build a tower that is one kilometer, maybe two kilometers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Any higher than that and we will have to do a lot of homework,&amp;quot; he told Construction Weekly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
