<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2631" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/01/05/world/uk-same-sex-bishops/index.html" date_published="2013-01-05 09:52:26" category="world" author="Ben Brumfield, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Priests in same-sex relationships may become Anglican Bishops</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">The priests in same-sex unions must remain celibate.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">The Anglican Church recognizes marriage as being only between a man and a woman.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">Sex should be practiced only within a marriage, the church says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="1">Women may be priests but are not allowed to become bishops.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-06 22:45:14" annotation_time="64.323">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="4">Men in a civil union will now be allowed to become bishops in the Church of England, but they are not allowed to have sex.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">Men and women in same-sex unions were already allowed to serve as priests in the Church of England, but there was a moratorium on advancement to the episcopate -- becoming a bishop -- while the church considered the issue.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">The church defines marriage &amp;quot;as a faithful, committed, permanent and legally sanctioned relationship between a man and a woman, is central to the stability and health of human society.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">It believes sex should be practiced exclusively within a marriage.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Men in a civil union will now be allowed to become bishops in the Church of England, but they are not allowed to have sex.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Intercourse between two men -- or two women -- remains a sin.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;Homosexual genital acts fall short of the Christian ideal and are to be met with a call to repentance and the exercise of compassion,&amp;quot; according to Anglican doctrine.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Men and women in same-sex unions were already allowed to serve as priests in the Church of England, but there was a moratorium on advancement to the episcopate -- becoming a bishop -- while the church considered the issue.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The church announced Friday that if men in celibate civil unions may be priests, then there is no reason for them not to be bishops, as long as they are &amp;quot;living in accordance with the teaching of the Church on human sexuality.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Any priest looking to become a bishop must undergo a thorough examination of &amp;quot;personal and family circumstances,&amp;quot; according to a statement released by the House of Bishops of the Church of England.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Female priests are barred from advancing to the position of bishop, as a vote on the measure in the church failed to pass lay approval last November despite an overwhelming majority of support within the church hierarchy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Women have been permitted to enter the priesthood since the early 1990s.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The church defines marriage &amp;quot;as a faithful, committed, permanent and legally sanctioned relationship between a man and a woman, is central to the stability and health of human society.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>It believes sex should be practiced exclusively within a marriage.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The British parliament is expected to consider legislation allowing same-sex marriage, but the Church of England and the Church in Wales would be prohibited from performing wedding ceremonies as long as it remains against canon law.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>In 2005, Britain allowed same-sex couples to register civil partnerships, prompting the church to consider the issue.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>It does not bless civil unions of any kind, for fear some of them may be sexual.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>But it also does not exclude gays and lesbians from the flock, according to it 2005 deliberations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The Anglican Church is a protestant denomination intimately associated with the American Episcopal Church.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The church and state in Britain are formally connected.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The two archbishops of the church, the Archbishop of Canterbury and the Archbishop of York, along with 24 other bishops, have seats in Parliament in the House of Lords.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Though women may not yet rise to high positions in its clergy, Queen Elizabeth is the Supreme Governor of the Church of England.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
