<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2909" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/10/09/world/americas/haiti-un-cholera-lawsuit/index.html" date_published="2013-10-09 18:05:29" category="world" author="Ivan Watson and Joe Vaccarello, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>U.N. sued for &amp;apost;bringing cholera to Haiti,&amp;apost; causing deadly outbreak</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Lawsuit in U.S federal court accuses U.N. of gross negligence and misconduct.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">Thousands of Haitians died of cholera in 2010, on the heels of a devastating earthquake.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="9">It was determined that sewage leaking from a U.N. base contributed to the outbreak.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="5">Secretary-general has said the U.N. has legal immunity, by international convention.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-09 14:37:04" annotation_time="22.742">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">New York Human rights lawyers filed a class action law suit in a U.S federal court accusing the United Nations of gross negligence and misconduct on behalf of victims of a cholera outbreak in Haiti in 2010.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="4">Earlier this year, however, Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon declared the United Nations could not receive claims for compensation from Haitian cholera victims, arguing that the organization had legal immunity according to an international convention.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">In October 2010, a cholera epidemic exploded in Haiti, striking as the island country was still reeling from a deadly earthquake earlier that year which killed tens of thousands of people.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="3">Several scientific and medical investigators eventually concluded that one of the likely sources of the outbreak was sewage leaking from a U.N. base housing Nepalese peacekeepers.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>New York Human rights lawyers filed a class action law suit in a U.S federal court accusing the United Nations of gross negligence and misconduct on behalf of victims of a cholera outbreak in Haiti in 2010.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;The claims are that the U.N. engaged in reckless and gross negligence and misconduct bringing cholera to Haiti,&amp;quot; said Ira Kurzban, a lawyer and board member with the Boston-based Institute for Justice and Development in Haiti.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The group is demanding financial compensation for the 8,300 Haitians who died as a result of the cholera epidemic as well as some 650,000 more survivors of the illness.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>U.N. spokesman Farhan Haq expressed to CNN &amp;quot;it is not the United Nations&amp;apost; practice to discuss in public claims filed against the Organization.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Earlier this year, however, Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon declared the United Nations could not receive claims for compensation from Haitian cholera victims, arguing that the organization had legal immunity according to an international convention.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>In October 2010, a cholera epidemic exploded in Haiti, striking as the island country was still reeling from a deadly earthquake earlier that year which killed tens of thousands of people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The cholera bacteria, which is not indigenous to Haiti, spread rapidly, ultimately killing an estimated 8,300 people.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The epidemic sparked riots in several cities and towns against the force of some 8,000 U.N. peacekeepers deployed there.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Several scientific and medical investigators eventually concluded that one of the likely sources of the outbreak was sewage leaking from a U.N. base housing Nepalese peacekeepers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The base was perched above a tributary stream leading into the Artibonite River near the town of Meille.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;The way we understand disease transmission today, there is no other good explanation for how a (cholera) strain that was present only in the northeastern region of the Indian subcontinent traveled 9,000 miles to Haiti and happened to end up in a river next to a base with U.N. peacekeepers from Nepal, said Jonathan Katz, a former Associated Press reporter who was one of the first journalists to investigate the source of outbreak in 2010.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Katz, who further investigated the U.N.&amp;apost;s response to the outbreak in his book &amp;quot;The Big Truck That Went By: How the World Came to Save Haiti and Left Behind a Disaster,&amp;quot; accused the United Nations of covering up its responsibility for the cholera epidemic.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;In 2010, the U.N. didn&amp;apost;t want anyone to talk about this,&amp;quot; Katz said, in a phone interview with CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;They were directly castigating anyone who would bring up the topic.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>In September, the prime minister of Haiti raised the issue during a speech before the U.N. General Assembly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;The United Nations has a moral responsibility for the eruption of the epidemic,&amp;quot; said Prime Minister Laurent Lamothe, according to a U.N. transcript.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Lamothe argued that the current efforts made by the U.N. to eradicate cholera were far from sufficient.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>He called for the creation of a joint commission to further study the disease.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>In a briefing to journalists on Wednesday, U.N. spokesman Farhan Haq said as a result of the Haitian epidemic, the organization was in the process of adopting steps to prevent the further spread of the disease.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;Part of our lessons learned from this has been to screen peacekeepers for cholera,&amp;quot; Haq said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Health authorities continue to document thousands of cholera cases a month.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>At least 182 Haitians died of cholera between April and August 2013, according to the World Health Organization.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
