<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2873" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/07/16/world/europe/uk-pedophile-probe/index.html?hpt=hp_t3" date_published="2014-07-16 11:30:07" category="world" author="Laura Smith-Spark, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>UK police arrest 660 suspected pedophiles</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">A six-month UK-wide operation snares 660 suspected pedophiles, police say.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">The operation targeted people accessing indecent images of children online.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">Police say more than 400 children have been protected from harm as a result.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="15">The operation comes amid public concern over the issue of sexual abuse of children.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-11 10:13:24" annotation_time="14.942">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">UK police have arrested 660 suspected pedophiles -- including doctors, teachers and scout leaders -- in a six-month operation spanning the country, the National Crime Agency said Wednesday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">The operation -- which targeted people accessing indecent images of children online -- involved 45 police forces across England, Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">More than 400 children across the United Kingdom have been protected from harm as a result, the National Crime Agency said in a statement.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="4">The operation comes amid wide public concern over the issue of sexual abuse of children in the United Kingdom.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>UK police have arrested 660 suspected pedophiles -- including doctors, teachers and scout leaders -- in a six-month operation spanning the country, the National Crime Agency said Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The operation -- which targeted people accessing indecent images of children online -- involved 45 police forces across England, Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>More than 400 children across the United Kingdom have been protected from harm as a result, the National Crime Agency said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Thirty-nine of the suspects were registered sex offenders, the statement said, meaning the vast majority were not previously known to police.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Their number also included social care workers and former police officers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The operation was kept under wraps until Wednesday to protect children and gather evidence against the accused, the statement said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The National Crime Agency is not revealing the methods used to track down the suspects because it hopes to deploy them again in the future.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The charges brought so far range from possession of indecent images of children to serious sexual assault, it said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Many suspects have yet to be charged in the case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is the first time the UK has had the capability to coordinate a single targeted operation of this nature,&amp;quot; said Phil Gormley, the agency&amp;apost;s deputy director general.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;Our aim was to protect children who were victims of, or might be at risk of, sexual exploitation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>A child is victimized not only when they are abused and an image is taken.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>They are re-victimized every time that image is viewed by someone.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Some of those who start by looking at indecent images online go on to abuse children directly, he said, so arresting them now may prevent them from crossing that line.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The operation comes amid wide public concern over the issue of sexual abuse of children in the United Kingdom.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Children&amp;apost;s TV entertainer Rolf Harris was sentenced this month to five years and nine months in prison for a string of indecent assaults against women and girls.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>His trial came in the wake of shocking revelations of predatory sexual behavior by the late TV host Jimmy Savile against vulnerable children and adults.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The publicity around those high-profile cases appears to have encouraged others to come forward with allegations of abuse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Chief Constable Simon Bailey said the majority of police forces in England and Wales are dealing with an &amp;quot;unprecedented increase&amp;quot; in reports of sexual abuse of children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;Forces are investigating exploitation of children and young people by groups and gangs, non-recent abuse including large-scale investigations into abuse in institutions over many years and sexual abuse by parents and family members,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
