<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2108" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/06/30/world/asia/china-baby-hatches-jinan/index.html?hpt=hp_bn7" date_published="2014-06-30 04:56:22" category="world" author="Connie Young, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>China &amp;apost;baby hatch&amp;apost; inundated with abandoned children</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Jinan &amp;apost;baby hatch&amp;apost; overwhelmed since opening on June 1.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">Over 100 children abandoned, all had disabilities or medical conditions.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">City has had to introduce new rules to reduce number of babies, children.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="37">Babies must now be less than one year old, from the local area.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-21 16:45:14" annotation_time="36.013">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">The government-run orphanage in eastern China opened its first baby hatch on June 1, International Children&amp;apost;s Day, as a symbolic step to show the country&amp;apost;s commitment to improving child welfare.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">However, it since proved so popular that authorities have had to introduce new rules to limit the number of babies and children being abandoned.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">In just 11 days, 106 children, all with disabilities or medical conditions, were dropped off at the Jinan facility, according to local state media.</sentence>
      <sentence id="37" ids_highlights="4">Now, babies must also be less than one year old, and can only be dropped off between the hours of 9 a.m. and 5 p.m.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Jinan, China Along a winding Chinese mountain road dotted with inns and restaurants is Jinan Orphanage, a place of refuge and site for troubled parents to dump unwanted children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The government-run orphanage in eastern China opened its first baby hatch on June 1, International Children&amp;apost;s Day, as a symbolic step to show the country&amp;apost;s commitment to improving child welfare.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>However, it since proved so popular that authorities have had to introduce new rules to limit the number of babies and children being abandoned.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>In just 11 days, 106 children, all with disabilities or medical conditions, were dropped off at the Jinan facility, according to local state media.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>That is more than the 85 orphans the city accepted the entire previous year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>In one reported case, a six-year-old girl was pushed out of a car in front of the hatch.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>In her pocket was $430 and a piece of paper with her birth date and time written on it, according to state media.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Waiting outside the hatch.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>CNN waited outside the hatch on a Tuesday afternoon to see how often it was being used.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The hatch is a small, detached room at the side of the orphanage, equipped with a crib, incubator and air conditioning.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Once the child&amp;apost;s guardian leaves the hatch, the door locks and an alarm sounds, alerting staff to the anonymous drop.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>In the first of two attempted drops, two men walked up to the hatch and started taking photos of a sign with detailed instructions on how to drop off a baby.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The instructions said that parents should leave a date of birth, as well as details of any medical conditions the child may have.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>It also asked people not to take any equipment from the hatch.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Half an hour later, the same two men pulled up in a silver hatchback with a woman in the back.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Orphanage workers and guards scurried over to the car.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The woman told them her baby had a congenital heart disease and they had no money to treat her.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The workers advised the woman to take her baby to the city hospital, which provides free medical services.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>If she could not be treated there, then she could bring the baby back, they said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The men quickly got back into the car drove away.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The second drop, only one hour later, involved a 21-year-old man from Sichuan, a province in southwestern China, who walked up the busy road, cradling a baby and a bag of belongings.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>As the man went to the hatch, orphanage staff and guards stood in his way, preventing him from opening the door.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>He walked back defeated, silent and stony-faced.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>When CNN caught up to him, he broke down in tears, sobbing as he held his baby closer to his chest.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>His son, dressed in clean clothes and a bonnet, was sleeping.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The young man said his baby had water on the brain.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;I just want to leave him there because with the state at least he has hope.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>We have no money.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>We&amp;apost;ve spent everything,&amp;quot; he said as he wept.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The man walked back about a half a mile down the road where his uncle had parked after driving him to the hatch.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>When asked why the orphanage would not accept the baby, the staff replied, &amp;quot;He&amp;apost;s not allowed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>We have regulations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>We only accept people from this city.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The orphanage staff told the father to travel back to his hometown in Sichuan -- more than 1,000 miles away on the other side of the country -- to drop off his baby.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>New rules imposed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>The locals-only rule was applied soon after the hatch opened to try to limit numbers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Now, babies must also be less than one year old, and can only be dropped off between the hours of 9 a.m. and 5 p.m.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>A handful of police, orphanage workers and volunteers stand guard at the hatch 24 hours a day, making it increasingly difficult for any parent to abandon a child anonymously.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>The country is divided on the topic of hatches, with many believing that the government is condoning child abandonment and even encouraging it by opening hatches.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Outside the hatch are prominently placed slogans condemning child abandonment, a reminder from the government that the practice is technically illegal, even though the provision of baby hatches amounts to turning a blind eye to that.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>History of China&amp;apost;s hatches.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>The first pilot hatch was introduced in 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Now there are 32 across the country, according to the official Xinhua news agency.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;We had to find a more humane way to take in abandoned babies,&amp;quot; said Dr. Wang Zhenyao, one of the founders for China&amp;apost;s child welfare policy and a retired Ministry of Civil Affairs official.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>&amp;quot;In reality, children were being thrown into trash cans, on the side of roads, in front of hospitals, or in front of the Ministry of Civil Affairs so we had to standardize it and regulate it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>According to UNICEF, there were around 712,000 orphans in China in 2010, but child welfare groups believe that the number could be in the millions if you account for children in non-government orphanages and foster homes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Unlike in the 1980s and 90s, when most abandoned babies were girls, now most suffer from a range of disabilities and medical conditions, such as cerebral palsy, Down syndrome, congenital heart disease, club feet and cleft lips.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Changing attitudes, improving welfare.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Wang said baby hatches were a step in the right direction for the country, but acknowledged that changing mindsets and improving social welfare would pose a challenge in the years to come.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>&amp;quot;If you don&amp;apost;t give up your child, then nobody will help you,&amp;quot; Wang told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>&amp;quot;But once you abandon your child, the government must take over.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is not a good solution.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>Instead the government should step forward to subsidize parents and enable them to take care of their children.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>This is a simple truth that is hard to explain to society.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>According to Wang, China has only 10,000 social workers handling 100,000 abandoned children, a ratio of one social worker to ten orphans.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>In more developed nations, the ratio is normally two social welfare workers to every orphaned child, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>The Ministry of Civil Affairs seems to have recognized the problem and has set an ambitious target of increasing the number of social welfare workers to two million by 2015.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>Until then, it&amp;apost;s likely the hatches will continue to be used by parents too poor or too overwhelmed to keep their children at home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
