<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2742" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/05/15/world/asia/south-korea-ship-sinking/index.html" date_published="2014-05-15 06:22:39" category="world" author="Jung-eun Kim, Paula Hancocks and Madison Park, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Sewol captain and 3 crew members face murder charges in South Korea</title>
  <keywords>South Korea ship sinking,Sewol</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Captain and three other crew members charged with murder, prosecutor says .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">The four could face death penalty if convicted.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">11 other crew members also face charges of abandonment.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-03 05:22:17" annotation_time="15.190999">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1"> The captain and three other crew members of the Sewol, the South Korean ferry that sank last month, have been charged with murder, chief prosecutor in the investigation Yang Joon-jin said Thursday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">The captain, Lee Joon-seok, along with the chief engineer, and the first and second mates, could face the death penalty if convicted of the charges.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">The remaining 11 crew members have been indicted on charges of abandonment and violating a ship safety act.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The captain and three other crew members of the Sewol, the South Korean ferry that sank last month, have been charged with murder, chief prosecutor in the investigation Yang Joon-jin said Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The captain, Lee Joon-seok, along with the chief engineer, and the first and second mates, could face the death penalty if convicted of the charges.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>But it has been nearly two decades since the capital punishment was last carried out in South Korea.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The remaining 11 crew members have been indicted on charges of abandonment and violating a ship safety act.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The prosecutor&amp;apost;s office said the captain and three crew members were charged with murder, because they didn&amp;apost;t use the ship&amp;apost;s facilities at their disposal -- such as life rafts, life vests and announcements to evacuate passengers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Seven crew members were first to flee the ship, instead of carrying out their responsibility to save the hundreds that remained inside the ferry, the office said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Passengers were instructed not to move and to stay in place as the ferry listed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The Sewol ferry sank en route to Jeju Island on April 16, killing 284 people and leaving 20 others still missing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Most of the passengers were students on a school field trip.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Obstacles in search efforts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>South Korean officials have recovered 242 bodies found inside the ferry and 42 outside the ship.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The maritime police expects search efforts to become more difficult as the currents could strengthen over the next three days.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Operations will be limited, Kim Seok-kyun, head of maritime police, said during a briefing Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The internal structure of the ship, which has been submerged for a month, is becoming weaker and more prone to collapse.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Authorities are looking into the possibility of cutting into the exterior of the ship to make an entrance using the cranes situated at the accident site.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Conduct during sinking.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>On April 16, the order to evacuate ship was never given, prosecutors said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>And none of the crew were prepared to deal with an emergency situation because they had never been trained for such a scenario.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>A few days after the incident, Lee initially defended his actions, saying he had not evacuated passengers because the rescue boats had not arrived yet, and the tide was strong, and the water cold.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Footage of the captain in what looks like his underwear hopping into the arms of the rescuer, while hundreds of passengers remained inside the sinking ship, infuriated South Koreans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Lee had not been at helm of the ferry when it started to sink.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The Sewol disaster caused widespread outrage in South Korea over lax safety standards and the failure to rescue more people as the ship foundered.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Investigators are looking at the overloading, the failure to secure cargo properly, the imbalance of weight on the ferry, and a sudden turn on the ferry as possible reasons for the Sewol&amp;apost;s sinking.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>