<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2065" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/06/10/world/asia/south-korea-sewol-ferry-trial/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-06-10 04:56:08" category="world" author="Paula Hancocks, K.J. Kwon and Greg Botelho, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Angry relatives yell at South Korean ferry captain, crew at trial</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="53">NEW: President says it makes no sense that the ferry company&amp;apost;s believed owner remains at large.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8">Ferry captain pleads not guilty to murder charge tied to the April 16 sinking.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="12">His lawyer says others are &amp;quot;more responsible,&amp;quot; accuses some of shifting blame.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="2">Relatives of the almost 300 people killed on the ferry yell at the crew members in court.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-08 23:24:12" annotation_time="62.046997">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="4">On Tuesday, inside a courtroom in the southwestern South Korean city of Gwangju, relatives of the some 300 killed on that ship -- many of them schoolchildren -- got their chance.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">Lee pleaded not guilty to a murder charge.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;I am concerned that those who are more responsible are shifting blame to the defendant,&amp;quot; said the attorney.</sentence>
      <sentence id="53" ids_highlights="1">The President said Tuesday in a statement that prosecutors and police had been working hard to arrest Yoo and that &amp;quot;it doesn&amp;apost;t make sense that he is still not caught.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>They&amp;apost;ve waited for this day for nearly two months -- to look the crew of the doomed Sewol ferry in the eyes and tell them how they felt.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>On Tuesday, inside a courtroom in the southwestern South Korean city of Gwangju, relatives of the some 300 killed on that ship -- many of them schoolchildren -- got their chance.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Yelling and screaming, those with loved ones from that stricken ferry vented Tuesday at Capt. Lee Joon-seok and 14 members of his crew.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>As a family representative explained in court, while weeks have passed since the April 16 sinking, their grief and anger have not.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;For us, time has stopped,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;When I see students wearing school uniforms, I feel like my child will come back home and say, &amp;apost;Dad, I&amp;apost;m home.&amp;apost;&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>While there&amp;apost;s no bringing back those killed, the trial does intend to bring a degree of justice -- though both sides have very different ideas on what that entails.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Lee pleaded not guilty to a murder charge.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>According to his lawyer, the captain is already living with guilt from the fact he left the ferry before everybody was rescued.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Attorney Lee Gwang-jae said that Lee was only helming the ship for six days, he was the last rescued of all the crew members and he wasn&amp;apost;t in charge of loading cargo.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Investigators have said a vast amount of cargo, more than double the ferry&amp;apost;s limit, and the failure to tie it down properly were partly responsible for the capsizing of the Sewol, which was carrying 476 passengers and crew.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am concerned that those who are more responsible are shifting blame to the defendant,&amp;quot; said the attorney.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Some in the court weren&amp;apost;t convinced -- yelling after the lawyer&amp;apost;s statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>And, of course, neither was the prosecution.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>According to its version of events, the crew members could have carried out a far more effective rescue operation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>They could have listened to requests for help, rather than ignored them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>They could have made taking care of the passengers their first priority, rather than taking care of themselves.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>According to the prosecution, what several members of the crew did can be summed up in one word: Murder.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>292 confirmed dead, 12 still missing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The captain and three of his crew members are facing murder charges.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>If convicted, they could face the death penalty, although it has been nearly two decades since capital punishment was last carried out in South Korea.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The other crew members have been indicted on charges of abandonment and violating a ship safety act.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The accused entered the Gwangju courtroom Tuesday wearing light green or light blue outfits.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>They were told to asked to stand and state their names, national ID numbers and addresses, before prosecutors read out the charges.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>A judge, not a jury, will decide their fate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>His decision could provide a degree of closure to the family members.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>But the feelings are still raw about the sinking of a vessel that should have been on a fairly routine four-day excursion from the city of Ansan to Jeju Island.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The anger has been directed in many ways.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Some blame the ferry company, saying it put profits before people in dangerously loading so much cargo.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Others have chastised the government, for what they see as an inadequate response as well as regulation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>And -- as was obvious in court Tuesday -- many blast crew members for not sounding the alarm sooner and doing more to help passengers to safety.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Dozens of passengers did survive.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Some 292 others are confirmed dead.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Twelve others remain missing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Lawyer questions: Is a fair trial possible?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>The ferry&amp;apost;s owner, Chonghaejin Shipping Company, was targeted Tuesday by prosecutors who claimed it put money -- by loading so much cargo -- above all else.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>But the crew is also culpable, the prosecution says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>The cargo was not just overloaded, but badly secured, it says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Then there are the allegations that that the crew did not use facilities at their disposal, such as life rafts, life vests and announcements to evacuate passengers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Instead, according to officials, passengers were told to stay where they were.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>President Park Geun-hye has already reached her own conclusion, calling the actions of the captain and surviving crew &amp;quot;akin to murder.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>That kind of attitude -- even before the trial began -- led a lawyer who visited the captain and two crew members in custody to question whether the trial can be fair.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Attorney Kang Jung-min says Sewol crew members have been demonized by the Korean media.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Kang told CNN: &amp;quot;The public and the court does not have a good impression of the crew members, so the crew are likely to become the scapegoats.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Search for ferry company owner.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Meanwhile, the hunt continues for South Korea&amp;apost;s most wanted man, who is believed to have ties to the company that operated the ill-fated Sewol ferry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Billionaire Yoo Byung Eun, 73, and his two sons are believed to have controlled the Chonghaejin Shipping Company through an investment vehicle and subsidiary, according to the semi-official Yonhap news agency.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Yoo is wanted for questioning in connection with an investigation into alleged funds embezzlement, tax evasion and other irregularities that prosecutors say could have contributed to the sinking, and a warrant has been issued for his arrest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>South Korean TV channel YTN reported Wednesday that some 6,000 police officers had entered a large religious compound owned by the Evangelical Baptist Church, also known as Gu Won Pa -- in which Yoo is a leading religious figure.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>A number of arrests have taken place, YTN reported.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>The officers are searching for Yoo and his son, as well as suspects believed to have helped him avoid arrest so far.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="37">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Four members of the religious group were arrested last month, accused of aiding him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="38">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>The President said Tuesday in a statement that prosecutors and police had been working hard to arrest Yoo and that &amp;quot;it doesn&amp;apost;t make sense that he is still not caught.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="39">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>She said authorities should look again at whether additional methods can be used, and that all measures should be considered so that Yoo faces justice.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="40">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>In late April, Yoo&amp;apost;s representatives sent a statement denying that he had any direct or indirect connection to Chonghaejin Marine Company.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>