<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2018" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/12/21/world/africa/harassmap-egypt-mobile-phones/index.html" date_published="2012-12-21 10:58:55" category="world" author="Ian Lee and Teo Kermeliotis, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>&amp;apost;Harassment map&amp;apost; helps Egyptian women stand up for their rights</title>
  <keywords>harassmap sexual harassment egypt</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">HarassMap aims to end the social acceptability of sexual harassment in Egypt.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">Women use its SMS-based system to to report incidents anonymously.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="12">Community outreach teams visit the sexual harassment hotspots to raise awareness.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="37">The group also uses mobile phones to provide victims with details of how to access services.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-10 13:16:08" annotation_time="24.793">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">Called HarassMap, the volunteer-based initiative is aiming to stop the social acceptability of sexual harassment in the North African country.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">HarassMap uses a simple SMS-based system to enable victims and witnesses to anonymously report sexual harassment incidents as soon as they happen.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="3">When sexual harassment hotspots are identified, HarrassMap volunteers visit these areas as part of a community outreach program aimed at raising awareness and ending tolerance of these kinds of incidents.</sentence>
      <sentence id="37" ids_highlights="4">Chiao, who set up the group after experiencing sexual harassment herself in Egypt, says that HarassMap is also using mobile technology to provide victims with details of how to access free support services.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>From fighting cancer and sparking revolutions to digitally transferring cash and bringing people together, mobile phones are increasingly being used in pioneering ways across Africa, helping to save lives and transform the continent.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>And the omnipresent devices are also on the front line in the fight against sexual harassment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>In Egypt, where verbal harassment, groping, stalking and indecent exposure are a common problem for women, an innovative tool has emerged to empower victims.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Called HarassMap, the volunteer-based initiative is aiming to stop the social acceptability of sexual harassment in the North African country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>It uses online and offline technology to invite women to speak out and also mobilize communities to stand up to harassers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>How it works.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>HarassMap uses a simple SMS-based system to enable victims and witnesses to anonymously report sexual harassment incidents as soon as they happen.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;You dial 6069 and then you type what happened and where,&amp;quot; explains Rebecca Chiao, who co-founded HarassMap at the end of 2010.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;Then you send and then in a minute or so you should get an auto-response.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Read: Innovation to save lives in Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The group then verifies the incoming reports and places them on a Google map of Egypt, creating a web-based documentation of the extent of the problem.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>When sexual harassment hotspots are identified, HarrassMap volunteers visit these areas as part of a community outreach program aimed at raising awareness and ending tolerance of these kinds of incidents.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are trying to change the social attitude and make it completely unacceptable,&amp;quot; says Chiao, an American who moved to Egypt in 2004 to work for an NGO.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>She adds: &amp;quot;We have teams of volunteers that go out once per month in their own neighborhoods and talk to their own neighbors in groups.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;They ask people who have a presence in the street -- shop owners, police, the guys that park the car, the doormen, the people who are hanging out in the street all the time -- and ask them to be watchful guardians of their neighborhoods.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;They ask them to watch out for sexual harassment and not ignore it and to speak against the harassers when they see it happen.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Chiao says the community outreach program has already had a big impact.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;About eight out of every 10 people they talk to in the street agree by the end of the conversation,&amp;quot; she explains.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;At the beginning everyone disagrees but by the time the conversation is over most people are not just agreeing but they are enthusiastic and want to take action.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;apost;Do you like sex with me?&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>On the HarrassMap website, victims&amp;apost; reports give a disturbing insight into sexual harassment on the streets of Egypt.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;On friday this week i went to a burger stand on sharia mansouriya near al aded street in Darassa and was asked where i was from.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>after i said i was from canada he said &amp;quot;canada helwa&amp;quot; and grabbed my hand towards his and said &amp;apost;do you like sex with me&amp;apost;?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>this was at 12pm,&amp;quot; reads one report posted on December 7.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Another one, from November 29, says: &amp;quot;I was getting off the train from Cairo to Alexandria in Sidi Gaber train station.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The train porter groped me three times while I was trying to get off the train with my suitcase.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>I challenged him the first time, and he pretended it was an accident, and then he did it two more times.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The issue of sexual harassment in Egypt grabbed international headlines in 2011 when CBS reporter Lara Logan was attacked in Cairo&amp;apost;s Tahrir Square after former president Hosni Mubarak stepped down.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Other women reported incidents ranging from mild harassment to violent attacks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>According to a 2008 survey of 1,010 women conducted by the Egyptian Center for Women&amp;apost;s Rights, 98% of foreign women in the country and 83% of Egyptian women said they had been sexually harassed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Chiao, however, says that more studies are needed to get a better insight into the problem.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;We can&amp;apost;t say today how bad the problem really is and that&amp;apost;s one of the things that we&amp;apost;re trying to do with HarassMap,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The power of mobile.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>In Egypt, total mobile subscriptions have jumped from nearly 13 million in 2005 to over 80 million last year, according to a recent World Bank study.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>In the whole of Africa, there were nearly 650 million mobile subscriptions in early 2012, more than in the United States or the European Union, making the continent the second fastest growing region in the world, after South Asia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>It is this explosive growth in mobile usage that initiatives like HarassMap are tapping into in order to change behaviors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Chiao, who set up the group after experiencing sexual harassment herself in Egypt, says that HarassMap is also using mobile technology to provide victims with details of how to access free support services.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;A lot of the women&amp;apost;s NGOs in Egypt offer services like free legal help, how to make a police report, psychological counseling, self-defense classes,&amp;quot; explains Chiao.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;So we took this opportunity to send an outgoing message to everyone who sends a report, telling them how to access these services.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>