<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2890" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/08/15/world/europe/ukraine-crisis/index.html?hpt=ieu_c2" date_published="2014-08-15 09:02:50" category="world" author="Victoria Butenko, Jason Hanna and Jethro Mullen, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Ukraine: We destroyed much of Russian military convoy</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">NEW: Foreign ministers from Russia, Ukraine, Germany, France to meet Sunday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Ukraine says it destroyed part of Russian military convoy that crossed border.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">British media outlets report they saw military vehicles cross from Russia into Ukraine.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="6">Ukrainian border guards are examining Russian aid trucks at a checkpoint, authorities say.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2015-01-30 14:59:10" annotation_time="41.09">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2"> Ukraine claims its artillery destroyed much of a military convoy that crossed from Russia into Ukraine this week -- an incursion that two British newspapers say they witnessed.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">Russia&amp;apost;s foreign ministry has denied any such incursion, and its foreign minister will meet in Berlin with his counterparts from Ukraine, Germany and France on Sunday, state-run news agency RIA-Novosti reported.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="4">Meanwhile, a separate Russian convoy -- more than 200 trucks that Moscow says contain relief goods for civilians in war-torn eastern Ukraine -- remained parked on the Russian side of the border, waiting for Ukrainian and other inspectors to decide whether to approve the aid&amp;apost;s entry.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">The Guardian reported that it witnessed 23 armored personnel carriers, in addition to other vehicles with Russian military plates, cross into Ukraine through a gap in a barbed wire fence.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Ukraine claims its artillery destroyed much of a military convoy that crossed from Russia into Ukraine this week -- an incursion that two British newspapers say they witnessed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>If true, Ukraine&amp;apost;s account and the British reports appear to give credence to what Kiev has long alleged -- that Russia has been sending troops and arms into eastern Ukraine, where pro-Russian rebels have battled the Ukrainian military for months.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>A diplomatic row was brewing Friday over the reports, with the United Kingdom&amp;apost;s foreign office summoning Russia&amp;apost;s ambassador in London to explain the incident.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Russia&amp;apost;s foreign ministry has denied any such incursion, and its foreign minister will meet in Berlin with his counterparts from Ukraine, Germany and France on Sunday, state-run news agency RIA-Novosti reported.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The meeting&amp;apost;s agenda wasn&amp;apost;t immediately released.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Meanwhile, a separate Russian convoy -- more than 200 trucks that Moscow says contain relief goods for civilians in war-torn eastern Ukraine -- remained parked on the Russian side of the border, waiting for Ukrainian and other inspectors to decide whether to approve the aid&amp;apost;s entry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>That Ukraine so far has blocked the aid reflects Kiev&amp;apost;s concerns -- held even before Thursday&amp;apost;s reported military incursion -- that Russia might try to smuggle more military supplies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Ukraine: Majority of vehicles destroyed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Those concerns took on a new light when British media outlets The Guardian and The Telegraph reported that armored personnel carriers, along with other vehicles with Russian military plates, crossed the border near , on Thursday night.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The Guardian reported that it witnessed 23 armored personnel carriers, in addition to other vehicles with Russian military plates, cross into Ukraine through a gap in a barbed wire fence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;Armed men were visible in the gloom by the border fence as the column moved into Ukraine,&amp;quot; the Guardian report reads.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>This is the first time foreign media recorded such an incursion, though it illustrates what Kiev has said has been happening for months -- that Russia has been sending troops and equipment to help the rebels -- Ukrainian military Col. Andriy Lysenko told reporters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Ukrainian President Petro Poroshenko told British Prime Minister David Cameron that Ukrainian forces destroyed &amp;quot;the majority&amp;quot; of the Russian vehicles, Poroshenko&amp;apost;s office said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Poroshenko &amp;quot;expressed concern over the situation on the border, particularly over the fact that the inflow of Russian arms and military machines in Ukraine through the open part of the border continued,&amp;quot; his office said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Lysenko said he didn&amp;apost;t know exactly how many vehicles crossed the border, or how many Ukraine&amp;apost;s artillery managed to destroy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Purported humanitarian convoy still in Russia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Back in southern Russia, across the border from Ukraine&amp;apost;s Luhansk region, 59 Ukrainian border guards and customs officers were inspecting the scores of trucks that Moscow says contain aid for civilians affected by fighting, the Ukrainian military said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Despite Ukraine&amp;apost;s suspicions, Lysenko said that the aid is needed and that Ukraine would allow the Red Cross to distribute it if Ukraine and the aid group find the material suitable.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Months of fighting has killed hundreds of people and, aid groups say, left thousands in eastern Ukraine without access to water, electricity and proper medical aid.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The Red Cross is trying to establish what exactly is in the trucks, Andre Loersch, a Red Cross spokesman in Kiev, said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The Red Cross &amp;quot;will temporarily deploy additional personnel to Ukraine and Russia for the purpose of this operation and is already in the process of identifying its staff ready for deployment,&amp;quot; Loersch said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;A four-member team is already present today in the vicinity of the convoy, and more staff are on their way.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Moscow says the trucks contain grain, sugar, baby food, medical supplies and sleeping bags.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Ukraine, meanwhile, says it is distributing its own aid through the Red Cross.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The Kiev-recognized governor of Luhansk, Irina Verigina, said this week that she doesn&amp;apost;t want aid from Russia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;They send us tanks and Grads (rocket-launching vehicles) overnight and offer to send humanitarian aid by day,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Battle rages on.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Tens of thousands of Ukrainian troops have recently stepped up efforts to retake areas in and around Luhansk, Donetsk and Horlivka, three cities held by rebels for months.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Donetsk has been the scene of intense shelling for days as rebels try to hold off Ukrainian forces.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Eleven civilians were killed in a 24-hour period straddling Thursday and Friday, the Donetsk mayor&amp;apost;s office said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Many districts were without power and water, the mayor&amp;apost;s office said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>A CNN crew that was in Donetsk earlier noted that the shelling had pushed some residents underground into cellars and half-built basements.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Five Ukrainian troops were killed in the past day, Lysekno said Friday, adding that some rebels were retreating, trying to dig in closer to the Ukraine-Russia border.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The ongoing fighting -- sparked last year with a political crisis over whether Ukraine would seek closer ties with Europe or Russia -- has left more than 2,000 people dead and just under 5,000 wounded in eastern Ukraine since mid-April, according to estimates from U.N. officials.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The United States and the European Union have applied steadily increasing sanctions against Russian officials, banks and other interests since March, when Russia annexed the Black Sea Ukrainian peninsula of Crimea.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Russia&amp;apost;s move came a month after Ukraine&amp;apost;s parliament ousted pro-Moscow President Viktor Yanukovych.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Yanukovych left office after violent protests against his government in the capital, Kiev.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Those protests were motivated in part by his decision to back out of a trade deal with the European Union in favor of closer ties with Russia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>