<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2718" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/05/14/world/africa/jonathan-jansen-south-africa/index.html" date_published="2012-05-14 12:21:57" category="world" author="Jessica Ellis and Diane McCarthy, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>S. Africa&amp;apost;s first black dean teaches &amp;apost;reconciliation over revenge&amp;apost;</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">Professor Jonathan Jansen is one of South Africa&amp;apost;s top academics .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">He is the rector of the University of the Free State in Bloemfontein.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="28">Jansen is passionate about teaching his moral code: reconciliation over retribution.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="7">He is also an author, columnist and the president of the South African Institute of Race Relations.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-28 14:02:58" annotation_time="72.69601" mapping_time_divergence="36.348003">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">As rector of the formerly all-white educational institution in Bloemfontein, South Africa, Jansen is about to use his graduation ceremony speech to teach his students one last lesson.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">Jansen, the first black dean of education at the University of the Free State, is one of South Africa&amp;apost;s leading academics and intellectuals.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="4">&amp;quot;The way out of poverty is through learning and those basic values I have carried with me throughout my leadership,&amp;quot; says Jansen, who is not only an academic but has a wider audience as author, newspaper columnist and the president of the South African Institute of Race Relations.</sentence>
      <sentence id="28" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;I don&amp;apost;t care what else you&amp;apost;ve learned at the University of the Free State,&amp;quot; he tells the graduates, &amp;quot;but you know this is a university that in the world is regarded as a place that chooses reconciliation over revenge, that chooses compassion over striking back, that chooses mercy over retaliation.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Bloemfontein, South Africa It&amp;apost;s graduation day and professor Jonathan Jansen strolls around the campus of the University of the Free State.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Every now and then he stops to greet his gown-clad students, standing out amid a crowd of beaming parents and proudly grinning teachers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>As rector of the formerly all-white educational institution in Bloemfontein, South Africa, Jansen is about to use his graduation ceremony speech to teach his students one last lesson.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;I urge you, in a country where there&amp;apost;s still a lot of rage, never respond by rage, respond through reason and you will have gotten not just a degree, but an education,&amp;quot; says Jansen, looking into the eyes of his students.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Jansen, the first black dean of education at the University of the Free State, is one of South Africa&amp;apost;s leading academics and intellectuals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Throughout his long and esteemed educational career, which has taken him from teaching biology in high school classrooms to leading one of South Africa&amp;apost;s premier learning institutions, Jansen has been doing everything he can to keep education uppermost in the minds of his students.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;The way out of poverty is through learning and those basic values I have carried with me throughout my leadership,&amp;quot; says Jansen, who is not only an academic but has a wider audience as author, newspaper columnist and the president of the South African Institute of Race Relations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The son of a preacher, Jansen was born in Cape Flats, a violent, gang-infested area on the fringes of Cape Town.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Life was tough for the future educator, coming of age in a country plagued by apartheid -- he says that growing up as a black boy in Cape Flats, there was a &amp;quot;greater chance&amp;quot; of going to prison than going to university.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>But despite the disadvantages of his surroundings, Jansen believes he thrived, thanks largely to the example set by his parents -- he described them as &amp;quot;Old Testament figures -- my father being Abraham, my mother being Sarah.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;Here you had parents that raised you in a bubble of decency, of this is what you do and don&amp;apost;t do, this is the direction out of poverty,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Even though his parents&amp;apost; families were both materially dispossessed under Apartheid, Jansen says his father and mother raised their children with a strong sense of not being bitter, of being generous to those who are poor and of living a life &amp;quot;without respect for color.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;That helped us enormously,&amp;quot; he says, &amp;quot;so as I looked outside I could see people killing each other, I witnessed the rape of women, I saw horrible things happening around me, but it was as if it did not happen because in this bubble that Abraham and Sarah raised us, there was an understanding of yourself that was unshakeable -- central to that was education.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Passionate about the transformative power of knowledge, Jansen holds strong opinions about the state of education in South Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>He argues that years of maladministration left the country with a failing state education system.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>He is also regularly heard lambasting the country&amp;apost;s low teaching standards, which allow students in some cases to pass exams with as little as 30%.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s odd for me because it&amp;apost;s like we don&amp;apost;t get it that in a modern interconnected economy you better be up there playing with the best,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;I take this to be another symptom of how we&amp;apost;ve succumbed to the apartheid message that we can&amp;apost;t, that we&amp;apost;re inferior, that we need to beg for participation and that does much more damage than any politician can imagine.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>A firm believer of the society&amp;apost;s responsibility to insist on a qualitative education system, Jansen, a Fulbright scholar, assumed his current role at the University of the Free State in 2009 after the institution faced controversy over racism and racial integration.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>In 2008, a video surfaced of four white students at the university urging at least five black housekeepers to eat what appeared to be urine-tainted beef stew.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The incident sparked national outcry and shed light over South Africa&amp;apost;s racial integration problems.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Citing reconciliation &amp;quot;on a deeply divided campus,&amp;quot; Jansen decided to invite the students to return to the university and resume their studies, regardless of their legal consequences.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;We decided ... to offer to the boys an institutional message of forgiveness and acceptance, that they could come back in and participate in a process of reconciliation with the people that they had hurt.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The students were fined after pleading guilty to deliberately injuring another person&amp;apost;s dignity, but they rebuffed Jansen&amp;apost;s invitation to return to the university.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Jansen was roundly criticized for that gesture, which only served to contribute to his reputation for being outspoken.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;If in the process of forgiving and reconciling, we enable other transformations to take place, which is exactly what happened, then that is a better way to go than the thirst -- the understandable thirst let me say -- for vengeance,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Back at the graduation ceremony, Jansen&amp;apost;s moral code of reconciliation over retribution returns once again.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;I don&amp;apost;t care what else you&amp;apost;ve learned at the University of the Free State,&amp;quot; he tells the graduates, &amp;quot;but you know this is a university that in the world is regarded as a place that chooses reconciliation over revenge, that chooses compassion over striking back, that chooses mercy over retaliation.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
