<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2066" link="http://www.cnn.com/2011/10/20/world/asia/china-dog-meat-rescue/index.html" date_published="2011-10-20 04:42:46" category="world" author="Jaime FlorCruz and Tian Shao, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Animal rights group rescues 800 dogs from China meat trade</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Nearly 800 dogs were rescued by a Chinese animal protection group.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">The caged dogs were headed to slaughter for dog meat restaurants .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">Dog meat is a popular dish in certain regions of China, but now under attack.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="25">In April 520 dogs were saved from dinner table by Chinese animal-rights activists.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-17 14:31:25" annotation_time="39.702">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Nearly 800 dogs were rescued by a Chinese animal protection group last Saturday night in the city of Zigong, in southwest Sichuan province.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">Last Friday night, a volunteer tipped off the group that hundreds of caged dogs were being loaded onto trucks in Zigong and headed to various restaurants in Southern Guangxi province.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">Dog meat has long been a popular dish in certain regions of China.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="4">In April 520 dogs were saved from dinner table by Chinese animal-rights activists who stopped a truck carrying them in cages on a highway near Beijing.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Nearly 800 dogs were rescued by a Chinese animal protection group last Saturday night in the city of Zigong, in southwest Sichuan province.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The Qiming Center, an animal-rights protection group in Sichuan, pulled off the rescue.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Last Friday night, a volunteer tipped off the group that hundreds of caged dogs were being loaded onto trucks in Zigong and headed to various restaurants in Southern Guangxi province.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The group dispatched a team of five to block the dog-trader while they posted microblogs online calling for help from animal-loving citizens.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>After a standoff and negotiation, the group agreed to pay the dog trader 83,000 yuan ($13,000) to secure the caged dogs&amp;apost; freedom, said Qiming president Qiao Wei.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s a compromise we took in an effort to let the dogs free - they are visibly suffering for being packed in small cages with very limited space.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>We spent hours negotiating with the trader,&amp;quot; Qiao told CNN in a phone interview.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;Finally with the help of local government he was willing to hand over the dogs in exchange for 83,000 yuan - 60,000 for personal compensation, another 20,000 for cages that we lack.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Qiming volunteers are now helping settle down the dogs, according to state-run media.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Dog meat has long been a popular dish in certain regions of China.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>But over time this cultural and culinary tradition is getting more and more unpopular, as international and Chinese animal protection organizations increase pressure against the dog meat trade.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Most dogs rescued Saturday were severely dehydrated.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Rescuers photographed and registered the dogs before tending to their health.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s a costly work but workers at the center are trying their best to take care of the dogs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Since their arrival, only one dog has died due to respiration system failure,&amp;quot; Qiao told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Ms Teng, a Qiming Center employee, said four full-time staff have been working round the clock.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>On the center&amp;apost;s official blog, the group frequently updates the dogs&amp;apost; latest conditions and solicits donations or voluntary assistance from animal lovers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Some dogs were stolen, and now their owners come to us to take back their pets.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Many would leave with a certain amount of money as appreciation for our work,&amp;quot; Teng told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;Once we&amp;apost;ve finished the health check up procedures, we&amp;apost;ll start helping the dogs find new homes.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Teng says through the rescue she and her fellow volunteers hope to send the general public one message: &amp;quot;No trading, no killing.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Meanwhile, dog trading remains rife in certain regions in China due to lack of a national law on animal welfare and protection.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;A major part of our work is proposing drafts of laws and regulations under which the government can effectively punish this kind of behavior,&amp;quot; Qiao added.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;Now we can only tackle the traders one at a time, and can hardly tell whether they&amp;apost;ll go back to the business again.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>In April 520 dogs were saved from dinner table by Chinese animal-rights activists who stopped a truck carrying them in cages on a highway near Beijing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>A 15-hour standoff between volunteers and the trader caused a temporary shut-down of nearby exits, until an agreement was reached.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The truck driver let the dogs free for 115,000 yuan.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The incident stirred online discussions about how far activists should go in protecting animal rights - a concept still under debate in China.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
