<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2188" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/17/world/asia/thailand-british-tourist-deaths-tribute/index.html?hpt=ias_c2" date_published="2014-09-17 07:07:22" category="world" author="Kocha Olarn and Katie Hunt, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Families pay tribute to Britons killed on Thai beach</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">The man and woman were found dead early Monday on a beach on Koh Tao.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Families pay tribute to the two tourists, who were said to have met only recently.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">Police said they were looking for a British man in connection with the deaths.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="10">But they are still pursuing other lines of inquiry.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-03 12:47:53" annotation_time="62.220333">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2, 3">Bangkok, Thailand The families of two Britons battered to death on a popular Thai resort island have paid tribute to them, as police said they were looking for a British man in connection with their killings.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">The bodies of the two tourists, identified as David Miller, 24, and Hannah Witheridge, 23, were found on a beach on the small southern island of Koh Tao on Monday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="4">However, Prachum told CNN that they were still pursuing other leads.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Bangkok, Thailand The families of two Britons battered to death on a popular Thai resort island have paid tribute to them, as police said they were looking for a British man in connection with their killings.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The bodies of the two tourists, identified as David Miller, 24, and Hannah Witheridge, 23, were found on a beach on the small southern island of Koh Tao on Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>In a statement issued by the British Embassy in Bangkok, Witheridge&amp;apost;s family said she was &amp;quot;a beautiful, intelligent, loving young woman who poured joy into the lives of all who knew her&amp;quot; and they were &amp;quot;utterly devastated and shocked by what has happened.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Miller&amp;apost;s family said: &amp;quot;David was an artist by temperament, so talented.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>He had a creative eye that he carried with him through life and in his degree.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>He was hard-working, bright and conscientious, with everything to look forward to.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Col. Prachum Ruangthong, the police chief of the local precinct, said on Wednesday one line of inquiry focused on a British friend of the male victim.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>He said that police had interviewed the man, who shared a room with the victim, but he had since left the island.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>He added that he had asked the British Embassy for their help in locating the man.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>However, Prachum told CNN that they were still pursuing other leads.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>He added that &amp;quot;from initial forensic examination, the victims were repeatedly hit.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Police issued a grainy image from a CCTV camera outside the bar where the two tourists were last seen.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>They said they were interested in speaking with the person, who they said was an Asian man.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Robbery ruled out.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The deaths are being investigated as murders and police said they had ruled out robbery as a motive for attack.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The victims were discovered partially undressed with severe injuries to their heads, and a hoe with blood on it was found near the bodies, police said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The two Britons were last seen hanging out with friends at a bar in the early hours of Monday before leaving together, said Maj. Gen. Kiatthipong Khaosumarng, the provincial police chief.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The deaths have shaken residents on the idyllic island, which takes up only 21 square kilometers (8 square miles) amid bright blue waters in the Gulf of Thailand.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Authorities said it was the first homicide case on Koh Tao in at least eight years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The island is popular among tourists for its diving locations, white sand beaches and vibrant nightlife.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Police said that interviews with friends of the victims indicated that the two Britons may have only recently met while on the nearby larger island of Koh Phangan before traveling to Koh Tao for a party excursion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The British Consul arrived in Koh Tao on Tuesday, the British Embassy in Bangkok said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Embassy is urgently seeking information from the local authorities and Consular staff stand ready to provide assistance to friends and family at this tragic time,&amp;quot; it said in a statement, declining to give any further details on the case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
