<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2180" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/05/25/world/europe/eu-elections/index.html" date_published="2014-05-25 19:21:06" category="world" author="Catherine E. Shoichet and Jim Boulden, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>EU elections: Far-right parties poised to gain ground</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="22">NEW: Vote shows the French &amp;quot;no longer want to be directed from the outside,&amp;quot; Le Pen says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">&amp;quot;The result is a shock, an earthquake,&amp;quot; French Prime Minister Manuel Valls says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">France&amp;apost;s far-right National Front party poised to win a nationwide vote for the first time.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="7">Voters across Europe have been casting ballots for 751 seats from 28 countries.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-10 13:21:14" annotation_time="26.287">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="3"> France&amp;apost;s far-right National Front has won a nationwide election for the first time, as far-right parties across Europe caused a political &amp;quot;earthquake,&amp;quot; with a string of victories in voting for the European Parliament.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">It is a shock, an earthquake.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="4">Voters across Europe have been casting ballots for days in the parliamentary vote.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="1">They no longer want to be directed from outside,&amp;quot; she said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>France&amp;apost;s far-right National Front has won a nationwide election for the first time, as far-right parties across Europe caused a political &amp;quot;earthquake,&amp;quot; with a string of victories in voting for the European Parliament.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The National Front, led by Marine Le Pen, notched up 24.95% of the vote in France, according to official estimates, well ahead of mainstream parties UMP and the Socialist Party.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Le Pen said the win showed that people want to see change in Europe.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>France&amp;apost;s Socialist Prime Minister Manuel Valls said the result was &amp;quot;more than a warning.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>It is a shock, an earthquake.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Right-wing parties also gained ground in the UK, Denmark and Austria, according to projections posted on the European Parliament&amp;apost;s official elections website.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Voters across Europe have been casting ballots for days in the parliamentary vote.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>There are 751 seats from 28 countries up for grabs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>With most of the ballots counted, provisional results indicate that left-center and right-center parties will still hold a majority of seats in the European Parliament, which plays a key role in shaping European laws and will weigh in on who the European Commission&amp;apost;s next President should be.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>But right-wing parties and other so-called Euroskeptic groups who oppose the European Union are gaining ground, said Simon Usherwood, an expert on European politics at the University of Surrey.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think what&amp;apost;s really changed is you&amp;apost;re seeing a lot more groups on the edges, particularly with the far right, who are going to be much more of a feature of the next five years of the parliament,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>So what does that mean?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;They don&amp;apost;t have enough votes to stop legislation going through,&amp;quot; Usherwood told CNN, &amp;quot;but what they will get, particularly on the far right, is the time for speaking in debates, the chairmanship of certain committees, which means that they&amp;apost;re going to have much more of a platform on which they can sell their message to voters.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>In France, which has 74 seats in the European Parliament, the National Front won 24.95% of votes, according to official estimates, coming in ahead of the center-right UMP, which scored 20.8%, and President Francois Hollande&amp;apost;s Socialist Party, which came in third with 14%.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Even though the vote was for a regional legislative body, the potential impact on France&amp;apost;s national political landscape was clear on Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The results sparked stunned reactions from some French politicians and triumphant victory speeches from others.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>PM Valls described the election as &amp;quot;a very serious moment for France and for Europe,&amp;quot; noting that projections indicate that voters are skeptical of the European Union.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;None of us can shirk their responsibilities,&amp;quot; he said, according to a summary of his remarks posted on the French government&amp;apost;s website.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Meanwhile, National Front leader Marine Le Pen said the results showed that French voters wanted more control.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;The sovereign people have proclaimed that they want to take back the reigns of their destiny into their hands.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Our people demand one type of politics: politics of the French, for the French, with the French.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>They no longer want to be directed from outside,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>She said the vote shows that President Francois Hollande should dissolve France&amp;apost;s parliament, where most lawmakers come from mainstream political parties.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Nearly 400 million Europeans were eligible to vote in the parliamentary elections.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Turnout was just over 43%, slightly higher than it was during the last vote in 2009, Parliament spokesman Jaume Duch said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;The clear message here is that people are unhappy with the way mainstream political parties have handled the economic crisis, and they&amp;apost;re giving them a good kicking,&amp;quot; said Petros Fassoulas, chairman of the pro-Europe European Movement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Before the election, analysts predicted that protest parties were likely to triumph at the polls.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Those parties are demanding tighter border controls, nationalized decision-making and a dissolution of the currency union.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>But they have little in common aside from a dislike of the Brussels bureaucracy, so it&amp;apost;s difficult for them to find much common ground, Usherwood said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;They can agree they don&amp;apost;t like the EU,&amp;quot; Usherwood said, &amp;quot;but they can&amp;apost;t agree what they like and what the answer is.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>