<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2377" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2011/10/08/world/africa/kenya-maathai-rites" date_published="2011-10-08 09:33:56" category="world" author="Faith Karimi, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Kenyans gather to say goodbye to Nobel laureate Wangari Maathai</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Maathai, 71, died last month after a battle with cancer .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">She was the first African woman to win the Nobel Peace Prize.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">The environmentalist also fought for the empowerment of impoverished communities.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="18">Known as the Tree Mother of Africa, her campaign led to the planting of 40 million trees in Kenya.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-09 14:22:05" annotation_time="11.544">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Maathai, 71, died last month after a battle with cancer.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">She was the first African woman to win the Nobel Peace Prize in 2004 for her years of environmental conservation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">The human rights activist also fought for the empowerment of impoverished communities in the continent.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="4">Known as the Tree Mother of Africa, she launched a campaign that led to the planting of 40 million trees in Kenya.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Kenyans gathered in the nation&amp;apost;s capital Saturday for a state funeral honoring Nobel laureate Wangari Maathai, marking a final journey for the first African woman to win the peace prize.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Maathai, 71, died last month after a battle with cancer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>She was the first African woman to win the Nobel Peace Prize in 2004 for her years of environmental conservation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The human rights activist also fought for the empowerment of impoverished communities in the continent.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Crowds gathered at the main park in Nairobi for a state service that included President Mwai Kibaki, Prime Minister Raila Odinga and other government officials.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Military forces stood guard next to a mounted picture of the activist, which had a small green shrub pinned on it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Nearby, a car carrying her coffin surrounded by green shrubs slowly made its way down a red carpet under police escort.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Throngs of citizens quietly walked next to it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>In true fashion to her cause, Maathai stated in her will that she did not want a wooden coffin, organizers said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The ceremony at the park included a tree-planting ceremony and interdenominational prayers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The park was a common venue for her protests, including a defiant rally to stop the government from building a high-rise on the site years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Following the gathering, close relatives left for a private event at the crematorium.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>At her request, her remains will be cremated and her ashes interred at a peace institute in the capital, according to the Green Belt Movement she founded.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>For decades, Maathai has been at the forefront of a tree-planting campaign to stop deforestation and give locals, especially women, access to resources such as firewood for cooking and clean water.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The former parliament member was the first woman in East and Central Africa to earn a doctorate degree.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>She was honored by Time magazine in 2005 as one of 100 most influential people in the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>During her activism work, she was beaten and arrested numerous times, especially during the former regime of President Daniel arap Moi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Known as the Tree Mother of Africa, she launched a campaign that led to the planting of 40 million trees in Kenya.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>She believed that lack of natural resources causes most conflicts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is evident that many wars are fought over resources which are now becoming increasingly scarce,&amp;quot; she said on receiving news that she had been awarded the Nobel prize.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;If we conserved our resources better, fighting over them would not occur ... protecting the global environment is directly related to securing peace.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Those of us who understand the complex concept of the environment have the burden to act.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>We must not tire, we must not give up, we must persist.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The first African woman to receive the Nobel Peace Prize died weeks before another milestone in the continent she fought for.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>On Friday, the Nobel Committee awarded the peace prize to three women activists: Liberians Ellen Johnson Sirleaf, the first African woman elected head of state and Leymah Gbowee, who campaigned for peace during the nation&amp;apost;s brutal civil war and anti-government protester Tawakkul Karman of Yemen.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
