<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2265" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/12/18/world/meast/hrw-report-saudi-activists-face-jail/index.html" date_published="2013-12-18 18:21:54" category="world" author="Mohammed Jamjoom, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Human Rights Watch: Saudi activists face harassment, jail</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">Activists in Saudi Arabia have turned to social media to speak out against the government.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">The establishment of independent human rights bodies inside the country is forbidden.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">Activists risk harassment and imprisonment says Human Rights Watch (HRW).</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="26">HRW: &amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s time for other countries speak up and tell Saudi Arabia to end its repression campaign.&amp;quot;.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-03 12:51:29" annotation_time="27.035002">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="3">Activists in Saudi Arabia utilizing new media tools to call for change &amp;quot;face a repressive and intolerant government,&amp;quot; and risk harassment as well as imprisonment, according to Human Rights Watch (HRW).</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">Activists in Saudi Arabia -- an absolute monarchy where dissent is little tolerated -- have increasingly turned to social media sites to express growing frustration with the government.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">As the government will not allow for the formation and licensing of independent human rights bodies inside the country, many internet-based nongovernmental rights organizations have been established, and frequently report on human rights abuses within the ultraconservative kingdom.</sentence>
      <sentence id="26" ids_highlights="4">&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s time for other countries speak up and tell Saudi Arabia to end its repression campaign.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Activists in Saudi Arabia utilizing new media tools to call for change &amp;quot;face a repressive and intolerant government,&amp;quot; and risk harassment as well as imprisonment, according to Human Rights Watch (HRW).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>A report by the rights group, &amp;quot;Challenging the Red Lines: Stories of Rights Activists in Saudi Arabia,&amp;quot; released Wednesday, accuses Saudi authorities of &amp;quot;arresting, prosecuting, and attempting to silence rights defenders and to quash their calls for change.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;Independent activists in Saudi Arabia have little to protect them from the repressive practices of their government,&amp;quot; said Adam Coogle, Saudi researcher for Human Rights Watch.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s time for other countries to break their silence and tell Saudi Arabia to allow independent activism,&amp;quot; Coogle told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Activists in Saudi Arabia -- an absolute monarchy where dissent is little tolerated -- have increasingly turned to social media sites to express growing frustration with the government.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Online participation by Saudis has increased so much that the country now has one of the highest usage rates of Twitter in the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>As the government will not allow for the formation and licensing of independent human rights bodies inside the country, many internet-based nongovernmental rights organizations have been established, and frequently report on human rights abuses within the ultraconservative kingdom.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>According to HRW, &amp;quot;despite the authorities&amp;apost; efforts to block online content, Saudis -- at least 49% of whom have Internet access -- use Internet forums to bypass heavily censored state media.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The report also highlights the stories of 11 prominent Saudi political and civil activists and &amp;quot;their struggles to resist government efforts to suppress them,&amp;quot; according to HRW.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>One of those activists, Waleed Abulkhair, was recently sentenced to three months in jail by a court in Jeddah for signing a petition critical of Saudi authorities two years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;Human rights activists are having a very bad time right now in Saudi Arabia,&amp;quot; Abulkhair told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Authorities don&amp;apost;t want anyone to speak out loudly and when we do, the government feels they lose control.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Abulkhair, a prominent human rights lawyer, said he is appealing his sentence, but that he&amp;apost;s now also being tried by the Specialized Criminal Court (which prosecutes terrorists) in the country&amp;apost;s capital city, Riyadh.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>According to Abulkhair, he&amp;apost;s been charged with &amp;quot;setting up an unlicensed organization&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;breaking allegiance with the Saudi King,&amp;quot; among other things.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Abulkhair believes he is being prosecuted solely for his activism and holds out little hope he&amp;apost;ll remain free much longer.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m sure that I will be convicted,&amp;quot; he told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Another Saudi activist highlighted in the report is Abulkhair&amp;apost;s brother-in-law and client, Raif Badawi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Badawi was recently sentenced by a Jeddah Criminal Court to seven years in prison and 600 lashes for violating the nation&amp;apost;s anti-cybercrime law.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>In jail since June 2012, Badawi was found guilty of insulting Islam through his website and in television comments.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Badawi&amp;apost;s legal troubles started shortly after he started the Free Saudi Liberals website in 2008, as a way to encourage discussion about religion; it didn&amp;apost;t take long for some clerics to brand him an unbeliever and apostate.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Badawi&amp;apost;s sentence is being appealed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The case of Adel Ali al-Labbad is also included in the report.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>It calls him &amp;quot;a political activist and poet from the Eastern Province city of Awammiyah.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>HRW says Saudi security forces have arrested al-Labbad, a Shiite, four times over the past ten years and tortured him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;Saudi Arabia&amp;apost;s conviction of eight prominent activists in 2013 alone for their peaceful activities has been largely met with silence by Saudi Arabia&amp;apost;s friends in the US and Europe,&amp;quot; said HRW&amp;apost;s Coogle.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s time for other countries speak up and tell Saudi Arabia to end its repression campaign.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Despite repeated attempts, CNN was unable to reach Saudi Arabia&amp;apost;s Interior Ministry or Justice Ministry for comment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Rights groups have frequently accused Saudi authorities of targeting activists through the courts and travel bans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Many were outraged in March this year, when two of the country&amp;apost;s most prominent reform advocates, Mohammed Al-Qahtani and Abdullah Al-Hamid were sentenced to 10 and 11 years in prison respectively.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>At the time, Amnesty International called their trial &amp;quot;just one of a troubling string of court cases aimed at silencing the kingdom&amp;apost;s human-rights activists.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Asked in January about accusations that Saudi Arabia is cracking down on dissent, Major General Mansour Al-Turki, spokesman for the Saudi Interior Ministry, told CNN, &amp;quot;At the Interior Ministry, our area of responsibility is security.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>He added, &amp;quot;My understanding is that these cases are being looked at by the courts now.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Nobody will comment on cases being looked at by the courts.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>According to HRW, &amp;quot;Saudi Arabia does not have a written penal code, leaving judges free to issue sentences based on their own interpretations of the Quran and the teachings of the Prophet Muhammad, the two agreed-upon sources of Islamic Sharia law.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;Defendants accused of political offenses -- including human rights activists -- are often sentenced by the Specialized Criminal Court, set up to try terrorism-related cases.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>This court sometimes denies defendants the most basic fair trial guarantees, including the right to a lawyer, and passes sentences in closed proceedings.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Despite repeated criticism of Saudi Arabia&amp;apost;s human rights record by numerous rights groups, in November the kingdom was elected to a three year term on the United Nations&amp;apost; Human Rights Council.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
