<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2356" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/01/10/world/asia/japan-whaling-detention/index.html" date_published="2012-01-10 05:12:55" category="world" author="Yoko Wakatsuki, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Japan to hand over detained whaling activists to Australia</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="11">Japan has lodged a protest with the Australian government over the boarding.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Japan will hand the three activists over to the Australian authorities.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">The Japanese fleet will continue its annual hunt in Antarctic waters.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="10">Environmental groups clash each year with Japan&amp;apost;s whaling vessels.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-09 14:21:53" annotation_time="16.632">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2, 3">Tokyo Japan said Tuesday that it would hand over to Australian authorities three Australian anti-whaling activists being held aboard a Japanese vessel, but that it would press on with its annual whale hunt in the seas near Antarctica.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="4">Each year, environmental groups like Sea Shepherd face off with Japan&amp;apost;s hunters in a high seas drama that has led to collisions of ships, the detaining of activists and smoke bombs fired back and forth between the groups.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="1">Japan has lodged a protest with the Australian government through diplomatic channels, asking it to prevent such boardings in the future, the Japanese foreign ministry official said Tuesday.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Tokyo Japan said Tuesday that it would hand over to Australian authorities three Australian anti-whaling activists being held aboard a Japanese vessel, but that it would press on with its annual whale hunt in the seas near Antarctica.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The activists had illegally boarded the ship, a patrol vessel supporting Japan&amp;apost;s whaling mission in Antarctic waters, to protest the hunting of the giant marine mammals in the area.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The three men will be released without charge after being questioned by Japan&amp;apost;s Coast Guard, an official at the Japanese Ministry of Foreign Affairs said Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The official declined to be identified as is customary in Japan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;They have not been violent after getting on board and had no record of joining past destructive actions by Sea Shepherd,&amp;quot; the official said, referring to the anti-whaling group that has clashed several times with the Japanese fleet.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>He said the Japanese whaling fleet needed the patrol boat to continue with its hunt.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Australia engaged in diplomatic discussions with Japan to ensure the well-being and safety of the three men, the Australian attorney-general, Nicola Roxon, said Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>She said that while Australia steadfastly opposes Japan&amp;apost;s whale hunt, the incident did not occur in Australian territorial waters, meaning that Australian law did not automatically apply to the case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Japan annually hunts whales despite a worldwide moratorium, utilizing a loophole in the law that allows for killing the mammals for scientific research.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Each year, environmental groups like Sea Shepherd face off with Japan&amp;apost;s hunters in a high seas drama that has led to collisions of ships, the detaining of activists and smoke bombs fired back and forth between the groups.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Japan has lodged a protest with the Australian government through diplomatic channels, asking it to prevent such boardings in the future, the Japanese foreign ministry official said Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Video footage released by Sea Shepherd showed the three men, from the environmental group Forest Rescue Australia, boarding the Japanese vessel from a small boat on Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Sea Shepherd had described the three activists -- Geoffrey Owen Tuxworth, 47, Simon Peterffy, 44, and Glen Pendlebury, 27 -- as &amp;quot;prisoners.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The organization said the men boarded the vessel to force Japan&amp;apost;s fleet to stop hunting whales.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>This is the third time activists have boarded ships involved in the Japanese whaling fleet.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>In 2008, two Sea Shepherd activists sneaked aboard a Japanese vessel.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>They were released back to the anti-whaling group.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>In 2010, Pete Bethune, a New Zealander, also boarded the Shonan Maru #2.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Bethune was arrested, taken back to Japan, and tried in a Tokyo court.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>He spent five months in prison and was released on a two-year suspended sentence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
