<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2463" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/07/06/world/meast/egypt-elbaradei-profile/index.html" date_published="2013-07-06 19:42:55" category="world" author="Michael Martinez, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Mohamed ElBaradei, among candidates for Egypt&amp;apost;s interim prime minister</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Mohamed ElBaradei was born in Cairo 71 years ago, but has been viewed as an outsider.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12">He traveled as a diplomat and chief of International Atomic Energy Agency.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">He unsuccessfully ran last year for president in first elections since revolution.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="4">He endured, however, as an opposition leader.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-09 14:22:31" annotation_time="26.214">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Mohamed ElBaradei, who is said to be a candidate for Egypt&amp;apost;s interim prime minister following a military coup, has been regarded as an outsider in his native land because of his international achievements as a diplomat and co-winner of the Nobel Peace Prize.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="3">An above-the-fray image hurt him when he unsuccessfully ran for president last year in the country&amp;apost;s first democratic elections following the 2011 ouster of despotic President Hosni Mubarak.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="4">As if to prove naysayers wrong, ElBaradei stayed in the fight for Egypt&amp;apost;s post-revolution government, and he endured as a reformer, becoming an opposition leader.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">He then left the country, traveling as a diplomat.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Mohamed ElBaradei, who is said to be a candidate for Egypt&amp;apost;s interim prime minister following a military coup, has been regarded as an outsider in his native land because of his international achievements as a diplomat and co-winner of the Nobel Peace Prize.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>An above-the-fray image hurt him when he unsuccessfully ran for president last year in the country&amp;apost;s first democratic elections following the 2011 ouster of despotic President Hosni Mubarak.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>At the time, ElBaradei was a Johnny-come-lately to the long grind of ground-level politics.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>As if to prove naysayers wrong, ElBaradei stayed in the fight for Egypt&amp;apost;s post-revolution government, and he endured as a reformer, becoming an opposition leader.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Now ElBaradei could possibly land deep inside Egypt&amp;apost;s power structure, in the nation&amp;apost;s capital where he was born 71 years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>His political party&amp;apost;s claim Saturday -- that ElBaradei was chosen to become interim prime minister -- was contradicted later in the day by a spokesman for Interim President Adly Mansour, who said a decision had yet to be made.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;I hope I&amp;apost;ll be the éminence grise,&amp;quot; ElBaradei told CNN this week, with a measure of laughter.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m getting on with the years ... and I think I&amp;apost;ll be much more effective.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;As a lawyer I want always to be within the bounds of constitutional legality but ... we still are between a rock and hard place,&amp;quot; he continued.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;Either you risk a civil war -- and we have quite a few of them around us -- or, as I said, take extra-constitutional measures to ensure that we get the country together.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Like his father, ElBaradei studied law, earning a bachelor&amp;apost;s degree at University of Cairo.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>He then left the country, traveling as a diplomat.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>By 1974, he earned a doctorate in international law from New York University, and a decade later, he joined the International Atomic Energy Agency -- which proved to be a brilliant career move because it eventually led him and the agency to share the Nobel Peace Prize in 2005.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>ElBaradei served as chief of the atomic agency for 12 years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>He and the agency won the honor for their work to curb nuclear proliferation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>As director general of the IAEA, he even challenged President George W. Bush&amp;apost;s claims that Iraq had a nuclear weapons program before Bush ordered a coalition-supported invasion of Iraq in early 2003.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>With those international laurels, ElBaradei was among those who successfully pushed for the ouster of Mubarak after 30 years as president.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Still, ElBaradei was considered an above-it-all technocrat who was viewed as an unlikely presidential candidate, though he did join anti-Mubarak protests in Egypt despite receiving death threats.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>He had no official protection during his participation in those protests.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>ElBaradei was reportedly placed under house arrest by Egyptian authorities, but he defied a government curfew and went to Cairo&amp;apost;s Tahrir Square to join protests in January 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The next month, Mubarak stepped down.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>In March 2011, ElBaradei announced he was running for president, and 10 days later, thugs attacked his car, keeping him from voting in a constitutional referendum.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The next month, he returned to his first love -- diplomacy and atomic weapons -- and published a book, &amp;quot;The Age of Deception: Nuclear Diplomacy in Treacherous Times.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The publisher&amp;apost;s blurb states that &amp;quot;ElBaradei takes us inside the nuclear fray, from behind-the-scenes exchanges in Washington and Baghdad to the streets of Pyongyang and the trail of Pakistani nuclear smugglers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>He decries an us-versus-them approach and insists on the necessity of relentless diplomacy.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>If that was a campaign strategy, it didn&amp;apost;t work: In January 2012, he quit the presidential race.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>In an example of how politics can make for strange bedfellows, ElBaradei then criticized the interim military government -- the same military that has now put him in power -- for failing to bring about &amp;quot;a real democratic system.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s clear now, however, that ElBaradei has the attention of Egypt&amp;apost;s generals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
