<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2021" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/02/18/world/europe/neknominate-drinking-game" date_published="2014-02-18 15:47:53" category="world" author="Peter Wilkinson and Isa Soares, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>&amp;apost;Lethal&amp;apost; drinking game Neknominate sweeps social media</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6">Neknominate game, thought to have originated in Australia, now sweeping the world.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">At least five men aged under 30 have died after drinking deadly cocktails.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="14">There appears to be no limit to the type of drinks that are consumed.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="20">The role of social media giants like Facebook is also coming under scrutiny.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-17 14:19:46" annotation_time="41.22">
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">The game, known as Neknominate, is thought to have originated in Australia and is now sweeping the world.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">But what started for some as fun has turned deadly; at least five men aged under 30 have died after drinking deadly cocktails.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="3">There appears to be no limit to the type of drinks that are consumed, and in what matter.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="4">The role of social media giants like Facebook is also coming under scrutiny.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>London &amp;quot;Thanks for the nomination Luke,&amp;quot; jokes a young man in a YouTube clip pouring what he says is a new, unopened bottle of Sambuca spirits into a pint glass along with another, unidentified drink.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>As the liquids mix, he observes: &amp;quot;And that is congealing nicely ... whew ... okay,&amp;quot; before knocking back the potion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>After a brief pause he declares: &amp;quot;I nominate [he names some friends].</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>You&amp;apost;ve got 24 hours lads.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Get it done.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The game, known as Neknominate, is thought to have originated in Australia and is now sweeping the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>It involves you filming yourself downing a drink -- often alcoholic and of large quantities -- and then nominating a friend to outdo you.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>All this is posted on social media -- be it Facebook or YouTube.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>But what started for some as fun has turned deadly; at least five men aged under 30 have died after drinking deadly cocktails.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Now health professionals are warning young people of the risks of consuming large amounts of alcohol in a short time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is a lethal game,&amp;quot; Dr. Sarah Jarvis, medical adviser for the UK-based charity Drinkaware, told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;The point about alcohol is that it affects your ability to recognize that you&amp;apost;re in danger, and it absolutely affects your ability to react to danger.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>So we have a double whammy.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>There appears to be no limit to the type of drinks that are consumed, and in what matter.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Each nomination becomes more and more daring and outlandish.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>It started as exhibitionism with this woman stripping in the supermarket and downing a drink, but the bravado has escalated into extreme cocktails: One mixes spirits with a dead mouse, in another a man drinks out of a toilet, and the craze has seen players consume alcohol with goldfish, insects, engine oil and dog food.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Unsurprisingly the trend has prompted politicians to demand that schools play a bigger role.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Facebook drinking game Neknomination has gone viral, and very sadly young people have died as a result,&amp;quot; said UK opposition spokesman Diana Johnson.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;What role do schools have in building resilience in our young people to resist peer pressure?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The role of social media giants like Facebook is also coming under scrutiny.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Brian Viner, whose own son has played the game, demanded that those companies face up to their responsibilities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>His son was nominated and pressured to play the game but drank water instead of vodka so as not to harm himself.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;I was cross with him but more cross with the social media involved and the way this game has just spread,&amp;quot; Viner said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;The whole thing is madness and it needs some kind of sharp and swift action on the part of these social networks to stop it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Facebook said in a statement: &amp;quot;We do not tolerate content which is directly harmful, for example bullying, but behavior which some people may find offensive or controversial is not always necessarily against our rules.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;We encourage people to report things to us which they feel breaks our rules so we can review and take action on a case by case basis.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>But Dr. Jarvis rejected this defense, saying Facebook must recognize its own role in the game.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s very difficult in this day of personal liberties to say that Facebook shouldn&amp;apost;t be condoning this or taking these videos offline.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;Personally, I would like to see that happening.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Frankly, if the thrill wasn&amp;apost;t there, your mates weren&amp;apost;t seeing you, I expect it would very rapidly fizzle out.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
