<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2981" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/07/05/world/meast/uk-syria-wikileaks/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2012-07-05 10:52:53" category="world" author="the CNN Wire Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>WikiLeaks releasing 2.4 million Syria e-mails</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">One e-mail shows a company trying to get around U.S. sanctions.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">The e-mails are in a range of languages including Arabic and Russian.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">WikiLeaks says the e-mails come from different government ministries.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="12">The WikiLeaks founder has been fighting extradition.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-18 14:58:11" annotation_time="22.800667">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="3">WikiLeaks said Thursday it has begun publishing some 2.4 million e-mails from Syrian politicians, government ministries and companies dating back to 2006.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">The e-mails, which are in a range of languages including Arabic and Russian, come from the ministries of presidential affairs, finance, information and foreign affairs, among others.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">One e-mail shows an Italian company trying to get around U.S. sanctions on Syria and another indicates that the company was sending engineers and helicopter radio equipment to Syria as recently as February 2012.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="4">Assange has been fighting extradition ever since, saying the allegations are retribution for his organization&amp;apost;s disclosure of American secrets.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>WikiLeaks said Thursday it has begun publishing some 2.4 million e-mails from Syrian politicians, government ministries and companies dating back to 2006.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The e-mails, which are in a range of languages including Arabic and Russian, come from the ministries of presidential affairs, finance, information and foreign affairs, among others.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>According to WikiLeaks, the e-mails &amp;quot;shine a light on the inner workings of the Syrian government and economy, but they also reveal how the West and Western companies say one thing and do another.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>One e-mail shows an Italian company trying to get around U.S. sanctions on Syria and another indicates that the company was sending engineers and helicopter radio equipment to Syria as recently as February 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Syrian forces began their crackdown against protesters in March 2011 and that has sparked a grass-roots uprising and a bloody regime offensive against dissenters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>WikiLeaks, which facilitates the anonymous leaking of secret information, has published about 250,000 confidential U.S. diplomatic cables, causing embarrassment to the government and others.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>It has also published hundreds of thousands of classified U.S. documents relating to the conflicts in Iraq and Afghanistan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Its founder, Julian Assange, was arrested in Britain in 2010 over allegations of rape and sex crime charges in Sweden.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Two women have accused Assange of sexually assaulting them in August 2010 when he was visiting Sweden in connection with a WikiLeaks release of internal U.S. military documents.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>He has been arrested in absentia, Swedish prosecutors have said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Swedish authorities want to question him about the allegations, which he denies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Assange has been fighting extradition ever since, saying the allegations are retribution for his organization&amp;apost;s disclosure of American secrets.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>His bail conditions included staying every night at the home of a supporter outside London.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Assange applied for asylum to Ecuador on June 19 and has been inside the Ecuadorian Embassy in London since then.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>It is unclear when Ecuador will decide on the request.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>He sought refuge at the embassy five days after the Supreme Court of the United Kingdom dismissed a bid to reopen his appeal of the decision to send him to Sweden -- his last option in British courts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>A representative for the WikiLeaks founder said Assange will not honor a notice that British police served him requiring that he surrender to authorities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;This should not be considered any sign of disrespect,&amp;quot; said Susan Benn of the Julian Assange Defense Fund, who read the statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Benn said the United States has empaneled a grand jury in its goal to press charges against Assange.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Turning himself in would have started a process that would have ended with Assange&amp;apost;s extradition to the United States, she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is clear that there is a plan to bring Julian Assange to the United States,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Citing what she called cruel, inhumane and degrading treatment of the alleged source of leaked documents, Pfc. Bradley Manning, Benn said that sending Assange to the United States &amp;quot;would be a violation of his rights.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Police said Assange has violated the terms of his bail by staying at the embassy, and that ignoring the notice to turn himself in is a further violation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
