<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2982" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/25/world/asia/indonesia-bill-directly-elect/index.html?hpt=ias_c2" date_published="2014-09-25 07:15:18" category="world" author="Kathy Quiano, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Will Indonesia lose right to directly elect governors?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Indonesia&amp;apost;s parliament will vote on a bill to strip the right to directly elect local leaders.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Critics say it is a retrograde move; backers say democracy has become too expensive.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">The move is being backed by the coalition that backed the losing presidential candidate.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="36">They could pass the bill into law before President-elect Joko Widodo takes office.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-02 10:57:13" annotation_time="25.433664" mapping_time_divergence="6.358416">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1, 2">Indonesia&amp;apost;s parliament is set to vote Thursday on a revised election bill that will take away voters&amp;apost; rights to directly elect local leaders, in what critics say it is a huge step backward for the country&amp;apost;s fledgling democracy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">The bill is being backed by the coalition behind losing presidential candidate Prabowo Subianto.</sentence>
      <sentence id="36" ids_highlights="4">The President can veto the bill before his term ends and Widodo takes over on October 20.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Indonesia&amp;apost;s parliament is set to vote Thursday on a revised election bill that will take away voters&amp;apost; rights to directly elect local leaders, in what critics say it is a huge step backward for the country&amp;apost;s fledgling democracy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Proponents of the bill, which would scrap direct elections for mayors and governors, say local elections have proven too costly, and are prone to conflict and corruption.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The bill is being backed by the coalition behind losing presidential candidate Prabowo Subianto.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;Democracy has become too expensive,&amp;quot; Fadli Zon, vice chairman of Subianto&amp;apost;s Gerindra party, recently told a forum of journalists.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Zon estimates the government will save about 60 trillion rupiah or $5 billion, if direct regional elections are eliminated.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;If the regional election is done by the regional house of representatives, it is estimated that the expenditure needed would only be the cost for tea and coffee,&amp;quot; he argued.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Bad move?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Critics disagree, and question the timing of the push to pass the bill, first proposed in 2012, just two months after the election of president-elect Joko Widodo.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Six of nine political parties support the revisions and most are part of the coalition that backed Subianto.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think it&amp;apost;s unseemly,&amp;quot; said Sarwono Kusumaatmadja, a former minister under former president Suharto, and now senior government affairs adviser at Transformasi, a Jakarta-based think tank.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;It won&amp;apost;t change the nature of politics, it won&amp;apost;t make politics any cleaner.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>It will only shift the money politics somewhere else, to the oligarchs, and the victims are the Indonesian people,&amp;quot; he added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;Just when they were just enjoying their rights and seeing some good people rise, based on a constituency based politics, they see the game being taken away from them.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Widodo&amp;apost;s rise.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Widodo was swept into power through the popular vote.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>He was first elected as mayor of Solo in Central Java in 2005 and then as governor of the nation&amp;apost;s capital Jakarta in 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;Direct elections are important because it is the fruit of the 32 years of Indonesia&amp;apost;s struggle for democracy,&amp;quot; student leader Mohamad Ivan Riansa told a small protest in front of the parliament building Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Under former dictator Suharto&amp;apost;s 32-year rule, local leaders were chosen by political parties that won seats in local assemblies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>After the fall of his regime in 1998, Indonesia launched a rapid process of political and electoral reform, involving a decentralization of power from the national government.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>In 2004, Susilo Bambang Yudhoyono became the first directly-elected president of Indonesia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>A year later, voters were given the right to choose their own local leaders for the very first time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The massive democratic undertaking required elections to be staggered over five years throughout the country&amp;apost;s 34 provinces and 511 districts or municipalities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Direct elections favored.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>A recent opinion survey by the Indonesian Survey Circle showed that 81% of Indonesians prefer direct local elections.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Choosing local leaders was a relatively new and confusing experience for some Indonesians, taxi driver Nana Suryana told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s better for the local assembly to choose the candidates because they know better than we do.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>People might choose the wrong one,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>While voter turnout had been declining since 2009, a new wave of politicians, including Widodo, energized a largely apathetic electorate this year, particularly young voters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;Most of us abstained from voting before the presidential 2014 elections,&amp;quot; musician Viddy Supit told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re now aware that we have to use our voices to develop our nation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s why we&amp;apost;re here to support direct regional elections.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Titi Anggraini, director of the Association for Elections and Democracy (Perludem), said that holding simultaneous elections, to decrease costs, and focusing on voter education would be more effective steps to strengthen Indonesia&amp;apost;s democracy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;If this bill is passed, it&amp;apost;s not only dangerous, but it is stealing our rights, our constitutional rights,&amp;quot; Anggraini said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>SBY veto?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Outgoing President Susilo Bambang Yudhoyono, whose Democrat Party supports the bill, has said he supports direct elections.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>The President can veto the bill before his term ends and Widodo takes over on October 20.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Anggraini said his group had appealed to Yudhoyono in an open letter.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;Pak Presiden SBY (Mr. President SBY), you are the person who gained the most from democracy, from reformasi (reform), so at the end of your term, please give us the sweet fruits of democracy&amp;quot;, said Anggraini.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Current parliamentarians are set to vote on the revised bill Thursday, just days before their terms end on September 30.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
