<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2316" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/03/11/world/asia/afghanistan-karzai-comments/index.html" date_published="2013-03-11 04:32:03" category="world" author="Matt Smith, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>ISAF chief: Karzai claim of U.S., Taliban collusion is &amp;apost;categorically false&amp;apost;</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">&amp;quot;We have fought too hard over the past 12 years,&amp;quot; Dunford says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Karzai had said the U.S. and the Taliban were holding daily talks.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="16">Hagel, Karzai meet to smooth over frictions.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="32">Taliban claims responsibility for Saturday attack.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2015-01-26 11:31:36" annotation_time="27.550499">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2">The commander of the NATO-led forces in Afghanistan has taken exception to President Hamid Karzai&amp;apost;s contention that the United States and the Taliban were holding daily talks, and that the militant group prefers that foreign troops remain in the country.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;We have fought too hard over the past 12 years.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="3">The meeting was an attempt to smooth over the latest dispute in the already strained relationship between the two allies.</sentence>
      <sentence id="32" ids_highlights="4">The Taliban claimed responsibility for Saturday&amp;apost;s attack at the Afghan defense ministry in Kabul, which killed at least nine people and wounded 14 others.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The commander of the NATO-led forces in Afghanistan has taken exception to President Hamid Karzai&amp;apost;s contention that the United States and the Taliban were holding daily talks, and that the militant group prefers that foreign troops remain in the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have fought too hard over the past 12 years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>We have shed too much blood over the past 12 years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>We have done too much to help the Afghan Security Forces grow over the last 12 years to ever think that violence or instability would be to our advantage,&amp;quot; said Marine Gen. Joseph Dunford, the commander of the International Security Assistance Force.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>On Sunday, after a weekend bombing in Kabul that killed at least nine people, Karzai said there are &amp;quot;ongoing daily talks between Taliban, American and foreigners in Europe and in the Gulf states.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Saturday&amp;apost;s attack, Karzai said, shows &amp;quot;that Taliban want longer presence of foreigners -- not their departure from Afghanistan.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;apost;No reason to support instability&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Dunford took exception to that characterization.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;President Karzai has never said to me that the United States was colluding with the Taliban.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>All I can do is speak for the coalition to tell you that it&amp;apost;s categorically false, and that we have no reason to be colluding with the Taliban,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have no reason to be supporting instability in Afghanistan.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>And all that we have been about over the past 12 years is to bring peace and stability to the Afghan people so that they can take advantage of the decade of opportunity that will follow 2014.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The United States plans to wind up its 11-year combat mission in Afghanistan by the end of next year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Dinner to smooth things over.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>On Sunday, several hours after Karzai made his remarks, he met with U.S. Defense Secretary Chuck Hagel over dinner in the Afghan capital.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The meeting was an attempt to smooth over the latest dispute in the already strained relationship between the two allies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Hagel told reporters he tried to reassure Karzai that the United States had no unilateral back-channel talks with the Taliban.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;The fact is, any prospect for peace or political settlements -- that has to be led by the Afghans.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>That has to come from the Afghan side,&amp;quot; Hagel said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;Obviously, the United States will support efforts if they are led by the Afghans to come to some possible resolution.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Hagel, a former senator who took the helm at the Pentagon last month, made his first trip to Afghanistan as defense secretary.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Karzai, meanwhile, has been increasingly critical of American forces in recent months.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>While there have been reconciliation talks in the past, the United States has not said any such talks are currently underway with the Taliban.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In January, a U.S. official said reconciliation talks were showing &amp;quot;some signs of life&amp;quot; after being dormant for a year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>News conference canceled.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Hagel&amp;apost;s dinner with the Afghan leader in Kabul came after a scheduled joint news conference between the two was canceled.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Pentagon spokesman George Little said the schedule had changed &amp;quot;for a variety of reasons, to include decisions related to security in Kabul that were reached in consultation with our Afghan partners.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;I know these are difficult issues for President Karzai and the Afghan people,&amp;quot; Hagel said after the meeting.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;I was once a politician, so I can understand the kind of pressures that especially leaders of countries are always under.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>I would hope, again, that we can move forward, and I have confidence that we can and will deal with these issues.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Taliban: Attack a message to Hagel.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The Taliban claimed responsibility for Saturday&amp;apost;s attack at the Afghan defense ministry in Kabul, which killed at least nine people and wounded 14 others.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>A Taliban spokesman expressed pleasure with Hagel&amp;apost;s proximity at the time, calling the attack &amp;quot;a message to him.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>ISAF rejected suggestions that the Taliban even knew of Hagel&amp;apost;s trip when they planned the operation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Tensions ahead of pullout.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Afghanistan&amp;apost;s National Security Council, chaired by Karzai, recently accused &amp;quot;armed individuals named as U.S. special force&amp;quot; of torturing and murdering innocent people in Wardak province.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>The government demanded members of the elite U.S. military units leave the province west of Kabul.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>But the council also said the United States rejected such suggestions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>U.S. military officials said all allegations of misconduct are taken seriously, and that the military was looking into the allegation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Last year, Karzai called for U.S. troops to pull out of outposts in Afghan villages and return to their main bases.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>In October, he complained the United States was failing to supply Afghan forces with weapons needed to fight insurgents.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Then-U.S. Defense Secretary Leon Panetta responded at the time that &amp;quot;it would be helpful if (Karzai), every once in a while, expressed his thanks for the sacrifices that have been made by those who have fought and died for Afghanistan, rather than criticizing them.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>The Obama administration is making decisions about bringing troops home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>In January, Panetta reiterated his opposition to pulling out all U.S. troops by 2014, saying it would take away negotiating leverage with the Taliban.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>&amp;quot;The stronger position we take about staying, the better chances we have to ultimately reach political reconciliation,&amp;quot; Panetta told journalists.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
