<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2749" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/02/22/world/africa/somalia-child-soldiers/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2012-02-22 16:54:32" category="world" author="Kathryn Tancos and Mohamed Amiin Adow, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Somali Islamist militia defends recruiting teen soldiers</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Al-Shabaab says Islam considers people to be adults at the age of 15.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">The Somalia Islamists are responding to Human Rights Watch criticism.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">The group says Al-Shabaab is using children as young as 10 as cannon fodder.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="10">Somalia&amp;apost;s government denies intentionally recruiting child soldiers.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-10 21:05:09" annotation_time="59.351334">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Somalia&amp;apost;s Al-Shabaab has brushed aside accusations from Human Rights Watch that the Islamist militia recruits child soldiers, saying that Islam considers people to be adults from the age of 15.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">&amp;apost;&amp;apost;If the territories of the Muslims are attacked, it is incumbent on the women and children to take up arms to fight the enemies, so we don&amp;apost;t care what Human Rights Watch says,&amp;apost;&amp;apost; Abu Musab said, speaking to Alfurqan radio, which supports the group.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">Human Rights Watch said this week that children as young as 10 increasingly face horrific abuse in war-torn Somalia as Al-Shabaab targets them to replenish its diminishing ranks of fighters.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="4">The head of the Somali national army, Gen. Abdulkadir Ali Diini, said Wednesday the government does its best not to recruit children as soldiers.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Somalia&amp;apost;s Al-Shabaab has brushed aside accusations from Human Rights Watch that the Islamist militia recruits child soldiers, saying that Islam considers people to be adults from the age of 15.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;The allegations from Human Rights Watch say that Al-Shabaab recruits young children at the age of 14, 15 and 17 as soldiers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>In Islam, a person becomes adult at the age of 15 so he or she must do what all other adults have to do,&amp;apost;&amp;apost; said Abu Musab, the group&amp;apost;s military spokesman.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;apost;&amp;apost;If the territories of the Muslims are attacked, it is incumbent on the women and children to take up arms to fight the enemies, so we don&amp;apost;t care what Human Rights Watch says,&amp;apost;&amp;apost; Abu Musab said, speaking to Alfurqan radio, which supports the group.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Islamic scholars consider a boy becomes a man at 15, or even younger if signs of puberty appear before then.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Human Rights Watch said this week that children as young as 10 increasingly face horrific abuse in war-torn Somalia as Al-Shabaab targets them to replenish its diminishing ranks of fighters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The Somali insurgent group&amp;apost;s recruitment of child soldiers is not new, but the report said the scale of child abductions over the past two years is like nothing documented in the past.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Shocking patterns have also emerged of children serving as human shields on the battlefields, according to the Human Rights Watch report released Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re beginning to see more and more instances where children are essentially being used as cannon fodder,&amp;quot; Tirana Hassan of Human Rights Watch told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The head of the Somali national army, Gen. Abdulkadir Ali Diini, said Wednesday the government does its best not to recruit children as soldiers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The government has discharged children who are mistakenly recruited, he told journalists in Mogadishu.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Human Rights Watch charged in its report that Al-Shabaab fighters abduct young girls and boys from their homes or schools, in some cases taking entire classes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Children can be sent out to recruit other children, according to the organization.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>One survivor told Human Rights Watch a group of kids asked him to play football at a nearby field.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>When he arrived, he and others were gathered up and sent to training camps, the survivor told Human Rights Watch.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The camps are places where children live in fear, said Hassan, an emergencies researcher for the international human rights group.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;They see injured and dead fighters, many of them children, coming back from the battlefield,&amp;quot; Hassan added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Recruits are taught to use weapons and to throw hand grenades and are subjected to a myriad of abuses, including rape, assault and forced marriages, according to Hassan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Dozens of recruits, mostly ages 14 to 17, are driven by truckloads to the front line, where they are told to jump out -- only to be mowed down by gunfire while Al-Shabaab fighters launch rockets from behind, according to Hassan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>A 15-year-old boy recruited by Al-Shabaab from his school in Mogadishu in 2010 told Human Rights Watch that &amp;quot;out of all my classmates -- about 100 boys -- only two of us escaped, the rest were killed.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;The children were cleaned off.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The children all died and the bigger soldiers ran away,&amp;quot; the youth told Human Rights Watch.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Human Rights Watch also criticized Somalia&amp;apost;s transitional government for not ending its use of child soldiers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;Al-Shabaab&amp;apost;s horrific abuses do not excuse Somalia&amp;apost;s Transitional Federal Government,&amp;quot; said Zama Coursen-Neff, the group&amp;apost;s deputy children&amp;apost;s rights director.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;The TFG should live up to its commitments to stop recruiting and using children as soldiers, and punish those who do.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The 104-page report, released two days ahead of a Somalia conference hosted by the British government, grimly details countless violations against children based on more than 160 interviews conducted over two years with Somali youngsters who escaped from Al-Shabaab forces as well as parents and teachers who fled to Kenya.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;For children of Somalia, nowhere is safe,&amp;quot; Coursen-Neff said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>On Thursday, senior representatives from more than 40 governments will converge on London in a diplomatic push to find political solutions to restore stability in Somalia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
