<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2788" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/06/02/world/meast/syria-elections-explainer/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-06-02 11:51:02" category="world" author="Frederik Pleitgen, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Syria&amp;apost;s presidential election: How fair can a vote be in a war zone?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">President Bashar al-Assad widely expected to be returned to power in Tuesday election.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="42">West and Syrian rebels say large swathes of war-torn country won&amp;apost;t be able to vote.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="40">Nearly 3 million have fled Syria; another 6.5 million have been internally displaced by war.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="34">Opposition presidential candidate says election only valid if at least 50 percent of country votes.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 13:23:07" annotation_time="67.133">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">The election, which has been branded a sham by the West and by the Syrian opposition, is widely expected to return President Bashar al-Assad to power.</sentence>
      <sentence id="34" ids_highlights="4">If the turnout is high, that would indicate people in the areas where voting is possible take it seriously -- and opposition candidate Nouri says the election can&amp;apost;t be considered valid if turnout is lower than 50 percent.</sentence>
      <sentence id="40" ids_highlights="3">Nearly 3 million Syrians have been forced to flee the country and more than 6.5 million are internally displaced.</sentence>
      <sentence id="42" ids_highlights="2">Large swathes of Syria&amp;apost;s north and northeast, as well as some places in the south, are not under government control and there will be no election in those areas.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Syria may be embroiled in a brutal three-year civil war, but that&amp;apost;s not stopping the government from holding controversial presidential elections this week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The election, which has been branded a sham by the West and by the Syrian opposition, is widely expected to return President Bashar al-Assad to power.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>CNN International Correspondent Frederik Pleitgen has reported from inside Syria numerous times during the conflict, which has left an estimated 150,000 people dead.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>He breaks down the key questions ahead of Tuesday&amp;apost;s election.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Why is it happening now?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The government says Syria&amp;apost;s new constitution stipulates that presidential elections must be held now.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The regime says it shows the country is moving forward and that it is the first time a president will be elected by the people rather than appointed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The opposition says the election is a fraud, that voting will be rigged and that the poll serves only to cement Assad&amp;apost;s power.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Who are the other candidates?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The other two candidates are relative unknowns.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>One is Maher Hajjar, an entrepreneur and member of parliament.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>He keeps out of the limelight and has not been heard from much.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Hajjar&amp;apost;s election posters declare that &amp;quot;Syria is with Palestine,&amp;quot; which seems like a very narrow slogan.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Other than that it is unclear what he would change should he win.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The more intriguing candidate is Hassan Nouri, a former economics professor and cabinet minister who told me he had to resign because he was too critical of Assad&amp;apost;s government.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Nouri studied at the University of Wisconsin and still refers to himself as a Badger.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>He says the election is an uphill battle for him, but feels he is making headway.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>His main message is economic.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>He is for market liberalization and fighting corruption in government and in the private sector.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>But when it comes to fighting Syria&amp;apost;s civil war, Nouri says he wouldn&amp;apost;t do anything differently -- and much like Assad, he refers to the regime&amp;apost;s three-year assault on the opposition as &amp;quot;fighting terrorism.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Are they for real?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s very hard to tell whether Assad&amp;apost;s opponents are for real.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>They certainly don&amp;apost;t seem to stand much of a chance, but Hassan Nouri says he is fighting.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>We talked to many people on the streets of Damascus and Homs, and many had never heard of the other two candidates.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>But as far as the campaigns are concerned, both of them are very present.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>There are many Hajjar and Nouri election posters up in Damascus, even though there are a lot more for Bashar al Assad&amp;apost;s re-election.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Assad&amp;apost;s campaign slogan is &amp;quot;unity&amp;quot; and he is trying to portray himself as a reluctant leader who is only running for office again because the people want him to.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>One of his election posters declares, &amp;quot;It is not your choice, the people have chosen you.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>It is hard to imagine that either candidate has a chance against Assad, but their campaigns certainly do not look like they are being repressed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>What should we look out for?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The big threat is that there could be widespread violence on election day.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The opposition says the poll is a sham and that it will be a major target.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Early voting at the Syrian embassy in Beirut had a massive turnout, but will that be replicated inside the country?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>If the turnout is high, that would indicate people in the areas where voting is possible take it seriously -- and opposition candidate Nouri says the election can&amp;apost;t be considered valid if turnout is lower than 50 percent.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Will the election be monitored?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Syria&amp;apost;s Deputy Foreign Minister Faisal al Mekdad told me there won&amp;apost;t be any monitors from the U.S., the EU, or the OSCE, but he did say that monitors from &amp;quot;other countries&amp;quot; will be present.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Mekdad said the presence of monitors would also depend on the security situations in certain parts of the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>What percentage of Syrians will be able to vote?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s almost impossible to say.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Nearly 3 million Syrians have been forced to flee the country and more than 6.5 million are internally displaced.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>It will obviously be difficult for them to vote.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Large swathes of Syria&amp;apost;s north and northeast, as well as some places in the south, are not under government control and there will be no election in those areas.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>There are some who say people could leave those areas and come over to the government side to vote, but that seems pretty utopian.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Voting will be possible in government-controlled areas, but it is not clear what percentage of the population actually still resides in these places.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Is it dangerous to vote?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>It is dangerous to vote in certain places.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>In areas along the Syrian coast like Tartus and Latakia it will not be too dangerous because they are firmly under the control of the government.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>But elsewhere there will be major security concerns as voters will be weary of the threat of car bombs and shelling at polling stations within range of rebel mortars.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>What will change?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>It is not clear what, if anything, will change as a result of this election.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>The agreement signed in Geneva earlier this year called for an inclusive body to govern Syria through a transitional period.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>The Syrian opposition and the West say the transitional period means that Assad must resign -- but while the regime acknowledges that institutions must be reshuffled to accommodate the opposition to some degree, it says Assad must stay at the helm.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>If Assad wins the election as expected, the prospect of him stepping down as part of a deal would seem even less likely than it does now.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>Why would someone &amp;quot;elected by the people&amp;quot; leave his post?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>That would be the argument coming out of Damascus.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>And the fact Assad now has the upper hand militarily in most places makes it even less likely he&amp;apost;ll step down any time soon.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
