<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2173" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/05/15/world/meast/egypt-al-jazeera-journalists-trial" date_published="2014-05-15 16:30:55" category="world" author="Sarah Sirgany and Reza Sayah, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Egypt trial of Al Jazeera journalists adjourned to May 22</title>
  <keywords>Al Jazeera journalists Egypt</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="15">NEW: Two lawyers quit the case, claim Al Jazeera wants to tarnish Egypt&amp;apost;s image.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Trial of Al Jazeera journalists on terrorism-related charges is adjourned to May 22.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">Court told the prosecution wants defense lawyers to pay $169,000 to see evidence.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="5">The defendants deny the charges against them, say they were doing their jobs.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-10 22:12:52" annotation_time="31.837">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2">Cairo The trial in Egypt of Al Jazeera journalists accused of terrorism-related offenses was adjourned Thursday until May 22.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="4">The journalists -- who are among a number of people arrested, not all of them Al Jazeera staff -- have denied the allegations against them, saying they were simply doing their jobs.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">The lawyer for Fahmy told the Cairo court that the prosecution had asked the defense lawyers to pay 1.2 million Egyptian pounds ($169,000) to see five CDs containing alleged evidence against their clients -- but refused to give them an official document indicating such request.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="1">The two lawyers representing Greste and Baher Mohamed quit the case Thursday, claiming in court that Al Jazeera was not concerned about the defendants and only wanted to tarnish Egypt&amp;apost;s image.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Cairo The trial in Egypt of Al Jazeera journalists accused of terrorism-related offenses was adjourned Thursday until May 22.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Correspondent Peter Greste, producer Mohammed Fahmy and producer Baher Mohamed have been in jail since December 29.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Their request for bail has been denied.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The three are charged with joining what the government says is a terrorist group -- the Muslim Brotherhood -- as well as broadcasting false information and working in Egypt without permits.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The journalists -- who are among a number of people arrested, not all of them Al Jazeera staff -- have denied the allegations against them, saying they were simply doing their jobs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The lawyer for Fahmy told the Cairo court that the prosecution had asked the defense lawyers to pay 1.2 million Egyptian pounds ($169,000) to see five CDs containing alleged evidence against their clients -- but refused to give them an official document indicating such request.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;The actual cost of copying five CDs doesn&amp;apost;t exceed 5 Egyptian pounds,&amp;quot; lawyer Khaled Abu Bakr told the court.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>He told CNN that he has never come across such exorbitant fees.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The judge ordered the prosecution to provide a document stipulating the fees.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Apart from Abu Bakr, all the defense lawyers and defendants want final arguments to begin.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Fahmy, who is a former CNN producer, told reporters that the prosecution is already stalling and won&amp;apost;t present the evidence purported to be on the CDs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Other defendants in the case, not including the three Al Jazeera journalists, told reporters they had been beaten and intimidated in prison after the last court hearing, when they complained to journalists of torture and abuse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>One of the defendants, Anas El Beltagy, son of Muslim Brotherhood leader Mohamed El Beltagy, said he had been put in solitary confinement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Another, Khaled Abdel Raouf, who has been on hunger strike for 55 days, said he had had no access to medical care.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The two lawyers representing Greste and Baher Mohamed quit the case Thursday, claiming in court that Al Jazeera was not concerned about the defendants and only wanted to tarnish Egypt&amp;apost;s image.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The lawyers were hired by Al Jazeera to represent the two journalists.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Assem Ghorob, Mohamed&amp;apost;s brother, told CNN that Al Jazeera has given assurances that the network will hire new lawyers for the case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;It was weird what happened in court today,&amp;quot; Ghorob said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m fine with getting new lawyers but I&amp;apost;m surprised the lawyers who quit criticized Al Jazeera in court.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>That could obviously hurt the case.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Human rights groups have criticized the trial, saying the arrests indicate authorities in Egypt are stifling dissent and freedom of the press.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Al Jazeera is a large TV news broadcaster and digital outlet with headquarters in Doha, Qatar.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
