<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2667" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/09/12/world/meast/syria-rebel-leader-accusation/index.html" date_published="2013-09-12 21:04:17" category="world" author="Mick Krever, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Rebel leader Idriss: Syria moving chemical weapons to Iraq, Lebanon</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Gen. Salim Idriss claims he has info showing Syria is moving chemical weapons.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">Senior Israeli officials say they haven&amp;apost;t seen such movement; Iraq firmly denies it.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="18">The Free Syrian Army chief says the rebels are getting &amp;quot;a lot of support&amp;quot; from the U.S. .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="23">He stresses that chemical weapons are one of many serious problems in Syria.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-11 18:16:45" annotation_time="57.042667">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">The head of the opposition Free Syrian Army told CNN&amp;apost;s Christiane Amanpour on Thursday he has intelligence showing Syrian President Bashar al-Assad&amp;apost;s government is moving its chemical weapons out of the country.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">Several senior Israeli officials told CNN&amp;apost;s Elise Labott that they have not seen movements into Lebanon or Iraq, and that they did not believe it made sense for the Syrians to be moving weapons so soon.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;We are getting now a lot of support from our American friends, but I can&amp;apost;t talk in detail about all kinds of the support,&amp;quot; he said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="4">And even if Idriss is proven wrong and Syria&amp;apost;s chemical weapons are wiped out as part of this process, the rebel leader stressed that bigger issues remain in a civil war that the U.N. estimates has killed more than 100,000 people -- most of them by conventional weapons.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The head of the opposition Free Syrian Army told CNN&amp;apost;s Christiane Amanpour on Thursday he has intelligence showing Syrian President Bashar al-Assad&amp;apost;s government is moving its chemical weapons out of the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;Today, we have information that the regime began to move chemical materials and chemical weapons to Lebanon and to Iraq,&amp;quot; Gen. Salim Idriss said from inside Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>CNN could not independently verify Idriss&amp;apost; claim.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Several senior Israeli officials told CNN&amp;apost;s Elise Labott that they have not seen movements into Lebanon or Iraq, and that they did not believe it made sense for the Syrians to be moving weapons so soon.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>And Iraq categorically denied that chemical weapons had crossed into its territory, with an adviser to Iraqi Prime Minister Nuri al-Maliki speculating &amp;quot;there is a political agency behind this claim.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;We were the victims of chemical weapons under Saddam&amp;apost;s regime,&amp;quot; said the adviser, Ali al-Moussawi.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;And we will never allow to let any country to transfer chemical materials to our lands at all.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Still, if the allegation were true, it could fundamentally shift the assessments of U.S. intelligence officials, CNN&amp;apost;s Barbara Starr reports.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Namely, these officials have said that al-Assad would not disperse his stockpile of chemical weapons because he knows the United States would not bomb it, that Syrian security forces firmly control the weapons and that there exists a large, secure infrastructure that has been moving these arms from rebel-held areas.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Moving these weapons into Iraq, Lebanon or some other country outside Syria might prompt U.S. intelligence authorities to question whether they were being transferred by a rogue element or whether it was evidence of a crack in the government&amp;apost;s control.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The Syrian opposition is afraid, Idriss told CNN&amp;apost;s Amanpour, that al-Assad&amp;apost;s forces will then use those weapons sometime in the future -- even after the international effort to collect and destroy its chemical weapons arsenal is finished.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;The regime,&amp;quot; he said, &amp;quot;is behaving like Saddam Hussein.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Idriss said he talked Thursday about what&amp;apost;s happening diplomatically with U.S. Secretary of State John Kerry, who the rebel leader claimed told him &amp;quot;that he will discuss with the Russians how honest the regime is.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;And if our friends discover that the regime is trying to play games and waste time,&amp;quot; Idriss said by way of summarizing Kerry&amp;apost;s remarks, &amp;quot;the threat of the strikes is still on the table.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Earlier on Thursday, Idriss told NPR that he had not received &amp;quot;any weapons from our American friends,&amp;quot; despite reports that lethal aid had indeed started reaching the Syrian opposition.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>That includes a U.S. official who told CNN on Wednesday that light and anti-tank weapons as well as ammunition -- paid for by the United States albeit made elsewhere -- had begun flowing to Syrian rebels over the past two weeks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Idriss told Amanpour that he &amp;quot;can&amp;apost;t talk about weapons,&amp;quot; though he did stress that opposition forces were getting help.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are getting now a lot of support from our American friends, but I can&amp;apost;t talk in detail about all kinds of the support,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>For its part, the opposition will support efforts to take control of and eventually dismantle Syria&amp;apost;s chemical weapons, with Idriss saying, &amp;quot;We will do our best to help them.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>But the rebel leader questioned that things will play out as hoped.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think the regime will prevent them to go to the locations and to do their job,&amp;quot; Idriss said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think the regime will tell them, &amp;apost;Today you can&amp;apost;t go out of the hotels because the situation is very dangerous, and tomorrow you can&amp;apost;t go,&amp;apost; and they will delay and delay.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>And even if Idriss is proven wrong and Syria&amp;apost;s chemical weapons are wiped out as part of this process, the rebel leader stressed that bigger issues remain in a civil war that the U.N. estimates has killed more than 100,000 people -- most of them by conventional weapons.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have many, many problems with the regime,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;The chemical weapons (are) not ... the only problem that we have.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
