<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2383" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/03/14/world/asia/kim-jong-un-companion" date_published="2014-03-14 16:48:48" category="world" author="Euan McKirdy, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Kim Jong Un&amp;apost;s voting companion sparks interest</title>
  <keywords>North Korea elections,Kim Jong Un,Kim Jong Un sister</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">North Korean leader Kim Jong Un won his first parliamentary election with 100% of the vote.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Who Kim chose to cast his vote with has sparked interest.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">Kim was accompanied to a polling station by his younger sister, Kim Yo Jong.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="11">Her presence was politically significant, the International Crisis Group told CNN.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-18 10:51:13" annotation_time="1775.799">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1, 2">That North Korean leader Kim Jong Un won his first parliamentary election with a clear 100% of the vote might not be remarkable, but who he chose to cast his vote with certainly has sparked interest amongst Korea-watchers.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="3">Kim was accompanied to a polling station at Kim Il Sung University of Politics by his younger sister Kim Yo Jong, in what was her first official appearance.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="4">Daniel Pinkston, Deputy Project Director, North East Asia for the International Crisis Group, told CNN that Kim Yo Jong&amp;apost;s presence by Kim&amp;apost;s side was politically significant.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>That North Korean leader Kim Jong Un won his first parliamentary election with a clear 100% of the vote might not be remarkable, but who he chose to cast his vote with certainly has sparked interest amongst Korea-watchers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Kim was accompanied to a polling station at Kim Il Sung University of Politics by his younger sister Kim Yo Jong, in what was her first official appearance.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The state-managed parliamentary election was the first &amp;quot;election&amp;quot; for Kim, who is the third leader in a dynastic lineage that has ruled the Stalinist state since 1948.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Critics have discounted North Korea&amp;apost;s electoral process as a political show to legitimize the country&amp;apost;s rubber stamp parliament, given that there is only one named candidate for each electoral district.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Unanimous vote, 100% turnout.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The country&amp;apost;s Central Election Committee released a report that Kim was unanimously elected as Deputy to the Supreme People&amp;apost;s Assembly (SPA) of the DPRK, with 100% turnout.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>On March 13, state media quoted a Foreign Ministry spokesman as saying: &amp;quot;All its citizens of the DPRK took part in the election to consolidate as firm as a rock the people&amp;apost;s power chosen by themselves, fully enjoying their rights as the genuine masters of the state and society, and voted for the candidates with loyalty and patriotism.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The spokesman criticized a U.S. State Department spokesman&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;impudent&amp;quot; comment that North Korea&amp;apost;s election process was undemocratic.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is nothing but a ridiculous jargon of those who cannot understand the advantageous election system of the DPRK as they are engrained with repugnance toward the Korean-style socialist system,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;The U.S. had better feel ashamed of the American-style election which decides everything with fraud and swindle and its dollar-almighty election system in which a duck on a pond can be a president if it has money, and mind its own affairs before impudently finding fault with others.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Daniel Pinkston, Deputy Project Director, North East Asia for the International Crisis Group, told CNN that Kim Yo Jong&amp;apost;s presence by Kim&amp;apost;s side was politically significant.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Recently over the past year there have been these glimpses of her in public and rumors about her position in the party,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s an event to introduce her.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Kim Yo Jong&amp;apost;s presence as a &amp;quot;senior official of the Party Central Committee&amp;quot; may point to a generational power shift, with some speculating that she may be ready to take over her aunt&amp;apost;s role in the upper echelons of North Korea&amp;apost;s political elite.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>There has been some confusion surrounding the current status of Kim&amp;apost;s aunt, who is also late ruler Kim Jong Il&amp;apost;s sister.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>South Korean intelligence agencies believe that it may refer to another individual.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Waning influence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>While Kim&amp;apost;s aunt&amp;apost;s name -- Kim Kyong Hui --appeared on a list of SPA members, a South Korean Unification Ministry spokesperson told CNN there is a possibility she has not been re-elected to the Assembly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;We cannot be 100% certain if that is her or someone else.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>We have not been able to confirm and need further verification,&amp;quot; the spokesperson said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Pinkston does not believe that Kim Kyong Hui is likely to suffer the same fate as her husband, Kim Jong Un&amp;apost;s former protector Jang Song Thaek, who was executed as an enemy of the state.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think her time is over and that her generation ... her time has passed ... she&amp;apost;s untouchable as part of the family whereas Jang Song Thaek was an outsider.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>(However) as far as political influence it&amp;apost;s basically over.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
