<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2717" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/04/06/world/africa/rwanda-cycling-team/index.html" date_published="2012-04-06 15:56:01" category="world" author="Errol Barnett, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Rwanda genocide survivors cycle towards London 2012</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Rwanda&amp;apost;s cycling team are survivors of its 1994 genocide.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">One member will compete at the 2012 Olympics.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6, 5, 4">Many started riding on heavy wooden bikes, used for farm transport.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-11 18:26:17" annotation_time="165.353" mapping_time_divergence="55.117664">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Musanze, Rwanda For Rwanda&amp;apost;s national cycling team, survivors of its genocide, cycling is proving to have an unlikely healing power.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">Eighteen years after the genocide of Tutsis that claimed an estimated 800,000 lives in all, Team Rwanda is now gaining international recognition, and one member will compete at this year&amp;apost;s summer Olympics.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">In Musanze, 96 kilometers outside the capital of Kigali, on one of the few paved roads in northwestern Rwanda, many get around on bicycles, some made entirely of wood.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">These wooden bicycles, typically made from acacia trees, evolved as a solution for wheel-barrowing crops from farm to farm.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">They are heavy, used by farmers to transport loads of up to 300 kg, and with only a thin piece of rubber for a tire, they are difficult to maneuver and brake suddenly.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Musanze, Rwanda For Rwanda&amp;apost;s national cycling team, survivors of its genocide, cycling is proving to have an unlikely healing power.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Eighteen years after the genocide of Tutsis that claimed an estimated 800,000 lives in all, Team Rwanda is now gaining international recognition, and one member will compete at this year&amp;apost;s summer Olympics.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>With a population of more than 11 million and a land size roughly half the size of Scotland, the east African nation of Rwanda is Africa&amp;apost;s most densely populated country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>In Musanze, 96 kilometers outside the capital of Kigali, on one of the few paved roads in northwestern Rwanda, many get around on bicycles, some made entirely of wood.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>These wooden bicycles, typically made from acacia trees, evolved as a solution for wheel-barrowing crops from farm to farm.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>They are heavy, used by farmers to transport loads of up to 300 kg, and with only a thin piece of rubber for a tire, they are difficult to maneuver and brake suddenly.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Because of this, they are banned from the main roads.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;If you hit something or somebody, that person would be dangerously hurt,&amp;quot; explains Francois Bizimana, one of the village&amp;apost;s bike makers, who has previously been hospitalized with injuries from an accident on one of his bikes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;You do a lot of damage when you get in an accident with them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Some of us are not used to road safety and rules, so that caused a lot of trouble for us.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>In 2006, when Rwanda&amp;apost;s first annual cycling festival was created by Jonathan &amp;quot;Jock&amp;quot; Boyer, the first American to finish the Tour de France, and mountain bike pioneer Tom Ritchey, it was named the Wooden Bike Classic in honor of these traditional contraptions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The event showcased so much talent that the next year, Boyer returned to establish and coach the country&amp;apost;s first national team, Team Rwanda.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>One of its five founding members, and winner of the first Wooden Bike Classic, Adrien Niyonshuti, will represent Rwanda at the 2012 summer Olympics.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Niyonshuti was seven years old in 1994, when conflict between two ethnic groups, the Hutu majority and the Tutsi minority, spiraled into a genocide that claimed an estimated 800,000 lives over 100 days.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>His grandmother and six of his brothers were killed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Another founding team member, Jean de Dieu &amp;quot;Rafiki&amp;quot; Uwimana contracted malaria while sleeping outdoors, after escaping with his grandmother.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>He was separated from his parents and brother, and thought they were dead for five years after the genocide.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Team Rwanda is a valuable means of bringing men from different backgrounds together.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Some team members travel as much as 230 kilometers -- by bicycle -- to get to training sessions at the team&amp;apost;s base in northwestern Ruhengeri.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Besides cycling three times a week, they do yoga and in the evenings, take English classes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;Then they get three great meals,&amp;quot; says Kimberly Coats, director of marketing and logistics.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;Nutrition is important.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Our food choices are limited,&amp;quot; she continues.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;They&amp;apost;re used to eating for bulk, not nutritional value.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Now, they&amp;apost;ve started to see the benefits of nutrition, stretching, training program and they&amp;apost;re doing well.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>For some, the rigorous training regimen is a welcome distraction from painful memories.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;You never forget it, in your life,&amp;quot; says Uwimana.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;But...I&amp;apost;m busy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>My future is looking good now.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Many people know me, and I&amp;apost;m changing life for my country and my family also.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Their success is helping to change lingering perceptions of Rwanda as a broken, dangerous and impoverished place.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s also helping to change how Rwandans view themselves.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Having toured America, South Africa and Gabon with his team, Uwimana has concrete aspirations for his homeland.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;So my future is to help my friends and to be an ambassador for my country.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
