<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2123" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/29/world/asia/china-censorship-hong-kong/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-09-29 09:48:55" category="world" author="Madison Park, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>China&amp;apost;s Internet firewall censors Hong Kong protests</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="33">China&amp;apost;s news and social media are stripped of discussions on Hong Kong protests.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="27">China fears discussion of political rights, dissent and civil disobedience, observers say.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">Instagram has been blocked since Sunday when protests heated up.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2015-01-26 11:24:37" annotation_time="46.081">
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">On the social media front, Instagram has been blocked in China since Sunday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="27" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;The Chinese government fears that the kinds of protest and exercise of rights demanding greater political freedom will be contagious and trigger something in China,&amp;quot; he said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="33" ids_highlights="1">Searches on China&amp;apost;s top search engine sites such as Baidu and Sogou for the terms &amp;quot;Hong Kong protest&amp;quot; or even &amp;quot;Hong Kong students&amp;quot; yielded irrelevant results such as stories showing a a blissful image of Hong Kong residents picnicking on the grass or how Hong Kong is welcoming tourists from the mainland during the national holiday week.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Hong Kong News articles, social media posts and images about Hong Kong&amp;apost;s pro-democracy protests are being heavily censored behind China notorious firewall.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Chinese state-run news outlets have largely ignored the pro-democracy protests except for the same Xinhua story in which the Hong Kong chief executive CY Leung denounced the demonstrations as &amp;quot;unlawful.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>In Hong Kong, residents have poured into the streets to defy Beijing&amp;apost;s vision for its political future in the midst of its longest series of political protests since the 1997 handover.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Their goal is to pressure China into giving the former British colony full universal suffrage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Dozens have been reported injured by authorities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>On the social media front, Instagram has been blocked in China since Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Users cannot view images and a message reads on the site: &amp;quot;Can&amp;apost;t refresh feed.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>China observers noted that while the app can&amp;apost;t be accessed in China for most, the country&amp;apost;s First Lady Peng Liyuan&amp;apost;s official Instagram account posted a picture of her and her husband, China&amp;apost;s President Xi Jinping, on Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The photo app has been viewed as a relatively non-political social media platform, said King-wa Fu, an assistant professor at the University of Hong Kong.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;In the past two days, we can see a lot of people holding phones and taking pictures of different (Hong Kong protest) scenes on Instagram, Facebook and sharing it around,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s a huge amount of pictures posted in a short period of time.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>That may have led to the blocking of the photo-sharing app, Fu said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The Chinese government maintains strict controls over what can be seen on the Internet and social media.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>This firewall extends to Facebook, Twitter and YouTube, and Google is rarely accessible.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Hong Kong does not fall under the same restrictions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>China&amp;apost;s massively popular microblogging site, Sina Weibo is being censored at the highest rate this year with &amp;quot;Hong Kong&amp;quot; as the most commonly deleted term, according to Weiboscope, a Hong Kong University effort that monitors deleted posts.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>About 152 out of 10,000 Weibo posts were blocked, said Fu, who also works on Weiboscope.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Why China censors Hong Kong demonstrations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Photos of police confronting young pro-democracy protesters are sensitive in China, because it&amp;apost;s a reminder of Tiananamen Square, in which Chinese authorities cracked down on student protesters on June 4, 1989, Fu said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;If you look at the political agenda of protests in Hong Kong, they have the same objectives.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>They&amp;apost;re calling for democracy in Hong Kong and political reform.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>These are two main sensitive topics in China.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>This is the topic they don&amp;apost;t want the Chinese citizens to widely discuss,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>But China cannot completely black out any knowledge of the Hong Kong protests, especially with 40 million mainland arrivals to the special administrative region every year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Chinese authorities cannot control whether its citizens know about pro-democracy Hong Kong protests, but they can shut down &amp;quot;autonomous communication space&amp;quot; where public discussions can take place in China, said Xiao Qiang, an adjunct professor for the School of Information at the University of California at Berkeley.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;That&amp;apost;s what they&amp;apost;re trying to repress,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Chinese government fears that the kinds of protest and exercise of rights demanding greater political freedom will be contagious and trigger something in China,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;That&amp;apost;s what they fear the most.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>What you can see in China.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The protest intensified Sunday when Hong Kong police unleashed tear gas on demonstrators.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>But there was no mention of it on the evening Chinese state-run CCTV news.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>On Monday morning, the homepage of China&amp;apost;s major portals such as Sina, Sohu, 163 and China&amp;apost;s state-run news agency Xinhua did not mention the events either.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Searches on China&amp;apost;s top search engine sites such as Baidu and Sogou for the terms &amp;quot;Hong Kong protest&amp;quot; or even &amp;quot;Hong Kong students&amp;quot; yielded irrelevant results such as stories showing a a blissful image of Hong Kong residents picnicking on the grass or how Hong Kong is welcoming tourists from the mainland during the national holiday week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>When relevant results appeared on the Chinese search engines, the articles contained a distinctively pro-China slant and even surfaced a month-old article about a small pro-Beijing counter-protest in Hong Kong.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Content that was more sympathetic to Hong Kong protesters had been removed with messages reading: &amp;quot;In accordance with relevant laws, regulations and policies, search results could not be displayed.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
