<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2505" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/05/01/world/africa/nigeria-abducted-girls/index.html?hpt=wo_c2" date_published="2014-05-01 08:35:56" category="world" author="Faith Karimi and Vladimir Duthiers, CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Nigerians demand government #BringBackOurGirls</title>
  <keywords>Nigeria abducted schoolgirls,Bring back our girls</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="31">NEW: &amp;quot;We mandate the federal government to bring back our daughters,&amp;quot; musician says .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">Armed men herded the girls out of bed and forced them into trucks on April 14.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">The convoy of trucks disappears into the dense forest bordering Cameroon.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="15">Angry parents accuse authorities of playing politics with the lives of their children.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-12 15:54:46" annotation_time="14.511499">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">Armed men herded the girls out of bed and forced them into trucks on April 14 in the town of Chibok.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">The convoy of trucks then disappeared into the dense forest bordering Cameroon.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="4">In Chibok, angry parents accused authorities of playing politics with the lives of their children.</sentence>
      <sentence id="31" ids_highlights="1">We mandate the federal government to bring back our daughters, and our children,&amp;quot; he said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content> Nigerians took to the streets Thursday to demand the government do more to rescue scores of girls abducted by militants more than two weeks ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Militants seized about 230 girls in the dead of the night at a high school in the nation&amp;apost;s far northeast, a hotbed for Islamist group Boko Haram.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Armed men herded the girls out of bed and forced them into trucks on April 14 in the town of Chibok.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The convoy of trucks then disappeared into the dense forest bordering Cameroon.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Roughly 200 girls are still missing, although the authorities and parents differ on the number.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Nigerians have rallied for days to criticize the government&amp;apost;s handling of the rescue efforts.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Hundreds wept and chanted &amp;quot;bring back our girls&amp;quot; during protests in the capital of Abuja on Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>A day later, protesters gathered in Lagos.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Shortly after the abductions last month, frustrated Chibok residents went into the forest in motorbikes to search for the girls.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>During their nine-hour trek, they never saw a single soldier in the forest where authorities believe the militants took the girls, said Enoch Mark, whose daughter and two nieces were among the kidnapped.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;A total of 230 parents registered the names of their daughters who were missing on the day of the kidnap,&amp;quot; said Asabe Kwambura, principal of the Government Girls Secondary School.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;From my records, 43 girls have so far escaped on their own from their kidnappers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>We still have 187 girls missing.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Angry relatives.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>In Chibok, angry parents accused authorities of playing politics with the lives of their children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Witnesses have seen militants in dozens of vehicles headed to nearby Cameroon, said Ayuba Alamson, whose two nieces were among the kidnapped.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>In a statement Thursday, Nigeria&amp;apost;s Defense Ministry said it&amp;apost;s committed to the search.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;A lot of information has been received in the efforts at securing the freedom of the girls.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The armed forces assures all Nigerians that it will continue to appraise every information received during this operation accordingly,&amp;quot; it said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;While it will not relent in its efforts in this search, the armed forces is mindful of the fact that some of the information with which it has been inundated are actually a ploy to distract it from its goal of dealing with terrorism and other violent crimes aimed at crippling the nation.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Borno state Education Commissioner Musa Inuwa Kubo similarly said that the government and military are doing whatever it takes to secure their release.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is a delicate situation that requires careful handling,&amp;quot; Kubo said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;When you have heavily armed men holding close to 200 girls hostage, you have to be very careful in your approach so as not to risk the safety of these girls you want to rescue.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>He said authorities are withholding information for safety reasons.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is a security issue and we just can&amp;apost;t be divulging all the efforts we are making to get these girls freed,&amp;quot; the education commissioner said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>#BringBackOurGirls.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>But angry Nigerians said authorities are not doing enough.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>They took to social media using hashtags #BringBackOurGirls and #BringBackOurDaughters to demand more from the government.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>David Peter, a sound engineer, music producer and recording artist in Lagos, sent CNN an iReport in which he calls on the government to do more.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;If you&amp;apost;re not safe anywhere in the world, you should be safe in your house, in your own back yard.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>We mandate the federal government to bring back our daughters, and our children,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Boko Haram&amp;apost;s name translates to &amp;quot;Western education is a sin&amp;quot; in the local language.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The group especially opposes the education of women.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Under its version of Sharia law, women should be at home raising children and looking after their husbands, not at school learning to read and write.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Rights groups say the militants kidnap girls to perform chores and sexual services.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>