<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2409" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/07/03/world/asia/malaysia-new-zealand-envoy-charge/index.html" date_published="2014-07-03 09:06:05" category="world" author="Tim Hume and Elizabeth Joseph, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Malaysia to return envoy to New Zealand over sex charge</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Malaysian official who used diplomatic immunity to flee a sex charge caused outcry in New Zealand.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="10">New Zealand PM John Key said he wanted the man to face justice in New Zealand.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">Malaysia said Wednesday it would return the official to cooperate with New Zealand authorities.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="3">The 38-year-old face charges of assault with attempt to commit rape, and burglary.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 20:55:28" annotation_time="68.45234">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Malaysia says it will send back to New Zealand an envoy who used diplomatic immunity to flee a sex charge there, defusing a messy wrangle between the nations.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="3">Malaysia&amp;apost;s government released a statement Wednesday saying it would return Second Warrant Officer Muhammad Rizalman Ismail to New Zealand &amp;quot;to cooperate fully and assist&amp;quot; authorities in their investigation into allegations against him.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="4">Ismail, 38, faces charges of burglary and assault with intent to commit rape, relating to an alleged attack in Wellington on May 9, according to officials in both countries.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="2">But it later emerged that while at a formal level New Zealand had pressed Malaysia to waive Ismail&amp;apost;s diplomatic immunity, Malaysian officials were under the impression after informal discussions that the New Zealand government was comfortable with him returning home to face justice, CNN affiliate TVNZ reported.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Malaysia says it will send back to New Zealand an envoy who used diplomatic immunity to flee a sex charge there, defusing a messy wrangle between the nations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Malaysia&amp;apost;s government released a statement Wednesday saying it would return Second Warrant Officer Muhammad Rizalman Ismail to New Zealand &amp;quot;to cooperate fully and assist&amp;quot; authorities in their investigation into allegations against him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Ismail, 38, faces charges of burglary and assault with intent to commit rape, relating to an alleged attack in Wellington on May 9, according to officials in both countries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Superintendent Sam Hoyle, commander of Wellington police district where the alleged offenses took place, said in a statement that Ismail would be arrested at the New Zealand border and taken to the nearest court on his return.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>No date had yet been set for Ismail&amp;apost;s return, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>New Zealand Foreign Minister Murray McCully welcomed the news of Ismail&amp;apost;s impending return, saying in a statement that it underlined the &amp;quot;good faith and integrity&amp;quot; with which Malaysia had approached the case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Ismail was working as a defense staff assistant at Malaysia&amp;apost;s High Commission in Wellington when he allegedly stalked a 21-year-old woman and attacked her in her home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>He was apprehended by police and appeared in court the next day, but returned to Malaysia with his family on May 22, Malaysia&amp;apost;s Ministry of Foreign Affairs said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The case caused an outcry when it was reported in the New Zealand media, with Prime Minister John Key telling reporters it was his country&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;very strong preference&amp;quot; that the man face justice there, rather than in Malaysia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>But it later emerged that while at a formal level New Zealand had pressed Malaysia to waive Ismail&amp;apost;s diplomatic immunity, Malaysian officials were under the impression after informal discussions that the New Zealand government was comfortable with him returning home to face justice, CNN affiliate TVNZ reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>McCully apologized Wednesday for his ministry&amp;apost;s handling of the case, TVNZ reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is now clear to me that officials engaged in informal communications over what is a complex case, in a manner that would have been ambiguous to the Malaysian government,&amp;quot; he said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;I can say that the Malaysian side have acted entirely in good faith.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Under the 1961 Vienna Convention, diplomats are granted full immunity from local laws while embassy staff are immune from criminal charges but not from specific civil matters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Malaysia&amp;apost;s Ministry of Foreign affairs said in its statement that it had &amp;quot;complete faith in the New Zealand legal system&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;full confidence&amp;quot; Ismail would be dealt with fairly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
