<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2161" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/07/30/world/europe/spain-train-crash" date_published="2013-07-30 16:21:02" category="world" author="CNN Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Driver on phone when Spanish train derailed, court says</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="14">NEW: Phone call may have distracted train driver shortly before crash, expert says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">Court: Driver received call from railway staff minutes before crash.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">At derailment, train was going 95 mph, court says; speed limit for bend is 49 mph.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="1">79 people killed in Wednesday&amp;apost;s derailment in northwestern Spain.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-08 23:28:34" annotation_time="35.134335">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="4">The driver of a train that derailed in northwestern Spain last week, killing 79 people, was on the phone with railway staff when the train crashed, court officials announced Tuesday, citing information from data recorders.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="3">The train was going 153 kph (95 mph) when it derailed, the superior tribunal of Galicia said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">Minutes before the derailment, Garzon received a call on his work phone, apparently receiving instructions on the way to Ferrol from a Renfe staff member, the court said Tuesday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="1">Steve Harrod, a railroad transportation expert at Ohio&amp;apost;s University of Dayton, said he was stunned by the report that the driver may have been speaking on the phone shortly before the crash.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The driver of a train that derailed in northwestern Spain last week, killing 79 people, was on the phone with railway staff when the train crashed, court officials announced Tuesday, citing information from data recorders.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The train was going 153 kph (95 mph) when it derailed, the superior tribunal of Galicia said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s nearly twice the speed limit on the curve where the accident happened.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Authorities have charged the train&amp;apost;s driver, Francisco Jose Garzon, with 79 counts of homicide by professional recklessness and an undetermined number of counts of causing injury by professional recklessness.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>A court has granted Garzon conditional release, but his license to operate a train has been suspended for six months.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>He also was required to surrender his passport and report to court weekly.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>CNN efforts to locate him have been unsuccessful.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The train, nearing the end of a six-hour trip between Madrid and Ferrol, derailed Wednesday evening as it hurtled around a bend in Santiago de Compostela.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Minutes before the derailment, Garzon received a call on his work phone, apparently receiving instructions on the way to Ferrol from a Renfe staff member, the court said Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Background noise suggested he was looking at or shuffling papers, the court said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>On Spain&amp;apost;s railroad system, command and control posts can communicate with drivers at any point during a journey, a spokeswoman from Renfe -- the Spanish railroad company -- told CNN&amp;apost;s Karl Penhaul.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Drivers communicate via radio-telephones known in Spanish as &amp;quot;tren-tierras&amp;quot; or train-to-land.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>But drivers also use mobile phones if radio-telephones are not working or &amp;quot;when it&amp;apost;s considered necessary,&amp;quot; the spokeswoman said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Steve Harrod, a railroad transportation expert at Ohio&amp;apost;s University of Dayton, said he was stunned by the report that the driver may have been speaking on the phone shortly before the crash.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>In the United States, Harrod said, railroad drivers are not allowed to use cell phones to prevent dangerous distractions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Shortly before the train crashed, according to reports, the Spanish train had passed from a computer-controlled area of the track to a zone that requires the driver to take control of braking and acceleration, Harrod said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s possible that the driver&amp;apost;s phone conversation -- which apparently was part of his official capacity as a driver -- distracted him and he missed the transition from automatic to driver control,&amp;quot; Harrod said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>He may have been unaware he was in control of the train and realized, &amp;apost;oh, no, we&amp;apost;re headed for a curve.&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>If that&amp;apost;s true, I really don&amp;apost;t think it was his fault.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The Renfe spokeswoman told CNN that command and control posts have real-time systems to show each train&amp;apost;s precise location at a given time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>If this were the case, a controller who would have phoned the train driver might have known the train was approaching a curve.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>According to an interview in state-owned Efe news service with the president of the state-owned Administrator of Railway Infrastructures, the train should have started slowing down about 4 kilometers (2.48 miles) before the curve.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>At 192 kph, the train would have been traveling about 3.2 kilometers a minute.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>He hit the brakes seconds before the crash, bringing the speed down from 192 kph (119 mph), according to the court.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>He was still on the phone when the train flew off the tracks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Of the 79 who died in the ensuing wreck, 63 were from Spain.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Others were from the United States, Latin America and Europe.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The victims were remembered Monday in a memorial Mass at a Catholic cathedral in Santiago de Compostela.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;Our brothers lost their lives ... when they had so many plans,&amp;quot; said Archbishop Julian Barrio.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>It is not easy to understand and accept this reality,&amp;quot; he said, &amp;quot;but I say to you, let our pain not be wasted.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Everything has meaning in our lives.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>We are not shouting in a vacuum.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
