<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2148" link="http://cnn.com/2013/10/02/world/africa/kenya-mall-attack-shabaab-warning/index.html" date_published="2013-10-02 11:12:44" category="world" author="CNN Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Deadly mall attack: It&amp;apost;s not over, Somali terrorists tell Kenya</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">The Somali terrorism group al-Shabaab issued a threatening statement to Kenya Wednesday .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">Al-Shabaab fighters held the mall for four days.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="16">Kenyan forces say they killed five terrorists and took at least 11 into custody.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-17 13:55:26" annotation_time="35.007">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">That was the message terrorists of Al-Shabaab gave to Kenya on Wednesday, as officials still sorted through rubble and clues left in the wake of the recent massacre that took 67 lives at a Nairobi shopping mall.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">For four days, starting on September 21, Al-Shabaab fighters spread gunfire and flames through Nairobi&amp;apost;s Westgate Shopping Mall, leaving it partially destroyed, stained in blood and littered with bodies.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="3">Kenyan forces killed five terrorists, and 11 others are in custody over possible links to the attacks, President Uhuru Kenyatta has said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>We&amp;apost;re not done yet.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>That was the message terrorists of Al-Shabaab gave to Kenya on Wednesday, as officials still sorted through rubble and clues left in the wake of the recent massacre that took 67 lives at a Nairobi shopping mall.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The Somali militant group handed the threatening statement to regional media, which passed it on to CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>For four days, starting on September 21, Al-Shabaab fighters spread gunfire and flames through Nairobi&amp;apost;s Westgate Shopping Mall, leaving it partially destroyed, stained in blood and littered with bodies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Members of Kenya&amp;apost;s government were mute about what they had seen inside after emerging from an inspection there earlier this week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>CNN learned that the Westgate mall attackers tortured some of the hostages.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Military doctors said militants severed hands, cut off noses and, in some cases, hanged hostages.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>CNN has seen photographic evidence of one dead victim with a hand amputated.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>In the coming days and weeks, members of Parliament are expected to grill intelligence officials to find out more about how the attack occurred.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Forewarned?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>A number of Kenya&amp;apost;s Cabinet members and defense officials were warned about the possibility that Al-Shabaab was planning to carry out such an attack a year before gunman stormed the Nairobi mall, according to several police and intelligence sources.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The warnings were made by the country&amp;apost;s National Intelligence Service as part of regular situational reports given to Cabinet members, the inspector general of police, members of the National Security Advisory Council and military intelligence officials.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>CNN has seen an electronic version of those reports, which contain an extensive list of terror threats from several regions across Kenya over an extended period, but they also specify Al-Shabaab posed a threat to several targets, including Westgate Shopping Mall.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The news about the intelligence warnings comes amid revelations that the mall favored by Westerners and tourists was long considered a possible terror target.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Al-Shabaab made statements claiming responsibility, including saying on Twitter that it sent the gunmen in retaliation for Kenya&amp;apost;s involvement in an African Union military effort against the group, which is al Qaeda&amp;apost;s proxy in Somalia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Kenyan forces killed five terrorists, and 11 others are in custody over possible links to the attacks, President Uhuru Kenyatta has said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>But an immense amount of work remains to learn how Al-Shabaab was able to pull off such a well-coordinated and brazen attack.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The terror group was thought to be badly bruised by recent losses in its Somalian homeland.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Kenyan military intervention.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Last year, the Kenyan military was part of a peacekeeping force that defeated Al-Shabaab forces to liberate the key Somali port of Kismayo.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Since Kenya launched attacks against Al-Shabaab in Somalia in 2011, the group has hurled grenades at Kenyan churches, bus stops and other public places.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The mall attack was the deadliest terror attack in Kenya since al Qaeda blew up the U.S. Embassy there in 1998, killing 213 people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Terrorism experts say the attack bears eerie similarities to the 2008 siege of a hotel in , another upscale target with Western appeal.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Lashkar-e-Tayyiba, a Pakistani terrorist group, held the hotel for more than three days, killing 166 people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>