<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2992" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/08/17/world/meast/yazidi-refugees/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-08-17 10:41:43" category="world" author="Ivan Watson and Warzer Jaff, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Yazidi refugees braced for life in exile</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7">Kurdish photographer Warzer Jaff spends week documenting Yazidi Kurds.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12">ISIS has hounded Yazidis from their ancient homeland in northern Iraq.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="14">Tens of thousands of families have sought shelter in Iraqi Kurdistan.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="16">Each refugee shares horrifying stories of abduction and murder.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2015-01-30 15:02:30" annotation_time="33.2725">
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">Kurdish photographer Warzer Jaff spent a week documenting the exodus of the Yazidis from their ancient homeland.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">In the weeks since ISIS militants overran cities and towns in northern Iraq, the Yazidis joined a modern-day exodus of hundreds of thousands of other Iraqis.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="3">Instantly made homeless, tens of thousands of these families have sought shelter in Iraqi Kurdistan.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="4">Each refugee shares horrifying stories of abduction and murder.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>They are the faces of an entire community on the run.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Singled out, threatened, chased at gunpoint from their homes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Pursued purely because they are members of an ethnic and religious minority.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Iraq&amp;apost;s Yazidi Kurds are no strangers to persecution.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Their faith teaches them that throughout history, they have been subjected to 72 genocides.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Many world leaders fear they are on the brink of a 73rd massacre, this time at the hands of the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria, which calls itself the Islamic State.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Kurdish photographer Warzer Jaff spent a week documenting the exodus of the Yazidis from their ancient homeland.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>What is immediately striking in his portraits are their piercing eyes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am fascinated with the deep sadness in their eyes,&amp;quot; Jaff says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;You don&amp;apost;t see one single happy face.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>There is little room for joy when one has been made instantly homeless.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>In the weeks since ISIS militants overran cities and towns in northern Iraq, the Yazidis joined a modern-day exodus of hundreds of thousands of other Iraqis.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Most of those fleeing come from the many other ethnic and religious minorities that make up the mosaic of the region, including Chaldeans, Assyrians, Turcomen, Shi&amp;apost;ites, Shabbak, Kurds.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Instantly made homeless, tens of thousands of these families have sought shelter in Iraqi Kurdistan.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Driving through this region, one can see families squatting under bridges, camping in derelict buildings, unfinished construction sites, churches, youth centers, open fields.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Each refugee shares horrifying stories of abduction and murder.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Even more disturbing, the frequent refrain that &amp;quot;our neighbors did this to us.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Their claims that Arab tribesmen joined in the looting and kidnapping of these defenseless minorities suggests there is little hope these communities will one day live side by side together again in peace.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>As one senior Kurdish official put it, &amp;quot;the social fabric has been torn.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;I don&amp;apost;t want to live with Arabs anymore, they take our land, they kidnap our women, and they kill us, why should I live with them?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>asked Ali Khalid, 75, a Yazidi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>He wandered amid the tents of a brand new refugee camp leaning on a cane; his long white mustache, a proud symbol for Yazidi men, drooping over his mouth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Like nearly every other displaced Iraqi we met over the last week, Khalid urged Western governments to grant his people asylum in Europe or North America.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Not far away, a grieving mother showed a laminated identity card.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>It belonged to her 20-year old daughter, Baran.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>She was fatally wounded by shrapnel two weeks ago, Khokhe Namir said, while racing out into the backyard to pull a child back to safety.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;I buried her with my own hands,&amp;quot; Namir said, scraping at the dirt with her fingers, as tears streamed down her cheeks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Amid the grief and despair, there are still moments of childlike innocence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>In a refugee camp for Iraqis that sprouted up in a Kurdish-controlled enclave in Syria, a red-haired girl picked through a pile of second-hand clothes donated by local Kurds.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;I like the bright colors and the flowers,&amp;quot; she said, after eyeing a long dress decorated with pink flowers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Last Friday, Jaff wandered up from a tent in a refugee camp in Iraqi Kurdistan visibly shaken.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;There&amp;apost;s a newborn baby who was born on the mountain, I&amp;apost;m afraid she&amp;apost;s going to die,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>In the tent, the parents of the 6-day-old girl had bound their infant in a sheet and laid her on the dirt, atop a pile of blankets and cushions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>They didn&amp;apost;t have a cradle for the child.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The girl was born on Sinjar Mountain.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Tens of thousands of Yazidis sought refuge on its heights as they fled ISIS fighters, only to find themselves trapped and surrounded by the militants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Jaff took the little girl&amp;apost;s parents into town and bought them a cradle and extra food for their baby.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Across the Kurdish regions of Iraq and Syria, there have been many similar acts of kindness and generosity from locals toward their less fortunate cousins from farther south.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>The baby&amp;apost;s parents told me despite the heat, she was eating normally.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The girl appeared healthy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Her mother said she was thinking of naming her child Hajar.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Loosely translated, that means migrant or as the family interpreted it, &amp;quot;Exile.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>READ: After the rescue: A Yazidi family&amp;apost;s harrowing flight to escape ISIS.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>