<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2966" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/05/28/world/asia/sewol-yoo-manhunt/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-05-29 02:52:43" category="world" author="KJ Kwon and Madison Park, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Where is South Korea&amp;apost;s most wanted man?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3, 1">73-year-old millionaire eludes capture, despite South Korea&amp;apost;s manhunt.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Yoo Byung Eun wanted for his ties to Sewol ferry operation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">His representative has denied Yoo had any connection to company.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="19">South Korean president denounces family for &amp;quot;mocking the law&amp;quot; .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 20:37:19" annotation_time="76.77767" mapping_time_divergence="19.194418">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1, 2">South Korea&amp;apost;s most wanted man, who is believed to have ties to the company that operated the ill-fated Sewol ferry, has eluded arrest for weeks, leaving authorities red-faced for not finding the high-profile billionaire.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">Through an investment vehicle and subsidiary, Yoo Byung Eun, 73, and his two sons are believed to have controlled the shipping company that operated the ferry, according to the semi-official Yonhap news agency.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">In late April, Yoo&amp;apost;s representatives sent a statement denying that he had any direct or indirect connection to Chonghaejin Marine Company.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="4">&amp;quot;The Yoo Byung Eun family, who is the fundamental cause of this tragedy, is mocking the law and causing public rage instead of coming in front of the people to apologize and tell the truth,&amp;quot; she said on Tuesday.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>South Korea&amp;apost;s most wanted man, who is believed to have ties to the company that operated the ill-fated Sewol ferry, has eluded arrest for weeks, leaving authorities red-faced for not finding the high-profile billionaire.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The Sewol ferry sank on April 16, killing 288 people on board.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Through an investment vehicle and subsidiary, Yoo Byung Eun, 73, and his two sons are believed to have controlled the shipping company that operated the ferry, according to the semi-official Yonhap news agency.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>In late April, Yoo&amp;apost;s representatives sent a statement denying that he had any direct or indirect connection to Chonghaejin Marine Company.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Yoo is wanted for questioning in connection with an investigation into alleged funds embezzlement, tax evasion and other irregularities that prosecutors say could have contributed to the sinking.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>A South Korean court has issued a warrant for Yoo&amp;apost;s arrest.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Investigators are looking into why the ferry capsized, including factors such as imbalance of weight on the ship, overloaded and improperly secured cargo, and actions by the company and crew.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The Incheon District prosecutor&amp;apost;s office said on Tuesday: &amp;quot;The ones who are most directly responsible for the accident are officials with Cheonghaejin ... Our prosecutor&amp;apost;s office is currently investigating Yoo Byung Eun, who is standing at the very top of it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Yoo has defied summons to report to the prosecutor&amp;apost;s office, and gone into hiding.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The prosecutor&amp;apost;s office has come under public criticism for waiting for Yoo to appear of his own volition, which some say gave him plenty of time to flee.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Searching for Yoo.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Yoo is known as the &amp;quot;millionaire without a face&amp;quot; because of his reluctance to appear in public.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Yoo has four sons and daughters, three of their whereabouts are unknown.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Four members of the religious group his father-in-law founded have been arrested, accused of aiding Yoo.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>South Korea&amp;apost;s Justice Department said it requested its French counterparts to make the &amp;quot;provisional arrest&amp;quot; of his daughter.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The younger Yoo has been detained by French authorities in connection with the Sewol investigation, said Magalie Josse, Paris court spokeswoman.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>French authorities will determine whether to extradite the younger Yoo, according to the South Korea&amp;apost;s Ministry of Justice.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>South Korean President Park Geun-hye lashed out against the Yoo family this week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Yoo Byung Eun family, who is the fundamental cause of this tragedy, is mocking the law and causing public rage instead of coming in front of the people to apologize and tell the truth,&amp;quot; she said on Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;Such an act by Yoo&amp;apost;s family is a challenge to our society and an act of crime that cannot be protected.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>This week, the reward for information for the capture of Yoo was raised to nearly $500,000 and about $100,000 for his eldest son.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>South Korean media showed pictures of possible disguises for Yoo and his appearance throughout the years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Yoo&amp;apost;s religious group.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Yoo is a religious figure of Gu Won Pa (which translates to &amp;quot;salvation group&amp;quot;), also known as the Evangelical Baptist Church.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Some members of the group have protested in front of the prosecutor&amp;apost;s office in what they consider religious persecution.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Last week, nearly a hundred members of the religious group stood outside its mountain compound as investigators arrived to search for Yoo.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The supporters said the church had nothing to do with the allegations and likened the case to religious persecution, according to Yonhap.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Investigators have also started looking into the practices of the group.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are also in cooperation with nationwide police forces closely investigating buildings and lands related to Gu Won Pa,&amp;quot; said an official from the prosecutor&amp;apost;s office.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are also not ruling out that he (Yoo) was smuggled out of the country and hence, we are collecting intelligence concentrated on ports.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Yoo&amp;apost;s history.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Yoo has had brushes with the law.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>He was convicted on fraud charges in the 1990s and spent four years in prison, according to South Korean media reports.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>In 1987, he was under investigation after more than 30 people from a religious group were found dead, bound and gagged in a factory outside of Seoul.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Officials investigated the incident as a mass murder-suicide, and also looked into whether Yoo had any connection to the event, but determined he wasn&amp;apost;t involved.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Yoo is also known to have an artistic alter ego -- Ahae -- a photographer who has won international acclaim.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>His website appears to show Yoo taking pictures, but his face is not visible.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>According the website bio, Ahae was born in 1941 in Japan, where his family was during Japanese colonial rule of Korea.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>On April 25, a lengthy statement from his representative was released sending condolences to the victims of the Sewol accident and condemning what it called an &amp;quot;undeserved attack against AHAE, his character and his credentials as an artist.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Meanwhile, off the southwestern coast of Korea, search operations continue around the sunken ferry as 16 people remain missing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
