<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2460" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/03/31/world/asia/malaysia-airlines-flight-simulator-mitchell-casado-profile/index.html?hpt=bosread" date_published="2014-03-31 21:20:02" category="world" author="Martin Savidge, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Mitchell Casado, reluctant &amp;apost;pilot of the people&amp;apost;</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Mitchell Casado doesn&amp;apost;t like to see himself on camera, but he is a natural on-air.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="19">Fascination with flying became obsession when he got a toy plane as a gift at age 7.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="21">He wasn&amp;apost;t good at math &amp;amp; suffered stint of homelessness en route to becoming pilot.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="61">He&amp;apost;s married to his childhood sweetheart, and he often worries about his pet dwarf rabbits.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 16:03:49" annotation_time="49.798">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">Casado never wanted to be on camera.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="2">Fascination about flying turned into obsession -- his word -- for all things aviation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="3">He wasn&amp;apost;t good at math, but his sights set firmly on the goal of flying one day, he studied hard to master calculus and geometry.</sentence>
      <sentence id="61" ids_highlights="4">He&amp;apost;s married to his childhood sweetheart, Deborah, whom he married three years ago.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Toronto The disappearance of Malaysia Airlines Flight 370 has propelled Mitchell Casado into the realm of aviation analyst celebrity -- and no one is more uncomfortable with that than Casado.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>I found him incredibly shy and modest, even by Canadian standards.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Casado never wanted to be on camera.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>In fact, he was horrified when we at CNN suggested it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>At 6-foot-2 and &amp;quot;gargantuan,&amp;quot; as he puts it, he hates to see himself on camera.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Yet in the cockpit he transforms, and it&amp;apost;s clear he has a gift that exceeds controlling a jumbo jet.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>His eyes light up, and his soft-spoken voice rises in level and confidence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>You not only know he can fly, but he makes you want to fly, too.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>On TV, he&amp;apost;s a natural and can take the most complex pieces of aircraft equipment or flight scenario and explain it in a way that&amp;apost;s clear and simple.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>He shuns jargon and acronyms and, unlike other aviation experts, uses words we already know.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s a pilot for the people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>But in a profession known for precision, he suffers for his everyman speak and appearance.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>His hipster facial hair and casual cockpit attire have earned him critiques from anonymous &amp;quot;pilots&amp;quot; sniping from online.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The negative comments can cut him to the bone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The reality is he dresses not for corporate aviation but comfort, and his journey to becoming a pilot and aviation analyst is far from typical.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Casado, 33, grew up in a tough, blue-collar suburb of Toronto.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>His father came from Central America, his mother from Europe.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>At age 7, a gift of a toy plane set him on the route where we find him today.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Fascination about flying turned into obsession -- his word -- for all things aviation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>At school he&amp;apost;d get in trouble for reading flying magazines tucked inside his textbooks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>He wasn&amp;apost;t good at math, but his sights set firmly on the goal of flying one day, he studied hard to master calculus and geometry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Because of a birth defect, he suffered almost constant, even violent bullying, and long before he started navigating jets through the air, he was plotting alternate courses home from school to avoid heckling classmates.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>After high school, he joined the Army to serve his country, and only after that did he turn his focus to flying.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>His parents helped him get his private pilot&amp;apost;s license, but a commercial license proved much more expensive because it required flight school and significant flying time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>He took any job he could to earn money, working in kitchens and fast food restaurants.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>His apartment, for a time, went without furniture.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>When he eventually had $14,000, he headed to a flight school in western Canada, thrilled to finally be on his way.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>But the dream turned to disaster when the flight school went bust, taking his money with it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s when the darkest days of his life began.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Homeless, he slept on park benches and in stairways until finally ending up at the place he knew best, the airport.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>By day, he&amp;apost;d sit in the terminals and at night, he&amp;apost;d sleep in the bathrooms.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>In the oversized handicapped stalls he would use a roll of masking tape to mark out runways and walk around them practicing approaches.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>He used a toilet seat for chair flying, imagining the controls and switches in his mind.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Eventually he made it back home and began working once more to earn money to fly.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>It would take him years before that final check flight.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>When the pilot turned and told him he had passed, Mitchell couldn&amp;apost;t help it: he cried.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>His dream had come true.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>By 2007 he was ranked in the top 10 of Canada&amp;apost;s amateur pilots.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Today, in addition to his multi-engine license, he has earned his seaplane rating, flown cargo routes and flown as a &amp;quot;bush pilot&amp;quot; in Canada and elsewhere.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>When he&amp;apost;s not in the air, he works as a simulator instructor on Boeing 737s and 777s.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>And, of course, there&amp;apost;s his new-found television talent.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>For his on air role, I have pushed him to do in the simulator what he would never attempt as a professional pilot.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Hence, he has probably virtually crashed a 777 more than anyone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s my fault.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>On TV we have had him fly a 777 at 5,000 feet in the Himalayas.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>I nearly lost my dinner on that one with all the banking and yanking.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Then there was the time I made him attempt to land the plane on a ridiculously small runway on a remote island.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Just to make it harder, I told him to make the weather stormy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>He had one shot live on TV with countless people watching.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>To his credit, he landed with room to spare but was so exhausted from the attempt he couldn&amp;apost;t answer our anchor&amp;apost;s questions afterward.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>A few days later he got a message from someone at the Federal Aviation Administration congratulating him on the landing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>The other day we made him simulate a scenario where the fuel runs out on a 777.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>It was awful.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>It was real.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>We both sat in silence for a minute when it was over.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>He apologized and left the cockpit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>I had become caught up in the &amp;quot;gee-whiz-what-if&amp;quot; angle of the simulator.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>Casado had not.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="59">
          <content>We may have flown in the virtual world, but as a pilot, Casado knew the heartbreaking loss for 239 passengers&amp;apost; families is real.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="60">
          <content>Casado also has a life outside the cockpit.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="61">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s married to his childhood sweetheart, Deborah, whom he married three years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="62">
          <content>When the hours go long -- and they do -- he worries about Buddy and Snowflake, his two Netherlands dwarf rabbits waiting at home.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="63">
          <content>Buddy&amp;apost;s a rescue.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="64">
          <content>He speaks to young people, often cautioning those who might be considering flying as a career that the airline industry isn&amp;apost;t what it once was.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="65">
          <content>The high-octane, high-paying days of commercial aviation are now a business.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="66">
          <content>There&amp;apost;s more he wants to do in life, but for now Casado spends most days flying and instructing in the 777 simulator where I met him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="67">
          <content>What&amp;apost;s unique about the place is it&amp;apost;s open to the public, so if you&amp;apost;ve ever fantasized about taking off from Los Angeles International or landing at Toronto Pearson, or even just doing touch-and-gos at Paris&amp;apost; Charles de Gaulle, Casado is the guy you want in the left seat.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="68">
          <content>He knows a thing or two about dreams, what it takes to make them come true and how sometimes there can be a turbulence along the way.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
