<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2836" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/06/01/world/asia/tiananmen-chinoy/index.html" date_published="2014-06-02 00:57:23" category="world" author="Mike Chinoy, Special for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Tiananmen Square crackdown: The CNN Effect</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="10">Chinoy: The Tiananmen Square crackdown was a watershed moment in the history of Western media.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="16">Coverage of the protests was the beginning of the &amp;quot;CNN effect&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="19">To this day, the event and the images continue to shape international perceptions of the country.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 21:13:57" annotation_time="13.977">
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="1">The events that night were a turning point for China, as well as a watershed moment in the history of the media.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="2">According to Bernard Shaw, who anchored CNN&amp;apost;s live round-the-clock coverage from Beijing for much of the crisis: &amp;quot;You could say that that was the beginning of the &amp;apost;CNN effect&amp;apost;&amp;quot; -- the idea, which became widespread after Tiananmen Square, that the immediacy of live TV news available 24 hours a day played a crucial role in influencing the behavior of key players during major crises.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="3">To this day, the event and the images continue to shape international perceptions of the country.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>It was 2:30 a.m. on the morning of June 4, 1989.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>From a balcony of the Beijing Hotel, I looked down Chang&amp;apost;an Avenue towards Tiananmen Square a few hundred meters away.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Red tracer bullets whizzed through the air.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The crackle of gunfire echoed through the humid Beijing night.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>I could see armored vehicles of the People&amp;apost;s Liberation Army moving just in front of the famous portrait of Chairman Mao hanging above the vast square.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Below me crowds gathered, surged forward, and then broke and dispersed as soldiers opened fire at them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Several people were hit.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>I watched as others loaded the dead and wounded onto flatbed bicycle carts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>As the drama unfolded, my colleagues and I reported it live on CNN over a scratchy phone line to transfixed TV audiences around the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The events that night were a turning point for China, as well as a watershed moment in the history of the media.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Weeks of student-led protests had become the largest movement for political reform in the history of the People&amp;apost;s Republic.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The military crackdown I covered had far-reaching consequences, not only for China&amp;apost;s development but also for its relations with the rest of the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Global coverage.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The protests generated unparalleled international coverage, and became a defining moment in the Information Age.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>It was the first time a popular uprising in an authoritarian state was broadcast live across the globe.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>According to Bernard Shaw, who anchored CNN&amp;apost;s live round-the-clock coverage from Beijing for much of the crisis: &amp;quot;You could say that that was the beginning of the &amp;apost;CNN effect&amp;apost;&amp;quot; -- the idea, which became widespread after Tiananmen Square, that the immediacy of live TV news available 24 hours a day played a crucial role in influencing the behavior of key players during major crises.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The images from that time -- the Goddess of Democracy, the man in front of the tank -- became enduring symbols of popular resistance to injustice.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>In the United States, the coverage of Tiananmen redefined the relationship between the press, public opinion, and foreign policy-making, and brought an end to the romance in Sino-American relations that had begun with Richard Nixon&amp;apost;s trip in 1972.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>To this day, the event and the images continue to shape international perceptions of the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>It was no accident that at a U.S. Congressional hearing on Tiananmen in late May, lawmakers from both parties emphasized how the television coverage from 25 years ago had influenced popular views of China.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Tiananmen legacy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Inside China, Tiananmen also continues to exert a profound influence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The crisis in 1989 led paramount leader Deng Xiaoping to purge liberal officials who had sympathized with the students, and replace them with more conservative figures.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Yet for Deng, a central lesson of Tiananmen was that public confidence in the Chinese Communist Party could only be maintained by continuing the market-oriented economic reforms begun in the 1980s.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>In the wake of Tiananmen, Deng pushed to revive and accelerate the reform process, triggering a bitter fight with the very conservatives he had relied on to back his decision to crack down in 1989.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>In what was his last great political battle, Deng triumphed, and his efforts paved the way for China&amp;apost;s emergence as an economic powerhouse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Yet for the same reason -- ensuring the Party&amp;apost;s survival -- Deng also stifled any new moves towards political reform, as did those who followed him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>In particular, fearing that the events of that June could undermine the Party&amp;apost;s legitimacy, Beijing has relentlessly sought to erase June 4 from public memory.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>All public discussion of the crisis is banned.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Every Spring, the authorities move against anyone seeking to raise the issue, whether dissidents, lawyers, or relatives of those who died.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The Communist Party in effect offered the Chinese people a bargain: greater economic opportunity and more personal -- as opposed to political -- freedom in return for not challenging the Party&amp;apost;s monopoly on power.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;apost;Suffocating control&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Despite pervasive political repression, it is a bargain many Chinese have accepted.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>And with the passage of time, the suffocating control of any public discussion, along with stunning economic growth, has meant that for the vast majority of Chinese, the events of 1989 have faded from memory.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>An entire generation knows little but the official government version of what occurred.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Yet memories of 1989 still haunt the Communist Party.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Ensuring that nothing like it occurs again remains a central feature of Beijing&amp;apost;s policies on a host of issues.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>This can be seen in the exceptionally nervous reactions to the Arab spring and so-called &amp;quot;color revolutions&amp;quot; in parts of the former Soviet Union, the growth of the internal security services, the intense repression in Tibet and Xinjiang, the harsh actions against dissidents like the imprisoned Nobel Peace Prize winner Liu Xiaobo, and the government&amp;apost;s management of the thousands of protests over local issues that occur in China every year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>So far, Beijing&amp;apost;s approach has generally worked and the Chinese leadership has proved itself to be more skillful and resilient than many in 1989 would have predicted.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>However, with the country&amp;apost;s economy slowing, social and economic tensions rising, and the Internet and other new forms of communication giving citizens new tools to voice their opinions and generate political pressure, the Communist Party is facing new challenges -- which could give new resonance to the legacy of Tiananmen Square.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Beijing&amp;apost;s approach to June 4 therefore remains a paradox.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>A quarter of a century later, the Communist Party still feels compelled to use all the powers of the state to convince people inside China that nothing worth remembering happened on a date that, outside the country, will be an occasion for reflection and analysis of what remains the gravest crisis the Party has faced since the revolution of 1949.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>