<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2465" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/09/15/world/meast/libya-diplomats-warning/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2012-09-15 10:26:24" category="world" author="Arwa Damon, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>More details emerge on U.S. ambassador&amp;apost;s last moments</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Local official says he warned U.S. diplomats about security in the area.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">&amp;quot;The situation is frightening, it scares us,&amp;quot; the official says .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">He says it was not the first time he warned foreigners about the worsening security.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 20:54:12" annotation_time="17.573668">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Benghazi, Libya Three days before the deadly assault on the United States consulate in Libya, a local security official says he met with American diplomats in the city and warned them about deteriorating security.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;The situation is frightening, it scares us,&amp;quot; Mabrouk said they told the U.S. officials.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">Mabrouk said it was not the first time he has warned foreigners about the worsening security situation in the face of the growing presence of armed jihadist groups in the Benghazi area.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Benghazi, Libya Three days before the deadly assault on the United States consulate in Libya, a local security official says he met with American diplomats in the city and warned them about deteriorating security.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Jamal Mabrouk, a member of the February 17th Brigade, told CNN that he and a battalion commander had a meeting about the economy and security.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>He said they told the diplomats that the security situation wasn&amp;apost;t good for international business.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;The situation is frightening, it scares us,&amp;quot; Mabrouk said they told the U.S. officials.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>He did not say how they responded.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Mabrouk said it was not the first time he has warned foreigners about the worsening security situation in the face of the growing presence of armed jihadist groups in the Benghazi area.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The main building in the compound is in charred ruins.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The suite where the body of the ambassador was found was protected by a large door with steel bars; the windows had steel bars.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>His body was recovered after looters broke into the room.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>It appears his security detail left him in the room while they tried to deal with the attack.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>There are numerous questions about what happened at the consulate where protesters had gathered to demonstrate against the film &amp;quot;Innocence of Muslims,&amp;quot; which reportedly was made in California by a filmmaker whose identity is unclear.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Chief among the questions is what happened to U.S. Ambassador J. Christopher Stevens, who went missing during the attack.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The State Department has not released details about how Stevens died, though numerous media reports have said the ambassador was taken from the consulate to the Benghazi medical center by locals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>He arrived at the hospital, according to the reports, unresponsive and covered in soot from the fire.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>A doctor was unable to revive him and declared him dead, the reports said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>According to one of the Libyan security guards who was stationed at one of the gates armed with only a radio, the assault began simultaneously from three directions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Heavy machine guns and rocket -propelled grenades were used, according to the guard.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>He said masked men threatened to kill him at gunpoint for &amp;apost;protecting the infidels.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>He declined to appear on camera for fear of repercussions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The February 17th Brigade -- a militia connected to the government but not part of Libya&amp;apost;s armed forces -- was closely involved in the rescue of the American staff trapped after the attack Tuesday night.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>After the consulate was attacked and set on fire, a number of Americans escaped to a safe-house in another part of the city.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>But that came under attack too.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Mabrouk said he received a call from an official in Tripoli, who said he had been called by a &amp;quot;terrified&amp;quot; American in Benghazi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The official was at the safe-house.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Mabrouk says the Brigade asked the Americans if they needed help -- but were told that while the situation was dangerous, it was under control.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>A few hours later, Mabrouk said he received another call from Tripoli about the arrival of a U.S. team at Benghazi airport that needed transport into the city.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>He met the seven Americans, who were heavily armed but not in military uniform, on the runway and provided them with an armed escort, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>As soon as the two vehicles carrying the seven Americans arrived at the safe house, they came under intense attack -- including a volley of grenades and machine-gun fire.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The assailants then fled.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The Libyan government has vowed to bring the perpetrators of the attack to justice.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>But on a visit to the heavily-damaged consulate, the country&amp;apost;s president said Libya expected help form its friends in the international community.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Asked whether the government was not capable of controlling extremist groups, he responded &amp;quot;You are not far from the truth.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
