<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2525" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/10/18/world/africa/kenya-norway-mall-attack-suspect" date_published="2013-10-18 09:49:36" category="world" author="Nima Elbagir and Laura Smith-Spark, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Norwegian may be suspect in Westgate mall attack, Kenya sources say</title>
  <keywords>Westgate Mall attack,Ikrima,Norwegian suspect,Kenya</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">A Norwegian citizen of Somali descent is investigated in the Kenya mall attack.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="26">Kenyan antiterror sources say he may have ties to a suspected Al-Shabaab commander.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">Norwegian intelligence services are in Kenya investigating both men.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="4">Norwegian authorities have not yet released the Norwegian citizen&amp;apost;s name.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-11 18:11:36" annotation_time="71.176">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Nairobi, Kenya Kenyan counterterrorism sources are looking at a Norwegian citizen of Somali descent as a possible suspect in the Westgate mall attack last month, the sources told CNN on Friday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">Norwegian intelligence services are in Kenya investigating Ikrima and the Norwegian citizen, the Kenyan sources said, and have also spoken to the latter&amp;apost;s sister in Norway.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="4">Norwegian authorities have not yet released the Norwegian citizen&amp;apost;s name.</sentence>
      <sentence id="26" ids_highlights="2">Stig Hansen, a security expert based in Norway and author of the book &amp;quot;Al-Shabaab in Somalia,&amp;quot; told CNN that if the Norwegian suspect is who he believes him to be, he lived in a small town in Norway but had connections with a wider group, not all of Somali origin.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Nairobi, Kenya Kenyan counterterrorism sources are looking at a Norwegian citizen of Somali descent as a possible suspect in the Westgate mall attack last month, the sources told CNN on Friday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The Norwegian citizen is believed to have ties to Mohamed Abdikadir Mohamed, known as Ikrima, who is regarded as one of the most dangerous commanders in the Somali terror group Al-Shabaab.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Norwegian intelligence services are in Kenya investigating Ikrima and the Norwegian citizen, the Kenyan sources said, and have also spoken to the latter&amp;apost;s sister in Norway.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Norwegian authorities have not yet released the Norwegian citizen&amp;apost;s name.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Kenyan authorities suspect Ikrima of involvement with the Westgate mall attack.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Al-Shabaab claimed responsibility for the bloody four-day siege at the upscale mall in Nairobi, where at least 67 people died.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>U.S. officials said Ikrima was the target of a raid earlier this month by U.S. Navy SEALs on an Al-Shabaab compound near the town of Baraawe in Somalia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s believed that he escaped after the U.S. troops came under heavy fire.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>A Kenyan intelligence dossier seen by CNN alleges Ikrima&amp;apost;s involvement with Briton Samantha Lewthwaite, a terror suspect known as the &amp;quot;White Widow,&amp;quot; in a foiled Mombasa attack in 2011 with Jermaine Grant, a fellow British citizen currently held in Mombasa on terror charges.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Kenyan intelligence sources say that Ikrima, who speaks six languages and grew up in Kenya, is the main &amp;quot;point person&amp;quot; between al Qaeda in Somalia and al Qaeda in the Arabian Peninsula, and that he has helped pinpoint Kenyan targets.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Recruiting operatives in the West?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Morten Storm, a former informant who has worked for several Western intelligence agencies, has told CNN that he developed a close relationship with an Al-Shabaab figure called Ikrima between 2008 and 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>He said he is confident that it&amp;apost;s the same person who was targeted by U.S. forces.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Storm, who is Danish, described Ikrima as a Somali-Kenyan Al-Shabaab operative who had spent time in Norway.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>He said that Ikrima made clear to him via e-mail that he was ready to send recruits from the West back home from Somalia to launch attacks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Norwegian journalist Bent Skjaerstad told CNN his sources have confirmed that Ikrima had indeed spent time in Norway and had tried to recruit for Al-Shabaab in Europe.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Skjaerstad, who reports on security and terrorism for TV2, said Ikrima had lived there between 2004 and 2008.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>He had failed to gain asylum status but had been given Norwegian travel papers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Skjaerstad told CNN that according to his sources, Ikrima had traveled to Somalia while living in Norway and had used about a dozen aliases.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Friends of Ikrima who knew him from his time growing up on the Nairobi suburb of Eastleigh told CNN he traveled to Norway in 2003 and grew increasingly radicalized there.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The sources, who had kept up with him over the years, said Ikrima traveled in 2007 to London, where they lost contact with him.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>In 2008 they heard that he was in Somalia, where he has been based since.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Arabic is among the six languages spoken by Ikrima, and he studied French for two years at the Alliance Francais in Nairobi, his friends say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Al-Shabaab in Norway.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The possible involvement of the Norwegian citizen in the Westgate mall attack has highlighted concerns about the widening reach of the Al-Shabaab group outside Somali borders.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Stig Hansen, a security expert based in Norway and author of the book &amp;quot;Al-Shabaab in Somalia,&amp;quot; told CNN that if the Norwegian suspect is who he believes him to be, he lived in a small town in Norway but had connections with a wider group, not all of Somali origin.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>He came to Norway at age 8 or 9 and stayed for a couple of years, during which time he gained Norwegian citizenship, Hansen said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>He later returned to Somalia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Al-Shabaab became quite popular among some Somali community groups in Norway from 2007 to 2009, Hansen said, &amp;quot;because they were wrongly seen as some kind of national resistance group.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Observers noticed contradictions between what the group said in its English- and Arabic-language messaging, he said, which contributed to ignorance within the diaspora about its real nature.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;But the terrorist attacks inside of Somalia made it easier for the wider ethnic Somali community to see that this was really a terrorist organization, and it distanced itself,&amp;quot; he said, making it less popular now.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>However, this development brought its own problems, Hansen said, and not just in Norway.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;What you have to look out for, also in the United States and the United Kingdom and all these other Scandinavian countries, are these small, small networks that are in one sense detached also from the Somali community leaders -- radicalized groups of youths and radical preachers, sheikhs, that go traveling around the various countries to try to incite,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;That&amp;apost;s what we have to watch these days.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
