<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2924" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/11/world/asia/china-us-isis/index.html" date_published="2014-09-11 07:06:06" category="world" author="Katie Hunt, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>U.S. likely to get Beijing&amp;apost;s &amp;apost;support&amp;apost; in ISIS fight</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">China has a long-held policy of non-interference in other countries affairs.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">But Beijing is likely to quietly support the U.S. fight against ISIS, analysts say.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="14">NEW: China&amp;apost;s foreign ministry says willing to enhance communication and cooperation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="20">Support is likely to be symbolic rather than substantive.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2015-01-30 14:59:47" annotation_time="28.018">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Hong Kong With a long-held ethos of non-interference in other countries&amp;apost; affairs, risk-averse China is perhaps an unlikely ally in President Barack Obama&amp;apost;s pledge to &amp;quot;degrade&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;destroy&amp;quot; ISIS in Iraq and Syria.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">But with Beijing&amp;apost;s growing unease about terrorist threats by Islamist extremists at home, analysts say China -- a U.N. Security Council permanent member - is unlikely to oppose plans to build a &amp;quot;broad coalition&amp;quot; to go after ISIS.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;Abiding by the principles of mutual respect and equal cooperation, China is willing to enhance anti-terrorism communication and cooperation with the international community so as to safeguard international security and stability,&amp;quot; she added.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="4">But its support is likely to symbolic rather than substantive, says Xie with scant chance of Chinese combat troops on the ground.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Hong Kong With a long-held ethos of non-interference in other countries&amp;apost; affairs, risk-averse China is perhaps an unlikely ally in President Barack Obama&amp;apost;s pledge to &amp;quot;degrade&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;destroy&amp;quot; ISIS in Iraq and Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But with Beijing&amp;apost;s growing unease about terrorist threats by Islamist extremists at home, analysts say China -- a U.N. Security Council permanent member - is unlikely to oppose plans to build a &amp;quot;broad coalition&amp;quot; to go after ISIS.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think China in principle will quietly support this idea to curb ISIS,&amp;quot; says Chen Dingding, an assistant professor of government at the University of Macau.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;ISIS has openly listed China as a major threat to them and if they gain more influence, it&amp;apost;s likely they will target Xinjiang and even other parts of China,&amp;quot; he added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Earlier this month, Iraqi news reports showed pictures of what they said was a captured Chinese national fighting for ISIS.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>China&amp;apost;s foreign ministry said it could not confirm the reports.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Many domestic observers assumed the man was Uyghur, a mainly Muslim minority group that lives in Xinjiang, an ethnically divided region in China&amp;apost;s north west.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>It remains unclear whether the captured man was actually Uyghur, but Xie Tao, a professor of political science at Beijing Foreign Studies University, says that there is &amp;quot;deep concern&amp;quot; among security analysts and commentators.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;If these groups have cells in Xinjiang, if it can be confirmed that ISIS members were recruited from China, if we are already becoming a ground for recruitment for these people then China has a stake in keeping ISIS away from its borders,&amp;quot; said Xie.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>While China, along with Russia, has blocked U.N. Security Council action on Syria during the three-year civil war, both Chen and Xie said that China would likely support a generic resolution that condemns terrorist atrocities and authorizes an international force to target ISIS.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is not going to be a resolution that China will veto.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>This is not about sovereignty or (Syrian President) Assad,&amp;quot; said Xie.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>In response to a reporter&amp;apost;s question on whether China would join U.S. efforts to combat terrorism, Hua Chunying, China&amp;apost;s foreign ministry spokesperson, said that China hoped that &amp;quot;with joint efforts of the international community, the countries involved will soon restore stability and order, achieve reconciliation, peace and development.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;Abiding by the principles of mutual respect and equal cooperation, China is willing to enhance anti-terrorism communication and cooperation with the international community so as to safeguard international security and stability,&amp;quot; she added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Criticism.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The United States has been critical of China&amp;apost;s reluctance to get involved in international security issues given its expanding global interests.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>In August, Obama called China a &amp;quot;free rider&amp;quot; for its reluctance to contribute to international security while importing oil and other resources from places like Iraq.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>China has sent a special envoy to the Middle East to help facilitate dialogue between Israel and Palestine but changes to its traditional non-interventionist foreign policy have been limited in scale.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Last week, National Security Adviser Susan Rice made her first visit to China, reportedly conveying hopes that China might join an international coalition to collectively combat terrorism.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>But its support is likely to symbolic rather than substantive, says Xie with scant chance of Chinese combat troops on the ground.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re not really ready to take that leap.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
