<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2542" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/02/07/world/europe/turkey-flight-bomb-threat/index.html" date_published="2014-02-07 17:08:46" category="world" author="Gul Tuysuz and Greg Botelho, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Officials: &amp;apost;Air pirate&amp;apost; claims bomb, tries to have plane go to Sochi</title>
  <keywords>Turkey flight bomb threat,Turkey plane passenger threat</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="22">NEW: Ukraine says the suspect turned himself in; a Turkish governor says otherwise.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="24">NEW: &amp;quot;We were trying to persuade him and he wasn&amp;apost;t persuaded,&amp;quot; governor says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="16">Passenger says there&amp;apost;s a bomb in the plane&amp;apost;s baggage hold, says it should fly to Sochi.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="3">F-16 jets escort the plane to Istanbul, where it lands safely; authorities detain the suspect.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-28 09:00:31" annotation_time="32.71">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="4">About 20 minutes later, the same report claimed two F-16 fighter jets scrambled to intercept the Boeing 737-800 and escort it over the Black Sea.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="3">While it was in air, &amp;quot;one of the passengers said that there was a bomb on board and asked the plane to not land in Sabiha Gokcen but rather to land in Sochi,&amp;quot; Transportation Ministry official Habip Soluk said on CNNTurk.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="1">The Ukrainian ministry said no explosives or guns were found aboard the plane and that the suspect &amp;quot;voluntarily turned himself into police.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;We had to use force because we were trying to persuade him and he wasn&amp;apost;t persuaded,&amp;quot; said Mutlu, adding Turkish authorities did not use guns and that the suspect suffered &amp;quot;a light injury.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A passenger announced Friday &amp;quot;that there was a bomb on board&amp;quot; his plane and wanted it diverted to Sochi -- the Russian city hosting the Winter Olympics amid terrorism fears -- Turkish officials said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Rather than abide by the request, the Pegasus Airlines&amp;apost; crew sent a hijacking alert that Turkey&amp;apost;s Air Force Control Center received at 5:20 p.m. (10:20 a.m. ET), Turkey&amp;apost;s semiofficial Anadolu news agency reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>About 20 minutes later, the same report claimed two F-16 fighter jets scrambled to intercept the Boeing 737-800 and escort it over the Black Sea.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Eventually, the airliner landed safely at Istanbul&amp;apost;s Sabiha Gokcen airport, where video shot soon thereafter showed police and security officials converging on it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Istanbul&amp;apost;s governor tweeted around 10 p.m. that &amp;quot;the air pirate has been neutralized&amp;quot; and all other passengers &amp;quot;disembarked from the plane without any problems.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Special forces who boarded the plane took him into custody &amp;quot;in a swift operation&amp;quot; without finding a &amp;quot;bomb on him,&amp;quot; Gov. Huseyin Avni Mutlu later told reporters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;The operation is complete,&amp;quot; the governor said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Mutlu said that the suspect -- who never made it into the cockpit and at one point apparently thought the aircraft was destined for Sochi -- &amp;quot;didn&amp;apost;t seem to have consumed alcohol, (but) he may have used some other substances.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>He&amp;apost;d brought a carry-on bag with personal electronics and other items onto the Pegasus plane, according to the governor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The incident came at a tense time given the various threats surrounding the Winter Games, which kicked off in earnest Friday night with its opening ceremony.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Russian security forces have cracked down in recent weeks on suspected militants in the restive North Caucasus republic of Dagestan -- which is located on the other side of the Caucasus Mountains from Sochi -- and elsewhere in recent weeks after twin suicide bombings in the city of Volgograd in December.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>There have also been concerns specifically about explosives-laden airlines.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>U.S. Rep. Michael McCaul said Wednesday night that the his nation&amp;apost;s Department of Homeland Security issued a bulletin to airlines flying into Russia warning that explosive materials could be concealed in toothpaste or cosmetic tubes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Official: Suspect is Ukrainian.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The flight started in Kharkov in Ukraine, and was headed to Istanbul, according to the Transportation Ministry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>While it was in air, &amp;quot;one of the passengers said that there was a bomb on board and asked the plane to not land in Sabiha Gokcen but rather to land in Sochi,&amp;quot; Transportation Ministry official Habip Soluk said on CNNTurk.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The man said the bomb was in the baggage hold, a Transportation Ministry official said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The aircraft ended up touching down at the Turkish airport at at 6:04 p.m., according to Anadolu, at which point it was moved to a safe zone on the tarmac.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Cihan News Agency of Turkey published a photograph it claimed came from inside the plane showing a man standing in a number 11 sports jersey with empty seats around him and two people in uniform.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Turkish officials have not confirmed that this photograph is from inside the Pegasus airliner or that the man at the center of it is the alleged hijacker.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The Ukrainian foreign ministry issued a statement identifying the suspect as one of its citizens, something that Soluk also said was the case.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The Ukrainian ministry said no explosives or guns were found aboard the plane and that the suspect &amp;quot;voluntarily turned himself into police.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Mutlu, Istanbul&amp;apost;s governor, offered a different take on how the alleged hijacker was detained.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;We had to use force because we were trying to persuade him and he wasn&amp;apost;t persuaded,&amp;quot; said Mutlu, adding Turkish authorities did not use guns and that the suspect suffered &amp;quot;a light injury.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The suspect never said anything about Circassians -- the residents in the volatile region around the North Caucasus mountains -- or having lived in the region, according to the governor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
