<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2901" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/12/12/world/meast/syria-civil-war/index.html" date_published="2013-12-12 17:56:46" category="world" author="Salma Abdelaziz, Hala Gorani and Ana Bickford, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>U.N. confirms use of chemical weapons in Syria</title>
  <keywords>Syria civil war,Free Syrian Army,Syrian rebels</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">The United Nations releases a much-anticipated report.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">It finds &amp;quot;convincing evidence&amp;quot; that such weapons were used against children.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">The report does not say who is responsible for the attacks.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-14 19:56:55" annotation_time="123.663506">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1, 2">&amp;quot;The United Nations Mission collected clear and convincing evidence that chemical weapons were used also against civilians, including children, on a relatively large scale in the Ghouta area of Damascus on 21 August 2013,&amp;quot; read the 82-page report, which was released on Thursday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">The report did not specify whether the government or opposition groups were responsible for the alleged attacks, which happened between March and August this year.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>In a much-anticipated report, the United Nations has concluded that chemical weapons have been used in the Syrian conflict.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Experts investigated seven instances of alleged use and found that chemical weapons were either used, or likely used, in five of those instances.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The case that was most clear to inspectors was an August incident near the capital, Damascus.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;The United Nations Mission collected clear and convincing evidence that chemical weapons were used also against civilians, including children, on a relatively large scale in the Ghouta area of Damascus on 21 August 2013,&amp;quot; read the 82-page report, which was released on Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Blood and urine samples from patients there tested positive for sarin and sarin signatures, it found.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Anti-government activist groups say more than 1,300 people were killed in the attack in Ghouta -- many of them women and children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Graphic video footage showed rows of bodies without apparent injury, as well as people suffering convulsions or apparently struggling to breathe.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>U.N. inspectors also said they collected credible information, or evidence consistent with the probable use of chemical weapons, in Khan al Asal, Jobar, Saraqueb and Ashrafiah Sahnaya.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>They were unable to corroborate the allegation that chemical weapons were used in either Bahhariyeh or Sheik Maqsood.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The report did not specify whether the government or opposition groups were responsible for the alleged attacks, which happened between March and August this year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The United Nations estimates that more than 100,000 people overall have died since the Syrian conflict began in March 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>It began with a government crackdown on peaceful protesters during the Arab Spring movement, then slowly spiraled into a bloody, full-blown civil war.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Rebel leader denies he fled.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Also Thursday, a top Syrian rebel commander denied that he had abandoned his post and said he is working to resolve fighting among opposition groups in the country&amp;apost;s north.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>In the meantime, a decision by the United States and Britain to halt nonlethal aid makes sense, said Salim Idriss, chief of staff of the Free Syrian Army.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Several U.S. administration officials had said that the fate of Idriss, a top rebel commander supported by the West, was uncertain as conflicts persisted between the Free Syrian Army and Islamist groups.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Idriss denied reports that he fled to a Gulf state after the Islamic Front allegedly seized a warehouse held by the Free Syrian Army.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>He did leave Syria, but is working at his office on the Turkish border and has not left his job, Idriss told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>In this case, he was already in Turkey when the attack on the warehouse happened, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>On Wednesday, Turkey sealed its border with Syria because of the fighting between opposition groups in Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>In the past two days, Idriss has been talking with different groups and has tried to resolve their differences, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;The situation in the north of Syria now is very complicated and very dangerous because there are some problems between some groups, and I think we will try and we should try everything now to find a solution for this problem,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The Islamic Front, which announced its formation last month, is an alliance that includes tens of thousands of fighters from some of Syria&amp;apost;s most powerful Islamist groups, including Ahrar al-Sham, Suqour al-Sham, the Islamic Army and the Tawhid Brigade.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The groups control territory in key areas across Syria and have been fighting forces loyal to President Bashar al-Assad along the critical lines of Damascus and Aleppo, among other places.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The front&amp;apost;s formation has diminished the stature of the Western-backed Free Syrian Army and its leadership abroad, the Syrian National Coalition, as leaders inside the country have sought to distance themselves from a command structure criticized for failing to serve the opposition&amp;apost;s needs on the ground.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;apost;Infighting is growing&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The seizure of the warehouse this week could prove key in shaping how the United States deals with the Syrian opposition.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Syrian opposition has never been a unified fighting force but infighting is growing and, naturally, this is hindering cooperation on the battlefield,&amp;quot; said one U.S. official.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;At least temporarily, there will be more turbulence within the opposition as the new groups that have cropped up compete for power.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>What isn&amp;apost;t clear yet is whether the various factions will refocus attention on toppling Assad or become embroiled in internecine fighting that would play to the regime&amp;apost;s advantage.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>According to Idriss, the Islamic fighters did not take over the warehouse, but attacked a Free Syrian Army battalion that was protecting it and took its inventory.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>It was unclear which group gave the orders to attack the battalion, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The inventory that was inside the warehouse -- which was not American aid, Idriss said -- is in good shape and will hopefully be returned.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Idriss admitted that he doesn&amp;apost;t fully trust the Islamists, but that an agreement must be reached to control the fighting and form a single command.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The fighting among these groups opposed to al-Assad led the United States and Britain to suspend nonlethal aid to the rebel groups.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is very difficult now to pass the support to the right hands.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>And that&amp;apost;s why I can understand the, let me say, freezing the support for a period of time,&amp;quot; Idriss said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>The Supreme Military Council of the Free Syrian Army called the allegations that Idriss had abandoned his post rumors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;Such rumors only serve to impact on the morale of our brothers fighting on the ground at a time when we need to concentrate on stopping the criminal regime, which continues to perpetrate horrific massacres all over the country against our people,&amp;quot; the council said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
