<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2543" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/07/16/world/europe/hungary-suspected-nazi/index.html" date_published="2012-07-16 14:23:47" category="world" author="Ashley Hayes, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Officials: Alleged Nazi war criminal found in Hungary</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">The Simon Wiesenthal Center says it tracked down Ladislaus Csizsik-Csatary.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8">He allegedly participated in sending 15,700 Jews to Auschwitz in spring 1944.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="26">Facing deportation, he fled Canada in 1997.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="1">The center is urging Hungarian authorities to prosecute him.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 16:01:08" annotation_time="55.76833" mapping_time_divergence="13.942082">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="4">A worldwide Jewish rights organization is pushing Hungarian authorities to prosecute a man it claims is a Nazi war criminal, recently discovered in Budapest, Hungary, who allegedly sent more than 15,000 Jews to Auschwitz in the spring of 1944.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">The Simon Wiesenthal Center found Ladislaus Csizsik-Csatary as part of its &amp;quot;Last Chance&amp;quot; project, said Efraim Zuroff, director of the center&amp;apost;s Israel office.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">Csizsik-Csatary participated in the deportation of 15,700 Jews to the Auschwitz concentration camp in 1944, witnesses have told the center.</sentence>
      <sentence id="26" ids_highlights="3">In October 1997, Paul Vickery, head of the Canadian Justice Department&amp;apost;s war crimes unit, told Radio Free Europe that when officials went to Csizsik-Csatary&amp;apost;s Toronto home, his daughter told them he was living in Europe.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A worldwide Jewish rights organization is pushing Hungarian authorities to prosecute a man it claims is a Nazi war criminal, recently discovered in Budapest, Hungary, who allegedly sent more than 15,000 Jews to Auschwitz in the spring of 1944.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The Simon Wiesenthal Center found Ladislaus Csizsik-Csatary as part of its &amp;quot;Last Chance&amp;quot; project, said Efraim Zuroff, director of the center&amp;apost;s Israel office.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The center cooperated with British tabloid The Sun to photograph Csizsik-Csatary, who reportedly is 97, and ask him questions, Zuroff said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re the ones who found him; they&amp;apost;re the ones who photographed him.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Csizsik-Csatary served as a senior Hungarian police officer in the city of Kosice, which is now in Slovakia but was under Hungarian rule in the 1940s, the center said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>He topped the Wiesenthal Center&amp;apost;s 2012 list of most wanted Nazi war criminals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;He was a commander of a ghetto,&amp;quot; Zuroff told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Csizsik-Csatary participated in the deportation of 15,700 Jews to the Auschwitz concentration camp in 1944, witnesses have told the center.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>He also played a role in &amp;quot;deportations to the Ukraine to be killed -- 300 Jews,&amp;quot; Zuroff said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;We found eyewitnesses on three different continents,&amp;quot; Zuroff said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Those witnesses told the center about Csizsik-Csatary&amp;apost;s cruelty to Jewish detainees and his role in the deportations to Auschwitz and Ukraine.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Confronted by a Sun reporter, Csizsik-Csatary denied the allegations, the tabloid reported Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>A witness to the August 1941 Ukraine deportations had nine family members who were deported, he told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Csizsik-Csatary made sure four of them were brought back from forced labor with the Hungarian army so they would be deported and killed, according to Zuroff.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>During the Auschwitz deportations, Csizsik-Csatary &amp;quot;forced these girls to dig a ditch with their hands -- young Jewish girls.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Two of the center&amp;apost;s witnesses were survivors of that deportation, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>According to The Sun, which cited documents released by the Wiesenthal Center, Csizsik-Csatary beat Jewish women with a whip he carried on his belt.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;A variety of factors&amp;quot; led to the center&amp;apost;s locating Csizsik-Csatary in Budapest, Zuroff said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;He wasn&amp;apost;t hiding under a false name.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>... He had no reason to fear.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Using the last name Csizsik, Csizsik-Csatary arrived in Canada in 1949, telling immigration officials he was Yugoslavian, according to The Toronto Star newspaper.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>A spokeswoman for Canada&amp;apost;s Department of Justice, Carole Saindon, said Monday that &amp;quot;It was alleged that when applying to immigrate to Canada, (Csizsik-Csatary) provided false information about his nationality, and failed to provide information concerning his collaboration with Nazi occupation forces while serving with the Royal Hungarian Police.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>It was further alleged that he participated in the internment and deportation of thousands of Hungarian Jews to concentration camps.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>As a result, the government of Canada revoked his citizenship on August 28, 1997.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>As deportation proceedings were under way, Csizsik-Csatary voluntarily left the country, Saindon said in an e-mail to CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>In October 1997, Paul Vickery, head of the Canadian Justice Department&amp;apost;s war crimes unit, told Radio Free Europe that when officials went to Csizsik-Csatary&amp;apost;s Toronto home, his daughter told them he was living in Europe.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Vickery told the network Csizsik-Csatary&amp;apost;s name would be placed on a watch list and he would be barred from re-entering Canada.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Csizsik-Csatary initially denied the allegations and asked the Canadian government to put the case on trial, but later withdrew that request, The Toronto Star reported in August 1997.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;In his statement of defense, Csizsik-Csatary admitted to some involvement in the ghettoization of Jews, to handing over at least two Jews to the Germans and to attending the last mass deportation of Jews out of Kassa (Hungary),&amp;quot; the Star said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The Sun said in its Sunday report that Csizsik-Csatary&amp;apost;s attorneys claimed he did not know where the Jews were being sent.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Of the 12,000 Jews transferred from a ghetto to a brickyard and deported, only 450 survived, the Sun reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Csizsik-Csatary returned to Hungary upon leaving Canada, Zuroff said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;Hungarian authorities knew that he was back,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Authorities in Hungary launched an investigation in September 2011 after receiving information from Zuroff regarding Csizsik-Csatary&amp;apost;s residence in Budapest and his role in the Auschwitz deportations, the center said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The Sun reported Sunday that when a reporter knocked on the door of Csizsik-Csatary&amp;apost;s two-bedroom Budapest apartment and asked him if he could justify his past, &amp;quot;He looked shocked and stammered, &amp;apost;No, no.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Go away.&amp;apost;&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Asked about the deportation case in Canada, the Sun said he replied, &amp;quot;No, no, I don&amp;apost;t want to discuss it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>The Sun reporter asked, &amp;quot;Do you deny doing it?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>A lot of people died as a result of your actions,&amp;quot; according to the report.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Csizsik-Csatary replied, &amp;quot;No, I didn&amp;apost;t do it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Go away from here,&amp;quot; and slammed the door, according to the newspaper.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>The Simon Wiesenthal Center said in a statement Sunday that Zuroff last week submitted new evidence to a Budapest prosecutor regarding Csizsik-Csatary and his &amp;quot;key role in the deportation of approximately 300 Jews from Kosice to Kamenetz-Podolsk, Ukraine, where almost all were murdered in the summer of 1941.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>&amp;quot;This new evidence strengthens the already very strong case against Csatary and reinforces our insistence that he be held accountable for his crimes,&amp;quot; Zuroff said in the statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;The passage of time in no way diminishes his guilt and old age should not afford protection for Holocaust perpetrators.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Csizsik-Csatary reportedly was convicted of war crimes in absentia and sentenced to death in 1948 in the Czech Republic, Zuroff said, but the center has not obtained documentation on the case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
