<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2236" link="http://www.cnn.com/2011/11/08/world/americas/haiti-cholera-lawsuit/index.html" date_published="2011-11-08 21:50:56" category="world" author="Moni Basu, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Haiti cholera victims demand U.N. compensation</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Epidemic has killed 6,700 people and sickened 485,000.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Post-quake epidemic has been linked to Nepalese peacekeepers.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">Waste was improperly dumped into river, report says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-15 11:42:28" annotation_time="15.321">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1, 2">The epidemic, which has killed 6,700 people and sickened 485,000, was linked to peacekeepers from Nepal, according to a report released in May by an U.N.-appointed panel of experts.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">The victims want acknowledgment from the United Nations that it was responsible for the epidemic after fecal matter from a U.N. camp where the Nepalese were based was improperly dumped into the Artibonite River after the January 2010 earthquake.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>More than 5,000 Haitian cholera victims have filed a petition with the United Nations, demanding millions of dollars in compensation for their suffering in an epidemic widely blamed on Nepalese peacekeepers, the victims&amp;apost; lawyers said Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The epidemic, which has killed 6,700 people and sickened 485,000, was linked to peacekeepers from Nepal, according to a report released in May by an U.N.-appointed panel of experts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The strain of cholera did not originate in Haiti, the report said, but was &amp;quot;very similar&amp;quot; to those circulating in South Asia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The victims filed their petitions with the claims unit of the U.N. Stabilization Mission and at the United Nations in New York, said one of their lawyers, Brian Concannon of the Boston-based Institute for Justice and Democracy in Haiti.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Concannon said Haitians who were sickened are demanding $50,000 each; the loved ones of those who are killed are seeking $100,000.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The victims want acknowledgment from the United Nations that it was responsible for the epidemic after fecal matter from a U.N. camp where the Nepalese were based was improperly dumped into the Artibonite River after the January 2010 earthquake.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The report from May said, &amp;quot;this contamination initiated an explosive cholera outbreak downstream in the Artibonite River Delta and eventually throughout Haiti.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Cholera spread rapidly in a nation still reeling from the devastating quake.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;This explosive spread was due to several factors, including the widespread use of river water for washing, bathing, drinking, and recreation,&amp;quot; the report said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>There was &amp;quot;regular exposure of agricultural workers to irrigation water from the Artibonite River.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;The victims want the U.N. to respond, to provide medical treatment and build clean water and waste treatment systems,&amp;quot; Concannon said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>He said his clients were challenging the institution to act consistently with what it knows to be true and just.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>At first, the United Nations resisted the idea that the outbreak may have stemmed from its peacekeepers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>A French epidemiologist, Dr. Renaud Piarroux, suggested in December that the Nepalese were the source of the outbreak.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>But a U.N. Stabilization Mission spokesman said the agency was skeptical about the doctor&amp;apost;s report.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>There is little precedence for compensation demands and lawsuits against peacekeepers in Haiti.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The global body signed a Status of Forces agreement with the Haitian government in 2004 that provides immunity for soldiers serving under its banner.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>If the U.N. Stabilization Mission does nothing, the Haitian cholera victims may not have other legal avenues.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>But New York attorney Nathaniel Burney said that Status of Force agreement also mandated that U.N. peacekeepers cooperate to their fullest extent to fight communicable diseases.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>If the United Nations knew that it was responsible for the cholera outbreak and was stonewalling, that may be a violation of the agreement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Phone calls to the U.N. Stabilization Mission were not immediately returned Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
