<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2677" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/07/03/world/meast/syria-torture-report/index.html" date_published="2012-07-03 04:00:24" category="world" author="Ivan Watson, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Report describes brutal torture in Syria</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="8">Human Rights Watch has released a report on Syria&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;state policy of torture&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">The report includes testimony from former prisoners, security officers.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="21">Among the victims, the report says, are women, senior citizens and children.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="18">Syria&amp;apost;s government routinely denies allegations of such abuse.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-15 23:39:36" annotation_time="29.029999">
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="1">According to a report published Tuesday by the New York-based human rights organization Human Rights Watch, the Syrian government has been carrying out &amp;quot;a state policy of torture&amp;quot; as part of an effort to crush dissent throughout the unrest.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">Human Rights Watch identified 27 detention centers across Syria where torture was systematically inflicted on prisoners, according to testimonies from more than 200 former prisoners and security officers who defected.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="4">The Syrian government routinely denies allegations of such abuses.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="3">Though most of the torture victims in Human Rights Watch&amp;apost;s report were men ranging from 18 to 35 years of age, the organization also interviewed women, senior citizens and children who said they were tortured.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Istanbul &amp;quot;Basat al reeh.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;Dulab.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;Falaqa.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>They are Arabic names for torture techniques that send chills through the hearts of Syrians, particularly the untold thousands who are believed to have been detained during the uprising of the last 15 months.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;We suffered torture all the time,&amp;quot; said Tariq, an opposition activist from the port city of Latakia who spent 40 days in solitary confinement in spring 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>He told CNN he endured &amp;quot;dulab,&amp;quot; in which torturers force the prisoner&amp;apost;s legs and head into a car tire before beating them, and &amp;quot;basat al reeh,&amp;quot; in which the prisoner is tied to a board and beaten.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;They threw cold water on our naked bodies and they also urinated on us ... they are really good at what they do,&amp;quot; said Tariq, who now is in Turkey helping mobilize men and weapons to rebels inside Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>According to a report published Tuesday by the New York-based human rights organization Human Rights Watch, the Syrian government has been carrying out &amp;quot;a state policy of torture&amp;quot; as part of an effort to crush dissent throughout the unrest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Human Rights Watch identified 27 detention centers across Syria where torture was systematically inflicted on prisoners, according to testimonies from more than 200 former prisoners and security officers who defected.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is a network of torture chambers that the authorities are using to intimidate and punish people who dare to oppose the government,&amp;quot; said Ole Solvang, a Human Rights Watch researcher.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;Nobody knows how many people are being detained, how many are being tortured,&amp;quot; he added.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;But one local activist group has collected names of 25,000 people in detention.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The numbers are absolutely staggering.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Human Rights Watch titled its report &amp;quot;The Torture Archipelago&amp;quot; in an overt attempt to link the Syrian prison system to the notorious Siberian gulags described in Alexander Solzhenitsyn&amp;apost;s Soviet dissident novel &amp;quot;The Gulag Archipelago.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The system is being run by at least four intelligence agencies collectively referred to as mukhabarat, or secret police, the report says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Those agencies include the Department of Military Intelligence, the Political Security Directorate, the General Intelligence Directorate and the Air Force Intelligence Directorate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;The authorities also established numerous temporary unofficial holding centers in places such as stadiums, military bases, schools and hospitals where the authorities rounded up and held people during massive detention campaigns before transporting them to branches of the intelligence agencies,&amp;quot; Human Rights Watch reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The Syrian government routinely denies allegations of such abuses.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Recently, Syria&amp;apost;s ambassador to the United Nations walked out of a meeting of the U.N. Human Rights Council in protest after the Syrian regime was accused of committing crimes against humanity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>But the eyewitness accounts gathered by Human Rights Watch as well as by CNN throughout the 15-month crisis are overwhelming.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Though most of the torture victims in Human Rights Watch&amp;apost;s report were men ranging from 18 to 35 years of age, the organization also interviewed women, senior citizens and children who said they were tortured.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;They electrocuted me on my stomach, with a prod.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>I fell unconscious,&amp;quot; said Hossam, a 13-year-old boy who told Human Rights Watch he was detained in the town of Tal Kalakh in May 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;When they interrogated me the second time, they beat me and electrocuted me again.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;The third time, they had some pliers and they pulled out my toenail.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>They said, &amp;apost;Remember this saying, always keep it in mind: We take both kids and adults, and we killed them both.&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>I started to cry, and they returned me to the cell.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>CNN has also interviewed more than a dozen Syrians who described enduring beatings, electrocution and horribly crowded conditions in prison cells.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>A dentist who was arrested for secretly providing medical care to wounded demonstrators told CNN in February that he endured beatings, near-drownings in buckets of toilet water and electric shocks to his genitals during 45 days in a prison cell that was built for 60 people but held 130 prisoners.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;They started beating me and asked me, &amp;apost;Who did you help?&amp;apost; &amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>the dentist recounted.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;I said, &amp;apost;I helped an old lady.&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Then they started beating me even harder.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The accounts of brutality match those shared by a former mukhabarat officer who said he was repeatedly ordered to torture prisoners until he defected and fled to Turkey with his family last year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;Whatever we wanted the prisoner to say, he would say.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Not what he wanted to say, whatever we ordered him to say,&amp;quot; said the former officer, who spoke to CNN outside a refugee camp in Turkey where he had been living for months.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;We took their fingernails out with pliers and we made them eat them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>We made them suck their own blood of the floor,&amp;quot; the officer added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>The officer&amp;apost;s descriptions of the detention facility where he worked in Damascus matched the descriptions of a former prisoner who had spent months incarcerated in the same building.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>That former prisoner&amp;apost;s finger was still mangled after it was crushed during a torture session in the Damascus facility.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>The officer said prison guards used grim humor during their interrogation sessions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;We would bring the prisoner and put him in the &amp;apost;basat al reeh&amp;apost; or the &amp;apost;dulab&amp;apost; and start beating him,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>&amp;quot;He would scream &amp;apost;for God&amp;apost;s sake,&amp;apost; and we would say OK, bring the &amp;apost;for God&amp;apost;s sake&amp;apost; stick.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>He would scream &amp;apost;for my mother, please&amp;quot; or &amp;apost;for [the prophet] Mohammed.&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>And we would bring the &amp;apost;my mother&amp;apost; stick and the &amp;apost;for Mohammed&amp;apost; stick.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Every stick had a name.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>&amp;quot;At the core, the crisis in Syria is about human rights violations,&amp;quot; said Solvang, who has traveled into Syria to gather evidence and testimony for &amp;quot;Torture Archipelago.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>&amp;quot;That is what is driving the crisis and driving people to take up arms.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>The Human Rights Watch report includes satellite maps showing the exact location of detention centers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>It also lists the names of commanders of individual detention centers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>Human Rights Watch is urging the U.N. Security Council to refer Syrian officials to the International Criminal Court for alleged crimes against humanity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>&amp;quot;Those who commit these abuses do so with complete impunity, thinking they will never have to answer for this,&amp;quot; Solvang said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>&amp;quot;By publishing these names, we are really putting them on notice, saying they will have to answer for these violations.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>