<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2470" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/07/10/world/europe/uk-shafilea-honor-murder/index.html" date_published="2012-07-10 08:14:49" category="world" author="Richard Allen Greene, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Mother suspected in UK &amp;apost;honor murder&amp;apost; implicates husband in teen&amp;apost;s killing</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3, 1">Shafilea Ahmed&amp;apost;s parents are accused of killing the 17-year-old in an &amp;quot;honor murder&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="17">They denied killing her, but on Monday, the mother said she saw her husband attack the girl.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="8">Shafilea&amp;apost;s sister testified last month that she saw her parents stuff a plastic bag into her mouth.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="30">The United Nations estimates there could be 5,000 honor murders per year worldwide.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 17:15:41" annotation_time="66.31234" mapping_time_divergence="16.578085">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">London Shafilea Ahmed&amp;apost;s parents have long denied killing their pretty teenage daughter for shaming the family, but the &amp;quot;honor murder&amp;quot; case that has gripped Britain took an unexpected turn this week.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">Iftikhar and Farzana Ahmed are on trial in Chester, England, accused of killing Shafilea, 17, (pictured left) in September 2003.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="3">Shafilea&amp;apost;s sister Alesha testified last month that she saw her parents kill the teen by stuffing a plastic bag into her mouth.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="2">On Monday, Farzana unexpectedly said she had seen her husband attack Shafilea.</sentence>
      <sentence id="30" ids_highlights="4">Reliable figures of the number of honor murders around the world are hard to come by, but the United Nations Population Fund has estimated there could be 5,000 per year.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>London Shafilea Ahmed&amp;apost;s parents have long denied killing their pretty teenage daughter for shaming the family, but the &amp;quot;honor murder&amp;quot; case that has gripped Britain took an unexpected turn this week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Shafilea&amp;apost;s mother, Farzana, abruptly changed her story in court and implicated her husband, Iftikhar, in the killing, CNN affiliate ITV reported Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Iftikhar and Farzana Ahmed are on trial in Chester, England, accused of killing Shafilea, 17, (pictured left) in September 2003.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>They have pleaded not guilty.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Her dismembered body was found on a riverbank months after she disappeared.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>She had been stripped of anything that would identify her, prosecutor Andrew Edis told the jury in May, according to ITV.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Newspapers, television and radio have all been reporting on the prosecution case that Shafilea&amp;apost;s parents killed her because they felt her &amp;quot;Western&amp;quot; lifestyle brought shame on the family.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Shafilea&amp;apost;s sister Alesha testified last month that she saw her parents kill the teen by stuffing a plastic bag into her mouth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>She said her parents were angry that Shafilea was wearing a short-sleeved, V-neck top, and no sweater, on the night she was killed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;Just end it here,&amp;quot; Farzana said to Iftikhar, according to their daughter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>They pushed Shafilea down onto a sofa and suffocated her despite her struggles, Alesha testified.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Prosecutor Edis called it &amp;quot;an act of suffocation by both parents acting together.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Alesha Ahmed did not tell police she had seen the killing until 2010, after she was detained by police in connection with a robbery of the family&amp;apost;s home, ITV reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>She has pleaded guilty to robbery.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Prosecutors said she had not been offered any sort of deal in exchange for testifying against her parents.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>She has testified that both her parents physically abused Shafilea &amp;quot;every day&amp;quot; over the course of five years, and that her mother did it more &amp;quot;because she was at home more.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>On Monday, Farzana unexpectedly said she had seen her husband attack Shafilea.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>She said that she tried to intervene to protect the girl, but that her husband pushed her away and punched her, ITV reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;Extremely scared,&amp;quot; she fled the room and stayed in a bedroom with other children until she heard a car leaving 20 minutes later.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>When her husband returned alone, she asked where their daughter was.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;If you care for your dear life and that of your children, don&amp;apost;t ever ask me this question again,&amp;quot; he told her, ITV reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Farzana Ahmed testified Monday that only one of their children, Mevish, was present when she saw her husband attacking Shafilea.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The jury was told that Shafilea had been taken to Pakistan for a hastily arranged marriage before her death, and drank bleach there when her parents suggested she was staying there when the rest of the family returned to England, ITV reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>She was hospitalized for three months after the family came home because of the bleach incident, Alesha testified.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Alesha testified in May that her parents were very strict with their daughters, ITV reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;Our family was very restricted.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>It was very different.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The Pakistani culture is more restrictive in terms of what you can wear or do,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The trial began in May and is expected to last several more weeks, prosecutors say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Reliable figures of the number of honor murders around the world are hard to come by, but the United Nations Population Fund has estimated there could be 5,000 per year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>So-called honor murders are a significant enough problem in Britain that the country&amp;apost;s Crown Prosecution Service has an expert specializing in cases where members of a family kill relatives because of behavior that they say shames the family.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The CPS began keeping statistics on honor violence in April 2010 and prosecuted 234 cases in the following year, just over half of which were successful.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The CPS expert, Nazir Afzal, told CNN earlier this year that convicting perpetrators can be difficult.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;There is a wall of silence around this, and people are not prepared to talk,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>But Afzal insisted that it was &amp;quot;absolutely important that you bring every single person to justice, because you want to deter other people from doing it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>There is a perception that the crime is particularly common among Muslims, but one vocal British campaigner says not all honor violence is perpetrated by Muslims.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Jasvinder Sanghera, who was the victim of a forced marriage, is not Muslim; she is Sikh.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;Significant cases are happening within South Asian communities, be it Pakistani, Indian, Sikh, Muslim, Kurdish, Iranian, Middle Eastern communities,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Afzal says &amp;quot;no faith on Earth&amp;quot; justifies killing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;At the end of the day, murder is murder,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;Abrahamic faiths say &amp;apost;Thou shalt not kill.&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>At the end of the day, nobody should die for this.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>The killings take place in many parts of the world, experts say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s definitely a problem that happens in many different places: the Middle East, Pakistan, Bangladesh and among immigrant communities in North America,&amp;quot; said Nadya Khalife, a researcher on women&amp;apost;s rights in the Arab world for Human Rights Watch.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="37">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Several Arab countries and territories, including Iraq, Kuwait, Syria, Yemen and the Palestinian territories, have laws providing lesser sentences for honor murders than for other murders, Human Rights Watch says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="38">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Egypt and Jordan also have laws that have been interpreted to allow reduced sentences for honor crimes, the group says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
