<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2693" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/07/20/world/asia/nauru-australia-riot/index.html" date_published="2013-07-20 12:56:15" category="world" author="Mitra Mobasherat and Ben Brumfield, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Riot on a tiny island highlights Australia shutting a door on asylum</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">150 asylum seekers burned down their shelters in an Australian refugee center on Nauru Island.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">It drew attention to a new law in Australia banning &amp;quot;boat people&amp;quot; from living in the country.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="44">A recent uptick in human trafficking has become an irritant to some Australians.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="47">With an election coming, the new law could garner more conservative votes.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 21:04:34" annotation_time="18.391">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">But when some 100 asylum seekers burned down their shelters in an Australian refugee processing center Friday on Nauru Island, it did not.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">Instead, it drew attention to a new restrictive law made in Australia the same day banning &amp;quot;boat people&amp;quot; from living in the country.</sentence>
      <sentence id="44" ids_highlights="3">There has been a recent uptick, which has become an irritant to some Australians.</sentence>
      <sentence id="47" ids_highlights="4">The new law, which Rudd&amp;apost;s government delivered, could also play well with more conservative Australian voters and garner Rudd&amp;apost;s party more votes.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A riot on a tiny island in the Pacific that killed no one would usually go unnoticed by the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But when some 100 asylum seekers burned down their shelters in an Australian refugee processing center Friday on Nauru Island, it did not.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Instead, it drew attention to a new restrictive law made in Australia the same day banning &amp;quot;boat people&amp;quot; from living in the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;As of today asylum seekers who come here by boat without a visa will never be settled in Australia,&amp;quot; said Prime Minister Kevin Rudd in a statement announcing the law.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The asylum seekers did not revolt because of the new law, an immigration spokeswoman said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>They may have not even known about it when the mayhem broke out.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>They are stuck on the island without papers for Australia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The United Nations has called the conditions on Nauru &amp;quot;unbearable,&amp;quot; noting that asylum seekers have been gone on hunger strike before because of them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Their alternatives: Go back to where they came from, places such as Iraq, Afghanistan and Iran, or wait in limbo on a lonely island.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The unrest began as peaceful demonstrations earlier in the week, but then things got out of hand, the spokeswoman said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The new law will put more people in their position -- marooned on an island with little choice of where to go next.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>On Saturday, Australian authorities intercepted the first boat smuggling refugees since the law was passed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>It was sailing near the Christmas Islands and was crammed full with 81 people, who will face that fate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Starting immediately, all &amp;quot;boat people&amp;quot; will be taken to the sparsely populated jungle island of Manus, which is a part of Papua New Guinea.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Australian officials Sunday said 15 Vietnamese asylum seekers on Manus were returned home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Middle of nowhere.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Nauru Island, where the insurrection broke out, is the epitome of the middle of nowhere.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>It is roughly 2,000 miles from Australia&amp;apost;s shores, where Rudd said in no uncertain terms that &amp;quot;boat people&amp;quot; are no longer to tread.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>There is not much room to roam on Nauru.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>It is just three miles across at its widest point.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>And there are not many people to talk to.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The nearly 600 &amp;quot;transferees,&amp;quot; as they are called, make up 5% of the island&amp;apost;s total population.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>And they speak various languages from Farsi to Pashtun.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>More than 150 miles of open ocean separate them from their nearest neighbor, which is another tiny island.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>One-way street.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Manus presents a similar situation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>People arriving there will have to wait for authorities to determine that they are true refugees, not just people seeking a better life in a richer country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;If they&amp;apost;re found to be genuine refugees, they will be resettled in Papua New Guinea,&amp;quot; Rudd said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Rudd described the country in optimistic terms as &amp;quot;an emerging economy with a strong future.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Those who settle there may find it to be more of a jungle island populated with mostly native peoples, as the CIA World Factbook says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Not much of a replacement for the immigration melting pot they had hoped for.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Australia is prepared for an unlimited influx of new asylum seekers to the neighboring country, with its cooperation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;Our governments will expand existing facilities on Manus Island, as well as establishing further facilities in Papua New Guinea,&amp;quot; Rudd said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;There is no cap on the number of people who can be transferred to Papua New Guinea.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Those not recognized as legitimate refugees would be sent packing again.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>The government has kicked off an ad campaign on traditional and social media in various pan-Asian languages to warn of the possibility of getting stuck in the new asylum cul-de-sac.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>It has drawn hefty criticism from some Australian politicians as being inhumane.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>As a consolation, if fewer boats arrive as a result of the policy, Australia plans to raise the number of legal asylum seekers it takes, Rudd said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Human trafficking and votes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The new law is designed to discourage &amp;quot;boat people&amp;quot; from paying human traffickers thousands of dollars to ferry them to Australia on unseaworthy crafts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;Our country has had enough of people smugglers exploiting asylum seekers and seeing them drown on the high seas,&amp;quot; said Rudd, who previously served as foreign minister.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>He is also tired of watching Australian crews risk their lives to fish passengers from waters in front of the Christmas Islands, where rusting buckets carrying them invariably capsize.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>The number of illegal immigrants arriving by boat spiked between 1999 and 2001, according to the Australian parliament, only to flatline after a few years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>There has been a recent uptick, which has become an irritant to some Australians.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Rudd, who heads the left-wing Labor Party, faces an election in September, and his opponent&amp;apost;s Liberal Party has dominated in the polls.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="37">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>His party recently voted down former Prime Minister Julia Gillard who was widely unpopular and put Rudd in her place to court favor with voters before time runs out.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="38">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>The new law, which Rudd&amp;apost;s government delivered, could also play well with more conservative Australian voters and garner Rudd&amp;apost;s party more votes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="39">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Riots over.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="40">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Back on Nauru, things have calmed down.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="41">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Authorities have moved the asylum seekers to an alternative location and have set up tented temporary housing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="42">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>The flames spared the kitchen, so there is food to go around for the &amp;quot;transferees.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="43">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>And the rioters may face legal consequences for their actions, Australia&amp;apost;s immigration minister said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>They could wander from the refugee camp to jail.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="44">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>&amp;quot;The sort of crimes that appear to be committed are serious -- with prison sentences,&amp;quot; Tony Burke said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="45">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>But they have returned to the camp.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="46">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>There is no place else for them to go on the tiny island, or much of anywhere else.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
