<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2341" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/05/06/world/europe/knox-americans-italians/index.html" date_published="2013-05-06 18:32:26" category="world" author="Barbie Latza Nadeau, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Italians ask: Can Americans get away with murder?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">A number of American suspects in high-profile cases have not been brought to justice, say Italians.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">In 1998, 20 people were killed when a U.S. Marine Corps jet sliced through steel wires supporting a cable car in the Italian Alps.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="19">In 2009, American troops opened fire at a Baghdad checkpoint, killing Italian secret service agent Nicola Calipari.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="22">The trial of Seattle student Amanda Knox, accused of killing her British roommate Meredith Kercher is also controversial.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-09 14:21:36" annotation_time="17.336">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">Italians point to a number of high-profile cases over the years in which they say American suspects have been accused of wrongdoing and criminal acts, but have been let off lightly.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">All 20 people inside the gondola were killed.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="3">In 2009, American troops opened fire at a Baghdad airport checkpoint, killing Italian secret service agent Nicola Calipari and wounding a just-freed Italian hostage, journalist Giuliana Sgrena, whom Calipari was trying to spirit out of the country.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="4">The trial of Seattle student Amanda Knox, accused of killing her British roommate Meredith Kercher in November 2007 when the two shared a house in Perugia, Italy, is also controversial.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Rome, Italy It doesn&amp;apost;t take a social anthropologist to see that Italians truly love a lot about American culture.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>It is evident everywhere, from the popularity of Coca-Cola and Levi&amp;apost;s to the prevalence of American music and movies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>But for all they like about American culture, it&amp;apost;s fair to say Italians are getting a little weary of the American attitude -- especially when it comes to justice.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Italians point to a number of high-profile cases over the years in which they say American suspects have been accused of wrongdoing and criminal acts, but have been let off lightly.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>These cases leave Italians with the feeling that it&amp;apost;s possible for Americans to get away with murder.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>In 1998, a U.S. Marine Corps jet on a low-level training flight sliced through steel wires supporting a cable car near the ski resort of Cavalese in the Italian Alps, sending a gondola plunging to the ground.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>All 20 people inside the gondola were killed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Italian prosecutors wanted the crew of the jet tried in Italy, but an Italian court ruled they should face court-martials in the U.S., in accordance with NATO treaties.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The aircraft&amp;apost;s pilot and navigator were found not guilty of involuntary manslaughter, even though the military admitted the plane had been flying lower and faster than authorized.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The defense argued that the incident was a tragic accident caused partly by the fact that the plane&amp;apost;s altimeter was not working and the gondola cable that the plane hit was not on the map that he was given.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>When it emerged a video that captured the accident from inside the plane had been destroyed, they were dismissed from the Marine Corps.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Italians were outraged, referring to the incident as the &amp;quot;massacre of Cermis.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>For years, many from the local resort area held anti-American protests on the anniversary of the accident.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>In another incident that raised tensions, Egyptian cleric Abu Omar was seized off the streets of Milan in 2003, and smuggled to Egypt, where he says he was tortured and released four years later.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Although Italy did not request the extradition of any of the suspects, 22 CIA agents were convicted in absentia of the kidnapping and sentenced to prison time for their role in the abduction, but none ever served time in Italy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>They were also ordered to pay $1.5 million to Omar&amp;apost;s family, who have received nothing so far.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Italians were outraged that Americans could conduct military-style operations on Italian soil, especially involving kidnapping and torture, and go unpunished.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Other cases involving the two nations have been equally controversial.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>In 2009, American troops opened fire at a Baghdad airport checkpoint, killing Italian secret service agent Nicola Calipari and wounding a just-freed Italian hostage, journalist Giuliana Sgrena, whom Calipari was trying to spirit out of the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>An Italian judge acquitted a U.S. soldier accused of killing Calipari, saying Italy had no jurisdiction in the case, and Italy did not request extradition.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>But the case is still a sensitive topic in Italy, where Calipari is considered to be a national hero killed by trigger-happy Americans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The trial of Seattle student Amanda Knox, accused of killing her British roommate Meredith Kercher in November 2007 when the two shared a house in Perugia, Italy, is also controversial.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Knox and her erstwhile lover Raffaele Sollecito were famously convicted of Kercher&amp;apost;s murder and sentenced to 26 and 25 years respectively in 2009.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>That conviction was sensationally overturned in 2011 and Knox went back to Seattle.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The acquittal was then overturned by Italy&amp;apost;s high court in March 2013, meaning Knox currently stands convicted of Kercher&amp;apost;s murder and her appeal will likely be heard early next year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Suspects are not required to attend court hearings in Italy, so Knox does not need to return to stand trial, at least in the short term.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>But if her original conviction is upheld on appeal and confirmed by Italy&amp;apost;s high court, she would almost certainly face extradition orders to return to Italy to serve time for Kercher&amp;apost;s murder.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>It could be years before a final decision is reached in the Knox case, and undoubtedly Knox&amp;apost;s legal team would fight extradition on every level if her conviction is upheld.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>In the meantime, Italians assume Knox will never set foot in Italy again, whether she is ultimately found responsible of Kercher&amp;apost;s murder or not.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;She will never come back here, whether she should legally or not,&amp;quot; the Kercher family lawyer Francesco Maresca told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;There are too many case precedents that clearly show America does not easily surrender its criminals.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
