<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2870" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/21/world/europe/isis-alan-henning/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-09-21 06:00:28" category="world" author="Jethro Mullen, Chelsea J. Carter and Phillip Taylor, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>UK hostage Alan Henning&amp;apost;s wife begs ISIS to let him go</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="43">NEW: Group calls on UK government to negotiate for Alan Henning&amp;apost;s release.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="32, 28">Henning was kidnapped in Syria as he was helping an aid convoy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="21">His wife says ISIS hasn&amp;apost;t responded to her attempts to communicate.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="24">Leading Muslims in the UK say killing Henning isn&amp;apost;t permitted by Islamic law.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-28 09:05:48" annotation_time="120.705">
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="3">Henning&amp;apost;s wife urged the militants to respond.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="4">Leading Muslim figures in the United Kingdom have also called for Henning&amp;apost;s release in a video posted on YouTube in which they say that killing him isn&amp;apost;t permitted by Islamic law.</sentence>
      <sentence id="28" ids_highlights="2">Henning was making his fourth trip to Syria with an aid convoy when he was abducted.</sentence>
      <sentence id="32" ids_highlights="2">Henning was kidnapped the next day.</sentence>
      <sentence id="43" ids_highlights="1">But in a marked difference from other groups issuing appeals, CAGE called on the UK government to negotiate with the hostage takers.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>London The wife of British hostage Alan Henning pleaded Saturday with ISIS to release him, describing her husband as a &amp;quot;peaceful, selfless man&amp;quot; who was only in Syria to help people in need.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;I cannot see how it could assist any state&amp;apost;s cause to allow the world to see a man like Alan dying,&amp;quot; Barbara Henning said, according to a message released by the UK Foreign Office.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>ISIS refers to itself as &amp;quot;the Islamic State.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Alan Henning, a taxi driver from near Manchester, England, was part of a team of volunteers that traveled to Syria in December to deliver food and water to people affected by the Middle Eastern country&amp;apost;s devastating civil war.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>He was abducted the day after Christmas by masked gunmen, according to other people in the aid convoy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>In a videotaped execution of British aid worker David Haines, made public last weekend, ISIS displayed Henning and threatened to kill him next.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>No response to messages.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The Sunni extremist group, which controls large areas of Iraq and Syria, has already beheaded three Western captives in recent weeks -- Haines, and the American journalists James Foley and Steven Sotloff.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The videos of the executions have pointed to U.S. airstrikes against ISIS forces in Iraq as the motivation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>In Haines&amp;apost; case, the militant group described the killing as &amp;quot;a message to the allies of America.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Henning&amp;apost;s wife said her husband, a father of two, was only trying to do good in Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Alan is a peaceful, selfless man who left his family and his job as a taxi driver in the UK to drive in a convoy all the way to Syria with his Muslim colleagues and friends to help those most in need,&amp;quot; she said in the statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>She expressed concern that his captors weren&amp;apost;t answering her calls for his release.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;I have sent some really important messages but they have not been responded to,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;apost;Executing this man is not the answer&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>ISIS has shown no regard in recent weeks for pleas from the families of its Western hostages.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Days before Foley&amp;apost;s killing was made public on August 19, his family sent the extremists a message, asking them to show mercy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>But they never heard back.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The week before Sotloff&amp;apost;s execution became known, his mother released a video pleading with ISIS leader Abu Bakr al-Baghdadi not to kill him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>And news of Haines&amp;apost; death came the same day that his family released a brief message to his captors through the UK Foreign Office.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Henning&amp;apost;s wife urged the militants to respond.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;I pray that the people holding Alan respond to my messages and contact me before it is too late,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;When they hear this message, I implore the people of the Islamic State to see it in their hearts to release my husband, Alan Henning.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Leading Muslim figures in the United Kingdom have also called for Henning&amp;apost;s release in a video posted on YouTube in which they say that killing him isn&amp;apost;t permitted by Islamic law.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;Whatever your grievance with American or British foreign policy, executing this man is not the answer,&amp;quot; said Shaykh Haitham Al Haddad, a judge on the Shariah Council in London.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;We ask you to adhere to the Shariah ruling on this matter and release him immediately and unconditionally.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The only non-Muslim.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Henning was making his fourth trip to Syria with an aid convoy when he was abducted.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>While part of the convoy stopped at the Turkish border, Henning -- the only non-Muslim in the group -- volunteered to cross into Syria with a 10-person advance party.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>In video shot on that day, he explained part of his rationale for answering the call to help.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s all worthwhile when you see what is needed actually gets where it needs to go,&amp;quot; he said, before hugging a colleague.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Henning was kidnapped the next day.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Dr. Shameela Islam-Zulfiqar, a volunteer doctor who stayed behind the main part of the convoy at the Turkish border, said they got a phone call saying Henning had been taken by masked gunmen.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;This was something that we thought was just a temporary measure, with him being a non-Muslim and being visibly English,&amp;quot; she told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The other members of the convoy thought &amp;quot;that they would just question him further and then they would let him go,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>But amid clashes between ISIS and rival rebel factions in the area, that didn&amp;apost;t happen.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;apost;He is not to blame&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Now, Islam-Zulfiqar says she has a message for the people holding Henning.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;As your sister in Islam, I would implore you and beg of you: please spare the life of this innocent man,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;He is not part of your struggle.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>He is not to blame for the actions of Western governments that you fight.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>CAGE, a Muslim-led human rights advocacy group in London, also called for Henning&amp;apost;s immediate release, saying he wasn&amp;apost;t involved in any hostilities toward Muslims.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>But in a marked difference from other groups issuing appeals, CAGE called on the UK government to negotiate with the hostage takers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Asim Qureshi, research director of CAGE, told CNN on Sunday that the releases of Turkish and continental European hostages through negotiations &amp;quot;should act as a wake-up call to the British government.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s called &amp;apost;Gadget&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="37">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Islam-Zulfiqar said other members of the convoy gave Henning the affectionate nickname &amp;quot;Gadget,&amp;quot; for his love of all things technical.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="38">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>&amp;quot;He really is the guy that fixes everything,&amp;quot; she told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="39">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>In Henning&amp;apost;s hard-scrabble hometown of Eccles in northern England, well-wishers have tied yellow ribbons to lampposts and street signs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>None of his workmates at the taxi company nor any of the neighbors on his street were willing to talk to the news media.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="40">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Islam-Zulfiqar says the situation is really difficult: &amp;quot;We know time is running out.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="41">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>Asked how people should think of Henning in his hour of need, she mentioned his smile, his concern for those around him and &amp;quot;his beautiful, beautiful golden heart.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
