<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2468" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/12/20/world/africa/egypt-violence/index.html" date_published="2012-12-20 19:22:56" category="world" author="Sarah Sirgany, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Morsy supporters accused of beating, detaining opponents</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6">Videos posted online showed men with bloodied and bruised faces.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12">One of those arrested was former diplomat Yahya Najm, who said he was refused medical treatment.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="21">According to witnesses, women were also beaten and detained but not for the entire night.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-18 10:57:31" annotation_time="1295.589">
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">Videos posted online showed men with bloodied and bruised faces held outside the gate of the presidential palace and told to confess to being paid.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">One of those arrested was former diplomat Yahya Najm, who said he was beaten and refused medical treatment.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="3">Women were also beaten and detained but not for the entire night, according to eyewitnesses.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Egypt At least 49 men were beaten and detained for up to 17 hours allegedly by supporters of President Mohamed Morsy during deadly clashes near the presidential palace in Cairo on December 5, human rights activists say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Despite allegations that these were paid thugs, the local prosecutor later released the 49 for lack of incriminating evidence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>While the men were still being questioned, President Morsy said in a televised speech that those arrested had confessed to being paid by &amp;quot;political powers&amp;quot; to instigate violence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;The basic message that I wanted to hear from the president... is that torture, abuse, illegal detention is never justified,&amp;quot; said Heba Morayef, research and Egypt director at Human Rights Watch.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The organization said in a statement that the president spoke against the victims instead of condemning their unlawful detention.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Videos posted online showed men with bloodied and bruised faces held outside the gate of the presidential palace and told to confess to being paid.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Supporters of President Morsy that night said they were fighting paid thugs, citing &amp;quot;confessions&amp;quot; they had heard as evidence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Gehad El-Haddad, senior advisor to the Muslim Brotherhood and its Freedom and Justice Party, described the president&amp;apost;s supporters as the &amp;quot;defending group&amp;quot; who first handed &amp;quot;attacking thugs&amp;quot; they caught to the police.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Stressing that the same scenario used to happen in Tahrir Square, he explained that police instantly released those arrested, leading the pro-Morsy group to hold them overnight until they could be handed over to the prosecutor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;When any of the attacking armed thugs was arrested or was caught by the supporters, he was beaten until someone would intervene and stop that beating.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>And later they would be put back in the ambulance to receive treatment and then were tied and put on the street,&amp;quot; El-Haddad said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>One of those arrested was former diplomat Yahya Najm, who said he was beaten and refused medical treatment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>His hands were tied and he was held outside the presidential gate until the next day.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>He appeared in several video reports during this detention and later at the prosecution office with a bloodied and bruised face.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Ten days after his release, he was still sporting two black eyes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;They were putting their shoes on my face, kicking me.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>They were standing on my face and chest,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;I was bleeding everywhere without any medical care all night.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Others at the same detention area, which was cordoned by police and men who identified themselves as Muslim Brotherhood members, had cut wounds resulting from stabbing, according to several eyewitnesses.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>They said one of those detained was a teenage boy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Women were also beaten and detained but not for the entire night, according to eyewitnesses.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Ola Shahba, a member of the Socialist Popular Alliance Party, said she was sexually harassed and beaten so she would confess to being paid.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;They used to ask naïve questions as to which embassy I was working with,&amp;quot; she said, speaking through a bruised face.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Her captors, she added, told her their names &amp;quot;because they know there&amp;apost;s no accountability.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Her fellow party member Ramy Sabry, who also claims to have been caught and held throughout the night with Najm, said the intensity of the beating increased when it became known that he was a Christian.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>His head and fingers are still bandaged.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Sabry said he filed reports against his captors, who he identified by name, and several Muslim Brotherhood leaders.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>He said that while still waiting in line for questioning, he heard the president&amp;apost;s speech citing confessions by defendants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>HRW&amp;apost;s Morayef noted violence had been documented on both sides of the clashes, with most of the fatalities on the Morsy supporters&amp;apost; side.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>She was concerned that investigations would only focus on that.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m worried we won&amp;apost;t see a real investigation into the detention of those 49 citizens by other private citizens in the presence of the police, basically with police complicity,&amp;quot; she explained.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Both El-Haddad and Morayef lambasted the police for their failure to stop the clashes on December 5.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>El-Haddad said the current situation reveals &amp;quot;an extremely dysfunctional state,&amp;quot; explaining the intervention of the president&amp;apost;s supporters that day.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;They can&amp;apost;t fill in for a police force of course, but I think that the word I would use is a human shield.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>They have put themselves in between the attacking mob and the sovereignty symbol of the state.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>For Morayef, this is &amp;quot;vigilantism.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>The group of 49 detained overnight &amp;quot;all had bloodied faces, they had bruises, many of them black eyes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Cuts in their faces, dripping in blood,&amp;quot; Morayef said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;The fact that many of those engaging were members of the president&amp;apost;s party meant that he himself had a political responsibility or political influence over one side of the demonstration.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>