<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2411" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/06/25/world/asia/malaysia-iranian-bomb-suspect/index.html" date_published="2012-06-25 07:49:27" category="world" author="the CNN Wire Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Malaysian court: Iranian can be extradited to Thailand over Bangkok blasts</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">The Iranian suspect is wanted by the Thai authorities in relation to a string of blasts in Bangkok.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="11">Masoud Sedaghatzadeh was arrested in Kuala Lumpur a day after the bombings.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">A judge rules he can be extradited, but Sedaghatzadeh plans to apply to be released.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="23">Two other Iranian suspects are being held in Thailand, while two more are still at large .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-18 10:54:12" annotation_time="62.086334">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Masoud Sedaghatzadeh is wanted by the Thai authorities for his alleged involvement in the Bangkok blasts along with several other Iranians.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">It is not yet clear when Sedaghatzadeh will be extradited, as he plans to file an application to a higher court in Malaysia, seeking his release from prison.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="2">The Malaysian prosecutor, Kamal Baharin Omar, said Sedaghatzadeh, 31, was arrested at Kuala Lumpur airport on February 15, a day after one of the bombs went off at a house in Bangkok.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="4">Two other suspects in the case are still at large, according to Gen. Pansiri Prapawat, the deputy national police chief who is heading the investigation into the bombings.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A Malaysian court has ruled that an Iranian man suspected of being involved with a series of bombs that went off in Bangkok in February can be extradited to Thailand.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Masoud Sedaghatzadeh is wanted by the Thai authorities for his alleged involvement in the Bangkok blasts along with several other Iranians.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>It is not yet clear when Sedaghatzadeh will be extradited, as he plans to file an application to a higher court in Malaysia, seeking his release from prison.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The explosions in Bangkok did not cause any deaths, but the Thai authorities have said they were intended for Israeli diplomats.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The devices used explosive materials that are not available in Thailand and were most likely smuggled in, the police have said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The Bangkok blasts came a day after a device attached to an Israeli Embassy van in New Delhi exploded, and another device, found on an embassy car in Tbilisi, the capital of Georgia, was safety detonated.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Israeli officials blamed Iran for the attacks, but Tehran has denied the accusations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>On Monday, the Malaysian judge, Justice S.M Komathy Suppiah, ruled that Sedaghatzadeh be remanded in prison for as many as 15 days, pending an extradition order from the Minister of Home Affairs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;In my view, the conduct of the respondent is inconsistent with that of an innocent man,&amp;quot; she said, referring to Sedaghatzadeh.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m allowing the application for extradition and the respondent is to be detained in prison pending an order from the minister for his render.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The Malaysian prosecutor, Kamal Baharin Omar, said Sedaghatzadeh, 31, was arrested at Kuala Lumpur airport on February 15, a day after one of the bombs went off at a house in Bangkok.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Mr. Kamal said the Thai police had CCTV footage showing Sedaghatzadeh entering and leaving the house where the explosives were detonated.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>He questioned why Sedaghatzadeh would leave the house and flee to Kuala Lumpur if he was not connected to the explosives.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;All the actions subsequent to the explosion do not show the innocence of the respondent,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Sedaghatzadeh&amp;apost;s lawyer, Mohamad Nashir Hussin, argued that the Thai police had not been able to show that the respondent was involved in the incident.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;There&amp;apost;s no evidence that the respondent had any contact or had even seen the explosives in the house,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Sedaghatzadeh, who was handcuffed and dressed in a polo shirt and jeans, told the court that he would file a habeas corpus, an application asking to be released from prison.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;I require more time to defend myself,&amp;quot; he said through a translator.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The Thai authorities have detained two Iranian suspects in the case: Saeid Moradi, 28, whose legs were blown off by his own bomb; and Mohammad Khazaei, 42, who was taken into custody at Bangkok&amp;apost;s Suvarnabhumi Airport as he tried to board a plane to Malaysia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Both are being held at a Bangkok prison until their next court appearance.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>They and Sedaghatzadeh face charges that include joint assembly of explosive devices, joint possession of explosive devices without permits and causing an explosion injuring other persons.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Moradi also faces charges of attempted killing of state officials on duty and the intentional attempted killing of other persons.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Two other suspects in the case are still at large, according to Gen. Pansiri Prapawat, the deputy national police chief who is heading the investigation into the bombings.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>They are Nikkahfard Javad, a 52-year-old Iranian man, and Rohani Leila, an Iranian woman.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Thailand has issued an arrest warrant for the suspects and sent their names to Interpol&amp;apost;s wanted list, Pansiri said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>