<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2113" link="http://cnn.com/2014/05/23/world/asia/china-xinjiang-explosions/index.html" date_published="2014-05-23 15:55:01" category="world" author="Jethro Mullen and Kevin Wang, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>China launches terrorism crackdown after Xinjiang region attack</title>
  <keywords>China Xingjiang explosions</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">State news agency: China begins &amp;quot;one-year crackdown on violent terrorist activities&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">The report offers no details of the crackdown, but authorities tighten security at entry ports .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">Thursday&amp;apost;s explosions killed at least 39 people and wounded more than 90, state media say.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-10 14:55:55" annotation_time="11.07">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1, 3">Without any details, the report said authorities had undertaken a &amp;quot;one-year crackdown on violent terrorist activities&amp;quot; in the volatile region after blasts in the heavily policed city of Urumqi killed at least 39 people and wounded more than 90, according to state media.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">In Urumqi, authorities tightened security checks at entry ports in an attempt to curb weapons smuggling, including inspections of individuals, luggage, transport facilities and postal deliveries at land border crossings, Xinhua reported Friday.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>China has launched a terrorism crackdown one day after a series of explosions in an open-air market killed dozens in the western Chinese region of Xinjiang, the country&amp;apost;s state news agency, Xinhua said Friday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Without any details, the report said authorities had undertaken a &amp;quot;one-year crackdown on violent terrorist activities&amp;quot; in the volatile region after blasts in the heavily policed city of Urumqi killed at least 39 people and wounded more than 90, according to state media.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The number of dead does not include the attackers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The state news agency reported Friday that five attackers were responsible for the blasts; four were killed in the explosions, and a fifth was arrested Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>They were identified through DNA testing, Xinhua said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>In Urumqi, authorities tightened security checks at entry ports in an attempt to curb weapons smuggling, including inspections of individuals, luggage, transport facilities and postal deliveries at land border crossings, Xinhua reported Friday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>After visiting the injured and the scene of the explosions, Guo Shengkun, minister of public security, called for severe punishment for those responsible, state media said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>President Xi Jinping also called for the terrorists behind it to be &amp;quot;severely&amp;quot; punished.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Two SUVs slammed into shoppers gathered at the market in Urumqi at 7:50 a.m. Thursday, and explosives were flung out of the vehicles, Xinhua said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The vehicles then exploded, according to the news agency.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Some of the photos circulating on social media suggested a hellish scene, with bodies strewn on the ground amid burning wreckage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Others showed flames and smoke billowing out of the end of a tree-lined street guarded by police.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;apost;An enormous sound&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;I heard an enormous sound, then I looked out from my balcony,&amp;quot; said a resident of a building near the explosion who would only give his surname, Shan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>He told CNN that trees obscured much of his view of the scene, but that he &amp;quot;could see there was chaos, with people injured.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Many of the victims caught in the blasts were elderly people who regularly visited the morning market, Xinhua reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s mainly people coming to trade vegetables, especially the elderly who get up early and buy vegetables to cook,&amp;quot; Shan said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The U.S. government condemned the attack.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is a despicable and outrageous act of violence against innocent civilians, and the United States resolutely opposes all forms of terrorism,&amp;quot; White House press secretary Jay Carney said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>String of recent attacks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Chinese authorities have stepped up security measures in Xinjiang in recent months amid a series of attacks within the region and in other major Chinese cities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>On Wednesday, Xinhua reported that 39 people had been sentenced to prison in the past two months for &amp;quot;inciting violence&amp;quot; in Xinjiang.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>But Thursday&amp;apost;s devastating blasts suggest the government is facing a foe determined to wreak havoc.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The market attack comes less than a month after an explosion hit a train station in Urumqi, killing three people and wounding 79 others.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The April 30 blast occurred just after Xi had wrapped up a visit to the region.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Ethnic tensions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Chinese officials have linked a mass knife attack in March that killed 29 people at a train station in the southwestern city of Kunming to Islamic separatists from Xinjiang.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>They have also blamed separatists for an October attack in Beijing&amp;apost;s Tiananmen Square in which a car rammed into a pedestrian bridge and burst into flames, killing two tourists and the three occupants of the vehicle.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The knife-wielding assailants in the Kunming attack and the people in the car that hit Tiananmen were identified as Uyghurs, a Turkic-speaking, predominantly Muslim ethnic group from Xinjiang.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Ethnic tensions between Uyghurs and Han Chinese people, millions of whom have migrated to resource-rich Xinjiang in recent decades, have repeatedly boiled over into deadly riots and clashes with authorities in recent years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Some Uyghurs have expressed resentment over harsh treatment from Chinese security forces and Han people taking the lion&amp;apost;s share of economic opportunities in Xinjiang.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The Han are the predominant ethnic group in China, making up more than 90% of the overall population.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Shift in targets.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The pattern of ethnic violence in the region goes back decades, according to James Leibold, an expert in ethnic relations in China at La Trobe University in Melbourne, Australia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;But what&amp;apost;s new, and what I think is significant, is that we have a shift in target,&amp;quot; Leibold said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have a targeting of innocent civilians, places where innocent civilians gather -- an attempt to maim innocent civilians in large numbers.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>The other change is that the violence has &amp;quot;seeped outside&amp;quot; the borders of Xinjiang into other parts of China, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>It remains unclear who is behind the recent high-profile attacks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Chinese officials have pointed to a murky separatist group, the East Turkestan Islamic Movement, which they have blamed for violent acts in the past.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>East Turkestan is the name used by many Uyghur groups to refer to Xinjiang.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>But analysts are divided about the extent of the that group&amp;apost;s activities and its links to global terrorist networks such as al Qaeda.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;Generally, the government response is to blame terrorists without providing many details,&amp;quot; Leibold said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>&amp;quot;So I suspect it&amp;apost;s going to be very difficult to get to the bottom of this incident like previous ones.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
