<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2809" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/05/22/world/asia/afghanistan-taliban-schools/index.html" date_published="2012-05-22 07:38:09" category="world" author="Nick Paton Walsh, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Taliban tightens grip on Afghan schools</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Recently, the Taliban demanded the closure of some schools.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">&amp;quot;The Taliban are fine with us as long as we do what they want,&amp;quot; a teacher says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="11">This power struggle in classrooms is symptomatic of broader fears.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="12">Some wonder if the Taliban will tighten its grip on daily life as war nears an end.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-02 10:22:30" annotation_time="41.432667">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">Recently, the Taliban demanded the closure of some schools in two eastern provinces.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;The Taliban are fine with us as long as we do what they want.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="3">This power struggle in classrooms is symptomatic of broader fears about the future.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="4">As the U.S.-led military effort winds down in Afghanistan will the Taliban tighten its grip on daily life in the country?</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Kabul, Afghanistan In parts of rural Afghanistan a fierce battle is going on between the Taliban and the country&amp;apost;s government.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>And the victims in this battle, it seems, are school children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Recently, the Taliban demanded the closure of some schools in two eastern provinces.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>In Ghazni province, the closure of schools was in retaliation for the government&amp;apost;s ban on motorbikes often used by insurgents.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>In Wardak province, the Taliban has been a little more compromising, locals say, and has allowed some schools to open late after making changes to the curriculum.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Taliban are fine with us as long as we do what they want.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>They tell us what to teach and what not to.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>If we don&amp;apost;t do what they say they have a representative who comes checking things,&amp;quot; one teacher said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;They have increased the number of hours we teach religious subjects in a week and decreased other subjects like English.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>If we didn&amp;apost;t, they would threaten teachers, and it is very much possible that they would close the school down.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>This power struggle in classrooms is symptomatic of broader fears about the future.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>As the U.S.-led military effort winds down in Afghanistan will the Taliban tighten its grip on daily life in the country?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>CNN&amp;apost;s cameras were allowed in one classroom in Wardak but those interviewed will not be identified for their own safety.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>In this classroom, teaching is allowed but a Taliban minder oversees the syllabus.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>One student in the class says he does not mind.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Taliban have only increased the religious subjects in our day-to-day schedule, which is very good as people should learn religious subjects,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Mohammad Sediq Patman, a deputy education minister said the government has to be flexible in order to keep schools open.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>In areas where the Taliban had more control, sometimes the government lets them influence what subjects are taught and even allows them to check student attendance, Patman said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;There was no deal between the government and the Taliban, but only in order to keep the schools open and running the Education Ministry had shown flexibility to this issue,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>One Taliban school minder spoke to CNN but chose to cover his face on camera so that he could not be identified.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;We didn&amp;apost;t allow schools to be opened here at the beginning of the school year because we wanted them to change,&amp;quot; the Taliban minder said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;Then we had a big meeting with school officials and concluded we would allow school to start, but teaching should be according to our principles and Islamic principles.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>They accepted that.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>We have only increased Islamic subjects so that even when a person becomes an engineer, he should have enough knowledge in Islam.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The minder said he was implementing instructions from Taliban leader Mullah Omar as are many others across Afghanistan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
