<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2647" link="http://cnn.com/2014/02/01/world/asia/thailand-gunfire" date_published="2014-02-01 11:08:42" category="world" author="Ben Brumfield and Kocha Olarn, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Protests delay elections in Bangkok district</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">NEW: Anti-government protesters successfully delayed elections in Bangkok&amp;apost;s Laksi district .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">At least seven people were wounded in the Saturday violence, medical officials say.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="7">At least eight gunmen emerged from the ranks of the anti-government protests.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="7">They opened fire for about 30 minutes toward police and pro-government demonstrators.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-14 16:57:57" annotation_time="18.978">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Bangkok, Thailand Anti-government protesters in Thailand can consider this round of resistance a success, after getting Sunday&amp;apost;s national elections delayed in the Bangkok district of Laksi.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">At least seven people were wounded, Erawan Medical Centre said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="3, 4">Witnesses saw at least eight gunmen emerge from the ranks of the anti-government protests and open fire for about 30 minutes toward police and pro-government demonstrators.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Bangkok, Thailand Anti-government protesters in Thailand can consider this round of resistance a success, after getting Sunday&amp;apost;s national elections delayed in the Bangkok district of Laksi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>National security chief Paradorn Pattanathabutr told CNN that Laksi postponed balloting for approximately 87,000 voters because demonstrators were blocking the administration office where the ballot boxes are kept.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The make-up voting date is yet to be determined.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Laksi, a district of mixed pro- and anti-government sentiment, witnessed violent protests on Saturday, when gunfire erupted during anti-government protests, witnesses said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>At least seven people were wounded, Erawan Medical Centre said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The violence came amid high tensions a day ahead of elections.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Witnesses saw at least eight gunmen emerge from the ranks of the anti-government protests and open fire for about 30 minutes toward police and pro-government demonstrators.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>It was not clear whether anyone fired back.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Of those injured, one remains in the intensive care unit, the medical center said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>In addition, a local journalist was injured by a firecracker hurled by someone in the crowd, according to witnesses.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Anti-government demonstrators say they will keep up protests and attempt to shut down Thailand&amp;apost;s capital city during elections.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>They have been campaigning for months against Prime Minister Yingluck Shinawatra, fueling unrest that previously left 10 people dead and hundreds more wounded.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Yingluck called the elections in December in a bid to ease mounting tensions on the streets of Bangkok.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>But the demonstrators and the main opposition party with which they&amp;apost;re affiliated have already rejected the vote.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Yingluck&amp;apost;s party is expected to win comfortably.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Her brother Thaksin Shinawatra is a business tycoon, who became Prime Minister before being overthrown in a military coup.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>He has since lived in exile, but his opponents accuse him of dominating politics from afar, including through Yingluck.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Lead-up to gunfire.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Before the gunfire broke out, protesters attempted to foil elections by interfering with preparations, CNN&amp;apost;s Saima Mohsin reported from Bangkok.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Some of them camped out at a center that is providing ballot boxes for the election and blocked police from entering it to inspect the boxes, a necessary measure before voting may proceed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Police initially were able to coax them away, but afterward, more protesters from both groups converged on the spot, the Laksi intersection, a major traffic spot in the capital.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Gunshots rang out and people ducked.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Rapid gunfire continued, mixed in with the sound of fireworks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Gun smoke filled the air.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;I could taste it; I could smell it,&amp;quot; Mohsin said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>There were few security forces present to respond.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Around 20 police officers and a dozen soldiers crouched behind their vehicles to avoid flying bullets.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Authorities have said that 10,000 security personnel are on standby.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>No further violence erupted overnight, but protesters were able to keep authorities from reaching the ballot boxes on Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Political battles.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The political elbowing goes beyond Bangkok&amp;apost;s streets and has spread dirty politics into many provinces, where some constituents have no candidates to represent them in the election, Mohsin reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>They were blocked from registering to run for election.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Many voters are being blocked from participating in the vote.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The lasting political instability has created fears of chaos in Thailand, which was shaken by severe bout of violence four years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The concerns have already hurt the country&amp;apost;s lucrative tourist industry and undermined investment in one of Southeast Asia&amp;apost;s main economies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
