<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2852" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/10/21/world/africa/tribal-beauty-photographer-vanishing/index.html" date_published="2013-10-21 09:29:05" category="world" author="Jenny Soffel, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Tribal beauty: Photographer gives snapshot of vanishing way of life</title>
  <keywords>Africa,African tribes,Jimmy Nelson,photography,Ethiopia,Kenya,Tanzania,Namibia,Beauty,maasai,himba,before they pass away</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5, 3">Jimmy Nelson photographed 35 tribes all over the world for book &amp;quot;&amp;apost;Before They Pass Away&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="17">Nelson photographed tribes in Ethiopia, Kenya, Tanzania and Namibia.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">He wanted to create a record of &amp;quot;a fast disappearing world&amp;quot;.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 16:40:54" annotation_time="54.30267" mapping_time_divergence="36.20178">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1, 3">That&amp;apost;s why British photographer Jimmy Nelson decided to travel the world for three years, visiting 35 tribes in all five continents, to document their lives and customs before they disappear.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">The result of his journey can be found in his new book of photographs, &amp;quot;Before They Pass Away.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="2">They visited five tribes in Ethiopia, and one each in Kenya, Tanzania and Namibia.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>As teenagers, the women of the Ethiopian Mursi tribe pierce their lower lips and put a clay plate in it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>They are one of the last tribes in the world who still practice this tradition and the new generation, influenced by the outside world, might decide to abandon it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s why British photographer Jimmy Nelson decided to travel the world for three years, visiting 35 tribes in all five continents, to document their lives and customs before they disappear.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>He drank vodka with the Mongolian Tsaatan tribe in freezing conditions and admired the beautiful Himba tribesmen in the Namib Desert.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The result of his journey can be found in his new book of photographs, &amp;quot;Before They Pass Away.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;The whole idea is to make (the tribes) iconic.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>To give them the attention that we give ourselves in the developed world,&amp;quot; the 45-year-old photographer says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>From a very early age, Nelson was confronted by cultural diversity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>He grew up in different African countries before moving to England at the age of seven to attend a catholic Jesuit boarding school.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Going back to Africa to meet with nine tribes in four different countries was a special experience for him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;Africa is evolving the quickest in my opinion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>It has lost the majority of its ethnicity and authenticity,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;I grew up in Nigeria, Sierra Leone, Gabon and in Cameroon.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>I&amp;apost;ve been living for 45 years, and what I saw in my childhood is not there anymore.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Being humble.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Nelson and his crew, consisting of an assistant and a cameraman, covered Africa in five trips.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>They visited five tribes in Ethiopia, and one each in Kenya, Tanzania and Namibia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Nelson says the most challenging part of his African journeys was approaching the tribes in southern Ethiopia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;There are many small tribes in a small area and everybody is protecting their own turf.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>So they can be quite intimidating,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>When first approaching the tribes, Nelson left the camera equipment behind.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>He says even though all the tribes had been documented before, he was conscious to explain to them what he wanted to do.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Only the Kenyan tribe, Samburu, knew he was coming.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Although he was always traveling with a local guide, Nelson had to rely on body language and gestures to communicate with the different tribesmen and gain their trust.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>But he says it was all about appealing to their vanity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;Initially it&amp;apost;s idolization.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>You put them on a pedestal and then you touch their muscles and show that through lots of gestures, lots of hero-worship,&amp;quot; Nelson explains of his initial meetings with the Ethiopian tribes, who would often greet him carrying Kalashnikov rifles.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;You arrive and they are all wild and intimidating, it&amp;apost;s all about being macho.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>One thing that stood out to Nelson when meeting the different African tribes was their awareness of their appearances.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>He says he noticed a lot of male vanity in the African tribes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>For example, many people think the men in the Namibian Himba tribe are actually women.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is a classic example of the whole idea behind the book that appearances can be deceptive,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;Very few of us will ever look as beautiful as these people.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Signs of modernization.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>When Nelson and his crew traveled across the Omo Valley four years ago, to find the southern Ethiopian tribes, it took them three weeks to reach them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Today, he says, the roads have been improved and it only takes a few days.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>He thinks this is one of the reasons some of the tribes are slowly abandoning their traditional lifestyle.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;At the moment (the African tribes) are evolving quickly because of the digital age.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Many of them have a mobile telephone, so they are aware of an outside world,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The book &amp;quot;Before They Pass Away&amp;quot; is just the first third of his project.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>The next step is to go back to all 35 tribes and show them their photos, explaining to them why he made them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>The idea is to then visit another 35 tribes in more politically unstable areas, where he would need the authorities&amp;apost; help to get access.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>But most of all Nelson hopes the portraits will encourage a deeper dialogue between the tribes and the developed world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;By illustrating these people in a grand aesthetic, romantic, idealistic and iconic way, I&amp;apost;m trying to attract the public&amp;apost;s attention to a subject matter that they wouldn&amp;apost;t normally be interested in,&amp;quot; the photographer explains.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Before Nelson embarked on his three-year-long journey, he was just expecting to make a visual document to celebrate the tribes for what they looked like.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>But now he thinks there are greater lessons to be learned.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>&amp;quot;In my eyes the tribespeople are emotionally and socially very rich but materially very poor, and we (in the West) are the opposite,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>&amp;quot;How aware of how special they are is debatable, hence why I want to start this discussion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Before they pass away.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
