<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2362" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/09/07/world/asia/china-leadership-change-florcruz/index.html" date_published="2012-09-07 08:01:57" category="world" author="Jaime A. FlorCruz, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Jockeying for position ahead of China&amp;apost;s leadership jamboree</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">18th Congress of the 82-million-member Chinese Communist Party chooses new leadership.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">President Hu Jintao will step down and likely be replaced by Vice President Xi Jinping.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">Political maneuvering has increased among various camps as congress nears.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="32">Two camps dominate: that of retired president Jiang Zemin and that of President Hu.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 20:53:14" annotation_time="14.692333">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">The 18th Congress of the 82-million-member Chinese Communist Party, expected to happen in mid-October, will be a landmark event -- it will usher in a new generation of leaders to rule China for the next 10 years.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">Hu Jintao, the incumbent president and party general secretary, will step down and be replaced by Xi Jinping, the current vice president.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">As the congress approaches, political maneuvering has increased among various camps, and there have been a few surprises already.</sentence>
      <sentence id="32" ids_highlights="4">China&amp;apost;s leaders are widely seen as divided into two camps: that of retired president Jiang Zemin and that of President Hu.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Beijing Divining what is going in China&amp;apost;s opaque political world is like reading tea leaves: it may be interesting but it&amp;apost;s ultimately a futile exercise.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The 18th Congress of the 82-million-member Chinese Communist Party, expected to happen in mid-October, will be a landmark event -- it will usher in a new generation of leaders to rule China for the next 10 years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Yet, little is known about what to expect.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Some changes are imminent.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Hu Jintao, the incumbent president and party general secretary, will step down and be replaced by Xi Jinping, the current vice president.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Many members of the 25-member Politburo and the 371-member Central Committee are also expected to be replaced.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>These are the two policy-making bodies in the party&amp;apost;s pyramid organization.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Who will compose the post-Hu leadership?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Speculation is rife.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>As the congress approaches, political maneuvering has increased among various camps, and there have been a few surprises already.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Last week, Ling Jihua, head of the party&amp;apost;s General Office, which runs the Leninist organization&amp;apost;s day-to-day affairs and oversees security of the top leaders, was abruptly &amp;quot;reassigned&amp;quot; to the important but less powerful United Front department.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Analysts say Ling, 55, may still be chosen for the Politburo, but he is out of the running for the all-important Standing Committee -- the very highest decision-making body made up of a handful of key leaders.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is evidently a loss for Hu Jintao,&amp;quot; said Bonnie Glaser, senior fellow at the Center for Strategic and International Studies (CSIS), a think tank based in Washington D.C.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;Ling Jihua was a Hu protégé.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Who knows if it was related to the car crash?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>In the early morning on March 18, Ling&amp;apost;s son, Ling Gu, 23, was said to have smashed a black Ferrari into a concrete-wall on the side of Beijing&amp;apost;s Fourth Ring Road while driving at high speed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Much was made of the incident in the media internationally, but much of this was rumor and speculation that CNN can not substantiate.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Reports and discussions about it have been censored from the local media and Internet.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Ling Gu may have survived the car crash but it seems to have damaged his father&amp;apost;s political career and dented the party&amp;apost;s reputation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;It casts a negative light on corruption among party members and makes the public question the legitimacy of the officials&amp;apost; source of wealth,&amp;quot; said Joseph Cheng, a professor at the City University of Hong Kong.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;It has tarnished the image of the leadership.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Did the car scandal benefit Xi at the expense of the outgoing Hu?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Other analysts actually credit President Hu for the move on Ling.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;The leadership is establishing a rule: your son misbehaves, you pay,&amp;quot; said Francesco Sisci, a long-time observer of Chinese politics.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;This move must have been approved by Hu and therefore it does not necessarily weaken him.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Ling has been replaced by Li Zhanshu, 62, a provincial party chief who is known to be an ally of Hu and has previous ties with the vice president.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Li, analysts say, may have been a compromise choice.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>According to Cheng, Xi has been smart to avoid clashes with the current leaders.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;What Xi needs to do now is to keep a clean slate and a low profile and figure out how to consolidate his power,&amp;quot; he explained.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;Everybody knows he is the presumptive new leader, so he only needs to be patient.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Xi also needs to stay above the factional fights.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>China&amp;apost;s leaders are widely seen as divided into two camps: that of retired president Jiang Zemin and that of President Hu.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Former president and party chief, Jiang, retains residual influence even in retirement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The 86 year old has a network of allies in the party -- sometimes known as the &amp;quot;Shanghai faction&amp;quot; after the former president&amp;apost;s time as Party leader in the city -- which he uses to influence policy and personnel decisions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Last summer Jiang was rumored to have died, but he has since made a rare public appearance looking frail but fairly healthy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Some China-watchers believe Jiang&amp;apost;s influence has waned, but others say he remains a player.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;He is still influential,&amp;quot; said Glaser.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;His Shanghai faction remains quite important and his people are in key positions.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Others say Hu&amp;apost;s camp, known as the Communist Youth League (CYL) faction, referring to the youth organization that Hu headed for years, will dominate the new leadership.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;The lineup of the Standing Committee and the full Politburo will show that the CYL remains the largest faction,&amp;quot; said Willy Lam, a China expert at the Chinese University of Hong Kong.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;The CYL is especially strong among the next tier of leaders, born in the 1960s, who will take over power in 2022.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Lam said Hu is now in a good position to anoint one of his protégé, Hu Chunhua, as Xi&amp;apost;s presumptive successor in 2022 by getting him selected into the next Politburo.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>The younger Hu, 49, is a provincial party chief who also headed the CYL.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>The official line is that the transition is now firmly locked in place, but it would not be China, or the Communist Party, if it were as straight-forward and predictable as that.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>&amp;quot;My guess is that appointments can be changed up until the very last minute,&amp;quot; Sisci said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>&amp;quot;It was so ten years ago, it will even more so today.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
