<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2606" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/12/24/world/asia/india-rape-protests" date_published="2012-12-24 06:32:14" category="world" author="Harmeet Shah Singh, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Police crackdown amid outrage over gang rape</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Russian President Vladimir Putin is due visit India Monday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">New Delhi&amp;apost;s government district is under a lockdown.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">Protesters demonstrate after the gang rape of a woman on a bus.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="5">Police say the woman was badly beaten and left for dead.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 16:02:02" annotation_time="32.988667" mapping_time_divergence="8.247167">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1, 2, 3">New Delhi Police locked down New Delhi&amp;apost;s key government district ahead of Monday&amp;apost;s visit by Russian President Vladimir Putin, after two days of pitched street battles following the gang rape of a woman on a bus.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="4">Furious weekend demonstrations rocked Raisina Hills as public outrage surged after a 23-year-old woman was sexually assaulted and beaten to near death on a bus on December 16 by a group of six suspects, now under arrest, police say.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>New Delhi Police locked down New Delhi&amp;apost;s key government district ahead of Monday&amp;apost;s visit by Russian President Vladimir Putin, after two days of pitched street battles following the gang rape of a woman on a bus.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Putin is scheduled to meet with Indian prime minister Manmohan Singh Monday afternoon and later with the Indian president.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Authorities erected security barriers throughout the city&amp;apost;s Raisina Hills area -- home to the presidential mansion, the parliament building and federal ministerial blocks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Only those authorized to work in the district were allowed to pass.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Furious weekend demonstrations rocked Raisina Hills as public outrage surged after a 23-year-old woman was sexually assaulted and beaten to near death on a bus on December 16 by a group of six suspects, now under arrest, police say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Singh again expressed solidarity with the rape victim in a televised address on Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>He also reiterated an earlier appeal for calm and a pledge of safety for women and children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>On Sunday, incensed protesters defied a police ban on demonstrations, clashing repeatedly with police.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>As officers sprayed water cannons, some dispersed, while others huddled tightly in a circle to brave high-pressure streams in the cold December weather.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;We want justice!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>the protesters shouted in chorus.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>In addition to banners and cardboard placards, many demonstrators carried Indian flags as they scuffled with police.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Authorities also fired tear gas to try to break up crowds.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Police spokesman Rajan Bhagat said &amp;quot;hooligans who had joined the protesters&amp;quot; hurled stones, injuring 78 officers on Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>At least 65 protesters were also injured, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Many police vans and a dozen public buses were damaged during the demonstrations, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>By Sunday night, the scene was cleared of all protesters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Earlier in the day, Singh called for calm after clashes escalated.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;We will make all possible efforts to ensure security and safety to all women in this country,&amp;quot; the Indian leader said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;I appeal to all concerned citizens to maintain peace and calm.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>In his statement, Singh acknowledged that the anger is &amp;quot;genuine and justified.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Authorities haven&amp;apost;t released the name of the rape victim, but protesters are calling her &amp;quot;Damini,&amp;quot; which means &amp;quot;lightning&amp;quot; in Hindi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;Damini&amp;quot; is also a 1993 Bollywood film whose lead female character fights for a housemaid, a victim of a sexual assault.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;We support you Damini.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>We&amp;apost;ll keep fighting for you,&amp;quot; a middle-aged woman at the historic India Gate said Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;Damini wants justice,&amp;quot; read a placard at the protest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The rape victim&amp;apost;s injuries were so severe she spent days in intensive care in a city hospital, battling for her life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Police said Saturday that she had recovered enough to give a statement to a magistrate from her hospital bed the night before.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>But on Sunday, she underwent another surgery to wash out infection in her abdomen, her doctors said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The protests were among many anti-rape demonstrations staged across the country over the past week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>A video journalist was killed by police gunfire Sunday during a violent protest in India&amp;apost;s remote northeastern state of Manipur, authorities said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The journalist, identified by the information and broadcasting ministry as Dhij Mani, was covering a protest against a separate molestation case in the provincial capital of Imphal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Protests have rocked Manipur over the alleged molestation of a local actress by a suspected militant on December 18, during a public performance, authorities say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Protesters torched a vehicle, forcing police to open fire, officer Manik Longjam said Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The journalist died in the gunfire, Longjam said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Police say the molester is still at large.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Reported rape cases have increased more than tenfold over the past 40 years -- from 2,487 in 1971 to 24,206 in 2011, according to official figures.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>New Delhi alone reported 572 rapes last year and more than 600 in 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>As fury about the assault gathered pace, some Indian lawmakers called for treating rape as a capital crime.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;ll work collectively to see we make a law which is deterrent and preventive,&amp;quot; said New Delhi&amp;apost;s chief minister, Sheila Dikshit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>India&amp;apost;s home minister Sushilkumar Shinde told reporters Saturday that the government would work toward increasing punishment in &amp;quot;rarest of the rare&amp;quot; rape cases.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>But pressed on whether the administration would agree to demands for death by hanging in such instances, he said: &amp;quot;We&amp;apost;ll have to see in what way it (the rape sentencing) can be enhanced.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Shinde said the government was pushing for a speedy trial for the attack.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Authorities are also taking a number of steps to improve security for women in New Delhi, particularly on public transport, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>&amp;quot;(The) government shares the widespread concern and support that has been expressed throughout society for the girl who has so suffered.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Government also respects the right of legitimate protest,&amp;quot; Shinde said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="37">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>&amp;quot;At the same time, there is need to exercise calm at this juncture and for everyone to work together to improve the safety and security environment.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
