<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2904" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/08/14/world/meast/syria-unrest/index.html" date_published="2012-08-14 07:17:50" category="world" author="the CNN Wire Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>U.N. humanitarian chief in Syria to highlight dire situation</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">NEW: Valerie Amos met with Syria&amp;apost;s prime minister, Syrian TV says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8">NEW: At least 70 people have been killed across Syria on Tuesday, opposition says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="16">Officials vote to suspend Syria from the Organization of Islamic Cooperation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="20">A Syrian envoy was visiting China on Tuesday; China considers inviting opposition.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 21:17:49" annotation_time="17.492666">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">She met with Prime Minister Wael al-Halaki, Syrian TV reported.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">At least 70 people were killed Tuesday, the Local Coordination Committees of Syria opposition group said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="3">Foreign ministers of Islamic countries have agreed to suspend Syria from the Organization of Islamic Cooperation, ahead of the group&amp;apost;s two-day emergency summit this week.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="4">Meanwhile, a Syrian presidential adviser was scheduled to visit China on Tuesday, the Chinese Foreign Ministry said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A top U.N. official arrived in Damascus on Tuesday in an attempt to &amp;quot;draw attention to the deteriorating humanitarian situation in Syria,&amp;quot; the United Nations said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Valerie Amos, the U.N.&amp;apost;s under-secretary-general for humanitarian affairs and emergency relief coordinator, is on a three-day trip to Syria and Lebanon.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;The humanitarian situation in Syria has further worsened in recent weeks as fighting has spread in Damascus and to Aleppo and other cities,&amp;quot; the United Nations said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;Two million people are now estimated to have been affected by the crisis, and over one million have been internally displaced.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>She met with Prime Minister Wael al-Halaki, Syrian TV reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>In Lebanon, Amos will meet with families who fled Syria and will talk with the government and humanitarian agencies about how to best support the refugees, her office said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Across Syria, the reports of relentless bloodshed mount by the hour.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>At least 70 people were killed Tuesday, the Local Coordination Committees of Syria opposition group said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The toll included 10 children and three women.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Syria said the assistant director of the Health Directorate in Daraa was &amp;quot;assassinated&amp;quot; by &amp;quot;an armed terrorist group&amp;quot; Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Attackers waited for Dr. Ma&amp;apost;moun al-Zoubi at the garage of his building &amp;quot;and opened fire on him, causing his martyrdom,&amp;quot; the state-run Syrian Arab News Agency (SANA) reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>In recent days, fierce shelling in and around dissident strongholds has aggravated the humanitarian crisis, opposition activists said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>In the Homs suburb of Rastan, residents pleaded for intervention &amp;quot;to break the siege of the disaster-stricken city, which has no access to any of life&amp;apost;s essentials including bread, water, baby formula or electricity,&amp;quot; the LCC said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Syria said authorities &amp;quot;arrested dozens of terrorists&amp;quot; in Aleppo and destroyed seven cars equipped with machine guns.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Armed forces also killed and injured &amp;quot;terrorists&amp;quot; in an area called al-Kura al-Ardiya, SANA reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Foreign ministers of Islamic countries have agreed to suspend Syria from the Organization of Islamic Cooperation, ahead of the group&amp;apost;s two-day emergency summit this week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The Syrian civil war is a key topic on the agenda of the summit, which opens Tuesday in the Islamic holy city of Mecca, Saudi Arabia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;There is an agreement to support the Syrian people, and standing by their side, we are agreeing on freezing the membership of Syria until it retains its balance,&amp;quot; Tunisian Foreign Minister Rafiq Abdul Salam said, according to the official Saudi Press Agency.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The heads of state must approve the suspension before it can take effect.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Meanwhile, a Syrian presidential adviser was scheduled to visit China on Tuesday, the Chinese Foreign Ministry said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>China, along with Russia, has repeatedly vetoed attempts at the U.N. Security Council to take stronger action against Syrian President Bashar al-Assad&amp;apost;s regime.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>A spokesman for the ministry said Bouthaina Shaaban, al-Assad&amp;apost;s political and media adviser, will meet with Chinese Foreign Minister Yang Jiechi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;To promote the political solution to the Syria problem, China has always actively balanced its work between the Syrian government and the opposition to urge Syria to put to practice (former Arab League and U.N. envoy Kofi) Annan&amp;apost;s suggestions and advice by the U.N. Security Council -- immediately cease fire and all violent actions, protect civilians and resolve the crisis through talks,&amp;quot; the spokesman said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;China is also considering inviting members of the Syrian opposition to visit,&amp;quot; the ministry said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The United States, meanwhile, lifted sanctions against the former Syrian Prime Minister Riyad Hijab, who recently broke with the regime.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;Recent civilian and military defections from the Assad regime are further indications that the government is crumbling and losing its grip on power,&amp;quot; David S. Cohen, under secretary for terrorism and financial intelligence at the U.S. Treasury, said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;The United States encourages other officials within the Syrian government, in both the political and military ranks, to take similarly courageous steps to reject the Assad regime and stand with the Syrian people.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>While the war rages on, Syrian rebels claimed one of their biggest achievements yet Monday -- the shooting down of a military jet.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Video posted by the rebel forces shows a jet framed in a cloudless sky being shot at, catching fire and falling out of frame.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;A MiG warplane shot down in Mouhassen!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>says an excited man off-camera, citing a location in Deir Ezzor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;God is great!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The government denied the jet was shot down, blaming the crash instead on a &amp;quot;technical failure.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>It said that the jet fighter was on an &amp;quot;ordinary training flight&amp;quot; and that the pilot ejected safely.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The search for the pilot was still under way late Monday, according to SANA.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>A few hours after the rebels made their claim, the opposition LCC posted a video showing what it said was the pilot, whom it identified as Col. Mufeed Mohamad Suleiman.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>No identification card was shown.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>The man, dressed in civilian clothes and surrounded by armed men, called on other military officers to defect.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>He said the rebels had provided first aid for the bruises on his face that he suffered in the parachute jump.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>A man who identified himself as a rebel captain said the pilot would be treated as a prisoner of war.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>CNN cannot independently confirm the authenticity of either video.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>A report Monday from opposition activists underscored the difficulty in resolving the Syrian crisis.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>It said that Syrian forces in Damascus had publicly executed at least 10 people in one town, and that residents were unable to reach the bodies because &amp;quot;regime forces have been firing at anything that moves,&amp;quot; the LCC said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>The Syrian crisis has claimed roughly 17,000 lives since it erupted last year, U.N. Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon said last month.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Opposition activists have put the toll at more than 20,000.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
