<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2155" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/07/02/world/africa/oscar-pistorius-trial/index.html" date_published="2014-07-02 10:24:02" category="world" author="Richard Allen Greene, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Doctors: Oscar Pistorius is suicide risk, depressed</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Oscar Pistorius does not have signs associated with violence against partners, doctors find.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">Pistorius is accused of deliberately shooting his girlfriend, Reeva Steenkamp .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">He says he shot Steenkamp accidentally in his bathroom, mistaking her for an intruder .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 20:45:47" annotation_time="26.461998">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">But he does not appear to have a history of abnormal aggression or psychopathic tendencies linked to &amp;quot;rage-type murders in intimate relations,&amp;quot; they found.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">The double amputee sprinter is on trial for killing his girlfriend Reeva Steenkamp in his home last year.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">He admits killing her but says he mistook her for a burglar and thought he was defending himself.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Pretoria, South Africa Oscar Pistorius is depressed, suffering from post-traumatic stress disorder, and is a suicide risk, the doctors who spent a month evaluating his mental health concluded.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But he does not appear to have a history of abnormal aggression or psychopathic tendencies linked to &amp;quot;rage-type murders in intimate relations,&amp;quot; they found.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The conclusions, read at the athlete&amp;apost;s murder trial on Wednesday, are a &amp;quot;slam-dunk for the defense,&amp;quot; CNN legal expert Kelly Phelps said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The double amputee sprinter is on trial for killing his girlfriend Reeva Steenkamp in his home last year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>He admits killing her but says he mistook her for a burglar and thought he was defending himself.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The prosecution says the two had an argument and he killed her intentionally.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The psychiatric report seemed to suggest that Pistorius&amp;apost;s version of events was plausible.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;When Mr. Pistorius&amp;apost;s appraisal of the situation is that he might be physically threatened, a fear response follows that might seem extraordinary when viewed from the perspective of a normal bodied person, but normal in the context of a disabled person with his history,&amp;quot; the doctors found.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>One of the questions Judge Thokozile Masipa must consider in determining her verdict is whether Pistorius behaved reasonably in the circumstances.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Several witnesses have testified that Pistorius tends to arm himself and go towards danger, rather than away from it, when he thinks he is under threat.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The track star&amp;apost;s specialist sports doctor testified Wednesday after defense lawyer Barry Roux read the mental health report.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Wayne Derman said that Pistorius was &amp;quot;hypervigilant.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Mentally sound.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The trial restarted Monday after a monthlong break when Pistorius was evaluated by mental health experts at the prosecution&amp;apost;s request.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>They found he was not mentally incapacitated when he shot and killed Steenkamp.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>An independent panel of doctors said that Pistorius was, at the time he shot Steenkamp, not mentally ill or incapacitated in any way that would make him &amp;quot;criminally not responsible of the offenses charged.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The report added that &amp;quot;Mr. Pistorius was capable of appreciating the wrongfulness of his act.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Had the doctors deemed Pistorius mentally incapacitated during the shooting, the trial would have immediately ended in a verdict of not guilty by reason of mental illness.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Verdict.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>At the trial&amp;apost;s conclusion, Judge Masipa will have to decide whether Pistorius genuinely made a mistake or killed Steenkamp intentionally.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>If she does not believe the athlete thought there was an intruder, she will find him guilty of murder and sentence him to a prison term ranging from 15 years to life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>South Africa does not have the death penalty.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>If Masipa accepts that Pistorius did not know Steenkamp was the person he was shooting at, she could find him guilty of culpable homicide, a lesser charge than murder, or acquit him, according to CNN legal analyst Kelly Phelps.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>A verdict of culpable homicide would leave the sentence at Masipa&amp;apost;s discretion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
