<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2609" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/07/13/world/africa/sudan-protests/index.html" date_published="2012-07-13 18:42:53" category="world" author="Isma&amp;apost;il Kushkush, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Police respond to protesters with tear gas, arrests near Sudan&amp;apost;s capital</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Sudanese march against rising prices, call for government&amp;apost;s ouster.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">Witness says rocks were thrown at police, who chased protesters.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">Activist social media sites have reported protests in at least three Sudanese towns.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="15">Police representative downplays scope of protests, but activists say 2,000 arrested so far.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 21:01:03" annotation_time="30.706665">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Khartoum, Sudan Sudanese took to the streets Friday in a fourth week of protests against rising prices and called for the ousting of the government.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;I saw protesters throw rocks at the police, who responded with tear gas,&amp;quot; a witness told CNN.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">Activist social media sites have reported protests in other Sudanese towns, including Khartoum North, El Obeid and Um Ruwwaba.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="4">Activists say that 2,000 protesters have been arrested so far.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Khartoum, Sudan Sudanese took to the streets Friday in a fourth week of protests against rising prices and called for the ousting of the government.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;The people want to bring down the regime!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>they shouted as they left the Imam Abd al-Rahman al-Mahdi Mosque after Friday prayers in the Omdurman neighborhood of Wad Nubawi, across the Nile from the capital of Khartoum.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Anti-riot police responded with tear gas, and plainclothes security officers arrested a number of protesters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;I saw protesters throw rocks at the police, who responded with tear gas,&amp;quot; a witness told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;There is heavy police and security presence, and they are chasing people into the allies of Wad Nubawi,&amp;quot; he added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The Imam Abd al-Rahman al-Mahdi Mosque, which is connected to the Ansar sect and the opposition National Ummah Party, has become a center for protests on Fridays after prayers for the past three weeks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Activists dubbed Friday&amp;apost;s day of action &amp;quot;Kandaka Friday&amp;quot; to honor Sudanese women.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;Kandaka,&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;Candace,&amp;quot; was the title of ancient Sudanese Nubian queens.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Activist social media sites have reported protests in other Sudanese towns, including Khartoum North, El Obeid and Um Ruwwaba.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Al-Sir Ahmad Umar, a Sudanese police representative, said that &amp;quot;there was no confrontation with the police&amp;quot; during protests at the Imam Abd al-Rahman al-Mahdi Mosque and that &amp;quot;only a limited number&amp;quot; of protesters reached the main street.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>He also said that the protest in the town of El Obied was limited to 20 people.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;Do you call that a protest?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Activists say that 2,000 protesters have been arrested so far.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>This week, Human Rights Watch and Amnesty International issued a statement condemning the arrest and detention of protesters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;Amnesty International and Human Rights Watch also urged the immediate and unconditional release of anyone arrested for participating in peaceful protests,&amp;quot; the groups said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The current wave of protests was started on June 16 by students at the University of Khartoum against government economic austerity measures that have increased fuel and food prices.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Protests have spread into neighborhoods in the greater Khartoum area and other Sudanese cities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Sudan&amp;apost;s economy has suffered since the separation of South Sudan last year, which took with it nearly 75% of the country&amp;apost;s oil wealth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>While most of the oil wells are in the south, the pipelines and port to export the oil are in the north.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The countries have not been able to agree on how to share oil revenues.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Sudanese President Omar al-Bashir has repeatedly downplayed the effect of the recent protests, calling the protesters &amp;quot;agitators&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;vagabonds.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;Those speaking of an Arab Spring in Sudan, we have a very hot summer here that will burn the enemies of Sudan!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>he said Wednesday to crowds at the opening of a sugar factory.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Most of the protests have been scattered and relatively small, with participants in the hundreds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>But Sudanese in the past have brought down two military governments through popular protest, in 1964 and in 1985.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
