<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2650" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/06/11/world/asia/psy-snoop-dogg-new-video/index.html" date_published="2014-06-11 05:25:58" category="world" author="Frances Cha, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Psy leads Snoop Dogg on Korean-style drinking binge</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="12">Psy and Snoop Dogg shot new &amp;quot;Hangover&amp;quot; music video in Incheon, South Korea.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">Video shows traditional Korean style of drinking and partying.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="31">Psy&amp;apost;s EP will be released later this year.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 21:03:42" annotation_time="44.699337">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">The &amp;quot;Hangover&amp;quot; video shows Psy taking Snoop on a ridiculous guided tour of what he does best -- hardcore drinking, Korean-style.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="1">Psy: When I first spoke with Snoop on the phone to discuss the collaboration idea, Snoop loved the title of the song, and I immediately suggested to him during that first conversation to shoot the music video in Korea and show us getting drunk and getting hungover in the most traditional Korean way.</sentence>
      <sentence id="31" ids_highlights="3">Psy&amp;apost;s new EP is slated to come out later this year.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Psy&amp;apost;s new song &amp;quot;Hangover&amp;quot; featuring Snoop Dogg dropped three days ago and the video has already racked up more than 31 million views on YouTube.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s actually a pretty slow start for the Korean superstar, considering &amp;quot;Gangnam Style&amp;quot; became the first video to pass two billion hits a week ago, while his follow-up single &amp;quot;Gentleman&amp;quot; also broke a record for the most views in 24 hours -- it currently has 694 million views on YouTube.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The &amp;quot;Hangover&amp;quot; video shows Psy taking Snoop on a ridiculous guided tour of what he does best -- hardcore drinking, Korean-style.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>This involves endless bomb shots, hanging out at a jjimjilbang (Korean bathhouse), throwing up and karaoke with strangers -- with one particularly surreal scene of Snoop, Psy and and two Korean women blithely skipping through an amusement park, presumably drunk.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>True to the premise, Psy told CNN he was actually hungover when the song came out.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Promotions for the new song kicked off Sunday on Jimmy Kimmel, with the unlikely trio of Kimmel, Psy and Snoop heading to a local karaoke bar in Los Angeles and bringing the house down with their yodeling.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>We asked Psy to talk about his hot new collaboration.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>CNN: How were you introduced to Snoop Dogg?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Psy: My manager Scooter Braun put me in touch with him at my request.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>When I first wrote this track, I thought that Snoop&amp;apost;s slow rapping would fit perfectly with my rapping on this track, so I asked him to put me in touch with Snoop and it&amp;apost;s how it all happened.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>CNN: Who came up with the ideas for the video?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Psy: When I first spoke with Snoop on the phone to discuss the collaboration idea, Snoop loved the title of the song, and I immediately suggested to him during that first conversation to shoot the music video in Korea and show us getting drunk and getting hungover in the most traditional Korean way.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>CNN: Where was the video filmed and who chose the locations?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Psy: It was shot in Incheon.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>I chose that location because Snoop only had 18 hours to shoot the video.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Since he was going to arrive at Incheon International Airport, I wanted to shoot the entire video in an area that is the closest to the airport to get the most out of those 18 hours.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>CNN: What was the filming process like?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Psy: I initially told him that the shoot would be very relaxed and that he would only be in five scenes to entice him to come to Seoul and shoot the video.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>He ended up being in more than 20 scenes in more than 10 different locations within those 18 hours.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>CNN: Why did you decide to go with a different director this time?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Psy: I co-directed this video so technically it&amp;apost;s the same director, but my co-director [Cha Eun-taek] was different from that of &amp;quot;Gangnam Style&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Gentleman&amp;quot; [co-directed by Cho Soo-hyun] because the type of the song is different -- electronic dance music versus 808 hip hop -- and I also wanted my fans to experience something different.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>CNN: What surprised you about working with Snoop Dogg?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Psy: We all know how diligent Snoop is.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>He is all about working hard every time -- haha.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>I am just joking.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>I was very surprised working with him because he ended up shooting 20 different scenes in a short time -- it was a tough schedule, but he was a total pro and I appreciated it so much.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>CNN: How did you celebrate passing two billion views of &amp;quot;Gangnam Style&amp;quot;?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Psy: I really did not have a chance or time to celebrate because I immediately flew to LA for the Jimmy Kimmel Live appearance and other promos.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>CNN: What are some events/concerts/collaborations coming up for you?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Although I cannot say at this moment who I collaborated with this past year [for an upcoming EP], but what I can tell you is that I worked with some big name artists!</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Psy&amp;apost;s new EP is slated to come out later this year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The lead single on the EP &amp;quot;Daddy&amp;quot; will be released this summer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
