<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2044" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/04/29/world/asia/india-transgender-gay-rights/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-04-29 14:47:41" category="world" author="Harmeet Shah Singh, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>A community constrained by taboos and stereotypes</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="56">India grants Hijras the right to self-identify their gender, a historic ruling to end discrimination.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="55">Activists say Supreme Court has come out with conflicting judgments on transgenders and gay community.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="38">India&amp;apost;s transgender community is seen as disproportionately vulnerable to HIV despite its tiny size.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-08 23:19:48" annotation_time="31.879">
      <sentence id="38" ids_highlights="3">According to the Indian government, the country&amp;apost;s transgender community is seen as disproportionately vulnerable to the deadly infection despite its tiny size.</sentence>
      <sentence id="55" ids_highlights="2">Within a span of few months, India&amp;apost;s Supreme Court has come out with what activists say are conflicting judgments, on transgenders and Hijras on one hand, and the gay community on the other.</sentence>
      <sentence id="56" ids_highlights="1">This month, the justices granted Hijras the right to self-identify their gender in what has been hailed as a historic ruling to end centuries-old discrimination against the country&amp;apost;s transgender citizens.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Sitting cross-legged at her office desk, Abhina Aher expounds on what it means to be trapped in the wrong body.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>She is a 37-year-old Hijra -- a South Asian term for male-to-female transgendered people.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>She appears at ease when she speaks about her sexual orientation and about the stereotypes associated with her community.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Aher is relaxed because she&amp;apost;s in the confines of a non-profit workplace espousing the cause of sexual minorities like herself.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Here, she&amp;apost;s not judged by her deep voice or her masculine face, its lines softened by make-up, or by her feminine dresses, nail-polish and jewelry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Aher has gained a new found place in her country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>India&amp;apost;s Supreme Court recently granted her and other transgendered people, status as a third gender.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>So, men can now be identified as females and females can be identified as males.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>But the outside world, she says, is harsh.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>In a largely conservative, family-structured region, proclaiming you are not what you are born could entail a harrowing ordeal that Aher suffered -- and survived.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>She raised a few eyebrows when she first slipped into her mother&amp;apost;s sari at the age of six.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Her cross-dressing habits, she remembers, were then ignored for some time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>But her secret desire to break free from her anatomic sex would only become more intense as she grew older.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;The issue about gender and sexuality kept coming back to me.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>But the unfortunate part of that was I did not have anybody to talk to; I had no one to share my thoughts with,&amp;quot; Aher says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>From rejection to acceptance.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Aher&amp;apost;s self-discovery created a sense of loss for her widowed mother, for whom Aher was a boy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;My mother would take me to a temple and make me swear by God that I would change my behavior,&amp;quot; Aher said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;But it was beyond my control.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>And Aher was rejected.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Her mother didn&amp;apost;t speak with her for almost nine years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Her teachers weren&amp;apost;t supportive either.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Rather, she became a target of jeers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The hurt became deeper when she stepped into the adult world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Her lovers, she says, also abandoned her.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;My journey was lonely.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>All my lovers rejected me.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>They either used me for money, or for sexual pleasure or for some momentary emotional support.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>There was a huge vacuum,&amp;quot; she says, her voice thick with emotion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s when, she says, she set off on a journey for acceptance within the Hijra community.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>And as is the protocol, the initiation into the fold required her to pursue a Hijra &amp;quot;guru&amp;quot; or a mentor, which she did.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>She also underwent a long, drawn-out feminization process.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The reward, she says, was priceless: liberation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>In contrast to Aher, opportunities for employment are extremely limited for most members of the Hijra community.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Many end up in prostitution and begging on streets, she says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>At a 45-minute drive from her office, a cramped, three-storied building along an unpaved road serves as a multi-purpose center for transgender and gay people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Volunteers walk up and down its dusty, unplastered stairs for an HIV counseling session on the first floor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>According to the Indian government, the country&amp;apost;s transgender community is seen as disproportionately vulnerable to the deadly infection despite its tiny size.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>A portion of a dimly lit room segregated by makeshift partitions is then used as a practice hall for the young Hijra members to hone their skills in dancing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>In today&amp;apost;s wired world, they don&amp;apost;t have to outsource professional instrument players.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Instead, it&amp;apost;s just a case of hooking a set of speakers into a mobile phone before setting off, dancing and lip-syncing to popular Bollywood songs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>But beneath the joyous mood, despair lurks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Many Hijras at this center are at least 10 years younger than Aher.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>They say they, too, faced tough social resistance to their choice to reject gender binarism.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Kyra Sharma, 27, says her family thought she was under the influence of black magic when she starting cross-dressing and applying cosmetic powder to her eyes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>She suppressed her true nature for a while.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>&amp;quot;I had to wear male outfits although I didn&amp;apost;t feel comfortable,&amp;quot; Sharma says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Her brother, she says, was more rigid than others.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>&amp;quot;There was a deadline for me to be home at 8 pm every day.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Life became difficult.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>But as transgender issues attracted more attention, she used the increased media focus to explain to her family she&amp;apost;s not the only one.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>&amp;quot;Eventually, there was some understanding.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>Thankfully, I don&amp;apost;t have to retreat into my biological sexual appearance now when I am home,&amp;quot; says Sharma, who aims to become a make-up artist.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>Equal rights for transgender and gay people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>Within a span of few months, India&amp;apost;s Supreme Court has come out with what activists say are conflicting judgments, on transgenders and Hijras on one hand, and the gay community on the other.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>This month, the justices granted Hijras the right to self-identify their gender in what has been hailed as a historic ruling to end centuries-old discrimination against the country&amp;apost;s transgender citizens.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>In December 2013 though, the same top court re-criminalized consensual homosexual relationships, reinstating a colonial-era law banning people from engaging in &amp;quot;carnal acts against the order of nature.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>Known as Section 377, that law was initially struck down in 2009 by a high court in New Delhi but its reinstatement has led to fears for gay people in the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="59">
          <content>Many of them came out in the open about their relationships when Section 377 was thrown out in 2009.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="60">
          <content>Image consultant Rishi Raj, who is gay, is now apprehensive.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="61">
          <content>&amp;quot;What happens to those teenagers and those young people who came out of the closet thinking that &amp;apost;my country is on my side, the court is on my side and my parents can&amp;apost;t throw me out&amp;apost;?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="62">
          <content>he asks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="63">
          <content>The anti-gay law and its revival, he feels, violate personal freedoms in a diverse democracy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="37">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="64">
          <content>&amp;quot;How can you take away something which is integrally my right -- what happens behind closed doors in my bedroom -- and judge me for that?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="65">
          <content>(To) call me a criminal for making love?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="66">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s just silly.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="38">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="67">
          <content>READ MORE: The transgender community: Legally invisible no more?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>