<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2815" link="http://cnn.com/2012/05/10/world/asia/china-philippines-dispute" date_published="2012-05-10 16:08:14" category="world" author="Stan Grant and Paul Armstrong, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Tensions over disputed island appear to ease</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">NEW: Manila says diplomats &amp;quot;are endeavoring to undertake a new diplomatic initiative&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">China and the Philippines have been involved in a standoff since April 10.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">Navy accuses Chinese boats of fishing illegally in waters off the Scarborough Shoal.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="7">Both countries claim the shoal, known by China as Huangyan, in the South China Sea.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-19 14:51:08" annotation_time="562.37665">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2, 3">A tense standoff between China and the Philippines that has been under way since April 10, when the Philippines Navy accused Chinese boats of fishing illegally off the Scarborough Shoal, appeared to ease somewhat Friday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">In Manila, Department of Foreign Affairs spokesman Raul Hernandez said that Philippine diplomats &amp;quot;are endeavoring to undertake a new diplomatic initiative, which we hope will help defuse the situation.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="4">Both countries claim the shoal, which China calls Huangyan Island.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A tense standoff between China and the Philippines that has been under way since April 10, when the Philippines Navy accused Chinese boats of fishing illegally off the Scarborough Shoal, appeared to ease somewhat Friday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>In Manila, Department of Foreign Affairs spokesman Raul Hernandez said that Philippine diplomats &amp;quot;are endeavoring to undertake a new diplomatic initiative, which we hope will help defuse the situation.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>China&amp;apost;s Foreign Ministry spokesman Hong Lei told reporters that China had noted the remarks as well as the action taken by the Philippine Foreign Ministry and noticed the resumption of diplomatic contact between the Philippine Foreign Ministry and the Chinese Embassy in Manila.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The diplomatic chafing that preceded those statements centered on the Scarborough Shoal, some 130 miles (200 kilometers) from the Philippine island of Luzon.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>A Chinese military newspaper had warned that the country&amp;apost;s armed forces would not allow anyone to challenge China&amp;apost;s sovereignty over the tiny island outcrop in the South China Sea.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Philippine navy sailors attempted to arrest the crew but were blocked by Chinese surveillance vessels deployed in the area.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Both countries claim the shoal, which China calls Huangyan Island.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Analysts believe the area is rich in mineral resources, natural gas and oil.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;We want to say that anyone&amp;apost;s attempt to take away China&amp;apost;s sovereignty over Huangyan Island will not be allowed by the Chinese government, people and armed forces,&amp;quot; said a report in the PLA Daily, the official newspaper of the People&amp;apost;s Liberation Army of China, said Xinhua, the state-run news agency.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;Don&amp;apost;t attempt to take away half an inch of China&amp;apost;s territory,&amp;quot; it warned.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>This week, an editorial in China&amp;apost;s state-run Global Times said the international community should not to be &amp;quot;completely surprised&amp;quot; if the standoff escalates into a military clash.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Peace will be a luxury if tensions continue to rise,&amp;quot; it added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The menacing tone appeared to echo the tone in comments from China&amp;apost;s Vice Foreign Minister Fu Ying following a meeting Monday with Alex Chua, Charge D&amp;apost;affaires of the Philippine Embassy in Beijing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Fu said China was not optimistic about the situation, and that China was prepared to respond to any escalation, Xinhua said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Fu added that Chinese vessels would remain on alert around Huangyan because of continuing provocation by the Philippine side, and that Chinese fishermen would be provided with &amp;quot;a positive environment to operate in their traditional fishing area.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Meanwhile, Chinese officials on Thursday accused Manila of inciting its people to take to the streets to demonstrate against China.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Planned protests prompted Beijing to advise its citizens there to remain indoors, and Chinese travel agencies suspended tours to the Philippines, state media reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Philippines has been repeatedly making strong-worded remarks over the Huangyan Island,&amp;quot; said Ministry of Foreign Affairs spokesman Hong Lei.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;China hopes the Philippines will not take any actions to magnify the dispute in a way that may affect the relationship between the two countries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;China remains unchanged in insisting on diplomatic dialogue to solve the Huangyan Island dispute.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>We urge the Philippine side to make a positive response, and move back on the right track.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Beijing and Manila were adamant their territorial arguments were justified.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;They both have claims,&amp;quot; said Stephanie Kleine-Ahlbrandt, the North East Asia project director and China adviser for the International Crisis Group.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;China goes back centuries, but the Philippines also says it has maps from the 18th century showing it belongs them.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The Philippine government, which says the islands are inside its 200-nautical mile exclusion zone, wants to resolve the dispute through international negotiation, Kleine-Ahlbrandt told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>But she said China rejects this as it has a long-standing distrust of Western-dominated mediators.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;There are a dozen ships in a standoff there right now,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;Both sides are really using this for all it is worth, whipping up nationalistic sentiment -- what is needed is something to de-escalate the situation.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
