<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2492" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/03/25/world/americas/rel-vatican-book/index.html" date_published="2012-03-25 04:25:39" category="world" author="Rafael Romo, Senior Latin American Affairs Editor" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>New book accuses Vatican of hiding cases of sexual abuse of minors</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Pope Benedict has been visiting Mexico.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">The visit comes as a book is released accusing the Vatican of hiding child sex abuse .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="20">Pope Benedict has not specifically addressed the accusations.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="20">However, he has spoken about the church&amp;apost;s role in protecting children.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-15 22:07:43" annotation_time="25.491">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1, 2">Leon, Mexico On the same day Pope Benedict addressed and blessed a group of 1,800 children in Guanajuato, Mexico, three Mexican authors released a book accusing the Vatican of hiding or ignoring cases of child sex abuse by Roman Catholic priests.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="3, 4">Pope Benedict has not specifically addressed the accusations, but in his message to the children at Plaza de la Paz, or Peace Square, in the colonial city of Guanajuato, he spoke about the church&amp;apost;s role in protecting children.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Leon, Mexico On the same day Pope Benedict addressed and blessed a group of 1,800 children in Guanajuato, Mexico, three Mexican authors released a book accusing the Vatican of hiding or ignoring cases of child sex abuse by Roman Catholic priests.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The book, &amp;quot;La Voluntad de no Saber&amp;quot; (Willing Not to be Aware), chronicles multiple cases of sexual abuse of minors committed by Marcial Maciel, a Mexican-born Roman Catholic priest who was influential at the Vatican.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Maciel, who died in January 2008 at age 87, was the founder and director of the Legion of Christ and the Regnum Christi movement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The book was authored by Jose Barba, a former seminarian who says he was the victim of sexual abuse by a priest.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Historian Fernando M. Gonzalez, a co-author, says the book is based on 212 documents leaked from the Vatican.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Alberto Athie, a former Catholic priest and whistle-blower, also contributed to the book.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>According to the book, the Vatican had knowledge of multiple cases of sexual abuse committed by Maciel decades ago, but church authorities chose to do nothing about it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Pope Benedict removed Maciel from active ministry in 2006 as a result of an investigation launched by his predecessor, Pope John Paul II.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Athie said the church either ignored or archived for years allegations of child sex abuse when he reported them during his years as a priest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;How could this have been possible?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Athie said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;How can one explain it?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>I had to face a reality that I never imagined, that I never expected and I never looked for.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Gonzalez said the Vatican documents provide solid proof of a policy geared towards hiding cases of abuse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;Anybody would have been able to perfectly learn about it by simply asking for the dossier (of sexual abuses cases).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Be it John Paul II, Paul VI, John XXIII, any of them should have figured out that a series of denunciations was being hidden, euphemized, protected, delayed, silenced and distorted,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Speaking to reporters Saturday, Cardinal Jose Francisco Robles, head of the Archdiocese of Guadalajara, defended the pope and the church.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;If there has ever been a pope who has faced (the sexual abuse problem) with realism and energy that&amp;apost;s Pope Benedict,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;Nobody can accuse him of being complicit or lacking will.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Pope Benedict has not specifically addressed the accusations, but in his message to the children at Plaza de la Paz, or Peace Square, in the colonial city of Guanajuato, he spoke about the church&amp;apost;s role in protecting children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;I raise my voice,&amp;quot; the pontiff said, &amp;quot;to invite everybody to protect and take care of children so that their smile never fades away, allowing them to live in peace and to look at the future with confidence.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Later, the 84-year-old pope on his first trip to Mexico, said, &amp;quot;You, my little friends, are not alone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>You can count on the help of Christ and his Church.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
