<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2822" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/02/20/world/asia/thailand-protests/index.html" date_published="2014-02-21 04:12:31" category="world" author="Kocha Olarn, Saima Mohsin and Jethro Mullen, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Thai Prime Minister denies corruption allegations over rice program</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="18">NEW: Rice farmers call off a planned protest at Bangkok&amp;apost;s main airport.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">&amp;quot;I have done nothing wrong,&amp;quot; Yingluck Shinawatra says in a statement.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">Thailand&amp;apost;s anti-corruption commission has called her to hear charges next week.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="1">It says she ignored warnings of possible corruption in a rice subsidy program.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 15:02:13" annotation_time="44.190002" mapping_time_divergence="11.047501">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="4">Bangkok, Thailand Thai Prime Minister Yingluck Shinawatra has denied allegations that she failed to heed warnings of possible corruption in a rice subsidy program whose recent problems have stoked anger among farmers in the country&amp;apost;s rural heartland.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">Thailand&amp;apost;s National Anti-Corruption Commission (NACC) said Tuesday that it was bringing charges against Yingluck over the program, which pledged to pay farmers well above the market rate for their rice but has run into financial problems.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;I wish to assure you that as I have served my duty with righteousness and contrary to the charges brought against me by the NACC, I have done nothing wrong,&amp;quot; Yingluck said in a statement Thursday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="1">The farmers said their planned protest wasn&amp;apost;t political -- unlike the anti-government demonstrators in central Bangkok, they say they don&amp;apost;t want to see the ouster of Yingluck.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Bangkok, Thailand Thai Prime Minister Yingluck Shinawatra has denied allegations that she failed to heed warnings of possible corruption in a rice subsidy program whose recent problems have stoked anger among farmers in the country&amp;apost;s rural heartland.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The controversy over the rice program has deepened the political crisis in which Thailand has been mired for months.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Thailand&amp;apost;s National Anti-Corruption Commission (NACC) said Tuesday that it was bringing charges against Yingluck over the program, which pledged to pay farmers well above the market rate for their rice but has run into financial problems.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The commission has summoned Yingluck, whose government is already under pressure from months-long protests in Bangkok, to appear February 27 to be notified of the charges.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;I wish to assure you that as I have served my duty with righteousness and contrary to the charges brought against me by the NACC, I have done nothing wrong,&amp;quot; Yingluck said in a statement Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The anti-corruption commission&amp;apost;s charges, which accuse Yingluck of ignoring warnings of corruption in the program, could eventually lead to the suspension of the Prime Minister from all political positions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;Though I may be charged in this criminal case and may have to give up my position in accordance to the wishes of those who want to topple my government, I will still lend my full cooperation and give necessary information to the NACC,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Yingluck insists that the rice subsidy program, introduced in 2011, has been successful and benefited farmers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>But critics says it has wasted large amounts of public funds trying to please rural voters, hurting exports and leaving the government with large stockpiles of rice it can&amp;apost;t sell without losing money.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The program has encountered intensified difficulties after an election earlier this month was disrupted by anti-government demonstrators and failed to deliver a conclusive result.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The situation has left Yingluck&amp;apost;s weakened caretaker government struggling to operate effectively and ensure payments are made to rice farmers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Angry farmers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Problems with the subsidy program have angered many farmers, normally an important component of Yingluck&amp;apost;s support base.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Groups of farmers have held protests in recent weeks after not being paid for their rice.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>About 3,000 farmers from central Thailand spent Thursday night camped out on the outskirts Bangkok after traveling on tractors, trailers and quad bikes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>They had threatened to take their protest to the city&amp;apost;s main airport, Suvarnabhumi, if they didn&amp;apost;t get paid what they&amp;apost;re owed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>But the leader of the group of farmers, Chada Thaiseth, said Friday that they would be heading home later in the day after the government informed them they would be paid early next week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The farmers said their planned protest wasn&amp;apost;t political -- unlike the anti-government demonstrators in central Bangkok, they say they don&amp;apost;t want to see the ouster of Yingluck.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>But they do want their money.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Long-running protests.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The tensions over the rice program come against the backdrop of the protests by groups affiliated with Yingluck&amp;apost;s political opponents.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Those demonstrations, calling for Yingluck to step down, have been taking place in central Bangkok since November and have been plagued by outbreaks of deadly violence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Earlier this week, police tried to clear demonstrators out some protest sites.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>But the efforts resulted in violent clashes that left five people dead, including one police officer, and dozens wounded.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Police have since suspended their attempts to seize the protest sites for the time being.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>And a court ruled Wednesday that the government can&amp;apost;t use force and weapons against peaceful unarmed protesters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The protest leaders say they want to rid the country of Yingluck and her wealthy brother, the deposed former Prime Minister Thaksin Shinawatra.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Thaksin, who lives in exile, faces a corruption conviction, which he says was politically motivated, if he returns to Thailand.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Political opponents say Yingluck, who convincingly won elections in 2011, is simply Thaksin&amp;apost;s puppet, an allegation she has repeatedly denied.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The protests were sparked in November by Yingluck&amp;apost;s government&amp;apost;s botched attempt to pass an amnesty bill that would have paved the way for her brother&amp;apost;s return to the political fray in earnest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The protesters say they want Yingluck&amp;apost;s government replaced by an unelected &amp;quot;people&amp;apost;s council,&amp;quot; which would oversee electoral and political changes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
