<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2229" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/17/world/africa/nigeria-violence/index.html?hpt=iaf_c2" date_published="2014-09-18 02:59:40" category="world" author="Greg Botelho and Aminu Abubakar, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Gunmen attack Nigerian college; 13 killed</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Police: 2 attack a lecture hall at the Federal College of Education campus in Kano.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5, 4">Police kill the attackers, recover their AK-47 rifles, undetonated explosives.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="9, 7">Boko Haram has been blamed for numerous attacks in the region, many targeting schools.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-28 15:54:13" annotation_time="71.863">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Kano state police commissioner Adelere Shinaboa said the attackers got on the Federal College of Education campus in Kano after opening fire at a checkpoint.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">The attack ended when responding police killed both assailants.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">Authorities recovered AK-47 rifles and unexploded bombs at the scene.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="3">While it was not immediately clear who was responsible, the northern city of Kano and the surrounding area has seen more than its fair share of bloodshed in recent years at the hands of Boko Haram.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="3">Schools have been a common target, befitting a group whose name Boko Haram translates in the local Hausa language as &amp;quot;Western education is forbidden.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Two gunmen set off explosives at a Nigerian college, then started shooting -- killing at least 13 people on another day of violence in the African nation, and yet another targeting students.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Kano state police commissioner Adelere Shinaboa said the attackers got on the Federal College of Education campus in Kano after opening fire at a checkpoint.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>About 3:30 p.m. (10:30 a.m. ET), they forced their way into a lecture hall, set off explosives and &amp;quot;began sporadic shooting,&amp;quot; according to police.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The attack ended when responding police killed both assailants.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Authorities recovered AK-47 rifles and unexploded bombs at the scene.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Thirteen others were also dead by then, police said, while 34 wounded were taken to a local hospital for treatment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>While it was not immediately clear who was responsible, the northern city of Kano and the surrounding area has seen more than its fair share of bloodshed in recent years at the hands of Boko Haram.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The Islamist extremist group is pushing to spread and enforce its strict interpretation of Sharia law over the territory it controls -- and showing no mercy on those who don&amp;apost;t subscribe to its beliefs and get in its way.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Schools have been a common target, befitting a group whose name Boko Haram translates in the local Hausa language as &amp;quot;Western education is forbidden.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The most well-known incident occurred in April, when militants abducted more than 230 schoolgirls from a school in the rural northeastern town of Chibok.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>On June 23, at least eight people were killed and 12 others wounded when a bomb exploded at a medical school in &amp;apost;s second-largest city.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>At least three people died later in the summer when a suspected suicide bomber targeted students at Kano State Polytechnic.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>After Wednesday&amp;apost;s attack, President Goodluck Jonathan&amp;apost;s office released a statement offering his sympathy for the loved ones of those killed &amp;quot;during the attack by terrorists.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;President Jonathan reassures the people of Kano and all Nigerians that the federal government continues to do all within its powers to further enhance the ability of police, armed forces and other security agencies to prosecute the war against terrorism to a successful conclusion and provide greater security of lives and property across the country,&amp;quot; the statement concluded.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Boko Haram, Nigeria engaged in yearslong fight.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Boko Haram was born 12 years ago, led by a charismatic cleric named Mohammed Yusuf who was pushing for a pure Islamic state.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Yusuf was killed by police in 2009, with Abubakar Shekau taking over the group and taking it in an even bloodier direction.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Much of this violence has been in Yobe, Kano, Bauchi, Borno and Kaduna states in the country&amp;apost;s north and east, though the capital of Abuja has also been hit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Boko Haram fighters have not only battled Nigerian troops for years, they&amp;apost;ve killed civilians in everything from bombings on crowded markets to attacks on otherwise peaceful villages.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Few have been spared in its brutal campaign.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The group has been blamed for killing Christians, government officials and Muslims, as well as the kidnapping of women and children.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>To give a sense of Boko Haram&amp;apost;s mentality, after the mass abduction of the Chibok schoolgirls, a man claiming to be Shekau promised in a video that he&amp;apost;d sell the girls &amp;quot;in the market.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Nigeria&amp;apost;s military has fought back, and garnered criticism in the process.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Rights groups, including Amnesty International, accuse government troops of committing war crimes and other abuses in their efforts to crack down on Boko Haram.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>