<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2368" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/09/07/world/asia/pakistan-girl-blasphemy/index.html?iref=allsearch" date_published="2012-09-07 08:57:24" category="world" author="Reza Sayah and Nasir Habib, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Judge in Pakistan grants bail to Christian girl accused of blasphemy</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="10">The girl has been in jail since last month after she was accused by a neighbor.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">The neighbor says she burned pages of the Quran, the Muslim holy book.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">A religious minorities alliance will pay her $10,000 bail fee.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="9">A Muslim cleric has been accused of planting evidence against her.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-09 11:02:21" annotation_time="96.426">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2">Islamabad, Pakistan A Pakistani judge on Friday granted bail to Rimsha, a 14-year-old Christian girl detained over accusations she burned pages of the Quran in a case that has heightened religious tensions in the volatile country.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="3">The All Pakistan Minorities Alliance, which represents religious minorities in the country, will pay the sum of roughly $10,000 to secure Rimsha&amp;apost;s release from jail, said Tahir Naveed Chaudhry, one of her lawyers and a leading member of the alliance.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="4">The case took a dramatic twist over the weekend when the police said a Muslim cleric had planted evidence in order to link her to the blasphemy allegations.The imam, Khalid Jadoon Chishti, will himself face blasphemy charges for tearing pages out of a Quran to use as evidence against the girl, police said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="1">Authorities arrested Rimsha last month after a neighbor accused her of burning pages containing texts from the Muslim holy book.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Islamabad, Pakistan A Pakistani judge on Friday granted bail to Rimsha, a 14-year-old Christian girl detained over accusations she burned pages of the Quran in a case that has heightened religious tensions in the volatile country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The All Pakistan Minorities Alliance, which represents religious minorities in the country, will pay the sum of roughly $10,000 to secure Rimsha&amp;apost;s release from jail, said Tahir Naveed Chaudhry, one of her lawyers and a leading member of the alliance.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Judge Muhammad Azam Khan said written details of his decision on the bail application would be released Saturday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>It was not immediately clear when Rimsha would be released.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The judge&amp;apost;s decision came after a lengthy argument Friday between Rimsha&amp;apost;s lawyer speaking in court, Pervez Khan, and lawyers representing the accuser.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Khan argued Rimsha should be granted bail because she was essentially an innocent girl with a lower than average IQ who was framed by a local cleric who planted evidence against her.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The accuser&amp;apost;s lawyer argued Rimsha committed blasphemy and should be punished no matter how old she is.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Rimsha&amp;apost;s family has left their home on the outskirts of Islamabad as a result of the tensions caused by the accusations against her.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The case took a dramatic twist over the weekend when the police said a Muslim cleric had planted evidence in order to link her to the blasphemy allegations.The imam, Khalid Jadoon Chishti, will himself face blasphemy charges for tearing pages out of a Quran to use as evidence against the girl, police said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Authorities arrested Rimsha last month after a neighbor accused her of burning pages containing texts from the Muslim holy book.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Rimsha had two shopping bags with her: one containing ashes and the other, the partially burned pages, police said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>She had gathered the paper as fuel for cooking, authorities said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Even though Rimsha&amp;apost;s lawyer said no one actually saw the girl burning the papers, the neighbor went to Chishti -- the neighborhood cleric -- with the bags for safekeeping as evidence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Chishti wasn&amp;apost;t certain that simply burning pages with texts from the Quran would be enough to convict Rimsha on blasphemy charges, the police said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>So, the imam added two pages from the holy book itself to the bag to bolster the case, according to the police.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Chishti was arrested on Saturday after three witnesses told a judge about the imam&amp;apost;s actions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>He was sent to jail for 14 days, accused of evidence tampering.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Chishti has denied the allegation, authorities said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
