<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2828" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/02/21/world/americas/profile-leopoldo-lopez" date_published="2014-02-21 15:56:22" category="world" author="Rafael Romo, Senior Latin American Affairs Editor" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>The face of Venezuela&amp;apost;s opposition</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="14">Leopoldo Lopez has long been a threat to socialists in Venezuela.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="15">In 2008, President Hugo Chavez&amp;apost;s government banned him from seeking public office .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">Lopez turned him in this week after the government accused of him terrorism, murder.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="36">Prosecutors formally charged him with arson and conspiracy; dropped more serious charges.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-03 11:26:55" annotation_time="75.048004">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">He went into hiding last week after the government of President Nicolas Maduro accused him of terrorism and murder and blamed him for inciting anti-government protests throughout Venezuela.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="1">Lopez, a fiery speaker and charismatic leader, has long been a threat to the socialists in power in Venezuela.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="2">Back in 2008, the government of then-President Hugo Chavez banned him from running for public office, accusing him of corruption and misuse of public funds.</sentence>
      <sentence id="36" ids_highlights="4">In a late-night hearing Wednesday, Venezuelan prosecutors formally charged Lopez with arson and conspiracy but dropped more serious charges of murder and terrorism.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>When Leopoldo Lopez turned himself in to authorities this week, he did it on his terms -- and not before climbing onto a statue of a Cuban national hero to deliver a passionate message to hordes of his supporters gathered at a square in the eastern Caracas neighborhood of Chacaito.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Lopez, 42, a former mayor and presidential candidate, had planned the event in advance, making extensive use of social media to summon his supporters to Brion Square.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>He went into hiding last week after the government of President Nicolas Maduro accused him of terrorism and murder and blamed him for inciting anti-government protests throughout Venezuela.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The protests have so far left several people dead and countless injured.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>After staying in a secret location for days, Lopez announced to Venezuelans, and the world, that after talking it over with his family, he would turn himself in.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>That announcement came via a YouTube video.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>At the square, Lopez used a megaphone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;The options I had were leave the country, and I will never leave Venezuela!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>he said to loud cheers and widespread applause as he stood on the statue of Jose Marti.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;The other option was to remain in hiding, but that option could&amp;apost;ve left doubt among some, including some who are here, and we don&amp;apost;t have anything to hide.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Later that night, his wife, Lilian Tintori, told CNN that Lopez was in good spirits behind bars.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;The last thing he told me was don&amp;apost;t forget why this is happening, don&amp;apost;t forget why he&amp;apost;s going to jail.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s asking for the liberation of political prisoners and students and an end to repression and violence,&amp;quot; Tintori said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Lopez, a fiery speaker and charismatic leader, has long been a threat to the socialists in power in Venezuela.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Back in 2008, the government of then-President Hugo Chavez banned him from running for public office, accusing him of corruption and misuse of public funds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Lopez countered that it was all political retribution and that he had nothing to hide.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>He took his case all the way to the Inter-American Court of Human Rights, where he was cleared three years later.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Political roots.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Politics runs in Lopez&amp;apost;s veins.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s the great-great-grandson of Venezuela&amp;apost;s first President and he also claims to be a descendant of Simon Bolivar, the South American liberator who, ironically, is revered by socialists in power, including Maduro.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Lopez was elected mayor of Chacao when he was only 29 years old and was reelected with 81% of the vote four years later.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>After being cleared of all corruption charges in September 2011, he launched his presidential candidacy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>In January of the following year, he chose to forge an alliance to unify the opposition, instead of running.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>He threw his support behind Henrique Capriles, another popular opposition leader, who narrowly lost to Chavez in October 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Lopez comes from a well-to-do family in Venezuela.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>He attended The Hun School of Princeton, a private boarding school, and graduated in 1989.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>He then attended Kenyon College in Ohio, where he graduated with honors, receiving a degree in sociology.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Lopez completed his education at Harvard University&amp;apost;s School of Government and earned a master&amp;apost;s degree.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Upon his return to Venezuela, he worked as an economic consultant and an economics professor at the Universidad Catolica Andres Bello, before jumping into politics in 1999.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>A magnetic personality.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>HLN Anchor Susan Hendricks, a close friend of Lopez&amp;apost;s in high school, says the opposition leader had the kind of personality that drew people to him.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;He was a hit with the ladies, but he wouldn&amp;apost;t even know (it),&amp;quot; Hendricks said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;He was very modest.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Hendricks says her heart broke when she learned he was in custody, but she is not surprised that he turned himself in.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;ve been tweeting and texting with people that are very good friends with him up until this day, have spoken with him about a month ago, and he said, &amp;apost;I will not leave Venezuela,&amp;apost; &amp;quot; Hendricks said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>In a late-night hearing Wednesday, Venezuelan prosecutors formally charged Lopez with arson and conspiracy but dropped more serious charges of murder and terrorism.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Conspiracy charges in Venezuela are punishable by up to 10 years in prison.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Now the good-looking, easygoing star student is in jail at the military complex known as Ramo Verde in the municipality of Los Teques, Miranda state.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Lopez&amp;apost;s future seems uncertain at best.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>But family members say they&amp;apost;re standing behind his decision to turn himself in.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;Manuela, my daughter, who&amp;apost;s 4 years old, asked me about it,&amp;quot; said Tintori, Lopez&amp;apost;s wife.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;I told her, &amp;apost;Manuela, he&amp;apost;s working for Venezuela.&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Because Leopoldo, wherever he is, in jail tonight, he&amp;apost;s going to be working for us and thinking of us.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>He&amp;apost;s going to keep on dreaming about a better Venezuela, as he always does.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>