<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2210" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/03/28/world/europe/uk-same-sex-marriage" date_published="2014-03-28 16:24:19" category="world" author="Marie-Louise Gumuchian and Erin McLaughlin, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Gay couples say &amp;apost;I do&amp;apost; in England and Wales</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="19">NEW: Church of England indicates it will no longer campaign against the issue.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">Historic law legalizing same-sex marriage comes into force in England and Wales.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="16">The legislation was approved in England and Wales last year, despite some opposition.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="27">Scotland gave green light to same-sex marriage last month.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-17 14:49:43" annotation_time="54.4525">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">After the clock struck midnight on Friday, the couple were among the first men marrying men and women marrying women in a range of ceremonies across England and Wales as a historic law legalizing same-sex marriage finally comes into force.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="3">In July, the legislation was approved to allow same-sex couples to officially marry in England and Wales.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="1">But in a shift in tone ahead of the weddings, Archbishop of Canterbury Justin Welby, leader of the world&amp;apost;s 80 million Anglicans, signaled the Church of England would mount no more resistance to gay marriage among churchgoers as Parliament had spoken.</sentence>
      <sentence id="27" ids_highlights="4">Scotland, which will hold a referendum on independence from Britain in September, last month became the latest to give the green light to gay marriage.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>London Andrew Wale is a writer and actor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>His partner, Neil Allard, is a guesthouse owner.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Together, they helped make history.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>After the clock struck midnight on Friday, the couple were among the first men marrying men and women marrying women in a range of ceremonies across England and Wales as a historic law legalizing same-sex marriage finally comes into force.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Wale and Allard have long known they wanted to commit officially and have waited five years for gay and lesbian couples to be able exchange vows legally in their home country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>That day has finally come.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;When we were born, it was illegal to be gay, let alone get married,&amp;quot; Wale, 49, said during last-minute preparations ahead of the wedding.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;I didn&amp;apost;t think about the possibility for most of my life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>It is only really recently that suddenly the option seemed to be on its way.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The marriage law was the final victory in a long battle that has secured the same age of consent as heterosexuals and the right to adopt.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>England and Wales are among 15 countries as well as parts of the United States and Mexico that allow same-sex marriage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The Netherlands was the first in 2001, and last year Brazil, Uruguay, New Zealand and France also joined the list.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;apost;They are equal&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Going through final details with the wedding&amp;apost;s organizers earlier this week, Wale and Allard said they were excited beyond measure.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The same-sex marriage bill was published by Britain&amp;apost;s coalition government in January last year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>In July, the legislation was approved to allow same-sex couples to officially marry in England and Wales.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Prime Minister David Cameron faced vocal opposition from some members of his Conservative Party.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The Church of England also objected, and was given an exemption from conducting same-sex ceremonies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>But in a shift in tone ahead of the weddings, Archbishop of Canterbury Justin Welby, leader of the world&amp;apost;s 80 million Anglicans, signaled the Church of England would mount no more resistance to gay marriage among churchgoers as Parliament had spoken.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think the church has reacted by fully accepting that it&amp;apost;s the law, and should react on Saturday by continuing to demonstrate in word and action, the love of Christ for every human being,&amp;quot; he told the Guardian newspaper.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>In an article on Pink News, an online magazine that focuses on the gay, lesbian, bisexual and transgendered community, Cameron said this weekend marked &amp;quot;an important moment for our country.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;It says we are a country that will continue to honor its proud traditions of respect, tolerance and equal worth,&amp;quot; he wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;It also sends a powerful message to young people growing up who are uncertain about their sexuality.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>It clearly says &amp;apost;you are equal&amp;apost; whether straight or gay.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>A rainbow flag flew above government offices in London in celebration.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Battles remain.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Scotland, which will hold a referendum on independence from Britain in September, last month became the latest to give the green light to gay marriage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The fourth British link, Northern Ireland, has stated it does not intend to introduce same-sex marriage legislation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Gay couples in Britain have spent years campaigning for gay rights.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Civil partnerships were introduced in England and Wales in 2005, effectively giving gay couples the same legal rights as heterosexuals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>But campaigners insisted that only full equality would do.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Unlike France, where legalizing same-sex marriage prompted fierce opposition from many social conservatives and the Catholic Church, there were no mass protests in Britain.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>But for all the joy the weddings will bring, discrimination and bigotry remain issues in Britain.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>In January, a local councilor was suspended from the anti-immigration UK Independence Party (UKIP) after blaming devastating floods on the legalization of gay marriage.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;We never really hold hands in the street, we&amp;apost;re quite careful about those kind of things -- simply because it was always quite a dangerous thing to do.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s still not entirely safe.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Our friends were beaten up six months ago for holding hands in the street,&amp;quot; Wale said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;Now I am feeling slightly more relaxed about that kind of thing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>I feel I have rights to be affectionate with this person that I am going to marry -- otherwise what does it represent?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>A recent Yougov poll in Britain showed that most people support the new change in law allowing same-sex couples to marry, but a third still think gay people are treated worse than straight people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Making a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>For Wale and Allard, the Royal Pavilion is where they met when they first started dating, so it was a fitting venue for the next step in their relationship.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>They put much thought into personalizing the ceremony, which was attended by friends from as far away as New York, and there was a cellist and songs sung by friends.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>The media also attended -- as with many of the first other same-sex weddings on Saturday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>The attention has been so huge that the local council has even received requests from ordinary Britons from across the country asking to attend Wale&amp;apost;s and Allard&amp;apost;s ceremony.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>For the couple, exchanging vows is not just about making a statement to each other, but to the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think it&amp;apost;s important to make those kind of statements, be visible, be proud of who you are and what you are in a world which seems to be stepping backwards in lots of different places,&amp;quot; Wale said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>&amp;quot;There are gay people struggling to be allowed to form relationships.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Many couples getting married say they hope to send out messages of support to other gays facing discriminatory laws in their own countries.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Last month, Ugandan President Yoweri Museveni signed into law a bill that toughens penalties against gay people and defines some homosexual acts as crimes punishable by life in prison.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>In Russia, a &amp;quot;propaganda&amp;quot; law bans even discussion of homosexuality anywhere that children might hear it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>&amp;quot;There are a lot of countries where it is illegal.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>We can show other countries that we are stepping forward,&amp;quot; Allard, 48, said, adding he felt lucky and privileged.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>Instead of gifts, the couple asked their guests to make a donation to Stonewall -- a charity that campaigns for equality and justice for lesbians, gay men and bisexuals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>&amp;quot;I want the wedding day to be a fully celebratory experience but at the same time, I don&amp;apost;t want to forget that it&amp;apost;s a relative freedom,&amp;quot; Wale said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>&amp;quot;We haven&amp;apost;t reached the end of the line.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>There is still a long way to go.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
