<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2218" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/03/26/world/meast/assad-family/index.html" date_published="2012-03-26 13:27:04" category="world" author="Nicole Dow, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Getting to know Syria&amp;apost;s first family</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Behind the scenes, the relatives of Syrian President Bashar al-Assad hold significant influence.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">Al-Assad has put some of them in important government positions.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="25">His brother Maher is a military leader often considered Syria&amp;apost;s second most powerful man.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="10">His nephew Rami Makhlouf is regarded as the richest person in the country.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-11 10:08:08" annotation_time="53.902332">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Syrian President Bashar al-Assad is the face of his country&amp;apost;s regime, but his family members are also believed to wield a powerful influence on issues facing the country.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;He has put members of his extended family ... in various parts of government and military security apparatus.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="4">Anisa&amp;apost;s nephew, Rami, is regarded as Syria&amp;apost;s wealthiest man, worth some $5 billion.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="3">Maher al-Assad is Bashar&amp;apost;s youngest brother and considered by many to be the second most powerful man in Syria.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Syrian President Bashar al-Assad is the face of his country&amp;apost;s regime, but his family members are also believed to wield a powerful influence on issues facing the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>In the past year, as pressure on the regime increased, al-Assad&amp;apost;s inner circle has become more of a family affair, said David Lesch, a professor of Middle East history and author of &amp;quot;The New Lion of Damascus: Bashar al-Assad and Modern Syria.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;That&amp;apost;s part of what Bashar has been doing ever since he came to power,&amp;quot; Lesch said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;He has put members of his extended family ... in various parts of government and military security apparatus.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>If the day came -- and it did come -- where there was a threat to the regime, he could count on the loyalty of those closest to him.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Here is a closer look at the al-Assad family, an authoritarian dynasty that has been in place for more than 40 years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The matriarchAnisa Makhlouf al-Assad.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Bashar&amp;apost;s mother, Anisa, was married to Hafez Assad, Bashar&amp;apost;s father and predecessor, who died in 2000.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The Makhlouf family gained wealth and status through Anisa&amp;apost;s marriage to Hafez, taking on contracts in key industries, among them telecommunications, banking and oil.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Anisa&amp;apost;s nephew, Rami, is regarded as Syria&amp;apost;s wealthiest man, worth some $5 billion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Anisa is said to be an influential figure within the regime despite keeping an extremely low profile over the years (she was not even seen during coverage of her husband&amp;apost;s funeral).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Syrian writer Ayman Abdel Nour, who went to college with Bashar, says there was distance between Bashar and his father and that Anisa was &amp;quot;the mother and father and mentor of the family.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The first ladyAsma Akhras al-Assad.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Asma al-Assad is the Syrian-British wife of the president.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Born to a cardiologist father and a diplomat mother, she grew up in London, where she was known by friends and classmates as &amp;quot;Emma.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Asma graduated from King&amp;apost;s College in London with a degree in computer science.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>She worked for JP Morgan as an investment banker before marrying Bashar in 2000, six months after he became president.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Her influence remains unclear.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Andrew Tabler, a Syria expert who knew Asma al-Assad and worked with her told CNN: &amp;quot;No one can say what&amp;apost;s happening behind closed palace doors, but I doubt she feels she has any control or would ultimately have much influence over what her husband is doing.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The last major profile of her was by Vogue in spring 2011; however, a cache of emails recently leaked to CNN shed deep light on the first lady&amp;apost;s personal life over the past year, amidst the civilian uprisings taking place in her country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>One e-mail features an apparent request to a friend for the latest &amp;quot;Harry Potter&amp;quot; DVD.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Another series of e-mails features exchanges about shopping for high-end jewelry, furniture and art.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>(More about Asma al-Assad).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The younger brotherMaher al-Assad.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Maher al-Assad is Bashar&amp;apost;s youngest brother and considered by many to be the second most powerful man in Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>He oversees two of the Syrian army&amp;apost;s strongest units: the Republican Guard, which protects the regime in Damascus, and the elite Fourth Armored Division, which suppressed the early uprisings in the southern part of Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>A hard-liner with a reputation for being cruel and moody, according to television channel France 24, Maher allegedly shot his brother-in-law, Asef Shawkat, in the stomach during an argument in the presidential palace in 1999.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>A New York Times profile on Maher reports that many Syrians who know him say he has a sharp intellect as well as a harsh and ruthless nature.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>He has apparently attempted to restructure Syria&amp;apost;s military and intelligence so that both entities reflect his persona.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The older sisterBushra al-Assad.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Bushra al-Assad is the eldest of al-Assad&amp;apost;s five siblings.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>A pharmacist by training, she is said to be very intelligent.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>She also had a close relationship with her late father.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Described by one insider as &amp;quot;ruthless,&amp;quot; Bushra, like her mother, brandishes influence in the Assad inner sanctum and stays out of the public eye.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>A profile of Bushra in Mideast Monitor said although &amp;quot;she shuns the spotlight, her behind-the-scenes political influence has been decisive at times.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>There have been reports of tension between Bushra and her sister-in-law Asma.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Bushra is said to disapprove of Asma&amp;apost;s public appearances in Syrian society, according to French newspaper Le Monde.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>In 1995, Bushra married Asef Shawkat, a military officer 10 years older and a divorced father of five.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Despite her family&amp;apost;s staunch objections to the union -- her brother Maher apparently had Asef imprisoned on several occasions to keep them apart -- they eventually accepted Asef into their circle, where he was appointed head of the army&amp;apost;s intelligence services for a time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Bushra has four children, all named after members of her family: Bushra, Maher, Basel and Anisa.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>The brother-in-lawAsef Shawkat.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Shawkat was once in charge of the army&amp;apost;s intelligence services, eventually becoming deputy chief-of-staff of Syria&amp;apost;s armed forces.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>He is said to be one of Bashar&amp;apost;s close allies, although there are reports that he was demoted after Hezbollah military commander Imad Mugniyeh was assassinated in Damascus in 2008.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>According to Mideast Monitor, Shawkat and Maher were once locked in a power struggle over who had the ear of the president.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Bushra is said to have interceded, easing tensions and resolving the dispute.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>[Update: July 18, 2012] Shawkat was killed in a blast at a national security building in Damascus during a meeting of ministers and security officials, state TV reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>The lost brothersBasel al-AssadMajd al-Assad.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Not much is known about the president&amp;apost;s brother Majd, who in 2009 died from &amp;quot;a long illness&amp;quot; at age 43, according to Syria&amp;apost;s official news agency SANA.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Majd, like many other members of his family, remained out of the public eye.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Basel al-Assad was 31 years old when he died in a 1994 car accident, crashing his Mercedes on a city highway in Damascus.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>Known to have been charismatic and outgoing, Basel was older than Bashar and groomed to be his father&amp;apost;s heir apparent, according to The Guardian.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Upon news of his brother&amp;apost;s death, Bashar was brought back to Damascus to undergo military training to eventually take his brother&amp;apost;s place as successor to their father&amp;apost;s role as president.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>At the time, Bashar was studying ophthalmology in London.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
