<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2729" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/10/28/world/australia-new-species-found/index.html" date_published="2013-10-28 14:35:02" category="world" author="Eliott C. McLaughlin, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Scientists discover lizard, frog species in Australian rainforest</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Scientists say the three new species have been isolated in forest for millions of years.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Discovered species include leaf-tail gecko, golden skink and a boulder-dwelling frog.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="14">Herpetologist: Gecko is &amp;quot;strangest new species to come across my desk in 26 years&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="30, 29, 1">Finding species in &amp;quot;lost world&amp;quot; of Cape Melville is &amp;quot;discovery of a lifetime,&amp;quot; scientist says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 17:26:48" annotation_time="80.69" mapping_time_divergence="20.1725">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="4">Scientists have found what they&amp;apost;re describing as a &amp;quot;lost world&amp;quot; on the northern tip of Queensland, Australia, hosting at least three previously undocumented species, including a frog that makes love in the rain.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1, 2">The discovered species, which also include a leaf-tail gecko and a golden skink, have been isolated in a remote mountain range on Cape York Peninsula for millions of years, according to James Cook University.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;The Cape Melville Leaf-Tailed Gecko is the strangest new species to come across my desk in 26 years working as a professional herpetologist.</sentence>
      <sentence id="29" ids_highlights="4">&amp;quot;The top of Cape Melville is a lost world.</sentence>
      <sentence id="30" ids_highlights="4">Finding these new species up there is the discovery of a lifetime,&amp;quot; Hoskin said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Scientists have found what they&amp;apost;re describing as a &amp;quot;lost world&amp;quot; on the northern tip of Queensland, Australia, hosting at least three previously undocumented species, including a frog that makes love in the rain.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The discovered species, which also include a leaf-tail gecko and a golden skink, have been isolated in a remote mountain range on Cape York Peninsula for millions of years, according to James Cook University.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The joint expedition between the university and National Geographic in March led James Cook&amp;apost;s Conrad Hoskin and Harvard University researcher Tim Laman, a National Geographic photographer, to the rugged range in northeast Australia&amp;apost;s Cape Melville, where millions of black granite boulders as big as houses and cars are piled hundreds of meters high.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Scientists have previously surveyed the base of the cape mountains, but the hot, dry, boulder-strewn rainforest on the plateau atop them is largely unexplored.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>A helicopter took Hoskin, Laman and a National Geographic film crew to the uplands.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;Finding three new, obviously distinct vertebrates would be surprising enough in somewhere poorly explored like New Guinea, let alone in Australia, a country we think we&amp;apost;ve explored pretty well,&amp;quot; Hoskin said in a statement from the university.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The scientists found a &amp;quot;host of other interesting species&amp;quot; that may also be new to science, but the three vertebrates, which are described as highly distinct, will be documented in this month&amp;apost;s issue of Zootaxa, a peer-reviewed journal for animal taxonomists.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Hoskin said the highlight of the expedition was the Cape Melville Leaf-Tailed Gecko, a &amp;quot;primitive-looking&amp;quot; lizard that is considered a relic from the days when the rainforest was more widespread in Australia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>It can grow up to 20 centimeters (almost 8 inches) long.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The gecko is a night hunter and hides in the boulders during the day.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>At night, the highly camouflaged critter sits motionless, head down, awaiting passing insects and spiders on rocks and in trees.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Its big eyes and long, slender body and limbs are likely &amp;quot;adaptations to life in the dimly lit boulder fields,&amp;quot; the release said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Hoskin, who said he knew it was a new species as soon as he saw it, named it Saltuarius eximius, meaning exceptional or exquisite, in reference to its distinct appearance.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Cape Melville Leaf-Tailed Gecko is the strangest new species to come across my desk in 26 years working as a professional herpetologist.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>I doubt that another new reptile of this size and distinctiveness will be found in a hurry, if ever again, in Australia,&amp;quot; said Patrick Couper, curator of reptiles and frogs at Queensland Museum.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The Cape Melville Shade Skink is also a lanky fellow, but unlike its gecko neighbor, it can be found hunting during the day, hopping across mossy boulders in search of insects.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>It has a golden hue and is isolated to the plateau rainforest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>It has been dubbed Saproscincus saltus.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Saltus means leaping, according to the university&amp;apost;s news release.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Also discovered was the Blotched Boulder Frog, which is found only in the boulder field at Cape Melville.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Its species name, Cophixalus petrophilus, means rock-loving.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;During the dry season the frog lives deep down in the labyrinth of the boulder field where conditions are cool and moist.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>In the summer wet season the frog emerges on the surface rocks to feed and breed in the rain,&amp;quot; the news release says, adding that the frog only comes to the surface when it&amp;apost;s raining.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>There are no nearby bodies of water, so the frog reproduces by laying its eggs in the moist rock cracks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The tadpoles develop within the eggs, which the male frog guards until the froglets hatch.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;These species are restricted to the upland rainforest and boulder fields of Cape Melville.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>They&amp;apost;ve been isolated there for millennia, evolving into distinct species in their unique rocky environment,&amp;quot; Hoskin said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Given the discoveries, there will likely be more expeditions -- and more secrets uncovered -- on Cape Melville in the future.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;The top of Cape Melville is a lost world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Finding these new species up there is the discovery of a lifetime,&amp;quot; Hoskin said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m still amazed and buzzing from it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Follow Eliott C. McLaughlin on Twitter: @CNNWriters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
