<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2024" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/01/03/world/africa/nigeria-fuel-protest/index.html" date_published="2012-01-03 20:32:08" category="world" author="Stephanie Busari, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>&amp;apost;Searing anger&amp;apost; as Nigerians protest fuel price increase</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Thousands of Nigerians protested Tuesday across the country .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Demonstrations over the removal of fuel subsidies that saw price of petrol double.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="24">Nigeria is one of Africa&amp;apost;s largest oil and gas producers .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-25 09:27:26" annotation_time="45.82367" mapping_time_divergence="15.274556">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1, 2">Car tires were set on fire and gas stations blockaded as hundreds of Nigerians took to the streets to protest the removal of fuel subsidies that saw the price of petrol more than double virtually overnight.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="3">Despite being one of Africa&amp;apost;s largest oil producers, Nigeria has no functioning refineries and has to import fuel.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Car tires were set on fire and gas stations blockaded as hundreds of Nigerians took to the streets to protest the removal of fuel subsidies that saw the price of petrol more than double virtually overnight.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Angry Nigerians chanted anti-government slogans and brandished placards in a largely peaceful protest Tuesday against the removal of government subsidies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>In what has been described as a &amp;quot;callous New Year gift,&amp;quot; the government ended its fuel subsidy Sunday, bringing the cost of a liter of gasoline from 65 naira (40¢) to 141 naira, (86¢).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Nigerians say this is the last straw in a country rich with oil reserves but with poor infrastructure and impoverished citizens who live on less than $2 a day, according to U.N. figures.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Shade Ladipo, 29, was one of those who marched for hours in Lagos, the country&amp;apost;s economic capital, where some major districts were shut down by protestors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;The atmosphere has been charged.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>We were stopping cars from moving, we told them to park their cars and join us.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Many people parked their cars and joined in.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Even the police have been calm and not hostile to us.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>They know that this rise affects everyone, even them.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Ladipo added that she and many Nigerians accepted the need for a price rise but accused the government of bringing the increase abruptly and without prior warning it would happen on January 1.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Nothing has been put in place for this,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;We still don&amp;apost;t have light.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The roads are terrible.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>It was already hard to live in Nigeria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>This will make life even worse.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>We are angry and we&amp;apost;re not going to take this,&amp;quot; she added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Ladipo, who runs a travel and tourism company, complained: &amp;quot;The government says that Nigeria is broke and the subsidies are needed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>But this rise will not affect them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>They still have their allowances and huge salaries.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Among the demonstrators were musician Seun Anikulapo-Kuti, son of afrobeat innovator Fela Kuti, and activists Femi Falana and Ganiyat Faweyinmi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Nigerian President Goodluck Jonathan&amp;apost;s government says it believes the removal of fuel subsidies would have a positive impact on the country&amp;apost;s economy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>They say money saved will be used to invest elsewhere such as refineries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Despite being one of Africa&amp;apost;s largest oil producers, Nigeria has no functioning refineries and has to import fuel.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Presidential spokesman Reuben Abati told CNN: &amp;quot;The fuel subsidy debate has been going on for two months and the president consulted widely during this period to explain the political and economic issues.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s natural for certain people to disagree.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>In a democracy that right to differ and to express opinion is sacrosanct.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>He added: &amp;quot;The protests have been largely peaceful and we have had no reports of violence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The president has no problems with people protesting as long as they do it in a civil way. &amp;quot;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Unrelated to the fuel subsidy issue but also causing problems for Jonathan&amp;apost;s administration is sectarian violence in northern Nigeria where, in recent months, states of emergency have been declared.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>But Nigerians protesting the new year&amp;apost;s price hikes say they no longer trust the government to fulfill its promises of investment and regeneration.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Chude Jideonwo, a youth activist, said: &amp;quot;There is a searing anger across the nation - and it&amp;apost;s not just about the fuel subsidy: marching with the hundreds today, this much was clear - Nigerians deeply distrust this government and it has squandered the goodwill it had barely a year ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;The demand is clear -- return to the old price.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>You cannot ask us to sacrifice while you run a government obese with waste and corruption.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>I don&amp;apost;t think Nigerians will back down from this, and we shouldn&amp;apost;t.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>The protests were organized by the country&amp;apost;s two labor unions, who released a joint statement Monday saying: &amp;quot;This New Year &amp;apost;gift&amp;apost; by the presidency is callous, insensitive and is intended to cause anarchy in the country.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>There were also protests reported elsewhere in the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>CNN iReporter Boma Tai, 24, narrated the scene of protests in the streets of Ibadan, Nigeria, as he participated in a demonstration over fuel price increases.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;At the center of the displeasure are other issues as massive unemployment, the shut down of the Nigerian government owned universities by the ASSU strike and lack of stable electric power.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>They are saying &amp;apost;No to subsidy removal,&amp;apost;&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>The storm of protest was not limited to the rallies on the ground.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Many Nigerians vented their anger on Twitter, including music star BankyW, who wrote: &amp;quot;Its not just about fuel subsidy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Its about electricity, healthcare, security, education, corruption &amp;amp; the quality of life 4 every Nigerian.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>While @samsonnnamdi tweeted: &amp;quot;this govt is wicked,how can you remove subsidy when the roads are not good ,refineries are not working,traffic jam everywhere.That is wickedness in high places.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
