<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2130" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/07/14/world/europe/uk-church-women-bishops/index.html?hpt=hp_t3" date_published="2014-07-14 16:09:33" category="world" author="Susannah Cullinane, CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Church of England to allow female bishops</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="18">NEW: Anglican priest says she thinks the decision is &amp;quot;wonderful news&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Church of England leaders have voted to allow women to become bishops.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">It required a two-thirds majority by all three voting bodies -- the bishops, clergy and laity.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="4">The church said the first female bishop could be appointed by the end of the year.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-26 18:53:10" annotation_time="234.10966">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2">Church of England leaders have voted to allow women to become bishops, the church announced Monday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="3">The measure required a two-thirds majority in all three voting bodies of the church: the House of Bishops, the House of Clergy and the House of Laity.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="4">The first female bishop could be appointed by the end of the year, the church said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;Yes but you CAN,&amp;quot; Hitchiner tweeted, who earlier called the decision &amp;quot;wonderful news.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Church of England leaders have voted to allow women to become bishops, the church announced Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The measure required a two-thirds majority in all three voting bodies of the church: the House of Bishops, the House of Clergy and the House of Laity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The legislation was passed at the church&amp;apost;s General Synod, the three-times-a-year meeting that sets policies for the church, which is being held in the city of York.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The first female bishop could be appointed by the end of the year, the church said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The head of the Church of England, Archbishop of Canterbury Justin Welby, said he was &amp;quot;delighted&amp;quot; with the result.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;Today marks the start of a great adventure of seeking mutual flourishing while still, in some cases disagreeing,&amp;quot; he said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;The challenge for us will be for the church to model good disagreement and to continue to demonstrate love for those who disagree on theological grounds.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The measure is subject to approval by Britain&amp;apost;s Parliament.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>This is seen as a legal formality.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The Church of England first began ordaining women as priests in 1994 and has been debating whether they should become bishops since 2005.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;To those who ask &amp;apost;What took you so long?&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>my answer is that every decision has a cost and there will be those within our body who will be hurting as a result of this decision, the archbishop of York, John Sentamu, said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;Our answer to the hurting should not be &amp;apost;Get over it&amp;apost; but rather &amp;apost;We will not let go until you have blessed us.&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;We move slowly because we move together.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>But in moving together we achieve not only what is just but also model what is right.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The Rev. Sally Hitchiner tweeted that she told her 8-year-old niece that she can be a bishop now.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The niece said she didn&amp;apost;t want to be a bishop.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Yes but you CAN,&amp;quot; Hitchiner tweeted, who earlier called the decision &amp;quot;wonderful news.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Two lay members of the church told the BBC that they were upset with the vote.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Lorna Ashworth told the network there is &amp;quot;not going to be a smooth road ahead,&amp;quot; and Susie Leafe said the decision fails 25% of those in the church who don&amp;apost;t believe women should be bishops.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Previous votes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>At its General Synod meeting in 2012, draft legislation that would have allowed women to become bishops failed by six votes to get a two-thirds majority in the House of Laity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>In 2010, the church&amp;apost;s governing body narrowly rejected a measure, aimed at satisfying conservatives, that would have allowed parishes that opposed women bishops to have an additional male bishop.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The Church of England is the largest church of the Anglican Communion, with more than 26 million baptized members.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The communion represents more than 85 million people in 165 countries, including the U.S. Episcopal Church.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The Anglican Communion News Service lists church districts that already have serving women bishops as New Zealand and Polynesia, Australia, Canada, The Episcopal Church, Cuba, Southern Africa, Ireland and South India.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The Church of England broke from the Catholic church in the 16th century during the Reformation, which saw the establishment of Protestant churches.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>On its website, the Church of England says it &amp;quot;consciously retained a large amount of continuity with the Church of the Patristic and Medieval periods in terms of its use of the catholic creeds, its pattern of ministry, its buildings and aspects of its liturgy, but which also embodied Protestant insights in its theology and in the overall shape of its liturgical practice.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
