<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2401" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/08/31/world/africa/madagascar-deforestation-baobab/index.html" date_published="2012-08-31 16:43:21" category="world" author="Errol Barnett and Teo Kermeliotis, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Madagascar&amp;apost;s bid to save its majestic baobab trees</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Six out of the eight species of the baobab tree are endemic to Madagascar.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">The island is home to a vast array of animal and plant life.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="14">Madagascar has lost 90% of its forest to deforestation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="18">The government is trying to protect the forests by marking areas as national parks.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-11 18:08:53" annotation_time="20.917665">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Six out of the eight species of the long-lived tree are endemic to Madagascar, the island country located in the Indian Ocean off the southeastern coast of Africa.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">The stunning country is home to a rich ecosystem that boasts an incredible mosaic of animal and plant life evolved for tens of millions of years in complete isolation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="3">Largely dependent on the island&amp;apost;s natural resources, many rural communities in Madagascar have to make ends meet by exploiting the land that surrounds them -- the country is estimated to have lost 90% of its forest to deforestation over the years.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="4">The country has launched several conservation and reforestation projects and has also marked many regions in the country as national parks, attracting ecotourists from across the world.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Antananarivo, Madagascar With their unique shape and imposing stature, the majestic baobab trees have been an icon of Madagascar&amp;apost;s landscape for centuries, unmovable symbols of the tropical island&amp;apost;s luscious scenery.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Six out of the eight species of the long-lived tree are endemic to Madagascar, the island country located in the Indian Ocean off the southeastern coast of Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The stunning country is home to a rich ecosystem that boasts an incredible mosaic of animal and plant life evolved for tens of millions of years in complete isolation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>As a result 90% of Madagascar&amp;apost;s wildlife exists nowhere else on the planet.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>In the midst of it all, the mighty baobab has stood tall for generations, its barrel-like trunk reaching a height of 18 meters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Often described as &amp;quot;the upside down tree&amp;quot; due to its unusual shape -- the tree&amp;apost;s branches look like roots sticking up in the air -- the baobab has sparked many legends throughout the centuries.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>An ancient myth goes that when the gods planted the trees, they kept walking away so they placed them upside down.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Read related: Madagascar&amp;apost;s &amp;apost;lemur lady&amp;apost; on saving endangered animals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Communities in Madagascar, one of the poorest countries in the world, have long been benefiting from the deciduous trees -- their fruits are edible, their leaves are used for medicinal purposes, while their large trunks are often excavated to serve as shelters or store water during dry periods.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;There are many interactions with the life of community living around forest,&amp;quot; explains botanist Jimmy Razafitsalama.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;First, they use the bark for the construction of their house and then they use leaves as medicinal plants.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>They eat also the fruit because the fruit are very rich in vitamins and don&amp;apost;t forget also it&amp;apost;s one of the attraction for tourists to come here.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>But while tourism proceeds can generate income for people often living on less than $2 a day, many other human activities are posing a serious threat to the baobab trees and the island&amp;apost;s one-of-a-kind ecosystem.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Largely dependent on the island&amp;apost;s natural resources, many rural communities in Madagascar have to make ends meet by exploiting the land that surrounds them -- the country is estimated to have lost 90% of its forest to deforestation over the years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Environmentalists say that activities like slash-and-burn agriculture -- where an area of forest is cut and burned to create fields -- logging for timber and fuelwood and charcoal production are all destroying the island&amp;apost;s beautiful rainforests and their endemic biodiversity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;They cut the trees down to clear the land for agriculture or for grazing their animals,&amp;quot; says Razafitsalama, who has moved to the island&amp;apost;s northernmost part near the city of Diego Suarez to teach locals about biodiversity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>In recent years, authorities in Madagascar have taken up a series of initiatives to save its precious forests.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The country has launched several conservation and reforestation projects and has also marked many regions in the country as national parks, attracting ecotourists from across the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Razafitsalama says that more needs to be done to safeguard the future of the baobab trees and the vast array of unique species living in Madagascar&amp;apost;s forests.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;Now the government they want to increase the surface of protected areas.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>They made a big effort but right now I see for baobab it&amp;apost;s not yet representative,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;A good example is this forest in front of us -- it is not protected but this has the highest concentration of population of this endemic species.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Unless more action is taken and behaviors change, Madagascar, one of the world&amp;apost;s true biodiversity hotspots, will risk losing more of its forests, putting in danger the survival of its unique species.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
