<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2706" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/08/world/europe/royal-spare-heir/index.html?hpt=ieu_mid" date_published="2014-09-08 17:31:22" category="world" author="Kate Williams, CNN royal commentator" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Royal baby: Why does the &amp;apost;spare heir&amp;apost; matter?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="18, 1">The Duchess of Cambridge is expecting her second child, Buckingham Palace announced.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">&amp;quot;Throughout history, the only way to secure a throne has been with a phalanx of children&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="7">Aristocratic wives were once told they needed to provide an &amp;quot;heir and a spare&amp;quot; at least.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="14">The second child has a vital role in carrying out royal duties and obligations.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-02 10:56:58" annotation_time="23.855667" mapping_time_divergence="5.963917">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">The Duchess of Cambridge&amp;apost;s announcement today puts an end to months of pregnancy speculation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">Throughout history, the only way to secure a throne has been with a phalanx of children -- nine for Victoria, thirteen for George III.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="3">Aristocratic wives were once told they needed to provide an &amp;quot;heir and a spare&amp;quot; at least -- and the same has always been true for the royals.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="4">Now we don&amp;apost;t expect the second child will come to rule, but he or she still has a vital role in carrying out royal duties and obligations.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="1">If the Duchess of Cambridge&amp;apost;s baby is a girl, she will be the next in line to the throne after her brother -- even if more sons follow.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The Duchess of Cambridge&amp;apost;s announcement today puts an end to months of pregnancy speculation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Number Two is on the way and with him or her comes a huge boost for the Royal Family.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The level of excitement won&amp;apost;t quite be the same as it was for Prince George -- but we can still expect great interest across the world and massive baby fever early next year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>But why does the &amp;quot;spare heir&amp;quot; matter?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>One child is never enough for a monarch.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Throughout history, the only way to secure a throne has been with a phalanx of children -- nine for Victoria, thirteen for George III.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Aristocratic wives were once told they needed to provide an &amp;quot;heir and a spare&amp;quot; at least -- and the same has always been true for the royals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Once, this was because high mortality rates meant that the more children the better -- for the first born son didn&amp;apost;t always come to be King.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Henry VIII was the second son, who became heir and ascended at 17 after the untimely death of his brother, Arthur.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>George V was also the second son -- and also became heir after his elder brother died young from influenza.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Both men married the women who&amp;apost;d been betrothed to their brothers -- Henry made Catherine of Aragon his queen and George wed Mary of Teck.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The current Queen&amp;apost;s father, George VI, was the second son of George V, and was never meant to be king.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>But when his elder brother, Edward VIII, gave up the throne in 1936 to marry American divorcee Wallace Simpson, the heir became the king -- much to his own surprise.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Now we don&amp;apost;t expect the second child will come to rule, but he or she still has a vital role in carrying out royal duties and obligations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The Royal Family - or &amp;quot;Firm,&amp;quot; as the current royals like to call it -- needs plenty of employees for the huge number of royal visits and receptions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>What is different in 2014 is that the heir and the spare heir can be female.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>After the law changed last year to allow women the same rights of accession to the throne as men, females are no longer pushed to the back of the line.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>If the Duchess of Cambridge&amp;apost;s baby is a girl, she will be the next in line to the throne after her brother -- even if more sons follow.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>This baby will be a huge boost to the Royal Family - and &amp;quot;Brand Windsor&amp;quot; across the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>But what will his or her life be like?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The role of the second-in-line is not easy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>For Princess Margaret being younger sister of the heir was no picnic -- she had all of the downsides of being royal, such as lack of privacy and restrictions on freedom, without the great compensation of becoming Queen.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Unable to find a role for herself or marry the man she loved, the Princess sank into depression and ill health.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Prince Harry, too, has been clear on how hard it is to find an occupation -- he was eager to fight on the frontline in Afghanistan but was accidentally exposed by Australian media and had to return.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s also been hard for him to find a woman who will take on the royal role.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;Royals are only private in the womb,&amp;quot; said the governess of Elizabeth II.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>We are fascinated by royal children -- most of all by the second or the &amp;quot;spare heir.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>What will be even more difficult for this second child is that he or she will grow up in a world of camera phones and social media, where private photos are gold dust and royals are the biggest celebrity big game of all.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The life of the second child can be exciting and dynamic -- but most of all it is one of extreme fame -- and a lot of responsibility.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
