<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2668" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/02/02/world/meast/yemen-unrest" date_published="2014-02-02 16:32:48" category="world" author="Hakim Almasmari, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Rebels overrun tribal stronghold in Yemen</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Shiite militants have been battling Sunni tribesmen in northern Yemen.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Hashid tribal stronghold was overrun on Sunday morning, tribal leaders say.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="9">At least 42 people died and more than a dozen were injured in fighting on Friday, officials say.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="12">Cease-fire negotiations have already been under way.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 16:18:56" annotation_time="16.002">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1, 2"> Shiite Houthi rebels have overrun a tribal stronghold in northern Yemen after weeks of fighting that has left scores dead, tribal leaders said Sunday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="3">On Friday, at least 42 people were killed and more than a dozen injured in clashes between Houthi militants and Hashid fighters in Amran province, which is about 30 miles north of the capital, Sanaa, and seen as a linchpin to controlling the region, officials said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="4">Cease-fire negotiations were already under way to put an end to the fighting that has plagued Yemen since late last year, spurred in part by a power vacuum left by the departure of former President Ali Abdullah Saleh.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Shiite Houthi rebels have overrun a tribal stronghold in northern Yemen after weeks of fighting that has left scores dead, tribal leaders said Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Leaders of the Sunni Hashid tribe said Houthi fighters managed to break through their defense lines in the al-Khamri district in Amran.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;Al-Ahmar tribesmen were surrounded by hundreds of Houthi militants who attacked using heavy artillery for seven continuous hours starting last night,&amp;quot; said Ali Al-Suraimi, a leader within the Hashid tribe, referring to Hashid tribal leaders.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;Hundreds of additional Houthi fighters reinforced those attacking the al-Ahmar fighters.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>They easily outnumbered the al-Ahmar tribesmen and this was key for the Houthis&amp;apost; success on the ground.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>He said the Hashid tribesmen had evacuated their stronghold on Sunday morning.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Hashid tribes are expected to regroup, and this is far from over,&amp;quot; Al-Suraimi said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Another Hashid tribal leader echoed this.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>On Friday, at least 42 people were killed and more than a dozen injured in clashes between Houthi militants and Hashid fighters in Amran province, which is about 30 miles north of the capital, Sanaa, and seen as a linchpin to controlling the region, officials said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>President Abdurabu Hadi has dispatched a committee to discuss a cease-fire with Houthi leaders and persuade them to leave the area, according to state-run media.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Cease-fire talks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Cease-fire negotiations were already under way to put an end to the fighting that has plagued Yemen since late last year, spurred in part by a power vacuum left by the departure of former President Ali Abdullah Saleh.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Tensions between the rebel Houthis and the Hashid tribe, which includes Sunni tribesmen and conservative Islamic Salafists, began to rise last October, when the Houthis blamed the Hashid for standing behind the killing of one of their members.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>At least 240 people from both sides have been killed since the beginning of January in the fighting.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Hundreds of civilians have evacuated their towns in Amran.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Yemen is home to al Qaeda in the Arabian Peninsula, believed by many analysts to be the most dangerous affiliate of the terror network.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Separately on Sunday, Yemeni officials said armed tribesmen kidnapped a German national in Sanaa.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Kidnapping has long been a problem in Yemen, with tribes often using foreign nationals as bargaining chips in their dealings with the central government.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>But the past 24 months have proven even more dangerous for foreigners.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>