<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2930" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/10/05/world/africa/somalia-us-shabaab-raid/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2013-10-05 22:57:54" category="world" author="Barbara Starr, CNN Pentagon Correspondent" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>U.S. official: Raid&amp;apost;s target was Al-Shabaab foreign fighter commander</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6">NEW: Kenyan officials said Ikrima helped recruit Kenyans into Al-Shabaab .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="30">The raid was led by members of SEAL Team Six, the unit that killed Osama bin Laden.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="30">The SEALs withdrew because they came under fire, a U.S. official says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="26">Al-Shabaab has claimed responsibility for last month&amp;apost;s Kenya mall attack.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-06 22:55:29" annotation_time="31.439">
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">Kenyan officials said last year that Ikrima had a significant role in recruiting and training Kenyans in Al-Shabaab.</sentence>
      <sentence id="26" ids_highlights="4">Al Qaeda claimed responsibility for both Mombasa attacks.</sentence>
      <sentence id="30" ids_highlights="2, 3">After coming under fire, the U.S. forces -- members of the Navy special forces unit known as SEAL Team Six, the same unit that killed Osama bin Laden in 2011 -- made a &amp;quot;prudent decision&amp;quot; to pull back, a senior U.S. official said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington A pre-dawn raid by elite U.S. forces in southern Somalia, in the heart of territory controlled by the al Qaeda subsidiary Al-Shabaab, targeted an Al-Shabaab commander connected to one of the 1998 U.S. embassy bombings, a senior Obama administration official said Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The suspected foreign fighter commander is named Ikrima, a Kenyan of Somali origin about whom little is known.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The official said Ikrima is associated with two now-deceased al Qaeda operatives who played roles in the 1998 bombing of the U.S. embassy in Nairobi, Kenya, and the 2002 attacks on a hotel and airline in Mombasa, also in Kenya.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>A recent Kenyan intelligence report alleged that Ikrima was behind several foiled terror conspiracies against targets in Kenya between 2011 and 2013.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The most recent was a plot to attack Mandera Airport in Kenya&amp;apost;s North Eastern province in April.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Kenyan officials said last year that Ikrima had a significant role in recruiting and training Kenyans in Al-Shabaab.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>He is thought to have been a close associate of Saleh Ali Nabhan, a fellow Kenyan and senior al Qaeda operative in east Africa, who was killed by U.S. forces in 2009 in Somalia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>He is thought to have been a close associate of the Saleh Ali Nabhan, a fellow Kenyan and senior al Qaeda operative in east Africa, who was believed to have been connected to the embassy attacks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>(Ali Nabhan was killed by U.S. forces in 2009 in Somalia.).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Ikrima also appears to be close to Al-Shabaab leader Mukhtar Abu Zubayr, who also goes by Ahmed Abdi Godane.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>How the raid happened.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>U.S. Navy SEAL members traveled by sea to reach the coastal villa frequented by top Al-Shabaab commanders, storming the house early Saturday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Until Sunday, no U.S. official disclosed the target of the raid.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The SEALs&amp;apost; mission didn&amp;apost;t go as planned, however.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The U.S. commandos encountered heavy fire and had to withdraw, not knowing whether their target was dead or alive.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Al-Shabaab is the U.S.-designated terrorist group that claimed responsibility for last month&amp;apost;s siege on a Kenyan shopping mall that killed 67 people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Residents of the port city of Barawe said the home belonged to Al-Shabaab leader Mukhtar Abu Zubayr, also known as Ahmed Abdi Godane.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>An Al-Shabaab spokesman had said Godane was the target of the attack.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The group said one of its fighters was killed in the attack.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>No SEAL members were killed or hurt, a U.S. official said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>It was one of two raids carried out by elite U.S. forces in Africa on Saturday against targets connected to the 1998 embassy bombing in Nairobi.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The other was an operation in Tripoli, Libya, by the U.S. Army Delta Force against Abu Anas al Libi, indicted in the United States for helping to plan the Nairobi embassy attack.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Delta Force members captured al Libi, who will eventually be taken to New York to face federal charges.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In the 2002 attacks, three suicide bombers detonated a car bomb outside the Israeli-owned Paradise Hotel in Mombasa, killing the bombers as well as 12 Kenyans and three Israelis.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The same morning, a missile attack unsuccessfully targeted an Israeli airliner taking off from Mombasa&amp;apost;s airport.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Al Qaeda claimed responsibility for both Mombasa attacks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Witness accounts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Residents of the port city of Barawe said about a dozen &amp;quot;foreign forces&amp;quot; went from a nearby warship to a smaller, faster boat before jumping onto the Somali mainland.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Before long, the sounds of heavy gunfire and several large explosions echoed across the city, locals said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>After coming under fire, the U.S. forces -- members of the Navy special forces unit known as SEAL Team Six, the same unit that killed Osama bin Laden in 2011 -- made a &amp;quot;prudent decision&amp;quot; to pull back, a senior U.S. official said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Barawe &amp;quot;is a main center, if not the center&amp;quot; for Al-Shabaab, said Matt Bryden, the former head of the U.N. Monitoring Group on Somalia and Eritrea.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s a big source of revenue for them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>It allows for trade,&amp;quot; said Bryden, now the director of a Kenya-based think tank, Sahan Research.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>They &amp;quot;fully control the town&amp;quot; and hold large exercises on the beach, including target practice and even sack races.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Once a tourist destination, the city is now an important port for charcoal, a common fuel in Somalia, Bryden said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>That makes it a revenue source for the jihadists, with the charcoal trade bringing in as much as $25 million a year to Al-Shabaab, the United Nations estimated in July.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Al-Shabaab&amp;apost;s growing menace.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Al-Shabaab, designated a terrorist organization by the United States, has a relationship with al Qaeda that goes back several years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Last year, the two groups effectively merged, said CNN national security analyst Peter Bergen.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Al-Shabaab hopes to turn Somalia into a fundamentalist Islamic state but has launched attacks in other countries as well.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>In 2010, Al-Shabaab claimed responsibility for two suicide bombings carried out in Kampala, Uganda, amid crowds of soccer fans watching televised screenings of the World Cup final.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>The bombings left 74 people dead.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>The group said at the time the attacks were retaliation for Ugandan participation in the African Union Mission in Somalia, known as AMISOM.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>One AMISOM goal is to support Somali government forces in cracking down on Al-Shabaab.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Al-Shabaab has also mounted many smaller attacks against targets in Kenya, hurling hand grenades into nightclubs, restaurants and schools.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>The group has also kidnapped tourists and aid workers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Its attack on the Westgate mall in Kenya on September 21 killed at least 67 people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Al-Shabaab said the attack was retaliation for Kenya&amp;apost;s involvement in the African Union effort against the group.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>In recent months, Al-Shabaab&amp;apost;s haven in south-central Somalia has been been increasingly squeezed as Kenyan forces fight the group from the south and African Union forces come down from Mogadishu, the Somali capital.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
