<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2474" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/04/09/world/africa/egypt-presidential-candidates/index.html" date_published="2012-04-09 17:27:46" category="world" author="Journalists Ian Lee and Mohamed Fadel Fahmy" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Muslim Brotherhood rejects ex-spy chief&amp;apost;s candidacy</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6">If Omar Suleiman wins, Egyptians will protest, Khairat el-Shater says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">Elections are scheduled to begin on May 23.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="15">El-Shater says his group&amp;apost;s priority is to ease sectarian tensions.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-09 14:25:20" annotation_time="169.365">
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;If there is a 1% chance of forgery in the elections, and he wins that way, then all the Egyptians -- not just the Muslim Brotherhood -- will take to the streets.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">Elections are scheduled to start May 23.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="3">Whatever happens in the election, the top priority for the Muslim Brotherhood and the Freedom and Justice Party is to ease sectarian tensions, which built under Mubarak&amp;apost;s regime, he said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Cairo, Egypt A Muslim Brotherhood candidate for next month&amp;apost;s presidential elections here lashed out Monday at the eleventh-hour entrance into the race by Omar Suleiman, the former spy chief to deposed strongman Hosni Mubarak.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are not against the concept of anyone running as long as he has the right legal status, but it&amp;apost;s unacceptable to have one of the symbols of Mubarak&amp;apost;s regime run for president,&amp;quot; Khairat el-Shater told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;The majority of Egyptians will not accept him.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>His candidacy is an insult to the revolution.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The only way Suleiman could win would be by forgery, el-Shater said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;If there is a 1% chance of forgery in the elections, and he wins that way, then all the Egyptians -- not just the Muslim Brotherhood -- will take to the streets.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Elections are scheduled to start May 23.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>El-Shater said the brotherhood&amp;apost;s political arm, the Freedom and Justice Party, would respect &amp;quot;all signed treaties,&amp;quot; including the 1978 Camp David Accords with Israel.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;Regardless of any opinion toward these treaties, they were accepted by decent entities in the country, and it does not mean that changing the political system will affect the treaties.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>But he noted that the accords included a component &amp;quot;about respecting the rights of Palestinians.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The Egyptians respected their part of the deal but the Israelis -- until now -- have not respected the Palestinian rights.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The Egyptians complied, but the Israelis did not.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>El-Shater said the timing of a loan from the International Monetary Fund to the Egyptian government could prove problematic.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;The timing is the problem because we don&amp;apost;t think this interim government is performing well, so we object that they take this loan and spend it in two months, then the new government worries about paying it back.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Whatever happens in the election, the top priority for the Muslim Brotherhood and the Freedom and Justice Party is to ease sectarian tensions, which built under Mubarak&amp;apost;s regime, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;Mubarak&amp;apost;s former regime really oppressed the Coptics and the Muslims because his system was based on tyranny.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>We aim to rebuild our nation again.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Suleiman entered the race just hours before the Sunday deadline, said Hatem Bjato, who heads the election committee.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Suleiman had initially said he would not seek the presidency in the first election for the post since the revolution that led to the toppling of Mubarak.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>But on Friday, Suleiman did an about-face, saying he felt obliged to supporters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;I promise you, my brothers and sisters, to complete the goals of the revolution and provide security and stability to the Egyptian people,&amp;quot; he said in a written statement Friday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Parliament, which is 70% Islamist, passed a bill against Suleiman&amp;apost;s running.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>But it is only symbolic, said Zakaria Abdel Aziz, the former head of the lawyer&amp;apost;s association.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;Only a decision from the administrative court would execute such a ban,&amp;quot; he told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;Banning former regime members from practicing their political rights for five years or even 10 has been discussed thoroughly, but the law has not been reactivated and there must be proof that Omar Suleiman has been implicated in political corruption before he is banned from running.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The status of another candidate was less certain.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>A court ruled that liberal opposition leader Ayman Nour will not be allowed to compete because he was jailed in recent years, the candidate&amp;apost;s son said Saturday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Nour was recently pardoned and plans to appeal, the son said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>That decision could affect the future of al-Shater, since he too was pardoned for his past convictions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>A millionaire businessman who served two prison terms under Mubarak, al-Shater is considered a conservative, though he is also credited as being the driving force behind the Brotherhood&amp;apost;s affirmation that Egypt should continue to honor its international agreements.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Fearful for the future of its candidates, the Muslim Brotherhood nominated Saturday an alternative, Mohammed Morsi, chief of the Freedom and Justice Party.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are protecting the revolution and all of its goals.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>... We have decided as the Brotherhood and its party to nominate Mohammed Morsi as our backup candidate for president,&amp;quot; it said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The group had pledged repeatedly that it would not field a presidential candidate.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>But candidates from its political arm won the largest share of seats in Egypt&amp;apost;s parliamentary elections in December.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>And Brotherhood leader Mohamed Badie has said the new Egypt &amp;quot;is under a serious threat&amp;quot; because its current military-led government &amp;quot;has failed to represent the will of the people.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>A military junta took power after Mubarak&amp;apost;s ouster.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Salafist candidate Hazem Abu Ismael was also disqualified from running in the election because of his mother&amp;apost;s U.S. citizenship, state television reported Saturday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>The deceased mother of Abu Ismael held U.S. citizenship and used her U.S. passport to enter Egypt three times, Egypt&amp;apost;s Interior Ministry has said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Ismael had said that his mother held a green card residency permit but was not a U.S. citizen.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>He told a private Egyptian TV program that his sister was married to an American and had obtained U.S. citizenship, but that his mother had not.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>The official number of candidates is 23.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
