<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2984" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/04/04/world/asia/when-china-rules-the-world/index.html" date_published="2014-04-04 05:17:00" category="world" author="" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Will the West ever understand China?</title>
  <keywords>China ,China&amp;apost;s doninance ,Martin Jacques,When China rules the world,John Gapper</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="21">It is clear that China is on the way to becoming a super power .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">Jacques believes China will become the largest economy in the world in 20 years.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="32">To understand China we need to accept that it is very different from western societies.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-11 18:23:44" annotation_time="32.520664">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">In his view, China will become the largest economy in the world within less than two decades.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="1">I imagine that most people think that as China rises it will be a bit like the U.S. in some shape or form in the way that it expresses itself, and I think this is probably wrong.</sentence>
      <sentence id="32" ids_highlights="3">To understand China we need to start by accepting that it is very different from western societies and it will remain very different and only if we understand China in its specificity, can we make sense of it.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>China has one of the fastest growing economies in the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Its rapid industrial progress, growing military strength, large population and steadily increasing international influence, are all clear signs that China will have a secure place among the super powers in the near future.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The question, raised in a book by journalist Martin Jacques, is not if China will rule the world, but simply when?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>In the interview below, Jacques argues that in the twenty-first century, China will challenge our perception of what it is to be modern, and the West will be forced to learn from growing eastern powers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>In his view, China will become the largest economy in the world within less than two decades.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The former Marxism Today editor is a Senior Fellow at the Department of Politics and International Studies at Cambridge University, and a Visiting Professor at Tsinghua University, Beijing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>His bestseller &amp;quot;When China Rules the World: the End of the Western World and the Birth of a New Global Order,&amp;quot; was first published in 2009 and has since sold over a quarter of a million copies and been translated into fourteen languages.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The Financial Times&amp;apost; Chief business commentator John Gapper interviewed Jacques at Names not Numbers 2014, an event where CNN International was a media partner.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>An edited version of the interview is below.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>John Gapper: Your book is called when China rules the world not if, why when?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Martin Jacques: Well, who knows what will happen, but I think that China&amp;apost;s rise will continue.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>We are witness to the greatest global economic transformation there&amp;apost;s ever been.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The result of it will be that China will become, in time, the leading power in the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>But I don&amp;apost;t think it&amp;apost;s ever going to rule the world, I was taking poetic license with the title!</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>JG: It seems to me that China don&amp;apost;t see themselves as a threat or as an inevitable power in the same way we do?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>MJ: I think that&amp;apost;s correct.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The Chinese always stress the fact that they are a poor country and that they are responsible for a fifth of the world&amp;apost;s population.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>There&amp;apost;s extraordinary unevenness.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The only reason they&amp;apost;re a large economic power is because they have so many people, so they&amp;apost;ve got a long way to go.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The way that the Chinese conceive of themselves in the world is very different from the western tradition.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>I imagine that most people think that as China rises it will be a bit like the U.S. in some shape or form in the way that it expresses itself, and I think this is probably wrong.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The whole Chinese tradition is very different from this, they never really colonized other areas.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>We tend to think the way that the West has done things is emblematic of the way everyone else will do it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>JG: It&amp;apost;s quite difficult then, to see China through a western frame.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>You&amp;apost;re not Chinese how do you get to understand it?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>And if it&amp;apost;s going to have such a huge impact on our lives, how do we get to understand it?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>MJ: With great difficulty!</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The difficulty with the western mentality is that for 200 years we&amp;apost;ve dominated culture, ways of thinking, the economy and military.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>So we have not really been open to other cultures and ways of thinking, we&amp;apost;ve thought that progress is about westernization and becoming more like us.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>And this is a tremendous weakness in western culture in an era when the center of gravity is going somewhere else, and we are going to be in the position where we will need to learn from something else.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Now we&amp;apost;re confronted with the task of making sense of China and it is going to be extremely difficult.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>To understand China we need to start by accepting that it is very different from western societies and it will remain very different and only if we understand China in its specificity, can we make sense of it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>And in my view it will take the whole of this century -- this is not a short term operation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
