<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2582" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/03/17/world/asia/pakistan-politics/index.html" date_published="2013-03-17 09:24:00" category="world" author="Nasir Habib and Saeed Ahmed, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Pakistani government makes history: 5 years of political survival</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Pakistan has had three military coups.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">Next, a caretaker government will oversee elections.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="8">The milestone has come with a price.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="29">Musharraf has said he will return this month.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-28 13:50:58" annotation_time="63.731" mapping_time_divergence="15.93275">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">In its short existence, Pakistan has experienced three military coups, been ruled by generals for half its life, and it remains mired in near-constant political turmoil.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">In the next few days, a caretaker government will be put in place to oversee the country through its next elections scheduled for May.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="3">While the five-year term completion is a milestone well worth nothing, it has come with a price.</sentence>
      <sentence id="29" ids_highlights="4">Against this backdrop comes news that Musharraf plans to return to Pakistan from self-imposed exile in the United Arab Emirates, and lead his party in upcoming elections.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Islamabad, Pakistan At the stroke of midnight Sunday, Pakistan made history.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>It marked the first time a democratically-elected government served a full five-year term in the country&amp;apost;s 65-year history.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>In its short existence, Pakistan has experienced three military coups, been ruled by generals for half its life, and it remains mired in near-constant political turmoil.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;Despite all the odds, completion of the term is an extraordinary and historic achievement,&amp;quot; Prime Minister Raja Pervez Ashraf said in an address to the nation Saturday night.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Ashraf said his country has a long history of confrontation between democratic and nondemocratic forces, but that democracy has now notched a victory.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>In the next few days, a caretaker government will be put in place to oversee the country through its next elections scheduled for May.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Success at a price.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>While the five-year term completion is a milestone well worth nothing, it has come with a price.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The ruling Pakistan Peoples Party rode to power on the back of a populace disillusioned with then-President Pervez Musharraf&amp;apost;s policies that led to shortage of essential food items, power cuts and a skyrocketing inflation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Pakistanis also disapproved of the way Musharraf carried out his end of the &amp;quot;war on terror&amp;quot; -- and used it as a crutch to explain away many of his unpopular moves.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>And the nation was collectively mourning the death of PPP leader Benazir Bhutto, who was assassinated just months before the.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>last elections in February 2008.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Very few held out hope the PPP would resolve the many problems that plagued Pakistan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>And throughout its five-year term, it seemed it couldn&amp;apost;t.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Minister after minister were tainted with accusations of corruption.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The power outages and food shortages that Pakistanis complained about remain.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Terror attacks in city centers continued with depressing regularity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Violence directed at the Shiite minority reached new heights.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>And Pakistanis called the government stooges of the United States, while Washington grumbled that Pakistan was not doing enough to confront militants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Through it all, the shaky coalition the PPP cobbled together seemed on the verge of collapse every few months as partners threatened to walk away at the slightest disagreement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;We could not provide rivers of milk and honey but tried our best to alleviate the country&amp;apost;s problems,&amp;quot; Ashraf said in his Saturday speech.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Staying the course.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>But credit goes to two factors that helped the government stay the course:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The military was content to sit on the sidelines through the topsy-turvy turns -- even when it seemed that the widening rift with the government would force it to intervene as it has in the past.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>And President Asif Ali Zardari -- Bhutto&amp;apost;s widower -- proved surprisingly agile at survival.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Three years ago, he handed over much of his power to the prime minister -- and in the process, robbed his critics of the accusation that he was amassing power like his predecessor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>He also transferred some power from the central government to the provincial level.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Musharraf&amp;apost;s return.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Against this backdrop comes news that Musharraf plans to return to Pakistan from self-imposed exile in the United Arab Emirates, and lead his party in upcoming elections.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Musharraf plans to fly on a commercial airline into Karachi on March 24, then attend a rally with 50,000 people, including more than 200 Pakistani expatriates from the United States, Canada, the United Kingdom and the United Arab Emirates, he said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Five years is often enough time for a populace to forgive and forget.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>It remains to be seen whether Pakistan, now soured by PPP&amp;apost;s reign, welcomes him back with open arms.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
