<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2335" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/01/03/world/meast/mideast-talks/index.html" date_published="2012-01-03 05:28:39" category="world" author="Guy Azriel, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Israeli, Palestinian officials meet in Jordan to relaunch negotiations</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="25">NEW: Hamas spokesman calls the meeting &amp;quot;a mockery&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Negotiators from both sides meet with representatives from the Middle East Quartet.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">The talks fell apart more than a year ago over Israeli settlements in the West Bank.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="2">Jordan is hosting the meeting in an effort to relaunch stalled peace talks.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-12 15:23:07" annotation_time="91.349">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2, 4">Israel&amp;apost;s special envoy, attorney Yitzhak Molcho, and chief Palestinian negotiator Saeb Erakat met in Amman with representatives of the Middle East Quartet -- made up of the United States, the European Union, the United Nations and Russia -- in an effort to relaunch negotiations after more than a year of deadlock.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">Peace talks between Israel and the Palestinians fell apart more than a year ago over disagreements on the issue of Israeli settlements in the West Bank.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="1">Hamas spokesman Fawzi Barhoum told CNN that the meeting of the Palestinians with the Israeli occupying forces &amp;quot;is a mockery.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Palestinian negotiators put forward proposals on security and borders during talks with Israeli representatives in Jordan, Palestinian media reported Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Israel&amp;apost;s special envoy, attorney Yitzhak Molcho, and chief Palestinian negotiator Saeb Erakat met in Amman with representatives of the Middle East Quartet -- made up of the United States, the European Union, the United Nations and Russia -- in an effort to relaunch negotiations after more than a year of deadlock.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Jordanian Foreign Minister Nasser Judeh told reporters that &amp;quot;serious and constructive talks&amp;quot; had taken place, the official Palestinian Authority news agency WAFA said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>He said the talks focused on the two-state solution, according to the Jordanian state news agency Petra.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The Israelis said they would consider the Palestinian proposals, and the two sides agreed to meet again in Jordan, the agency cited Judeh as saying.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>However, no significant breakthrough was made, Judeh acknowledged.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;The gap is wide between the two sides on all issues,&amp;quot; he is quoted as saying by WAFA.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;The issues are complicated and we do not expect to resolve them in a day or two.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Petra quoted Judeh as saying, &amp;quot;We don&amp;apost;t want to raise the expectations about this meeting and we don&amp;apost;t want to underestimate its importance in the same time.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Peace talks between Israel and the Palestinians fell apart more than a year ago over disagreements on the issue of Israeli settlements in the West Bank.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>In September, Palestinian Authority President Mahmoud Abbas made a bid for the United Nations to recognize a Palestinian state, a move Israel called premature without direct talks to address its long-standing security concerns.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Filling the vacuum created by the removal of Egypt&amp;apost;s former President Hosni Mubarak, Jordan&amp;apost;s King Abdullah has taken a more active role in trying to bridge the gulf between Israelis and Palestinians.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>In November, King Abdullah made a rare visit to the Palestinian political capital of Ramallah in the West Bank, followed by a meeting in Amman a week later with Israeli President Shimon Peres.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The United States has voiced its support for the new initiative.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are hopeful that this direct exchange can help move us forward on the pathway proposed by the Quartet,&amp;quot; Hillary Clinton, the U.S. secretary of state, said Sunday night in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;The status quo is not sustainable and the parties must act boldly to advance the cause of peace.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>But while both sides thanked the Jordanian government for its role in bringing about the meeting, few expected any serious breakthroughs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Speaking to Voice of Palestine radio beforehand, Erakat said the meeting would not constitute the resumption of negotiations, but rather would be one that could lead to the restarting of talks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Former Quartet participant and American diplomat Robert Danin wrote Sunday for the Council on Foreign Relations that, while the resumption of contacts between the two sides would be a positive development, it &amp;quot;inadvertently makes the situation on the ground riskier.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;Abbas is returning to talks without attaining his long-standing demand that negotiations resume with an Israeli settlement freeze,&amp;quot; Danin wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;Unless he can demonstrate quickly that talks produce tangible benefits for the Palestinians, he will feel compelled to break them off.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>This, Danin said, could add impetus to Abbas concluding ongoing talks with Hamas about forming a Palestinian unity government -- an idea vehemently opposed by representatives of Israel and the United States, who consider the Islamist group a terrorist organization.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Sami Abu Zuhri, a spokesman for Hamas, said Monday he was surprised by the meetings.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>He said Hamas considered them a repetition of a failed initiative and called on the Palestinian Authority to cancel the meeting Tuesday with Israeli representatives.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Hamas spokesman Fawzi Barhoum told CNN that the meeting of the Palestinians with the Israeli occupying forces &amp;quot;is a mockery.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;Israeli government spokesman Mark Regev told CNN last week that &amp;quot;if Mahmoud Abbas walks toward Hamas, he is walking away from peace.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
