<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2735" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/12/07/world/asia/afghanistan-hagel-visit/index.html" date_published="2013-12-07 16:35:36" category="world" author="CNN Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Security pact a topic in Hagel&amp;apost;s Afghan trip</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Hagel visiting troops in Afghanistan.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">Defense secretary gets assurances .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="17">Karzai visiting Iran on Sunday.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 14:53:10" annotation_time="59.623337" mapping_time_divergence="19.874445">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">Hagel met with Afghanistan&amp;apost;s officials, including the country&amp;apost;s defense minister, as Washington works to get Afghanistan to ink a bilateral security agreement to keep some U.S. and other coalition troops in the country after next year.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">The Defense secretary said that from what he has heard in his discussions with Afghan ministers, they believe it&amp;apost;s in the country&amp;apost;s interest to have such an agreement -- which lays out the U.S. military presence in Afghanistan after 2014, when the NATO-led force of some 80,000 troops is scheduled to leave.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="3">Karzai, meanwhile, is scheduled to make a visit to Iran on Sunday.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>U.S. Defense Secretary Chuck Hagel says his Afghan counterpart assured him that an important security pact will be reached with Kabul in a &amp;quot;timely manner,&amp;quot; despite a failure so far to forge a deal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Hagel made the remark during a visit to Afghanistan on Saturday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>What is known as the bilateral security agreement -- ready to be implemented but still unsigned -- initially has been front and center in Hagel&amp;apost;s visit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Hagel met with Afghanistan&amp;apost;s officials, including the country&amp;apost;s defense minister, as Washington works to get Afghanistan to ink a bilateral security agreement to keep some U.S. and other coalition troops in the country after next year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The Defense secretary said that from what he has heard in his discussions with Afghan ministers, they believe it&amp;apost;s in the country&amp;apost;s interest to have such an agreement -- which lays out the U.S. military presence in Afghanistan after 2014, when the NATO-led force of some 80,000 troops is scheduled to leave.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;The minister of defense assured me that the BSA would be signed and would be signed in a very timely manner,&amp;quot; Hagel said, making reference to Defense Minister Bismullah Khan Mohammadi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>But failure to forge a security pact with Afghan President Hamid Karzai has generated growing consternation among U.S. officials.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The security agreement itself has been endorsed by the Afghan council of tribal leaders, called the loya jirga, but Karzai said he won&amp;apost;t sign it until after the country&amp;apost;s elections in April and until certain conditions are met.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>These conditions include an end to U.S. raids on Afghan homes and the release of Afghan prisoners from the Guantanamo Bay detention center.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Washington has resisted such changes, saying Karzai&amp;apost;s demands are new provisions added to a deal that was already reached.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Hagel said he hadn&amp;apost;t planned to meet with Karzai and played down the significance of being in Afghanistan and not meeting with the president.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>He said the trip had been planned for weeks and its purpose was visiting troops and meeting with Afghan commanders to assess their progress.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>And, he told reporters, there have been many discussions at the political level with Karzai during recent visits by other others, such as Secretary of State John Kerry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Hagel emphasized the importance of the loya jirga&amp;apost;s decision and said &amp;quot;we are planning for a post-2014 presence here.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>But he said NATO -- which commands the multination International Security Assistance Force in Afghanistan -- will eventually need clarity on the security agreement&amp;apost;s status so it can properly plan its work in the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>NATO warned it may be forced to withdraw all of its troops from Afghanistan by the end of next year if Karzai doesn&amp;apost;t sign a security agreement with the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Karzai, meanwhile, is scheduled to make a visit to Iran on Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Iran&amp;apost;s semi-official Mehr News said Karzai will be meeting with Iranian President Hassan Rouhani.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>According to state-run Press TV, an Iranian Foreign Ministry spokeswoman said Tehran doesn&amp;apost;t believe the security agreement will benefit the Afghan government and nation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Marzieh Afkham said Tehran&amp;apost;s position is that the security pact is not &amp;quot;useful for the long-term expedience and interests of Afghanistan.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>and could have a negative impact on regional issues.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
