<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2862" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/06/13/world/europe/turkey-protests" date_published="2013-06-13 10:24:59" category="world" author="Michael Martinez. Ben Brumfield and Gul Tuysuz, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Turkish prime minister to meet for first time with protest leaders</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Prime minister met with Taksim Solidarity Platform, a coalition of protesters.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="36">Prime Minister Erdogan to EU: &amp;quot;How dare you make such decisions about my country?&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="9">It&amp;apost;s time to clean out the park for sanitary reasons, he says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="13">Erdogan: Peaceful protesters should not complain about police action.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 16:04:38" annotation_time="80.114334">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Istanbul Turkey&amp;apost;s prime minister held his first meeting Thursday night with leaders of Taksim Solidarity Platform, a loose coalition of various groups of demonstrators from Gezi Park, platform leader Eyup Muhcu said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="3">Gezi Park reeks, making it high time for police to clear it out, Erdogan said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="4">But he also told peaceful protesters they need not complain about the actions of his police, because they had put themselves in the line of tear gas fire by associating with the wrong people and illegal groups.</sentence>
      <sentence id="36" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;How dare you make such decisions about my country?&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Istanbul Turkey&amp;apost;s prime minister held his first meeting Thursday night with leaders of Taksim Solidarity Platform, a loose coalition of various groups of demonstrators from Gezi Park, platform leader Eyup Muhcu said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The meeting came after 24 hours of calm in Istanbul and followed a Wednesday evening gathering between the prime minister and a group of individuals attempting to act as mediators for the protesters in Gezi Park.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Earlier, the prime minister called on protesters camped out in the park to pack up and leave.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are running out of patience,&amp;quot; Recep Tayyip Erdogan told members of his party in the capital, Ankara, on Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am making this warning for one last time.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The government has been delivering conflicting messages.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>On the one hand, it appeared to slightly soften its stance by saying it would hold a referendum on Gezi Park&amp;apost;s fate, but at the same time, the government delivered yet another ultimatum Thursday for the demonstrators to evacuate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Erdogan intensified his heated rhetoric, at times pushing into the absurd.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Gezi Park reeks, making it high time for police to clear it out, Erdogan said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;It stinks of pee.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>In fact, some of them even poo in there.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>He lashed out at rowdy demonstrators, whom he called &amp;quot;vagabonds&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;thugs.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>But he also told peaceful protesters they need not complain about the actions of his police, because they had put themselves in the line of tear gas fire by associating with the wrong people and illegal groups.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;Where dry wood is burning, fresh wood will also burn unnecessarily,&amp;quot; Erdogan said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>He vowed to continue routing out rowdies and ordered peaceful protesters out of the park, asking them to leave police alone with &amp;quot;illegal groups.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;Come forward, mothers, fathers, please, claim your children.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Let those children withdraw from that area,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are on the one hand waiting for the judiciary process.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>On the other hand, we would take a step towards a plebiscite and we&amp;apost;ll follow whatever Istanbul people decide.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;But please own up to your children, take them out,&amp;quot; he continued.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;Otherwise we cannot wait any longer, because Gezi Park does not belong to occupation forces; Gezi Park belongs to Istanbul people and the whole nation.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Erdogan&amp;apost;s party has organized counterprotests for the weekend to give a voice to Turkey&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;quiet majority to the people and the world,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>They will show the international community &amp;quot;a real, true picture of Turkey.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Two rallies will be held away from anti-government protests to avoid possible confrontations, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Negotiations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>On Wednesday, the prime minister met with protest mediators for four and a half hours, but some leaders, such as with the Taksim Solidarity, one of the main protest groups, backed out because of what it described as heavy-handed police measures Tuesday night in the square.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>But on Thursday night, leaders of Taksim Solidarity were heading to meet with the prime minister in Ankara.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Harsh actions against protesters could strain Erdogan&amp;apost;s strategic friendships with much of the West -- relationships that are particularly critical in light of the civil war ravaging Turkey&amp;apost;s neighbor, Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Turkey is a NATO ally with a democratically elected government.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The anti-Erdogan protests show no sign of abating.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>What began in late May as a demonstration focused on the environment -- opposition to a plan to build a mall in Gezi Park -- has evolved into a wider protest against Erdogan that&amp;apost;s spread around the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>International criticism.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Erdogan also dealt a slap to the European Union for a resolution it passed Thursday condemning his country&amp;apost;s police crackdown on protesters and the suppression of opposition voices.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;The European Parliament&amp;apost;s decisions about us, I am not recognizing those decisions,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The comments triggered a thunderous standing ovation and roaring cheers from party members.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;How dare you make such decisions about my country?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>His angry words were echoed by Foreign Minister Ahmet Davutoglu, who said the European Parliament had no right to censure Turkey if it didn&amp;apost;t do the same when other European nations tackled protests in similar ways.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>For example, he said, water cannons and tear gas were used by German security forces at an Occupy protest in Frankfurt on June 1, the same day as they were deployed in Turkey, without drawing criticism.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;Turkey will always support the freedom of demonstration ... but if this is misused, we distinguish between the innocent demonstrators and the marginal groups who try to misuse the right of demonstration,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>He accused some people of trying to damage Turkey&amp;apost;s image in the eyes of the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Turkey has for many years expressed the desire to become a member of the European Union.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Experts and human rights groups say Erdogan&amp;apost;s government lags when it comes to human rights and freedom of expression by opponents.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>&amp;quot;Prosecutors and courts continued to use terrorism laws to prosecute and prolong incarceration of thousands of Kurdish political activists, human rights defenders, students, journalists and trade unionists,&amp;quot; Human Rights Watch wrote in a 2013 report on Turkey.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Turkish journalists are afraid to write anything critical of the government, and media companies are slapped with huge tax fines for covering uncomfortable topics.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>According to the Committee to Protect Journalists, Turkish authorities have targeted journalists with detention for covering the protests.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>The prime minister has said many times he will not back down.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>On Wednesday evening, Taksim police took two foreign nationals into custody on grounds that they resisted police, according to the Turkish Radio and Television Corp. official website.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>It was reported that the two men were journalists working for a Canadian television and covering the protests in Taksim Square.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="37">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>On Thursday, the U.S. Embassy in Ankara issued a security message to American visitors, highlighting a risk of terrorist attacks on U.S. diplomatic, consular and military facilities in Turkey.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="38">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>&amp;quot;The U.S. Embassy has received an increased number of reports indicating terrorist organizations are targeting these facilities,&amp;quot; the advisory said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="39">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>It said U.S. diplomatic facilities will remain open for business &amp;quot;in the absence of specific and credible threat information that cannot be otherwise countered.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
