<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2774" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/05/27/world/africa/sudan-christian-woman-apostasy/index.html" date_published="2014-05-27 10:49:24" category="world" author="Faith Karimi and Mohammed Osman, CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Sudanese woman sentenced to die for Christianity gives birth in prison</title>
  <keywords>Sudan Christian Woman Apostasy</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Meriam Yehya Ibrahim, 27, gave birth in prison .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Sources: Her husband was not allowed to attend the birth.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">Ibrahim was convicted of apostasy.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-26 09:48:03" annotation_time="32.617332">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">A Sudanese woman sentenced to die for refusing to renounce her Christianity gave birth to a baby girl in prison Tuesday, her lawyers said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">Meriam Yehya Ibrahim, 27, delivered her baby at a women&amp;apost;s prison in Khartoum, but her husband was not allowed to be present for the birth, sources told CNN.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">Ibrahim was convicted of apostasy, or the renunciation of faith, about two weeks ago while she was eight months pregnant.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A Sudanese woman sentenced to die for refusing to renounce her Christianity gave birth to a baby girl in prison Tuesday, her lawyers said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Meriam Yehya Ibrahim, 27, delivered her baby at a women&amp;apost;s prison in Khartoum, but her husband was not allowed to be present for the birth, sources told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>They asked not to be named for safety reasons.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Ibrahim was convicted of apostasy, or the renunciation of faith, about two weeks ago while she was eight months pregnant.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>A Sudanese lawyer filed an appeal last week to reverse the verdict by the lower court.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>She is in prison with her 20-month-old son, but Sudanese officials have said the toddler is free to leave any time, according to her lawyer, Mohamed Jar Elnabi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Her husband, Daniel Wani, is a U.S. citizen who uses a wheelchair and &amp;quot;totally depends on her for all details of his life,&amp;quot; her lawyer said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The appeal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The appeals court in Khartoum will issue a ruling on the case in the next week, but it will first ask the lower court to submit the documents it used to make the ruling, according to her lawyer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Once that&amp;apost;s done, it will issue a case number, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;We will continue checking with the appeals court, but Inshallah (Allah willing) ... the appeals court will reverse the sentence and set her free,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Christian or Muslim?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Ibrahim says her father was a Sudanese Muslim and her mother was Ethiopian Orthodox.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Her father left when she was 6, and she was raised as a Christian.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The court had warned her to renounce her Christianity by May 15, but she held firm to her beliefs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Sudanese Parliament speaker Fatih Izz Al-Deen said claims that Ibrahim was raised as non-Muslim are untrue.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>She was raised in an Islamic environment, and her brother, a Muslim, filed the complaint against her, according to Al-Deen.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The complaint alleges that she went missing for several years, and her family was shocked to find out she married a Christian, according to her lawyer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>However, because her father was Muslim, the courts considered her one too, which would mean her marriage to a non-Muslim man is void.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Attempts to contact Sudan&amp;apost;s justice minister and foreign affairs minister for comment were unsuccessful.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>100 lashes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>In addition to the death sentence, the court convicted Ibrahim of adultery and sentenced her to 100 lashes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The Parliament speaker has said the verdict is not final and will go through all the judicial stages to reach the constitutional court.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Worldwide condemnation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Rights groups and foreign embassies worldwide condemned the verdict.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;The fact that a woman could be sentenced to death for her religious choice, and to flogging for being married to a man of an allegedly different religion, is abhorrent and should never be even considered,&amp;quot; said Manar Idriss, Amnesty International&amp;apost;s Sudan researcher.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Katherine Perks with the African Centre for Justice and Peace Studies said the verdict goes against Sudan&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;own constitution and commitments made under regional and international law.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Foreign embassies in Khartoum, including those of the United States, United Kingdom and Canada, urged the government to reverse course.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>In past cases involving pregnant or nursing women, the Sudanese government waited until the mother weaned her child before executing any sentence, said Christian Solidarity Worldwide spokeswoman Kiri Kankhwende.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
