<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2129" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/05/14/world/africa/sudan-christian-woman-apostasy/index.html" date_published="2014-05-14 22:34:11" category="world" author="Jessica King and Dana Ford, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Christian woman could face death for her faith in Sudan</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Meriam Yehya Ibrahim, 27, was convicted of apostasy and adultery.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">She considers herself Christian, but a court contends that she is Muslim.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">She could be sentenced to death and to flogging.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="15">Foreign embassies in Khartoum are urging the government to reverse course.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-08 23:26:25" annotation_time="19.491667">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Meriam Yehya Ibrahim, 27, was convicted by a Khartoum court this week of apostasy, or the renunciation of faith, Amnesty International said Wednesday, a day before the expected ruling.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">The court considers her to be Muslim.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;The fact that a woman could be sentenced to death for her religious choice, and to flogging for being married to a man of an allegedly different religion, is abhorrent and should never be even considered,&amp;quot; Manar Idriss, Amnesty International&amp;apost;s Sudan researcher, said in a statement.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="4">Foreign embassies in Khartoum are urging the government there to reverse course.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A Christian woman in Sudan reportedly has until Thursday to either recant her faith or face a possible sentence of death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Meriam Yehya Ibrahim, 27, was convicted by a Khartoum court this week of apostasy, or the renunciation of faith, Amnesty International said Wednesday, a day before the expected ruling.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The court considers her to be Muslim.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>According to the rights group, she was also convicted of adultery because her marriage to a Christian man was considered void under Sharia law.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;The fact that a woman could be sentenced to death for her religious choice, and to flogging for being married to a man of an allegedly different religion, is abhorrent and should never be even considered,&amp;quot; Manar Idriss, Amnesty International&amp;apost;s Sudan researcher, said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;&amp;apost;Adultery&amp;apost; and &amp;apost;apostasy&amp;apost; are acts which should not be considered crimes at all, let alone meet the international standard of &amp;apost;most serious crimes&amp;apost; in relation to the death penalty.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>It is flagrant breach of international human rights law,&amp;quot; the researcher said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Ibrahim is eight months pregnant and currently in custody with her 20-month-old son, according to Amnesty International, which considers her a prisoner of conscience.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Christian Solidarity Worldwide, another rights group, described Ibrahim&amp;apost;s case as follows:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>She was born to a Sudanese Muslim father and an Ethiopian Orthodox mother.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Her father left when she was 6 years old, and Ibrahim was raised by her mother as a Christian.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>However, because her father was Muslim, she was considered by the courts to be the same, which would mean her marriage to a non-Muslim man is void.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>In past cases involving pregnant or nursing women, the Sudanese government waited until the mother weaned her child before executing any sentence, said Christian Solidarity Worldwide spokeswoman Kiri Kankhwende.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>After-hours attempts Wednesday to contact the Justice Minister and Foreign Affairs Minister in Sudan were unsuccessful.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Foreign embassies in Khartoum are urging the government there to reverse course.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;We call upon the Government of Sudan to respect the right to freedom of religion, including one&amp;apost;s right to change one&amp;apost;s faith or beliefs, a right which is enshrined in international human rights law as well as in Sudan&amp;apost;s own 2005 Interim Constitution,&amp;quot; the embassies of the United States, United Kingdom, Canada and Netherlands said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;We further urge Sudanese legal authorities to approach Ms. Meriam&amp;apost;s case with justice and compassion that is in keeping with the values of the Sudanese people,&amp;quot; it read.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
