<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2336" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/01/01/world/meast/mideast-talks/index.html" date_published="2012-01-01 18:10:53" category="world" author="Guy Azriel, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Israeli, Palestinian officials to meet in Jordan</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Jordan is hosting the meeting in an effort to relaunch stalled peace talks.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="10">The talks fell apart more than a year ago over Israeli settlements in the West Bank.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">Negotiators from both sides will meet with representatives from the Middle East Quartet.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-10 15:11:29" annotation_time="27.198">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Jerusalem Israeli and Palestinian representatives will meet in Amman, Jordan, on Tuesday in an effort to relaunch negotiations between the two sides after more than a year of deadlock, Jordanian state media reported.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">Netanyahu&amp;apost;s special envoy, attorney Yitzhak Molcho, and Erakat will meet with representatives of the Middle East Quartet -- made up of the United States, the European Union, the United Nations and Russia.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="2">Peace talks between the two sides fell apart more than a year ago over disagreements on the issue of Israeli settlements in the West Bank.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Jerusalem Israeli and Palestinian representatives will meet in Amman, Jordan, on Tuesday in an effort to relaunch negotiations between the two sides after more than a year of deadlock, Jordanian state media reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;Jordan&amp;apost;s efforts are based on the belief that the two-state solution, which leads to the establishment of an independent and sovereign Palestinian national state, is a top Jordanian interest,&amp;quot; a spokesman for the Jordanian Foreign Ministry said, the country&amp;apost;s state-run Petra news agency said Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Yoaz Hendel, chief media adviser to Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, thanked Jordanian officials in a statement Sunday &amp;quot;for their efforts to bring the two sides together under the outline of international quartet.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Chief Palestinian negotiator Saeb Erakat also expressed his appreciation to Jordan&amp;apost;s King Abdullah for his role in the breakthrough.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;This invitation is part of ongoing Jordanian efforts to compel Israel to comply with its international legal obligations and those under the Quartet road map, specifically its obligation to freeze all settlement construction in all the occupied Palestinian territory, including occupied East Jerusalem,&amp;quot; Erakat said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Netanyahu&amp;apost;s special envoy, attorney Yitzhak Molcho, and Erakat will meet with representatives of the Middle East Quartet -- made up of the United States, the European Union, the United Nations and Russia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are hopeful that this direct exchange can help move us forward on the pathway proposed by the Quartet,&amp;quot; U.S. Secretary of State Hillary Clinton said in a statement Sunday night.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;As the president and I have said before, the need for a lasting peace is more urgent than ever.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The status quo is not sustainable and the parties must act boldly to advance the cause of peace.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Peace talks between the two sides fell apart more than a year ago over disagreements on the issue of Israeli settlements in the West Bank.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>In September, Palestinian Authority President Mahmoud Abbas made a bid for the United Nations to recognize a Palestinian state, a move Israel called premature without direct talks that address its long-standing security concerns.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Erakat called upon Israel to &amp;quot;seize this opportunity to stop all settlement construction, accept the two-state solution on the 1967 border, and release Palestinian prisoners, in order to have the conducive environment called for under the Quartet statement of 23 September 2011, for meaningful and credible talks.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Netanyahu&amp;apost;s spokesman, Mark Regev, told CNN Sunday: &amp;quot;We have said so before and will say this again, we are ready for immediate resumptions of peace talks without preconditions.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Filling the vacuum left open by the removal of Egypt&amp;apost;s former President Hosni Mubarak, Jordan&amp;apost;s King Abdullah has taken a more active role in trying to bridge the gulf between Israelis and Palestinians.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Last month, King Abdullah made a rare visit to the Palestinian political capitol of Ramallah in the West Bank followed by a meeting in Amman a week later with Israeli President Shimon Peres.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>While both sides thanked the Jordanian government for its role in bringing about the meeting, few are expecting any serious breakthroughs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Speaking to Voice of Palestine radio, Erakat said the meeting would not constitute the resumption of negotiations, but rather is one that could lead to the resumption of negotiations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Former Quartet participant and American diplomat Robert Danin wrote Sunday for the Council on Foreign Relations that while the resumption of contacts between the two sides would be a positive development, it &amp;quot;inadvertently makes the situation on the ground riskier.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;Abbas is returning to talks without attaining his long-standing demand that negotiations resume with an Israeli settlement freeze,&amp;quot; Danin wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;Unless he can demonstrate quickly that talks produce tangible benefits for the Palestinians, he will feel compelled to break them off.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>This, Danin says, could add more impetus to Abbas concluding ongoing talks with Hamas about forming a Palestinian unity government -- an idea vehemently opposed by Israel and the United States, which both consider the Islamist group a terrorist organization.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Israeli government spokesman Regev told CNN last week that &amp;quot;If Mahmoud Abbas walks toward Hamas, he is walking away from peace.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
