<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2865" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/02/24/world/africa/uganda-homosexuality-interview/?hpt=bosread" date_published="2014-02-24 18:12:14" category="world" author="Elizabeth Landau. Zain Verjee and Antonia Mortensen, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Uganda president: Homosexuals are &amp;apost;disgusting&amp;apost;</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="21">NEW: People who perform same-sex marriages could face up to seven years in prison.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="24">Ugandan President Yoweri Museveni signed an anti-homosexuality bill Monday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="24">The White House says Museveni took his country a &amp;quot;step backward&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="17">Museveni changed positions on the bill several times before signing it.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2015-01-30 14:55:13" annotation_time="46.6155">
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="4">Museveni, whose public position on the measure changed several times, signed the bill into law at a public event Monday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="1">The new law also includes punishment -- up to seven years in prison -- for people and institutions who perform same-sex marriage ceremonies, language that was not in the 2009 version of the bill.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="2, 3">The White House issued a statement Monday: &amp;quot;Instead of standing on the side of freedom, justice, and equal rights for its people, today, regrettably, Ugandan President Museveni took Uganda a step backward by signing into law legislation criminalizing homosexuality.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>President Yoweri Museveni, who made anti-homosexuality laws in Uganda much tougher Monday, told CNN in an exclusive interview that sexual behavior is a matter of choice and gay people are &amp;quot;disgusting.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>After signing the bill that made some homosexual acts punishable by life in prison, Museveni told CNN&amp;apost;s Zain Verjee that, in his view, being homosexual is &amp;quot;unnatural&amp;quot; and not a human right.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;They&amp;apost;re disgusting.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>What sort of people are they?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;I never knew what they were doing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>I&amp;apost;ve been told recently that what they do is terrible.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Disgusting.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>But I was ready to ignore that if there was proof that that&amp;apost;s how he is born, abnormal.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>But now the proof is not there.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Museveni had commissioned a group of Ugandan government scientists to study whether homosexuality is &amp;quot;learned,&amp;quot; concluding that it is a matter of choice.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;I was regarding it as an inborn problem,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;Genetic distortion -- that was my argument.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>But now our scientists have knocked this one out.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Dean Hamer, scientist emeritus at the National Institutes of Health, wrote an open letter to the Ugandan scientists in the New York Times last week urging them to reconsider and revise their report.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Among his responses to their conclusions: &amp;quot;There is no scientific evidence that homosexual orientation is a learned behavior any more than is heterosexual orientation.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Museveni, whose public position on the measure changed several times, signed the bill into law at a public event Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The bill was introduced in 2009 and originally included a death penalty clause for some homosexual acts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The nation&amp;apost;s Parliament passed the bill in December, replacing the death penalty provision with a proposal of life in prison for &amp;quot;aggravated homosexuality.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>This includes acts in which one person is infected with HIV, &amp;quot;serial offenders&amp;quot; and sex with minors, according to Amnesty International.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The new law also includes punishment -- up to seven years in prison -- for people and institutions who perform same-sex marriage ceremonies, language that was not in the 2009 version of the bill.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Lawmakers in the conservative nation said the influence of Western lifestyles risked destroying family units.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The bill also proposed prison terms for anyone who counsels or reaches out to gays and lesbians, a provision that could ensnare rights groups and others providing services to lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The White House issued a statement Monday: &amp;quot;Instead of standing on the side of freedom, justice, and equal rights for its people, today, regrettably, Ugandan President Museveni took Uganda a step backward by signing into law legislation criminalizing homosexuality.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The statement continued: &amp;quot;As President Obama has said, this law is more than an affront and a danger to the gay community in Uganda, it reflects poorly on the country&amp;apost;s commitment to protecting the human rights of its people and will undermine public health, including efforts to fight HIV/AIDS.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>We will continue to urge the Ugandan government to repeal this abhorrent law and to advocate for the protection of the universal human rights of LGBT persons in Uganda and around the world.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights Navi Pillay also denounced the law, saying it institutionalizes discrimination and could promote harassment and violence against lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;This law violates a host of fundamental human rights, including the right to freedom from discrimination, to privacy, freedom of association, peaceful assembly, opinion and expression and equality before the law -- all of which are enshrined in Uganda&amp;apost;s own constitution and in the international treaties it has ratified,&amp;quot; Pillay said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Museveni also told CNN that the West should not force its beliefs onto Ugandans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;Respect African societies and their values,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;If you don&amp;apost;t agree, just keep quiet.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Let us manage our society, then we will see.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>If we are wrong, we shall find out by ourselves, just the way we don&amp;apost;t interfere with yours.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>He also said Westerners brought homosexuality to his country, corrupting society by teaching Ugandans about homosexuality.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The West has also helped make children at schools homosexual by funding groups that spread homosexuality, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Attitudes against homosexuality are prevalent in Uganda.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>A 2013 report from Pew Research found that 96% of Ugandans believe society should not accept homosexuality.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Thirty-eight African countries have made homosexuality illegal.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Most sodomy laws there were introduced during colonialism.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Even before Museveni signed the bill into law, homosexual acts were punishable by 14 years to life in prison.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Ugandan gay rights activist Pepe Julian Onziema told CNN&amp;apost;s Christiane Amanpour that some gay people in Uganda would rather kill themselves than live under the new law.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;Prior to the bill becoming law today, people attempted suicide because they are like, &amp;apost;I&amp;apost;m not going to live to see this country kill me -- so I would rather take my life.&amp;apost; &amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Many have already left the country in fear of violence, Onziema said, and among those who stay, many are stopping their activism.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Onziema, however, says he is not afraid.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>He says he won&amp;apost;t let the law take away his voice.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>