<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2321" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/09/world/meast/isis-isil-islamic-state/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-09-09 18:24:06" category="world" author="Ray Sanchez, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>ISIS, ISIL or the Islamic State?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="30">ISIS is translation of the acronym in Arabic for the Islamic State of Iraq and al-Sham.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="12">U.S. officials, the U.N., some media use ISIL: Islamic State in Iraq and the Levant.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="38">Jihadist group prefers &amp;quot;the Islamic State&amp;quot; or just &amp;quot;the State&amp;quot;.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-13 14:30:58" annotation_time="41.199">
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="2">President Obama, the United Nations and some news organizations refer to the jihadist group by the acronym ISIL, which stands for Islamic State in Iraq and the Levant.</sentence>
      <sentence id="30" ids_highlights="1">ISIS is an English translation of the acronym in Arabic for Al-Dawla Al-Islamiya fi al-Iraq wa al-Sham, or the Islamic State in Iraq and al-Sham.</sentence>
      <sentence id="38" ids_highlights="3">They prefer to be known either as the Islamic State -- al-Dawla al-Islamiya in Arabic -- or just the State, al-Dawla.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Is it ISIL, ISIS or Islamic State?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Whatever you call the jihadist group known for killing dozens of people at a time, carrying out public executions, beheadings, crucifixions and other brutal acts, there is no denying they have captured the world&amp;apost;s attention.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>On the eve of President Barack Obama&amp;apost;s speech outlining Washington&amp;apost;s strategy against the group, in which he will likely refer to it as ISIL, we ask: What&amp;apost;s in a name?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>It all started in 2004 when the late Abu Musab al-Zarqawi formed an al Qaeda splinter group in Iraq.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Within two years, al-Zarqawi&amp;apost;s al Qaeda in Iraq was trying to fuel a sectarian war against the majority Shiite community.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>In June 2006, al-Zarqawi was killed in a U.S. strike.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Abu Ayyub al-Masri, his successor, several months later announced the creation of the Islamic State in Iraq (ISI).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>In April 2013, Islamic State in Iraq absorbed the al Qaeda-backed militant group in Syria, Jabhat al-Nusra, also known as the al-Nusra Front.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Its leader Abu Bakr al-Baghdadi said his group will now be known as Islamic State in Iraq and the Levant.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Since then, the English-speaking world seems to have had a hard time settling on a name for them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>ISIL.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>President Obama, the United Nations and some news organizations refer to the jihadist group by the acronym ISIL, which stands for Islamic State in Iraq and the Levant.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>CNN Global Affairs Correspondent Elise Labott said the U.S. has stuck with ISIL because the group appears to have to set it sights beyond Iraq and Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>And also because Washington doesn&amp;apost;t want to recognize their plans for a caliphate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>CNN national security analyst Peter Bergen believes ISIL is a more accurate translation of the group&amp;apost;s name.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The &amp;apost;L&amp;apost; stands for Levant which is a translation of &amp;quot;al-Sham&amp;quot; -- the word the group uses to refer to itself, Bergen said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;But the Levant is a relatively obscure word in English -- in English, we refer to Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Of course, the Levant is larger than Syria,&amp;quot; Bergen said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;We believe this is the most accurate translation of the group&amp;apost;s name and reflects its aspirations to rule over a broad swath of the Middle East,&amp;quot; said John Daniszewski, vice president and senior managing editor for international news for The Associated Press, according to an AP blog post.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Al-Sham is a reference to a region that stretches from Turkey through Syria to Egypt and includes the Palestinian territories, Jordan and Lebanon, according to Rashid Khalidi, a Columbia University professor and expert on Syrian history.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Part of the confusion stems from the fact that al-Sham has many meanings in Arabic.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Khalidi said: &amp;quot;How you translate &amp;apost;al-Sham&amp;apost; determines whether you have an &amp;apost;L&amp;apost; or an &amp;apost;S&amp;apost; in English.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s the same word in Arabic.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>How you translate the term into English determines if you&amp;apost;re of the &amp;apost;ISIL&amp;apost; camp or the &amp;apost;ISIS&amp;apost; camp.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The Levant, which can extend from northern Egypt to Greece, is not as precise.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>On the United States government&amp;apost;s use of ISIL, Khalidi surmised: &amp;quot;Maybe because you don&amp;apost;t want to give the dignity of the name that they give themselves.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Nawaf Obaid, a visiting fellow at the Belfer Center for Science and International Affairs at Harvard University, said via email that ISIL is preferable in English &amp;quot;to make it clear to a Western audience.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Levant denotes Syria and Lebanon in Arabic, &amp;quot;so better to stick to ISIL and clarify that it&amp;apost;s the same as ISIS, but a more accurate translation from the Arabic,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>ISIS.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>ISIS is an English translation of the acronym in Arabic for Al-Dawla Al-Islamiya fi al-Iraq wa al-Sham, or the Islamic State in Iraq and al-Sham.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The organization has said its goal is to form an Islamic state, or caliphate, over the entire region, stretching from Turkey through Syria to Egypt and including the Palestinian territories, Jordan and Lebanon.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Some think ISIS flows better as a word in English.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>It also happens to be the name of one of a goddess of ancient Egypt.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>CNN has been referring to the organization as ISIS, shorthand for the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Arabic speakers say al-Sham can be translated to mean the Levant, Syria, greater Syria, and even Damascus.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Islamic State.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>The jihadists like to refer to themselves simply as the Islamic State, a term more accurately reflecting the organization&amp;apost;s aspirations of creating a caliphate across national borders.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>They prefer to be known either as the Islamic State -- al-Dawla al-Islamiya in Arabic -- or just the State, al-Dawla.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>That is what they call themselves in online videos.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>DAIISH.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Finally, a lesser-known acronym to Western readers: DAIISH.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>It is the straight Arabic shorthand for the group known as: al-Dawla al-Islamiya fi Iraq wa al-Sham, commonly used in the Arab world and among many Arab media outlets and politicians.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>When people in the Arab world, use the term DAIISH, it&amp;apost;s derogatory, according to Columbia&amp;apost;s Khalidi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;Those who disagree with them, call them DAIISH,&amp;quot; Khalidi said, adding that the jihadists have objected to the name.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
