<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2938" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/08/27/world/meast/isis-iraq-syria/index.html?hpt=imi_c1" date_published="2014-08-28 02:33:01" category="world" author="Chelsea J. Carter and Barbara Starr, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>U.S. weighs airstrikes for Iraqi town besieged by ISIS</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="23">NEW: U.S. general meets with top officials in Baghdad and Irbil.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Airstrikes and humanitarian airdrops are being considered, White House official says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">ISIS fighters have besieged the town of Amerli since June.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="7">&amp;quot;There are fears of an imminent massacre,&amp;quot; a U.N. official says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2015-01-30 15:00:28" annotation_time="31.005499">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2">Washington U.S. President Barack Obama is considering airstrikes and humanitarian airdrops to help save thousands of Iraq&amp;apost;s Shiite Turkmen, who officials said Wednesday are facing a potential slaughter at the hands of fighters with the so-called Islamic State.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">ISIS fighters have besieged the town of Amerli, 70 miles north of Baquba, since the Sunni extremists swept into Iraq from Syria since mid-June.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="4">&amp;quot;Residents are enduring harsh living conditions with severe food and water shortages, and a complete absence of medical services -- and there are fears of a possible imminent massacre,&amp;quot; U.N. High Commissioner for Human Rights Navi Pillay said this week.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="1">Gen. Lloyd J. Austin III, commander of the U.S. Central Command, met with top officials in Baghdad and Irbil on Wednesday to discuss &amp;quot;U.S.-Iraq defense cooperation and regional security issues,&amp;quot; the U.S. Embassy in Baghdad said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington U.S. President Barack Obama is considering airstrikes and humanitarian airdrops to help save thousands of Iraq&amp;apost;s Shiite Turkmen, who officials said Wednesday are facing a potential slaughter at the hands of fighters with the so-called Islamic State.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;These kinds of options are on the table because they do alleviate some of the suffering that is sustained by religious and ethnic minorities that are being persecuted or at least threatened&amp;quot; by ISIS, White House Press Secretary Josh Earnest said during a briefing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The news followed reports of a new round of U.S. airstrikes targeting ISIS positions near the Kurdish regional capital of Irbil.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;apost;Possible imminent massacre&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>ISIS fighters have besieged the town of Amerli, 70 miles north of Baquba, since the Sunni extremists swept into Iraq from Syria since mid-June.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The town&amp;apost;s fewer than 20,000 residents are without power.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;Residents are enduring harsh living conditions with severe food and water shortages, and a complete absence of medical services -- and there are fears of a possible imminent massacre,&amp;quot; U.N. High Commissioner for Human Rights Navi Pillay said this week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Their situation echoes the ordeal of Iraq&amp;apost;s ethnic Yazidis, whose plight after they were forced to flee into the mountains to escape ISIS militants triggered U.S. aid drops and the first U.S. airstrikes against ISIS.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Similar to the chaotic scenes that played out in the Sinjar Mountains, Iraqi military helicopters have been carrying out food drops and picking up Turkmen desperate to get out.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Scant defenses.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Surrounded on four sides, the 17,400 residents have had to defend themselves with only the help of local police, Masrwr Aswad of Iraq&amp;apost;s Human Rights Commission has said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>ISIS have vowed to push the Shiite Turkmen out, calling them heretics.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Turkmen are descendants of a Turkic-speaking, traditionally nomadic people, who share culture ties with Turkey.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>There are Sunni and Shiite Turkmen in Iraq, and they account for up to 3% of Iraq&amp;apost;s population.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The United Nations estimates that of the besieged Turkmen population in Amerli, roughly 10,000 are women and children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Turkmen have been subjected to violence before at the hands of Sunni extremists.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>In 2008, a truck bomb exploded in Amerli, killing more than 100 people and leveling homes and businesses.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>At the time, it was considered one of the single deadliest attacks of the Iraq War.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>U.S. airstrikes hit ISIS.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>On Wednesday, American warplanes carried out three airstrikes near Irbil, destroying a number of vehicles and a building, the U.S. military said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Among the vehicles was a Humvee, the military said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>ISIS seized a large number of military vehicles either abandoned or captured from Syrian and Iraqi forces.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Gen. Lloyd J. Austin III, commander of the U.S. Central Command, met with top officials in Baghdad and Irbil on Wednesday to discuss &amp;quot;U.S.-Iraq defense cooperation and regional security issues,&amp;quot; the U.S. Embassy in Baghdad said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Austin met with leaders including Iraqi President Fuad Masum and Prime Minister-designate Haider al-Abadi in Baghdad, and Kurdistan Regional Government President Masoud Barzani, the embassy said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>U.N. report alleges atrocities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The airstrikes in Iraq came as a U.N. human rights investigators accused both ISIS and Syrian government forces of committing war crimes and atrocities in their brutal fight in Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The U.N. report released Wednesday said that public executions, torture and mock crucifixions have become regular fixtures in ISIS-controlled areas of Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>It also said that the extremist group is forcing children to fight.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;Among the most disturbing findings in this report are accounts of large training camps, where children, mostly boys, from the age of 14 are recruited and trained to fight in the ranks of ISIS along with adults,&amp;quot; said Paulo Pinheiro, the chairman of the U.N. commission of inquiry on Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The report also accuses the regime of Syrian President Bashar al-Assad of repeatedly using chemical weapons against civilians.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The U.N. investigators said the Syrian government dropped what was thought to be chlorine gas on civilian areas on eight different occasions in April.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The government forces are believed to have made particular use of barrel bombs dropped by helicopters to unleash the gas, said Vitit Muntarbhorn, a commissioner with the inquiry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Video posted on social media purports to show several of the alleged chlorine attacks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>While CNN can&amp;apost;t independently confirm the video, it shows a number of Syrian civilians fleeing the smoky aftermath of an explosion with their faces covered.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>More video shows wounded civilians, including children, in a field hospital.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Some are having difficulty breathing, several are treated with oxygen masks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>The investigators say they hope to use their evidence to build a case for future prosecution at the International Criminal Court.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
