<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2834" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/04/24/world/africa/yemen-al-qaeda-threats" date_published="2014-04-24 22:44:35" category="world" author="Barbara Starr, CNN Pentagon Correspondent" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Threats from al Qaeda in Yemen rose recently, U.S. officials say</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">&amp;quot;There is an increased threat stream,&amp;quot; says one senior U.S. official .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="14">At least 65 suspected al Qaeda members were killed in a Yemeni-U.S. joint operation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="18">Yemeni authorities are on high alert, expecting &amp;quot;imminent retaliatory attacks,&amp;quot; an official says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 21:13:43" annotation_time="25.208666">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;There is an increased threat stream,&amp;quot; said one senior U.S. official, who spoke on the condition of anonymity.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="2">At least 65 suspected terrorists were killed in assaults from both the ground and sky in southern Yemen this week.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="3">The official added that Yemeni authorities are on high alert and expecting &amp;quot;imminent retaliatory attacks&amp;quot; from AQAP.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Threats from al Qaeda operatives in Yemen increased in recent weeks and were a reason Yemen and the United States partnered in drone strikes and counterterrorism operations over the last several days, U.S. officials told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;There is an increased threat stream,&amp;quot; said one senior U.S. official, who spoke on the condition of anonymity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>CNN has learned the United States believes there is intelligence potentially indicating specific targets in Yemen, including the U.S. Embassy there.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Other possible targets include Westerners, as kidnap victims, and Yemeni government and military installations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Although several officials stressed the U.S. Embassy in Yemen is a constant target for terrorists, one U.S. source familiar with the latest information said at least one threat against the embassy was disrupted recently.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>A separate U.S. official was not aware of a recent specific threat on that embassy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The rise in threats from al Qaeda in the Arabian Peninsula -- known as AQAP -- continues, the sources said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The uptick is of particular interest to U.S. officials because it comes after a significant effort last year to disrupt a direct threat to the U.S. Embassy in Yemen, as well as other U.S. embassies, which led to several of them being closed around the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Since the 2013 disruption and subsequent leaks to the news media about how AQAP communicates, the group has significantly cut back on its electronic communications, making it extremely difficult for authorities to track it, a separate U.S. official said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have much less vision about what they are doing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>We&amp;apost;re not totally blind, but we are not 20/20.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>We&amp;apost;re not even anywhere near 20/20,&amp;quot; said the official.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Sources emphasized the recent counterterrorism operation had been planned for weeks and was part of a broader effort to disrupt AQAP.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>At least 65 suspected terrorists were killed in assaults from both the ground and sky in southern Yemen this week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Many suspected al Qaeda militants, who survived the strikes in Abyan province, are fleeing toward Azzan in the south central part of the country, a town that could fall under the control of al Qaeda, according to a senior Yemeni government official.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>There is a lack of government and army presence in that area, that official said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The two military brigades currently in southern Shabwa province, which includes Azzan, &amp;quot;can&amp;apost;t try to follow those militants on the move and are preoccupied with securing the (liquefied natural gas) facilities,&amp;quot; the official said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The official added that Yemeni authorities are on high alert and expecting &amp;quot;imminent retaliatory attacks&amp;quot; from AQAP.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
