<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2359" link="http://cnn.com/2014/02/13/world/asia/murayama-comfort-women" date_published="2014-02-14 03:57:31" category="world" author="Euan McKirdy, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Japanese ex-prime minister meets comfort women on S. Korea tour</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Ex-Japanese P.M. met former comfort women during three-day visit to South Korea.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="22">Murayama will not meet the country&amp;apost;s president, who says she&amp;apost;s too busy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="19">Former leader is perhaps best known for his 1995 apology to victims of Japanese aggression.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="25">Tells Korean lawmakers that Abe will &amp;quot;ultimately uphold&amp;quot; 1995 Statement.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-14 00:57:45" annotation_time="48.670666">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Tomiichi Murayama, who served as the nation&amp;apost;s premier from 1994 to 1996, visited South Korea this week for a three-day visit, during which he met with former comfort women in Seoul.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="3">Murayama is perhaps best-known for his 1995 address, known as the Murayama Statement, in which he apologized to the victims of Japanese aggression during World War II.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="2">The country&amp;apost;s president, Park Geun-hye, declined to meet Murayama, citing her schedule.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="4">Kyodo news reported that Murayama told Korean lawmakers on Wednesday that that Abe has said he will &amp;quot;ultimately uphold&amp;quot; the Murayama statement, but stopped short of elaborating on when Abe made the pledge.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>While recent nationalist gestures from Japan&amp;apost;s political rulers continue to rile neighbors South Korea and China, a former prime minister is aiming to make some amends in his own way.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Tomiichi Murayama, who served as the nation&amp;apost;s premier from 1994 to 1996, visited South Korea this week for a three-day visit, during which he met with former comfort women in Seoul.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>On Tuesday, the first day of the 89-year-old&amp;apost;s trip, he attended an exhibition of art made by women who had endured sexual slavery at the hands of the Imperial Japanese Army.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>He was presented with an artwork entitled &amp;quot;Flower destroyed unbloomed&amp;quot; and shook the hands of the three former comfort women in attendance.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Murayama told them to &amp;quot;stay healthy.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>One of the three, Kang Ul-Chul, told him that the Japanese government should fully apologize and offer compensation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Murayama said Japan&amp;apost;s wartime policy of providing comfort women to its troops meant that it had committed &amp;quot;indescribable wrongdoings,&amp;quot; the Japan Times reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The number of women who were enslaved by the Japanese from around 1932 during the colonization of the Korean peninsula up to and during the World War II, is dwindling.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Hwang Keum-ja, an 89-year-old who was lured into sexual slavery in Japan&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;comfort stations&amp;quot; during World War II, died earlier this month.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Only 55 of the approximately 200,000 women subjected to the ordeal from around 1932 remain living.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The issue of comfort women, and the Japanese acknowledgement of them, is controversial and consistently topical in South Korea.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The Japanese Ministry of Foreign Affairs states: &amp;quot;Japan has extended its sincere apologies and remorse to all those women on various occasions such as an apology statement by the Chief Cabinet Secretary Yohei Kono in 1993.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The country has helped establish the Asian Women&amp;apost;s Fund in 1995, which is supported by government funds and provides assistance to former comfort women.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>But it has resisted direct payments to the victims, prompting activists and former comfort women to say leaders are avoiding officially acknowledging what happened.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Japan maintains that a 1965 treaty between the two nations have settled wartime compensation claims.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The South Korean government however does not believe this is enough.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Along with the surviving comfort women, it is calling for an official government apology, acknowledging legal responsibility for the crimes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Seoul wants Tokyo to provide direct compensation to the victims.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Murayama is perhaps best-known for his 1995 address, known as the Murayama Statement, in which he apologized to the victims of Japanese aggression during World War II.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>It was hailed as a significant step and a catalyst for improving relations between Japan and its neighbors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Murayama also spoke at Korea&amp;apost;s National Assembly this week, as part of a trip organized by Korea&amp;apost;s minor opposition Justice Party, as well as meeting members of both the ruling party and the opposition.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The country&amp;apost;s president, Park Geun-hye, declined to meet Murayama, citing her schedule.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>She has previously refused to engage with the Japanese government until it fully acknowledges South Korea&amp;apost;s historical grievances.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Japan&amp;apost;s Prime Minister, Shinzo Abe, has ruffled his East Asian neighbors&amp;apost; feathers recently through high-profile nationalistic gestures, including a visit to the Yasukuni Shrine, which enshrines the souls of some of Japan&amp;apost;s war dead -- including several war criminals, and by suggesting that the Murayama statement be revised.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Kyodo news reported that Murayama told Korean lawmakers on Wednesday that that Abe has said he will &amp;quot;ultimately uphold&amp;quot; the Murayama statement, but stopped short of elaborating on when Abe made the pledge.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Territorial disputes -- most notably the claim of both countries on the islands known as Dokdo by South Koreans and Takeshima by the Japanese -- have added to the tension.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
