<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2473" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/02/08/world/europe/uk-phone-hacking" date_published="2012-02-08 11:33:33" category="world" author="Jonathan Wald and Richard Allen Greene, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Murdoch group pays hundreds of thousands in phone-hacking suits</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">NEW: Murdoch&amp;apost;s News Group Newspapers has now settled 59 of 60 cases.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Celebrities and politicians sued News of the World&amp;apost;s publisher over phone hacking.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="7">News of the World was shut down over the hacking scandal.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="15">Police, lawmakers and an independent inquiry are all probing the scandal.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-06 20:56:35" annotation_time="35.35667">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2">London The publisher of Rupert Murdoch&amp;apost;s now defunct News of the World tabloid paid out hundreds of thousands of pounds Wednesday to settle lawsuits over phone hacking from celebrities and politicians, including a former Tony Blair spokesman.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">With Wednesday&amp;apost;s settlements, News Group Newspapers has settled 59 of the 60 lawsuits against it.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="3">The phone-hacking scandal prompted Murdoch&amp;apost;s son, News Corp. executive James Murdoch, to shut down News of the World in July.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="4">British Prime Minister David Cameron set up an independent inquiry into press ethics and practices in response to the scandal, and police are carrying out three separate investigations into elements of it: phone hacking, e-mail hacking, and police bribery.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>London The publisher of Rupert Murdoch&amp;apost;s now defunct News of the World tabloid paid out hundreds of thousands of pounds Wednesday to settle lawsuits over phone hacking from celebrities and politicians, including a former Tony Blair spokesman.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The publisher apologized for intercepting phone messages of Alastair Campbell, the Blair aide, and agreed to pay costs and damages, Campbell said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>He did not say how much the settlement was worth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>With Wednesday&amp;apost;s settlements, News Group Newspapers has settled 59 of the 60 lawsuits against it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>But former child singing star Charlotte Church, who has testified publicly about the damage phone hacking did to her personal life, has refused to settle.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Her case is expected to go to court as soon as this month.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The phone-hacking scandal prompted Murdoch&amp;apost;s son, News Corp. executive James Murdoch, to shut down News of the World in July.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The best-selling British newspaper was 168 years old.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Wednesday&amp;apost;s agreement may not end Campbell&amp;apost;s legal action against Murdoch&amp;apost;s newspaper group, lawyer Gerald Shamash said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The publisher said it would continue searching for documents related to the hacking of Campbell&amp;apost;s voice mail and disclose what it found to him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>News Group Newspapers &amp;quot;has agreed that Mr. Campbell may be entitled&amp;quot; to further legal action, Shamash said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Comic actor Steve Coogan, who also settled Wednesday, echoed the words of many who have sued over phone hacking.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;This has never been about money,&amp;quot; he said outside the court.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;Like other people who have sued, I was determined to do my part to show the depths to which the press can sink in pursuit of private information.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>British Prime Minister David Cameron set up an independent inquiry into press ethics and practices in response to the scandal, and police are carrying out three separate investigations into elements of it: phone hacking, e-mail hacking, and police bribery.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Two parliamentary committees are also investigating the scandal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The publisher of the shuttered tabloid is paying £40,000 ($63,000) and legal costs to Coogan, £45,000 ($71,000) plus costs to Liberal Democrat politician Simon Hughes, and £75,000 ($119,000) plus costs to sports agent Sky Andrew, lawyers and judges announced Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Retired soccer star Paul Gascoigne was paid £68,000 plus costs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The Murdoch group admitted both hacking his phone messages and having him followed by a private investigator, Derek Webb.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Former lawmaker George Galloway got £25,000 ($40,000) plus costs as the publisher admitted hacking his phone messages after the start of the second Gulf war.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>A number of other high-profile figures, including actors Jude Law and Sienna Miller, and former Deputy Prime Minister John Prescott, have already received settlements from Murdoch&amp;apost;s publishing group.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Its parent company, News International, said at the time that the company &amp;quot;made no admission as part of these settlements that directors or senior employees knew about the wrongdoing by NGN or sought to conceal it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>However, for the purpose of reaching these settlements only, NGN agreed that the damages to be paid to claimants should be assessed as if this was the case.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Both James and Rupert Murdoch, as well as senior executives at News International, have testified before British lawmakers examining allegations of wrongdoing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>There have been 13 arrests in connection with Operation Elveden, the Metropolitan Police investigation into bribery of police officers by journalists.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>There have been 17 arrests in relation to Operation Weeting, the phone-hacking inquiry.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Three people have been arrested in connection with both investigations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>No one has been charged.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>