<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2077" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/08/27/world/asia/australia-malaysia-mh370/index.html" date_published="2014-08-28 03:06:40" category="world" author="Jethro Mullen, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Australia: Sat phone info gives extra detail on MH370</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Official: Airline staff tried to reach the plane by satellite phone after it dropped off radar.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">The call failed, but later analysis has given experts a better idea of MH370&amp;apost;s position.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="26">The Indian Ocean search zone for the missing aircraft remains the same.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="10">Some areas a little to the south may be of &amp;quot;particular interest,&amp;quot; Australian deputy PM says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-14 12:12:06" annotation_time="37.081497">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">After Flight 370 dropped off radar on March 8, Malaysia Airlines ground staff tried to make contact with the plane using a satellite phone, Australian Deputy Prime Minister Warren Truss said at a news conference in the Australian capital, Canberra.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">The attempt was unsuccessful, he said, but subsequent analysis of the failed call has given experts a better idea of the aircraft&amp;apost;s position and where it was traveling.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="4">But some of the information that the analysts now have suggests that areas of the zone farther to the south may be of &amp;quot;particular interest,&amp;quot; he said, noting that the focus of the search continues to be refined as experts keep reviewing the available data.</sentence>
      <sentence id="26" ids_highlights="3">The search for the remains of the plane and the people on board remains primarily focused on a 60,000-square-kilometer area, roughly the size of West Virginia, in the southern Indian Ocean.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s another small sliver of information in the expanse of mystery surrounding Malaysia Airlines Flight 370.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>A failed satellite phone call suggests the missing passenger jet may have turned south slightly earlier than previously thought during its enigmatic journey, Australian authorities said Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>After Flight 370 dropped off radar on March 8, Malaysia Airlines ground staff tried to make contact with the plane using a satellite phone, Australian Deputy Prime Minister Warren Truss said at a news conference in the Australian capital, Canberra.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The attempt was unsuccessful, he said, but subsequent analysis of the failed call has given experts a better idea of the aircraft&amp;apost;s position and where it was traveling.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The latest analysis of the available data has put a focus on southern parts of the search area in the Indian Ocean, Truss told reporters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>MH370 vanished with 239 people on board during a flight that was meant to go from Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, to Beijing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The search operation, described by Australian officials as the largest in history, has so far turned up no debris from the plane.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>International aviation experts have relied on information from radar and satellites to try to plot the Boeing 777&amp;apost;s course, concluding that it went down in a remote part of the southern Indian Ocean, far off Australia&amp;apost;s west coast.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The experts are sticking to the same vast search zone announced in June, Truss said at the news conference Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>But some of the information that the analysts now have suggests that areas of the zone farther to the south may be of &amp;quot;particular interest,&amp;quot; he said, noting that the focus of the search continues to be refined as experts keep reviewing the available data.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Uncertainty over location of turn.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Flight 370 was last detected by radar flying northwest over the sea between Peninsular Malaysia and the Indonesian island of Sumatra.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>A series of subsequent communications between satellite systems and the errant plane -- known as &amp;quot;handshakes&amp;quot; -- determined that at some point, MH370 turned south toward the southern Indian Ocean.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>It was initially assumed that the southern turn took place at the northwestern tip of Sumatra.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>But the team of experts has since said there&amp;apost;s no conclusive evidence about where the turn to the south took place.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>To calculate the current search area, they said they took two approaches to the uncertainty surrounding the turn.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>They analyzed the satellite data using a range of assumed locations for the turn, and also without any assumption of where the turn took place.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The final radar detection of MH370, by the Malaysian military, occurred nearly an hour after the plane had veered off its planned course.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Three minutes later, a satellite handshake indicated that the plane was still traveling northwest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The unanswered phone call took place 14 minutes after the handshake, according to information previously released by Australian authorities.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Just over an hour later, a second handshake suggested that the plane had turned and was heading south or southeast.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s unclear from Truss&amp;apost; comments Thursday how much more clarity the analysts now have on the timing and location of the turn.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The crucial question of why the aircraft flew wildly off course also remains unanswered.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Without the aircraft&amp;apost;s wreckage and flight recorders, investigators are struggling to piece together what happened.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Undersea volcanoes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The search for the remains of the plane and the people on board remains primarily focused on a 60,000-square-kilometer area, roughly the size of West Virginia, in the southern Indian Ocean.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>An underwater search that will involve three ships is expected to start in the area next month, using a range of sophisticated sonar equipment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The process is expected to take about 12 months, Truss said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Officials hope as much searching as possible can be done in the next few months before weather conditions are likely to deteriorate, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Ships have already been mapping the undersea terrain in the isolated swath of ocean to help the searchers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Much of the geography of the area was previously unknown before MH370&amp;apost;s disappearance drew attention there.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The mapping process has revealed dramatic new challenges for the search teams.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The &amp;quot;remarkable geographic features&amp;quot; discovered by the surveying include at least two volcanoes and an area where the seafloor drops away from a depth of 600 meters (1,970 feet) to 6,600 meters (21,650 feet) over a short distance, Truss said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;It would not be safe to put the towed sonar equipment into the water if we didn&amp;apost;t have this kind of information about the seabed,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Cost of search to be shared.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Truss spoke after meeting with Malaysian Transport Minister Liow Tiong Lai and Chinese Vice Transport Minister He Jianzhong.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Liow said at the news conference that Malaysia&amp;apost;s financial contributions to the search will match Australia&amp;apost;s commitment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Australia has estimated a yearlong underwater search will cost $48 million.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>The Australian Transport Safety Bureau is overseeing the underwater search at Malaysia&amp;apost;s request.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The majority of the people on board MH370 were Chinese.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>All countries involved remain &amp;quot;cautiously optimistic&amp;quot; that the wreckage of the missing plane will be found, Truss said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
