<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2737" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/06/27/world/africa/senegals-dead-sea-lake-retba/index.html?hpt=hp_bn6" date_published="2014-06-27 09:37:53" category="world" author="Olivia Yasukawa, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Senegal&amp;apost;s &amp;apost;Dead Sea&amp;apost;: Salt harvesting in the pink lake</title>
  <keywords>lake retba,pink lake,pink lake senegal,salt harvesting,salt senegal,salt harvester</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">Bright pink lake in Senegal is as salty as the Dead Sea.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8">Salt harvesters spend seven hours a day immersed in the lake.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="25">Each bucket of salt makes them just 60 cents .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-10 21:04:01" annotation_time="37.174">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">The salt content of Lake Retba or Lac Rose, as it&amp;apost;s locally known, rivals that of the Dead Sea -- exceeding 40% salinity in some parts -- and it is a combination of the sun and a salt-loving micro-algae, dunaliella salina, which has turned the water a brilliant shade of strawberry pink.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">He works alone, chest-high in the lake, for seven hours a day with the most basic of tools -- a basket, spade and stick.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="3">Fame makes 60 cents for each bucket of salt he collects.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>On the edge of Senegal&amp;apost;s Cap Vert peninsula, a lush coastal region, lies Lake Retba ... a coral pink lake.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Nestled between white sand dunes and the Atlantic Ocean, this unique body of water was once the finishing point of the off-road car race, the Dakar Rally.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The three square kilometer fuchsia lake has been a candidate for UNESCO World Heritage status since 2005 and is fast becoming one of Senegal&amp;apost;s most popular tourist destinations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>While the rally may have shifted to South America five years ago, men and women from West Africa continue to come here for an entirely different reason -- to harvest salt.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The salt content of Lake Retba or Lac Rose, as it&amp;apost;s locally known, rivals that of the Dead Sea -- exceeding 40% salinity in some parts -- and it is a combination of the sun and a salt-loving micro-algae, dunaliella salina, which has turned the water a brilliant shade of strawberry pink.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Men once used to fish in the lake but by the 1970s, in response to ongoing droughts and economic hardship, locals began to collect and sell salt to supplement their families&amp;apost; income.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>24-year-old Moussa Fame came from Mali to work in the lake seven years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>He works alone, chest-high in the lake, for seven hours a day with the most basic of tools -- a basket, spade and stick.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>To protect his skin from the harsh salinity, Fame rubs shea butter on his body before entering the water.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;As a harvester, if you don&amp;apost;t put shea butter on your skin, the salt will damage it and cut you,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;The longer you stay inside the lake, the larger the salty water makes your wounds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>If you do not cover those wounds with shea butter, they will become worse.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>With a depth of only three meters, Fame paddles to his chosen area using a long stick to push against the bottom of the lake.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The boat he rents is called a pirogue and is made of wood -- any engine or metal fixture would immediately start to rust.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;I know where to collect the salt from.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>When the stick I am using touches the salt, I can feel it,&amp;quot; Fame said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;If I find a place, I attach my boat and use the shovel to see if there is enough salt in that place.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>After that, I put the sticks in place and start piling the salt around those sticks.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>It is estimated 1,000 people work around this lake -- 600 men and 400 women who collect 24,000 tons of salt each year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;The people working here as harvesters are Malians, some are Guineans, some Ivorians, Burkinabe and even some from Guinea-Bissau.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>There are also some Senegalese,&amp;quot; Moussa said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>It is mainly men who work as harvesters, filling their baskets with salt before heaving it over their heads into their boats.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;Sometimes I harvest 10 to 12 buckets,&amp;quot; Fame said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>By the time Fame paddles back, his 21-year-old wife, Mariame, is onshore, awaiting his return to carry the salt from boat to land.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Fame makes 60 cents for each bucket of salt he collects.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>His wife earns five cents for every bucket she transports.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>In the midday heat, men and women move between piles of salt -- transporting, drying and trading the mineral.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Over 70% of it is exported around West Africa, particularly to the Ivory Coast.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;Here, we have two different types of salt,&amp;quot; said Demba Dieng, a wholesaler who buys and re-sells salt.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;The first is called &amp;apost;medium salt.&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>This type of salt is bought by people drying fish or working in the leather industry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;The &amp;apost;big salt&amp;apost; is the second type which we use in Senegal in our food,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;However, in Europe, they use the &amp;apost;big salt&amp;apost; to melt ice on the roads.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>While most of Fame&amp;apost;s salt will be sold on, he has kept some for his family back in Mali in the hopes that one day, he can share it with his father, who also used to be a salt harvester on Lake Retba.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;It will be a gift to my mother that she will cook with,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
