<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2857" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/08/08/world/europe/turkey-election-explained" date_published="2014-08-08 11:14:51" category="world" author="Ivana Kottasova, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Turkey elects Erdogan as president</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Turkish PM Recep Tayyip Erdogan has won the country&amp;apost;s first direct presidential election.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">The president&amp;apost;s role is more formal, he represents the country as the head of the state.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">But Erdogan has already indicated he will seek more powers as the president .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-14 19:52:35" annotation_time="27.032001">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Turks have picked prime minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan to be the country&amp;apost;s first directly elected president.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">The president&amp;apost;s role is more formal, and represents the country as the head of the state -- similar to the Queen in the UK.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">But Erdogan has already indicated he would like to see more powers being transferred to the presidential palace, speaking about a &amp;quot;new era&amp;quot; in his victory speech.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Turks have picked prime minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan to be the country&amp;apost;s first directly elected president.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Erdogan secured 52% of the votes in the first round of the presidential election, narrowly avoiding a runoff, according to Turkish election board.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Turkey is a parliamentary democracy and the prime minister is the head of its government.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The president&amp;apost;s role is more formal, and represents the country as the head of the state -- similar to the Queen in the UK.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>But Erdogan has already indicated he would like to see more powers being transferred to the presidential palace, speaking about a &amp;quot;new era&amp;quot; in his victory speech.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;With the president elected directly by the citizens, all barriers between the people and the presidential palace have been removed,&amp;quot; he was reported as saying in his speech by the Turkish media.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Here is what you need to know about the historic election.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Why does Erdogan want to be president if he is more powerful as prime minister?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The former mayor of Istanbul and the leader and co-founder of the Justice and Development Party (AKP) came to power in 2003 and has been serving his third term as prime minister.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>While the constitution would have allowed Erdogan to run again when his term finishes next year, his own party rules prohibited him from seeking fourth term.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>His transition to presidency was seen as a logical step for a politician who wanted to maintain political power.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Karabekir Akkoyunlu, researcher at the London School of Economics, said the country&amp;apost;s constitution -- drawn up by the military junta in 1982 -- gave the head of state significant authority.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Erdogan, Akkoyunlu said, would likely push those to the limit by &amp;quot; invoking the &amp;apost;national will&amp;apost; he claims to embody.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>What issues will he face next?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The Kurdish peace process is one of the most pressing issues of the coming months.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Turkey passed a law in July establishing a legal framework for peace talks with the Kurdish militants to end three decades of insurgency.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Kurdish peace process is also linked with regional dynamics and the rise of the Islamic State, which is now threatening the Kurds in northern Iraq and Syria,&amp;quot; Akkoyunlu said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Erdogan will also have to work with the government in trying to tackle Turkey&amp;apost;s economic troubles.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The IMF and OECD have both warned Turkey&amp;apost;s economy remains vulnerable to dangers outside its borders.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>High inflation, low employment and the country&amp;apost;s chronic inequality are putting it at risk.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Who else was running?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The main opposition parties, the Republican People&amp;apost;s Party (CHP) and the Nationalist Movement Party (MHP) had nominated Ekmeleddin Ihsanoglu as their joint candidate.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The former secretary general of the Organization of Islamic Cooperation (OIC) was campaigning on the idea of national unity and secured 38% of the vote.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Selahattin Demirtas, a left-wing politician popular with Turkey&amp;apost;s Kurdish minority, ran for the Peoples&amp;apost; Democratic Party (HDP) and finished third with 10%.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Around 25% of people in Turkey identify themselves as Kurdish.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Why does this matter?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Turkey&amp;apost;s geographical position and cultural make-up has contributed to the country being seen as a powerful bridge between Asia and Europe.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Its membership of NATO and candidacy to join the European Union reflect its importance.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The country&amp;apost;s $800 billion economy is among the 20 biggest in the world and attracts $200 billion in foreign direct investment every year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Turkey also plays a key role in the Middle East, bordering Syria, Iraq and Iran.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
