<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2825" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/06/05/world/asia/afghanistan-singer-womens-rights/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-06-05 10:21:05" category="world" author="Monica Sarkar, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>The Afghan voice that won&amp;apost;t be silenced</title>
  <keywords>Afghanistan women&amp;apost;s rights,Afghanistan elections,Aryana Sayeed,Women in Afghanistan</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="31">Popular Afghan singer Aryana Sayeed has received death threats for dressing liberally.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="31">Sayeed says she&amp;apost;s targeted for advocating women&amp;apost;s rights.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">A poll ranked Afghanistan as the most dangerous place in the world for women in 2011.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="40">In the 1950s to 1970s, however, Afghan women could walk the streets in skirts and heels.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-09 14:35:51" annotation_time="22.147">
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">In a country ranked by a Thomson Reuters Foundation poll as the most dangerous place in the world for women in 2011, what Shabana Faryad did was brave.</sentence>
      <sentence id="31" ids_highlights="1, 2">Sayeed sings.</sentence>
      <sentence id="40" ids_highlights="4">The gallery at the top of this page shows the contrast between Afghanistan, past and present: during the 1950s to 1970s, women could walk the streets in skirts and high heels -- a far cry from the usual burqa-clad images which circulate today.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Dressed modestly, with a red headscarf loosely draped over her head and shoulders, she steps onto the stage and nervously paces back and forth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Waiting for the music to begin and break the silence, she almost misses her first note before quietly singing into the microphone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Her voice chokes when one of four judges turns his chair to face her; she awkwardly bows her head and smiles.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>But she sings more confidently when the sole female judge turns around a few minutes later.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The singer is through to the next stage.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>In a country ranked by a Thomson Reuters Foundation poll as the most dangerous place in the world for women in 2011, what Shabana Faryad did was brave.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Very brave.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Faryad was the only female contestant to have auditioned for the first series of &amp;quot;The Voice of Afghanistan&amp;quot; last year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>And the claps and cheers that loudly resounded throughout the studio came from an audience of men.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Aryana Sayeed -- a popular Afghan singer who was a judge on the show -- said she turned her chair around purely because the contestant was a woman.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;I had to do it,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;She at least had the courage to come along, to step onto the stage.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>But Sayeed says her own appearance on the show put her life at risk.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Dressed in fashionable, figure-hugging attire, certain religious hard liners were angered by the fact that her wardrobe lacked one item: a headscarf.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>In the view of her critics, women should be covered and compliant.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>As a result, Sayeed says mullahs threatened her with death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;They said that whoever kills this singer would go to heaven,&amp;quot; she recalls.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;It was getting really difficult, I couldn&amp;apost;t go anywhere.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>I was basically a prisoner in my hotel room, I had bodyguards with me all the time.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Sayeed, 28, was born and raised in Kabul and left at the age of eight with her parents and five sisters for Pakistan, where she lived for a few years before heading to Switzerland.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>She eventually settled in London in 2000.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>War and violence forced her family to flee Afghanistan.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;All I have seen and have grown up with is war, guns and problems,&amp;quot; she says, recalling an incident when a rocket hit a tree in her garden in the early hours of the morning while she and her family were sleeping.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;We used to hear the gunshots all the time, it had become so normal,&amp;quot; Sayeed says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;You heard them while you were just sitting there talking and it didn&amp;apost;t even scare you.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>I remember all that when I was a child.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>At the age of 24, after convincing her family to allow her to pursue a career as a singer -- a profession which she says is looked down upon for Afghan women -- Sayeed rose to fame in her homeland and travelled back and forth for television appearances and concerts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>She released &amp;apost;Lady of the Land of Fire,&amp;apost; her first female-empowerment song, last year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>It opens with provocative scenes of the violence and oppression experienced by Afghan women.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;Who says I am a mother to this world?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Sayeed sings.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am nothing but a burden on the son&amp;apost;s shoulders, I am a slave because I am a wife, I am a headache when I am a sister.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The video, shot on the streets of Kabul, was released during the time when the singer was receiving death threats.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Softly spoken yet self-assured, Sayeed says she is targeted because of her openness about women&amp;apost;s rights and not just because of how she dresses.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;If I just did my concerts and my music, most of these extremists would not have cared so much as they are caring right now.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>She also feels her aims are misinterpreted and that women should have the freedom to choose how they dress.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;When I talk about freedom and women&amp;apost;s rights, it&amp;apost;s not that you have to take your scarves off.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>I never say that.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>My mum wears a scarf and I respect that.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The gallery at the top of this page shows the contrast between Afghanistan, past and present: during the 1950s to 1970s, women could walk the streets in skirts and high heels -- a far cry from the usual burqa-clad images which circulate today.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;My mum was somebody who had chosen to wear a scarf, whereas my auntie would wear short skirts,&amp;quot; recalls Sayeed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;They were free to do whatever they wanted... My aunt is now having to cover up.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>She even has to cover up the new generation, her children, even more than her.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s unbelievable.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Sayeed is reminded of a story another aunt told her, about how she was walking down the street wearing a burqa and white slippers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Members of the Taliban, in power from 1994 to 2001, saw her and beat her -- for wearing the color of their flag on her feet.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>&amp;quot;This was a 60-year-old woman who had the freedom, when she was young, to go to school, work, have a normal life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>And now, even though she was wearing a burqa, they picked on her because of her shoes.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Sayeed says she regularly receives a barrage of abusive messages on her Facebook page, criticizing her for dressing liberally.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>But she is driven by those who value her work, especially girls and women who write appreciative letters and embrace her after concerts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>However, there are some fans she is particularly concerned about: after holding a ladies-only concert a couple of months ago, she received messages pleading for help.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>She says mullahs had seen clips of a group of females attending the show -- and labelled them as whores.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>&amp;quot;They were so scared; they only came out [to the concert] because of me,&amp;quot; Sayeed says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>Despite the singer&amp;apost;s efforts to reply and offer help, she has not heard back from them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s something that&amp;apost;s stuck in my mind.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>She pauses, her voice slightly breaking.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m thinking about it all the time.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>But Afghanistan has seen some advances.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="59">
          <content>Women appearing on TV were forbidden under Taliban rule: times have changed with shows like &amp;quot;The Voice.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="60">
          <content>Women also have a say in the current presidential elections.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="61">
          <content>Their right to vote was reinstated after U.S. and allied military toppled the Taliban in 2001.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="62">
          <content>&amp;quot;To other people it&amp;apost;s just an election, but it&amp;apost;s such an emotional time for me,&amp;quot; says Sayeed, &amp;quot;looking at these women voting with ink on their fingers and so much passion and hope.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="63">
          <content>They have a choice to choose a leader now, before it was never the case.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="64">
          <content>Personal reasons may stop her from participating as a judge on season two of &amp;quot;The Voice,&amp;quot; set to run soon, she explains.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="65">
          <content>But she asserts that the threats have not disheartened her.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="66">
          <content>Her next single, &amp;quot;Champion,&amp;quot; will be released this year and bears another powerful message on women&amp;apost;s rights.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="67">
          <content>&amp;quot;Champion is about, no matter what you say to me, no matter what you do to me, I&amp;apost;m not going to give up.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="68">
          <content>Fact is, there isn&amp;apost;t much that can stop Sayeed from carrying out her advocacy, which she feels is her duty to her fellow Afghan women.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="69">
          <content>&amp;quot;For me, since I&amp;apost;ve been travelling to Afghanistan, seen the women, heard the stories, seen the country from close, it has affected me so much.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="70">
          <content>It has become my number one priority, more than anything else, even my music.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="71">
          <content>And I&amp;apost;m going to carry on doing it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>