<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2058" link="http://www.cnn.com/2011/11/20/world/meast/syria-violence/index.html" date_published="2011-11-20 05:41:46" category="world" author="the CNN Wire Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Al-Assad: &amp;apost;Syria will not bow down&amp;apost;</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="24">NEW: The Local Coordination Committees say 12 are killed in violence .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="14">Officials say Arab League representatives will meet again to discuss Syria Thursday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">The Arab League rejects Syria&amp;apost;s proposed changes to a plan to send observers to Syria.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="6">Syria&amp;apost;s foreign minister says clarifications are needed to the Arab League&amp;apost;s observer plan.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-17 14:30:31" annotation_time="31.3965">
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3, 4">Meanwhile, Syria&amp;apost;s foreign minister said an Arab League plan to send observers into his country needed clarification before Syria would sign on.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="2">Arab League representatives will meet again Thursday in Cairo to discuss the situation in Syria, officials from the foreign ministries of Egypt and Jordan said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="1">The Local Coordination Committees of Syria, a network of opposition activists, said 12 people were killed on Sunday.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Officials sparred Sunday over a proposed plan to send observers into Syria as the nation&amp;apost;s president warned against military intervention.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>In an interview with the Sunday Times in the United Kingdom, President Bashar al-Assad warned that any potential military intervention against his country would lead to &amp;quot;very dire&amp;quot; repercussions, and said that Syria &amp;quot;will not bow down&amp;quot; despite international threats of economic sanctions over the government&amp;apost;s crackdown on protesters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>He accused the Arab League, which recently suspended Syria&amp;apost;s membership, of helping pave the way for western intervention.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;If they are logical, rational and realistic, they shouldn&amp;apost;t do it because the repercussions are very dire,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;Military intervention will destabilize the region as a whole, and all countries will be affected.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Meanwhile, Syria&amp;apost;s foreign minister said an Arab League plan to send observers into his country needed clarification before Syria would sign on.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;I would like to make the situation clear between us so that ... a proper decision is taken.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The situation does not bear or require hastiness or reaction,&amp;quot; Syrian Foreign Minister Walid Moallem told reporters, urging the Arab League to take more time to develop a plan that the organization&amp;apost;s foreign ministers approved last week.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;It requires a study that is rational, because clearly any analysis shows that some Arab parties want to use the Arab League as a tool to get to the (United Nations) Security Council.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Earlier Sunday, the Arab League said it had rejected changes Syria proposed to the plan.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The league said in a statement that Syria&amp;apost;s request &amp;quot;impinges on the core of the Arab peace plan&amp;quot; and would &amp;quot;radically&amp;quot; alter the observers&amp;apost; mission.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>On Wednesday, Arab League foreign ministers gave Damascus three days to implement a protocol to allow observers to enter the nation to verify whether the regime has taken measures to protect civilians.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The league&amp;apost;s statement Sunday said it had no mandate to further negotiate its with Syrian officials.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Arab League representatives will meet again Thursday in Cairo to discuss the situation in Syria, officials from the foreign ministries of Egypt and Jordan said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Syria&amp;apost;s foreign minister Sunday criticized the Arab League&amp;apost;s stance on Syria and repeated claims that &amp;quot;armed groups&amp;quot; -- not government security forces -- were responsible for violence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Arab League, they ignore the presence of armed groups, the terrorist armed groups who kill the people, and if they would recognize the presence of such groups they would not have conducted themselves in the way they are behaving,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;I would say, and I am confident of what I am saying, there will not be civil war however much they try to manufacture it, and our people are aware enough in order to get rid of such a division.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The state-run Syrian Arab News Agency said &amp;quot;huge masses&amp;quot; of Syrians rallied in the capital to reject the Arab League stance on their country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Activists said rocket-propelled grenades had hit the ruling Baath Party&amp;apost;s headquarters in Damascus.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Moallem told reporters that report was &amp;quot;completely untrue.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>CNN was not able to confirm the reports independently because of the restrictions Damascus places on foreign journalists.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The Syrian president faces increasing international pressure to step aside as his government continues an eight-month crackdown on the opposition.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The United Nations has said more than 3,500 people have been killed in the violence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The Local Coordination Committees of Syria, a network of opposition activists, said 12 people were killed on Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Al-Assad disputed reports that thousands of civilians have been killed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>His office placed the actual number at 619.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;We, as a state, do not have a policy to be cruel with citizens,&amp;quot; he told the Times.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;The important thing is to look for the wrongdoers and hold them responsible for their actions.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Al-Assad told The Sunday Times that recent attacks on the Syrian army showed he was facing armed fighters, not peaceful demonstrators.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;The conflict will continue, and the pressure to subjugate Syria will continue,&amp;quot; he told the newspaper.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;Syria will not bow down.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Al-Assad vowed he would personally fight and die to resist foreign forces, according to the Times.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>When asked how he felt seeing images of children shot, al-Assad told the Times, &amp;quot;Like any other Syrian, when I see my country&amp;apost;s sons bleeding, of course I feel pain and sorry.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Each spilt drop of blood concerns me personally.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>But my role as president is in deeds, not words and sorrow.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>My role is to think about the steps I should take to prevent more bloodshed.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Protesters in Syria are demanding al-Assad&amp;apost;s ouster and democratic elections.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Al-Assad has been in power since 2000.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>His father, Hafez, ruled Syria for three decades.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>In his interview with the Times, al-Assad said he intends to hold elections early next year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re going to have a new parliament.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>After that, we&amp;apost;re going to have a new government.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>We&amp;apost;re going to have a new constitution.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>That constitution will set the basis of how to elect a president,&amp;quot; he said, adding he would step aside if he lost a presidential election.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
