<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2811" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/05/01/world/africa/tanzania-maasai-eviction/index.html" date_published="2013-05-01 10:31:00" category="world" author="Nima Elbagir, CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Tanzania&amp;apost;s Maasai fight government, game hunters for ancestral lands</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">Tanzanian leaders threaten to evict Maasai community to create conservation corridor.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="36, 35">More than 60,000 Tanzanian Maasai live in the 4000 sq. km. that make up Loliondo region.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="42">Maasai have been repeatedly evicted from their lands since colonial era.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="10">Maasai say they will refuse to be relocated this time.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 16:27:54" annotation_time="42.233">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">The Tanzanian government is threatening to evict the local Maasai community from the area in a bid to create a 4000 square kilometer &amp;quot;conservation corridor.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="4">Maasai leaders say it means they will be evicted from their own land and will lose about 40 percent of their grazing land.</sentence>
      <sentence id="35" ids_highlights="2">More than 60,000 Tanzanian Maasai live in the 4000 sq. km.</sentence>
      <sentence id="36" ids_highlights="2">that make up Loliondo.</sentence>
      <sentence id="42" ids_highlights="3">This is not the first time the Maasai have been forcibly moved from their land.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Loliondo, Tanzania Traditional Maasai living in one of the world&amp;apost;s most famous wildlife centers are pitting themselves against the government in a fight for land.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The Loliondo region in northern Tanzania lies along the famed southern migratory route, where herds of wildebeest and zebra graze at roadsides and antelope dart around the trees.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>In colonial times it was a hunting ground for European royalty.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Today, it is Emirati royals and other wealthy visitors being granted the right to hunt, fanning a controversy that has simmered for two decades.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The Tanzanian government is threatening to evict the local Maasai community from the area in a bid to create a 4000 square kilometer &amp;quot;conservation corridor.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>They say it is to protect the wildlife -- which is also a major source of income from hunting and safaris -- from Maasai cattle overgrazing the land.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Under the plan, most of the conservation corridor will still be accessible for grazing but no one will be allowed to live there.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The other 1500 sq. km.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>will be a &amp;quot;game controlled area&amp;quot;, where hunting is permitted and access controlled.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Maasai leaders say it means they will be evicted from their own land and will lose about 40 percent of their grazing land.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Loliondo&amp;apost;s lush hills are where the Maasai take their cattle to graze during the dry season.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>To restrict their access, the Maasai say, is &amp;quot;a death sentence.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>For rural Maasai cattle provide milk, meat, blood -- and can even be used as currency.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Their survival is the community&amp;apost;s survival.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Maasai activists date their land conflicts with the current government to 1992, when they were first accused of illegal settling and ordered to move.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The same year the government granted a hunting concession to the Otterlo Business Corporation (OBC).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Owned by royals from the United Arab Emirates, the terms of OBC&amp;apost;s concession grant it hunting rights in Loliondo.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>OBC spokesman Isaak Mollel told CNN the land issue has nothing to do with his corporation, as they do not actually own land in Loliondo.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>He says, in fact, that the new conservation corridor will reduce their areas, with the government set to deduct 2,500 sq. km.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>from their hunting concession.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;Our hunting operations are guided by Tanzania wildlife acts and regulations,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;Everything is done according to procedures.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>In one Loliondo village, Maasai gathered from all over the district to discuss the issue.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Many walked for miles to get there -- eager to hear what their leaders would propose.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Elias Ngorisa is head of the Ngorongoro District Council, under which Loliondo falls.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>He has a government notice which he says details the intended eviction.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>In his hands he holds a thick dossier.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>In it, he says, are their land title deeds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Ngorisa says: &amp;quot;I can show you all the title deeds of the village land.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>How can they say that the land does not belong to the community?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is because the government wants to give the OBC, the hunting company, the Arab hunting company land for hunting without being disturbed by the local communities.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The Tanzanian government maintains it owns the land.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>In response to the Maasai allegations, the Tanzanian government referred CNN to an earlier statement in which the minister for natural resources denied OBC were a factor in the decision to evict.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The statement read: &amp;quot;It took this decision with the understanding that environment conservation is as important for eco-system protection as it is for community livelihood and community development ... Surely no government in the world can be blamed for meeting its responsibilities to such high levels.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>More than 60,000 Tanzanian Maasai live in the 4000 sq. km.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>that make up Loliondo.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Human rights groups say every one of them will be affected if the eviction goes through.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Ngorisa told CNN they were pleading for a government rethink.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>He said: &amp;quot;If [they] do this, the livelihoods of these people, the citizens of this country, will be lost and we are saying we will not move from here.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is our last weapon,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is better to die rather than to just leave this land.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>This is not the first time the Maasai have been forcibly moved from their land.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>They were evicted repeatedly in colonial times and then again to make way for East Africa&amp;apost;s famed wildlife reserves.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>The Maasai say each move eroded their livelihoods and way of life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>This time they say they will not be moved, whatever the consequences.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>The Tanzanian parliament has announced plans to convene a two-day debate to discuss options.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
