<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2424" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/03/05/world/europe/dinosaur-predator-europe/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-03-05 23:35:28" category="world" author="Elizabeth Landau, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Meet Europe&amp;apost;s largest dinosaur ever: 33 feet long and 4-inch teeth</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Torvosaurus gurneyi is said to be a new species.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">A new study says it lived about 150 million years ago and roamed Europe.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="15">It probably ate herbivorous dinosaurs on the Iberian Peninsula.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 19:43:51" annotation_time="9.981501">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;I suppose it wouldn&amp;apost;t be a good idea to cross the way of this dinosaur,&amp;quot; said Christophe Hendrickx, doctoral candidate at the New University of Lisbon in Portugal.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">Torvosaurus gurneyi lived about 150 million years ago.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="3">The dinosaur appears to have been a carnivore that probably ate herbivorous dinosaurs.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>At about 33 feet long, weighing 4 to 5 tons and baring large blade-shaped teeth, the dinosaur Torvosaurus gurneyi was a formidable creature.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;I suppose it wouldn&amp;apost;t be a good idea to cross the way of this dinosaur,&amp;quot; said Christophe Hendrickx, doctoral candidate at the New University of Lisbon in Portugal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Thanks to Hendrickx and paleontologist Octavio Mateus, Torvosaurus gurneyi may have the distinction of being the largest terrestrial predator found in Europe.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Hendrickx and Mateus describe this dinosaur in a new study in the journal PLOS One.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The remains of Torvosaurus gurneyi were discovered at the Lourinha Formation, a fruitful site of dinosaur bones north of Lisbon.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Before this study, bones that scientists say belong to the new species were thought to belong to Torvosaurus tanneri, a North American dinosaur species.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>But comparisons between the remains of the Portuguese and North American specimens suggest that they warrant distinct species names.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>For instance, Torvosaurus tanneri had at least 11 teeth, while Torvosaurus gurneyi had fewer, scientists said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Torvosaurus gurneyi lived about 150 million years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The continents had previously all been one land mass, but by the time of this dinosaur, the Iberian Peninsula had broken off from North America, Hendrickx said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;The study provides compelling evidence in support of the hypothesis that temporary connections between North America and Europe existed during the Late Jurassic, and these allowed for intercontinental faunal mixing,&amp;quot; Gregory Erickson, a Florida State University paleobiologist not involved in the study, said via e-mail.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Subsequent geographic isolation led to the development of distinct species, Erickson said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The Tyrannosaurus, Carcharodontosaurus and Giganotosaurus from the Cretaceous period -- defined as 145.5 million to 65.5 million years ago -- were larger than Torvosaurus gurneyi.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>But this European giant seems to have been a powerful predator.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The dinosaur appears to have been a carnivore that probably ate herbivorous dinosaurs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Its teeth were nearly 4 inches long; its skull was thought to be about 45 inches long.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The environment where it lived was tropical, with temperatures ranging from 86 to 95 degrees Fahrenheit.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>A diverse collection of dinosaurs roamed the area.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;The fauna was certainly dominated by dinosaurs,&amp;quot; Hendrickx said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Specimens that most likely belong to this species include an upper jaw bone, teeth and partial tail vertebrae, remnants discovered in 2003.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Hendrickx proposes other material found at the same site in Portugal also belongs to Torvosaurus gurneyi.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>A tibia and femur seem to fit the profile, as do embryos that Hendrickx, Mateus and colleagues described in the journal Nature last year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Torvosaurus gurneyi could have been covered with proto-feathers, given evidence from closely related dinosaurs, the scientists said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>But as for its colors, no one yet knows.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Erickson called the discovery exciting.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>It demonstrates that large theropods -- meat-eating dinosaurs -- lived in Europe during the Late Jurassic.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;Torvosaurus gurneyi was the T. rex of its time,&amp;quot; Erickson said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Hendrickx named the species after James Gurney, an artist and writer known for the illustrated &amp;quot;Dinotopia&amp;quot; book series about -- guess what?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>-- a society of people and dinosaurs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
