<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2216" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/03/31/world/europe/ukraine-crisis/index.html" date_published="2014-03-31 07:59:32" category="world" author="Jason Hanna, Marie-Louise Gumuchian and Alla Eshchenko, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Germany: Putin says he&amp;apost;s pulling some troops back from Ukraine border</title>
  <keywords>Ukraine crisis,Dmitry Medvedev ,Crimea</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7">NEW: U.S. State Department: Pullback &amp;quot;would be a welcome preliminary step&amp;quot; if accurate.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">German Chancellor Angela Merkel, Russian President Vladimir Putin talk by phone.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="28">Ukrainian officials say Russia is repositioning some troops massed on its border.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="10">Russian Prime Minister goes to Crimea in the highest-level visit since Moscow annexed region.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-25 13:58:45" annotation_time="70.14733">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2">Potentially easing a diplomatic standoff with the West, Russian President Vladimir Putin told Germany Chancellor Angela Merkel on Monday that he&amp;apost;d ordered a partial withdrawal of Russian troops from his country&amp;apost;s border area with Ukraine, Merkel&amp;apost;s office said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">U.S. State Department spokeswoman Jen Psaki said that if reports about Russia removing troops from the border were accurate, &amp;quot;it would be a welcome preliminary step.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="4">The news about Russian troops came on the day that Russian Prime Minister Dmitry Medvedev traveled to Crimea -- the highest-level visit from Moscow since Russia annexed the region -- in part to unveil measures aimed at integrating the peninsula into the Russian economy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="28" ids_highlights="3">Before Merkel&amp;apost;s announcement, a U.S. official said Monday it was too soon to conclude whether Russia was moving its troops away from the Ukraine border.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Potentially easing a diplomatic standoff with the West, Russian President Vladimir Putin told Germany Chancellor Angela Merkel on Monday that he&amp;apost;d ordered a partial withdrawal of Russian troops from his country&amp;apost;s border area with Ukraine, Merkel&amp;apost;s office said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Putin made the comment to Merkel in a phone call about Ukraine, her office said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The Kremlin made no mention of a withdrawal in its description of the call but said the two leaders discussed Ukraine, including &amp;quot;possibilities for international assistance to restore stability.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Further details about Putin&amp;apost;s reported order weren&amp;apost;t immediately available.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>But a withdrawal may ease tensions simmering since Russia annexed Ukraine&amp;apost;s Black Sea peninsula of Crimea this month -- a move that has led to the worst East-West relations since the Cold War.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Earlier Monday, Russian media reported that one Russian infantry battalion was being moved from the border area to its base deeper into Russia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>U.S. State Department spokeswoman Jen Psaki said that if reports about Russia removing troops from the border were accurate, &amp;quot;it would be a welcome preliminary step.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;We would urge Russia to accelerate this process,&amp;quot; Psaki said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;We also continue to urge Russia to engage in a dialogue with the government in Kiev to de-escalate the situation, while respecting the sovereignty and territorial integrity of Ukraine.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The news about Russian troops came on the day that Russian Prime Minister Dmitry Medvedev traveled to Crimea -- the highest-level visit from Moscow since Russia annexed the region -- in part to unveil measures aimed at integrating the peninsula into the Russian economy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Ukrainian and Western officials for weeks have voiced alarm about Russia&amp;apost;s reported military buildup on Ukraine&amp;apost;s eastern border, which has raised fears that Russian troops would enter the Ukrainian mainland.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Russia may have 40,000 troops near its border with eastern Ukraine and another 25,000 inland on alert and prepared to go in, two U.S. officials have told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Moscow has said it had no intention of ordering armed forces to cross over into its neighbor, insisting its troops have been conducting exercises.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>But Putin has said Russia reserves the right to protect ethnic Russians in Ukraine from what he calls threats from Ukrainian nationals -- a reasoning he also used in this month&amp;apost;s annexation of Crimea.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Putin&amp;apost;s conversation with Merkel came a day after U.S. Secretary of State John Kerry and Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov held talks in Paris about ways to defuse the crisis over Ukraine.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Kerry told Lavrov that progress depended on a Russian troop pullback from Ukraine&amp;apost;s borders but no breakthrough was announced.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The West imposed sanctions against some Russian officials because of the Crimea crisis and threatened more if tensions weren&amp;apost;t eased.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Ukraine: Russian troops &amp;apost;conducting unclear maneuvers&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Amid reports that Russia may have started withdrawing from the border, but before the Merkel announcement, government sources in Kiev told CNN that Russian troops were not backing away but were repositioning their forces farther north.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>One Ukrainian official said intelligence indicated that Russian troops are &amp;quot;conducting unclear maneuvers at the Ukrainian border.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Meanwhile, Russian state news agency ITAR-Tass reported Monday that one Russian infantry battalion was being withdrawn from a region bordering Ukraine.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>That battalion, having finished military exercises, is returning to its base in Russia&amp;apost;s Samara region, hundreds of miles away from the border, the outlet reported, citing Russia&amp;apost;s Defense Ministry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Details about how many troops are in that battalion weren&amp;apost;t immediately available.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>During a daily briefing Monday, Ukrainian Foreign Ministry spokesman Evhen Perebyinis said Russia had not told Kiev about the intentions of any military forces in the area.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;At some border districts the troops are withdrawn, in others they approach the border,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are concerned about this movement of the army.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>U.S. official: &amp;apost;Too soon&amp;apost; to discern Russian intentions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Before Merkel&amp;apost;s announcement, a U.S. official said Monday it was too soon to conclude whether Russia was moving its troops away from the Ukraine border.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The official was reacting to statements from Ukraine about Russian troop maneuvers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have nothing to back that up one way or the other so far,&amp;quot; the official said, speaking on condition of anonymity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Barring any significant withdrawal from the border, the Russians are positioned &amp;quot;in a way (that) they could conduct a swift movement into Ukraine,&amp;quot; the official said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Russian Prime Minister in Crimea.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Medvedev arrived in Crimea&amp;apost;s capital, Simferopol, for talks Monday on social and economic development.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;As a result of entering Russia, not a single citizen of Crimea should lose anything -- they need only to benefit from it,&amp;quot; Medvedev said in a news conference carried by Russian state television.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;Citizens need to understand that they&amp;apost;re citizens of a powerful country.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>The Premier met with Crimean officials, including its Prime Minister, the speaker of the regional parliament and mayor of Sevastopol, among others.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>He said Crimean state salaries and pensions should be raised to Russian levels, as should the pay for military personnel, while compulsory social insurance would be introduced to the region next year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Economic measures.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Unveiling a list of measures for the region, Medvedev also said Moscow would make Crimea a special economic zone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Tax breaks may also be offered to companies, he added, calling for mortgage programs to be introduced to the region and for a review of water supply projects.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>After visiting a school and children&amp;apost;s hospital, Medvedev added that Crimea needed modern medical equipment and reforms in education.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>He offered to establish a new federal university.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
