<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2485" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/01/12/world/meast/syria-violence/index.html" date_published="2014-01-12 14:57:13" category="world" author="Saad Abedine, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Nearly 700 killed in Syria rebel infighting</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="14">NEW: Kerry says he&amp;apost;s confident Syrian opposition will attend Paris talks.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="29">U.N humanitarian chief visits Damascus, expresses concern for displaced persons.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">Activists say 697 people killed in nine days of rebel fighting.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="2">Al Qaeda-affiliated ISIS forces battling Free Syrian Army fighters, other factions.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-14 16:47:37" annotation_time="58.724">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="3">Nearly 700 people have been killed in nine days of fierce clashes between an al Qaeda affiliate and other Islamist and rebel groups, activists said Sunday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="4">Forces from the al Qaeda-affiliated Islamic State of Iraq and Syria have increasingly come into conflict with Free Syrian Army fighters and other hard-line factions opposing the Syrian regime, while ISIS attempts to impose its strict form of Islamic Sharia law on areas coming under its control in northern Syria.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;I am confident the Syrian opposition will come to Geneva,&amp;quot; Kerry said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="29" ids_highlights="2">On a visit to Damascus on Sunday, the United Nations humanitarian chief expressed concern for communities cut off by the months of fighting between government and rebel forces.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Nearly 700 people have been killed in nine days of fierce clashes between an al Qaeda affiliate and other Islamist and rebel groups, activists said Sunday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Forces from the al Qaeda-affiliated Islamic State of Iraq and Syria have increasingly come into conflict with Free Syrian Army fighters and other hard-line factions opposing the Syrian regime, while ISIS attempts to impose its strict form of Islamic Sharia law on areas coming under its control in northern Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>In the last nine days, 697 people have been killed in the fighting, activists said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The victims include 351 combatants from the Islamist and non-Islamist rebel battalions, 246 ISIS fighters, and 100 civilians, the Britain-based Syrian Observatory for Human Rights said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The activist group said the deaths took place between January 3 and January 12.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Among the 100 civilians killed in the clashes, 21 were executed by ISIS in the children&amp;apost;s hospital in Qadi Askar in the northern rebel stronghold of Aleppo, the group said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>CNN cannot independently verify daily death tolls, but the United Nations has said more than 100,000 people have been killed in Syria since 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Foreign ministers meet.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The violence came as the &amp;quot;Friends of Syria&amp;quot; group of foreign ministers, including U.S. Secretary of State John Kerry, convened in Paris on Sunday in a last-ditch attempt to persuade the Syrian opposition to attend a peace conference in Geneva, Switzerland, at the end of January.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The Western-backed rebels are deeply divided on whether to go and will announce a decision on January 17.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;There is no military solution to the violence,&amp;quot; Kerry said Sunday about a proposed new round of peace talks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;There is no other alternative to saving the nation of Syria than negotiations.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Kerry said he has &amp;quot;no expectations&amp;quot; about the success of the so-called Geneva II talks, but that the sides need to enter the meetings with the goal of &amp;quot;waging an even stronger effort to provide for this political solution.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am confident the Syrian opposition will come to Geneva,&amp;quot; Kerry said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Kerry added that Russian leaders have assured him they&amp;apost;ll attend.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>In a statement, the alliance of mainly Western and Gulf Arab countries called on armed groups to &amp;quot;respect democratic and pluralistic values&amp;quot; and allow humanitarian access.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>It condemned the presence of foreign fighters in Syria, &amp;quot;both those fighting with the regime such as Hezbollah and other Iranian backed forces, and those fighting within other extremist groups,&amp;quot; and demanded their immediate withdrawal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>It urged democratic opposition forces to keep opposing groups affiliated with al Qaeda.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;We fully support the Supreme Military Council of the Free Syrian Army and other democratic opposition forces in their action against the Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant,&amp;quot; it said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant is another name for ISIS.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Uneasy alliance.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>For months, the rebel groups maintained an uneasy alliance as they fought to topple Syrian President Bashar al-Assad&amp;apost;s government.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>But now, the infighting has threatened to tip the balance among rebel forces toward militant groups and away from more secular brigades.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In a statement, the opposition Syrian Coalition media office condemned &amp;quot;any and all violations&amp;quot; and said armed gangs were taking advantage of the infighting between ISIS and the Free Syrian Army.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The statement, signed by Syrian Coalition media office director Khalid Saleh, cited these as &amp;quot;illegal practices, intimidating civilians, and theft, taking place all over Syria; particularly in the northern parts of the country.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;We call on FSA brigades to work with civil revolutionary bodies and local councils operating in those areas to address the threat of those gangs, and make sure those gangsters are hunted down and brought to justice,&amp;quot; the statement said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>In Iraq, where at least nine people were killed and more than 40 wounded in several car explosions on Sunday, security forces in Mosul said they have detained 137 ISIS suspects in a series of raids in the city over the past seven days.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>U.N. official in Damascus.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>On a visit to Damascus on Sunday, the United Nations humanitarian chief expressed concern for communities cut off by the months of fighting between government and rebel forces.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am particularly worried about the reports of starvation,&amp;quot; Valerie Amos said in a statement after meeting with government officials as well as humanitarian organizations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;The world must do more for all the people who are displaced.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Many families are living in abandoned buildings, schools or in makeshift shelters, without enough food, clean water or medicine.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>We must help them to get through this very cold winter,&amp;quot; she said after visiting a shelter in rural Damascus.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Amos recognized steps taken by the government to approve visas so aid can get in.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;But we need to do more in a crisis of this magnitude,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
