<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2950" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/08/26/world/asia/china-bo-xilai-trial-transparency/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2013-08-27 03:40:17" category="world" author="Alexis Lai, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Was Bo Xilai&amp;apost;s trial in China truly transparent?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Bo Xilai trial proceedings posted on live courthouse micro-blog, attracting more than 590,000 followers.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">China hailed micro-blog as &amp;quot;historic transparency&amp;quot; but flow of information was selective.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="25">Analysts: &amp;quot;Selective transparency&amp;quot; was one-off gesture for high-profile show trial.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="30">Unintended effect is raised public expectations of a fair trial in China, analysts say.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-11 18:23:25" annotation_time="53.39133">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Case updates, photos, excerpts of video testimony and partial transcripts were posted on the court&amp;apost;s Twitter-like Sina Weibo account during the course of the five-day trial of the former high-flying politician on charges of bribery, embezzlement and abuse of power, attracting more than 590,000 followers.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">State media rushed to herald the micro-blog as a reflection of &amp;quot;historic transparency&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;historic progress for the rule of law&amp;quot; in a country that regularly clamps down on the free flow of information and dissent.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="3">For all the party&amp;apost;s efforts to create an impression of fairness and transparency in the Bo trial, analysts interpreted them as one-off gestures tailored for a high-profile case.</sentence>
      <sentence id="30" ids_highlights="4">At the same time, human rights analysts believe the theatrics will have the unintended effect of raising public expectations of a fair trial in China.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Amid the swirl of claims and counter-claims involving sex, lies, and witness videotapes, one of the most intriguing aspects of Bo Xilai&amp;apost;s so-called &amp;quot;trial of the century&amp;quot; in China has been the live micro-blogging of proceedings from the courthouse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Case updates, photos, excerpts of video testimony and partial transcripts were posted on the court&amp;apost;s Twitter-like Sina Weibo account during the course of the five-day trial of the former high-flying politician on charges of bribery, embezzlement and abuse of power, attracting more than 590,000 followers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>State media rushed to herald the micro-blog as a reflection of &amp;quot;historic transparency&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;historic progress for the rule of law&amp;quot; in a country that regularly clamps down on the free flow of information and dissent.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>But while the court&amp;apost;s micro-blog offered unprecedented glimpses into what was widely viewed as a tightly-orchestrated show trial, the flow of information was nonetheless a selective drip-feed that sparked questions about its objectivity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Some Sina Weibo users complained of deleted comments that went against the party line of the trial&amp;apost;s fairness and the certainty of Bo&amp;apost;s guilt.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Speculation -- in mainstream as well as social media -- about what lay beyond the micro-blog and what was excluded from the transcripts underscored the lack of openness the party claimed to offer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>People with detailed knowledge of the court proceedings told CNN that the micro-blog left out details that may have placed Bo in a good light and Bo&amp;apost;s claims of threats made against him and his family during party investigations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>And while criminal trials in China are theoretically open to the public, in practice, the gallery is as open as the state wants it to be.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Bo&amp;apost;s trial lacked independent observers -- Bo&amp;apost;s family, government officials, and a handful of pre-approved journalists were allowed into the courtroom -- while foreign media were relegated to a hotel across the street.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;For that class of trial, the Bo Xilai trial was a showcase for how to be more transparent about what goes on inside the courthouse,&amp;quot; said Nicholas Bequelin, a Hong-Kong-based researcher for Human Rights Watch, comparing it to the information vacuum during the brief, closed trials of Bo&amp;apost;s wife and his former right-hand man Wang Lijun last year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;But that&amp;apost;s not real transparency; it&amp;apost;s selective transparency,&amp;quot; Bequelin added.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;The party remains in charge of what gets said to the public.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Joshua Rosenzweig, another Chinese human rights researcher based in Hong Kong, agreed there was a relatively high amount of information released compared to the vast majority of Chinese criminal trials, but he questioned the motives behind it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;One motivation is to control the narrative.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Part of what spawns rumors online is the lack of transparency,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;When you try to take control of the release of information, it draws people into the information and doesn&amp;apost;t give as much opportunity for straying from that narrative.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Concurrently, the trial comes against a heightened crackdown on activism under President Xi Jinping -- with regular arrests of micro-blog users for &amp;quot;rumor mongering&amp;quot; and activists for &amp;quot;assembling a crowd to disrupt order in a public place.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Over the past several months, state media has reported the arrests of numerous journalists and ordinary citizens across China for &amp;quot;fabricating online rumors&amp;quot; on their Weibo accounts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>On Friday, prominent human rights advocate Xu Zhiyong was formally arrested for disturbing public order after he was detained last month.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The same day, Charles Xue, a major liberal activist with more than 12 million followers on Sina Weibo, was detained by Beijing police on prostitution charges, prompting online speculation that Xue was the victim of a set-up.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The crackdown on dissent is a similar attempt to manage public opinion by setting boundaries around key opinion-makers with large followings on micro-blogging platforms, Rosenzweig said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Bequelin said the arrests reflect how the Xi administration is &amp;quot;very conservative on political matters.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Their rationale is that China is going through a turbulent period and they need to make some structural adjustments to the economy, civil services, all the acute problems that the system is facing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Therefore, they cannot to afford to have anything destabilize the country.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>For all the party&amp;apost;s efforts to create an impression of fairness and transparency in the Bo trial, analysts interpreted them as one-off gestures tailored for a high-profile case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;This was a sensitive case because it revealed so much of the inner workings of the party and the abuses of power and the elite, so it needed a trial that was a match for that,&amp;quot; Bequelin said, calling the proceedings a &amp;quot;good-quality show trial.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;But in no way does it indicate a systemic shift in China toward greater standards in the administration of justice,&amp;quot; he added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Rosenzweig agreed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s far too early to see this as a transformative event that will trickle down into criminal proceedings,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>At the same time, human rights analysts believe the theatrics will have the unintended effect of raising public expectations of a fair trial in China.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;At the end of the day, Chinese criminal trials are primarily about reasserting social and political order over society, not providing a process that pays considered attention to the rights of defendants,&amp;quot; Rosenzweig said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Chinese public is desirous of a criminal process that is more rights-based.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>So seeing this in practice in such a spectacular form, while it might be a one-off, does set a precedent in people&amp;apost;s memories of what a criminal trial can look like.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>In China, the role of a judge is not to determine guilt, but rather to decide on a sentence based on information provided by the prosecution.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The role of the defense is extremely limited, and criminal cases tend to be open-and-shut, with a conviction rate of 99.9%.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>While Bo&amp;apost;s long and fiery rebuttal of the charges against him is unlikely to alter what is an all-but-certain guilty verdict, the fact that he defended himself at all is highly unusual in the Chinese criminal system.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>It is precisely this tension between a party bent on preserving its power and the public&amp;apost;s push for greater rights that will fuel the development of the rule of law in the China, according to analysts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;Twenty years ago, [the party] didn&amp;apost;t need to go through all this,&amp;quot; Bequelin said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;But now, if you want to give the citizenry the impression that someone got a fair trial, the bar is much higher.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
