<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2247" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/09/06/world/india-rape-charge-asaram-bapu/index.html" date_published="2013-09-06 10:12:30" category="world" author="Ramy Inocencio, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Holy man castrates self after India guru Asaram Bapu arrested for raping 16-year old</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Indian guru Asaram Bapu, 72, charged with raping 16-year-old school girl.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">Bapu follower, Baba Premdas, castrates self, found bleeding in home.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="8">Bapu has denied all sexual assault allegations.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="13">India has gained international attention over series of rapes since December 2012.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-26 19:04:59" annotation_time="153.60234">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Police have charged the 72-year old guru with raping a 16-year-old schoolgirl at one of his ashrams, or religious centers, in August.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">Authorities in the northern Indian state of Uttar Pradesh found Baba Premdas, a 60-year old follower of Bapu, bleeding at his home in Amethi from apparently self-inflicted wounds, city police chief Alankrita Singh told CNN.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="3">Bapu has denied the sexual assault allegations leveled by the teenage girl and her parents, both devotees of the guru.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="4">This month&amp;apost;s unfolding rape case against Bapu is just the latest in a series of sexual assault incidents in India since late 2012 that have gained high-profile attention both for their frequency and ferocity.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Hong Kong A Hindu holy man castrated himself in India Wednesday following the arrest of popular preacher Asaram Bapu, revered by millions across the country for his sermons on enlightenment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Police have charged the 72-year old guru with raping a 16-year-old schoolgirl at one of his ashrams, or religious centers, in August.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Authorities in the northern Indian state of Uttar Pradesh found Baba Premdas, a 60-year old follower of Bapu, bleeding at his home in Amethi from apparently self-inflicted wounds, city police chief Alankrita Singh told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Premdas was admitted to a local hospital and then taken to a bigger health facility for surgery where his condition &amp;quot;is stable&amp;quot;, said Singh.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Asked whether his act was related to the arrest of Asaram Bapu, Singh added, &amp;quot;We have heard such things, but all this is unconfirmed.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;Some say it was because of Bapu&amp;apost;s arrest,&amp;quot; said Singh to AFP earlier, &amp;quot;some say it was because he feared ending up in Bapu&amp;apost;s situation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>No one knows.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Bapu has denied the sexual assault allegations leveled by the teenage girl and her parents, both devotees of the guru.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The elderly preacher has also claimed he is physically incapable of rape but police say medical tests show him to be in good shape.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;The team of doctors is saying he is perfectly, medically, mentally and physically fit,&amp;quot; said Ajayal Lamba, Deputy Commissioner of Police in Jodhpur.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Bapu, also referred to as the &amp;quot;godman&amp;quot; in local Indian media, is currently in jail awaiting trial after a court rejected his bail plea earlier this week, public prosecutor Anand Purohit told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The prosecution plans to present a detailed dossier of the charges in the trial soon, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>This month&amp;apost;s unfolding rape case against Bapu is just the latest in a series of sexual assault incidents in India since late 2012 that have gained high-profile attention both for their frequency and ferocity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>It was the gang rape and murder of a 23-year-old student in New Delhi last December that galvanized Indian society and the media in particular, to examine the pervasive incidence of rape and other forms of violence against women.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The barbarity of the crime ignited a wide-ranging discussion across all levels of the Indian media and prompted multiple debates in the national and regional assemblies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Stung into action by public outrage, the government instituted new laws and crucially stricter punishments, which includes the death penalty when victims are killed or left in a vegetative state.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Furthermore in a sharp departure with previous practice, predatory behavior such as voyeurism, stalking and groping can now lead to arrest and punishment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>India&amp;apost;s court system is now making greater use of fast-track trials to prosecute the most heinous and high-profile crimes against women.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Local and national media have maintained their spotlight on sexual assaults and other violence against women, leading to a torrent of disturbing reports following last December&amp;apost;s horrific rape incident.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>In March, at least five men from a local tribe gang-raped a Swiss woman camping with her husband in a forest in India&amp;apost;s Datia district.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>A court convicted six men to life in prison four months later.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>In April, a 4-year-old Indian girl was raped by a 35-year-old man in India&amp;apost;s central Maharashtra state.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The girl suffered brain damage and was in a coma for two weeks before dying from cardiac arrest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>And in June, at least three men gang-raped a 31-year-old American tourist in northern India after she visited the Vashishth Temple after midnight.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>She accepted a ride from the group after failing to find a taxi.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>They drove her to a wooded area where they assaulted her.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>While such incidents have been covered extensively by international news media, an even larger number of cases are only reported in domestic Indian news outlets -- and an unknown number simply go unreported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Just this week in local media, the Times of India reported two men gang-raped a 27-year-old woman who had gone to a local dairy in northern Uttar Pradesh state, the Hindustan Times reported at least six to seven girls were lured to and raped at a deserted steel mill south of Mumbai over the past half year, and the Indian Express reported the story of a 14-year-old girl who was allegedly raped by two people over several months in western Gujarat state.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Villagers discovered the girl was pregnant but later miscarried twin babies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>According to India&amp;apost;s National Crime Records Bureau, the country recorded 24,923 cases of reported rape in 2012 -- a 57% rise in reported cases since 2003.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>This number is widely considered to be extremely underreported for a country of more than 1 billion people.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The United States, with a population of more than 310 million, recorded 270,000 cases of rape in 2010, the most recent year for which national rape statistics are available.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
