<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2817" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/08/27/world/asia/japan-fukushima-health-effects/index.html?hpt=ias_c2" date_published="2014-08-27 08:04:45" category="world" author="Yoko Wakatsuki and Madison Park, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>TEPCO found liable in landmark Fukushima suicide case</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="11">TEPCO ordered to pay out in suicide case linked to Fukushima .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4, 3">Woman set herself on fire four months after Fukushima disaster.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="17">Fukushima government releases data showing more cases of thyroid cancer.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2015-01-30 14:52:48" annotation_time="34.884003">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">Four months after three reactors melted down at the Fukushima plant following a devastating earthquake and tsunami, Hamako Watanabe and her husband lost their home, their jobs and the prospect of restoring their lives.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">She doused herself in kerosene and set herself on fire after slipping into depression.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="1">The Fukushima District Court ordered TEPCO to pay 49 million yen ($471,063 U.S.) to her family, in a ruling that found a link between the nuclear accident and Watanabe&amp;apost;s death.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="3">The Fukushima Prefectural Government found more cases of thyroid cancer, with 57 people confirmed cases and 46 others listed as possible cases, according to data released this week.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Four years after the meltdown at the Fukushima Daiichi nuclear plant, questions about the lingering physical and mental health toll of the disaster persist.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The Fukushima District Court ruled Tuesday in favor of a family who filed a landmark lawsuit blaming Tokyo Electric Power Company (TEPCO), the plant operator of the crippled nuclear reactor, for the suicide of a woman in 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Four months after three reactors melted down at the Fukushima plant following a devastating earthquake and tsunami, Hamako Watanabe and her husband lost their home, their jobs and the prospect of restoring their lives.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>She doused herself in kerosene and set herself on fire after slipping into depression.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Her husband, Mikio Watanabe, found her charred body.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;We lost everything,&amp;quot; her widower told CNN in 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;We were forced to evacuate.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>We lost our jobs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>I lost my wife in such a terrible way.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>I really lost everything.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The Fukushima District Court ordered TEPCO to pay 49 million yen ($471,063 U.S.) to her family, in a ruling that found a link between the nuclear accident and Watanabe&amp;apost;s death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is well assumed that the stress caused by sudden loss of the base of her life against her will and unknown future in evacuation was unbearable for her,&amp;quot; according to the court ruling.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>A spokeswoman of TEPCO Mayumi Yoshida said: &amp;quot;We express deep condolence for the loss for Mrs. Hamako Watanabe.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>We will examine the ruling closely and continue to deal with it sincerely.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Thyroid cancer cases monitored.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>In the wake of the worst nuclear disaster since Chernobyl in 1986, the local government began monitoring the health of residents who were under the age of 18 at the time of the March, 2011 incident.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The Fukushima Prefectural Government found more cases of thyroid cancer, with 57 people confirmed cases and 46 others listed as possible cases, according to data released this week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The risk of thyroid cancer increases in people who&amp;apost;ve been exposed to high doses of radiation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Children are more sensitive to radiation and at risk for a longer period of time than adults, according to medical literature on thyroid cancer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The cancer rate -- 57 out of 296,026 -- is high compared to known international statistics, but it&amp;apost;s difficult to link the nuclear accident to the rates of pediatric thyroid cancer, according to the Fukushima prefecture&amp;apost;s health office.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The high rate may be attributed to the thorough method of testing for thyroid cancer, according to the office.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Hisakatsu Kotani, from the Fukushima prefectural government&amp;apost;s health research section, said there were no patterns detected between the cases of thyroid cancers and high radiation areas.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;Experts have been saying this is not the time yet to see any health impact by the accident,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In the case of Chernobyl, thyroid cancer cases in children reached a peak about 10 years after exposure, according to a report analyzing radiation exposure and the risk of pediatric thyroid cancers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>A scientific review published in 2011, found that pediatric thyroid cancers only account for 0.5 to 3% of all types of cancers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>That review also found that girls have four times higher frequency for pediatric thyroid cancer than boys.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Of the 104 people who were diagnosed with potentially cancerous tumors at Fukushima, 68 were females and 36 were males.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>More than half of them, 58, had surgery to remove the growth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>