<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2093" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/04/17/world/africa/boko-haram-explainer/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-04-17 06:14:18" category="world" author="Faith Karimi and Chelsea J. Carter, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Boko Haram: A bloody Nigerian insurgency, a growing challenge</title>
  <keywords>Nigeria boko haram,Nigeria kidnapped schoolgirls,bring back our girls</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="9">Boko Haram&amp;apost;s aim is to impose strict enforcement of Sharia law in Nigeria.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8">The name translates to &amp;quot;Western education is sin&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="13">The group was founded 12 years ago by Mohammed Yusuf, a charismatic cleric.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="14">Nigerian police killed him in 2009 in an incident captured on video and posted online .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-17 14:32:43" annotation_time="60.247">
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">The name translates to &amp;quot;Western education is sin&amp;quot; in the local Hausa language.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="1">The militant group says its aim is to impose a stricter enforcement of Sharia law across Africa&amp;apost;s most populous nation, which is split between a majority Muslim north and a mostly Christian south.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="3">The group was founded 12 years ago by Mohammed Yusuf, a charismatic cleric who called for a pure Islamic state in Nigeria.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="4">Police killed him in 2009 in an incident captured on video and posted to the Internet.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>(CNN)Boko Haram&amp;apost;s escalating danger is indisputable.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The militant group has bombed schools, churches and mosques; kidnapped women and children; and assassinated politicians and religious leaders alike.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>It made headlines again recently with the abduction of 230 schoolgirls in the town of Chibok in northeastern Nigeria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>After a fierce gunbattle with soldiers, the militants herded the girls out of bed and onto buses, and sped off.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Only a few dozen of the girls have escaped.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>What exactly is Boko Haram, and why has it turned into a Nigerian synonym for fear and bloodshed?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>What does &amp;apost;Boko Haram&amp;apost; mean?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The name translates to &amp;quot;Western education is sin&amp;quot; in the local Hausa language.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The militant group says its aim is to impose a stricter enforcement of Sharia law across Africa&amp;apost;s most populous nation, which is split between a majority Muslim north and a mostly Christian south.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>In recent years, its attacks have intensified in an apparent show of defiance amid the nation&amp;apost;s military onslaught.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Its ambitions appear to have expanded to the destruction of the Nigerian government.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>How long has it been around?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The group was founded 12 years ago by Mohammed Yusuf, a charismatic cleric who called for a pure Islamic state in Nigeria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Police killed him in 2009 in an incident captured on video and posted to the Internet.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The crackdown, some say, made Boko Haram more violent and defiant.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Abubakar Shekau took control of the group and escalated the attacks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>It murdered and kidnapped Westerners, and started a bombing campaign that targeted churches, mosques and government buildings.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Why not just kill Abubakar Shekau?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>One word: elusive.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Questions have swirled about Shekau, including whether he&amp;apost;s dead or alive.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Even his age is unknown -- estimates range between 35 and 44.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>In recent years, the Nigerian military has touted his death, only to retract its claim after he appeared alive and vibrant in propaganda videos.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>He uses the alias Darul Tawheed, and analysts describe him as a ruthless loner and master of disguise.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>He does not speak directly with members, opting to communicate through a few select confidants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Why would an Islamist militant group target the Muslim north?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Despite its religious fanaticism, Boko Haram does not consider all Muslims as supporters and allies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>There have been suggestions that it attacks certain mosques because members have spoken out against it and helped federal officials with their crackdown.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Its attacks are aimed at striking fear at the heart of the local population to prevent cooperation with the government, analysts say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Does the north support the group?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Although the northern populace mostly abhors the violence, there is considerable local sympathy and support for Sharia law, seen by many as the only way to end what is widely regarded as a corrupt and inept government.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Poverty is prevalent in the northern region, and as the military struggles to halt Boko Haram&amp;apost;s attacks, the militant group is winning perhaps its most important battle: making Nigerians question government competency.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Rights groups have accused local authorities of human rights violations in the fight against the group, adding to the anti-government sentiment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>What&amp;apost;s the West doing to help?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The United States has put a $7 million bounty on Shekau&amp;apost;s head.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>It also designated Boko Haram as a foreign terrorist network last year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Though it has provided technical and financial support to the Nigerian teams battling the insurgency, there has been a reluctance to put boots on the ground unless there&amp;apost;s a direct national security threat to the West.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Boko Haram&amp;apost;s attacks have been limited primarily to Nigeria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>I don&amp;apost;t live in Nigeria, so why should I care?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>With a population of 175 million, Nigeria is Africa&amp;apost;s most populous nation and is considered a political and economic powerhouse in the continent.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The key U.S. partner is rich in oil, a major trading partner with China, and is the hub of global business in the region.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>And as we&amp;apost;ve learned with Mali, any unresolved local Islamist insurgency has the potential of spiraling into a world problem.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Last year, Shekau released a statement vowing to attack the United States and Europe.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>&amp;quot;Our strength and firepower is bigger than that of Nigeria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Nigeria is no longer a big deal to us, as far as we are concerned.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>We will now comfortably confront the United States of America,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Does it have ties to al Qaeda?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>The U.S. says Boko Haram has links to the al Qaeda affiliate in West Africa and to extremist groups in Mali.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>What other attacks has the group conducted?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Just this week, a massive explosion ripped through a bus station in the Nigerian capital, killing at least 71 people.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>In a video, Shekau said the group was behind the attack.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>In November, the group abducted dozens of Christian women, most of whom were later rescued by the military.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Some were pregnant or had children, and others had been forcibly converted to Islam and married off to their kidnappers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>In 2011, a Boko Haram suicide attack on the United Nations building in Abuja killed at least 25 people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
