<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2263" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/11/22/world/europe/london-slaves-accused-questions/index.html" date_published="2013-11-22 16:38:30" category="world" author="Peter Wilkinson, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>How to recover after decades of slavery?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">A couple is alleged to have held three women captive in London for more than 30 years.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">Experts and charities explain how they might recover from their ordeal.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="14">Time of the essence when suspected victims of slavery or imprisonment are rescued.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="23">Captives in similar situations draw strength from each other, experts say.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-18 09:15:04" annotation_time="29.769669">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">London Three &amp;quot;extremely traumatized&amp;quot; women are being cared for by a charity after managing to leave a London house where they had allegedly been held captive for more than 30 years.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">Experts and charities explain how they might recover from their ordeal.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="3">Time is of the essence when suspected victims of slavery or imprisonment are rescued, and the first moments are known as the &amp;quot;golden hour.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="4">Captives in similar situations draw strength from each other, Reed said, just as the three women who escaped this year after 11 years of sexual abuse in Cleveland, U.S., did.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>London Three &amp;quot;extremely traumatized&amp;quot; women are being cared for by a charity after managing to leave a London house where they had allegedly been held captive for more than 30 years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>One of the women -- a 30-year-old Briton -- &amp;quot;appears to have been in servitude for her entire life,&amp;quot; Metropolitan Police Detective Inspector Kevin Hyland said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>She and the other two women, a 57-year-old from Ireland and a 69-year-old from Malaysia, have been taken to a place of safety.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Experts and charities explain how they might recover from their ordeal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>How are the three women faring?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>A television documentary on forced marriages relating to the work of Freedom Charity prompted one of the victims to call for help; that organization&amp;apost;s founder Aneeta Prem told CNN the women were coping despite their ordeal.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;ve seen them on a number of occasions,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;They&amp;apost;re doing remarkably well considering how harrowing it&amp;apost;s been for them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Every effort has been made to ensure they&amp;apost;re being taken care of, but it&amp;apost;s going to be a very long journey.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;Now we&amp;apost;ve heard of the arrests of the two people allegedly involved in this and that&amp;apost;s going to be another journey in itself.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s going to be very difficult.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>We&amp;apost;re really pleased with the work that we&amp;apost;ve done in partnership with the police and they&amp;apost;re to be commended for taking this seriously.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>How can victims of slavery or abuse be rehabilitated?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Time is of the essence when suspected victims of slavery or imprisonment are rescued, and the first moments are known as the &amp;quot;golden hour.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Ann Reed, anti-trafficking response co-ordinator for the Salvation Army which helps trafficking victims in the UK for the first 45 days, said it was very important to quickly give them back their self-worth.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;Many victims will have had no opportunity to make decisions for themselves, even down to the smallest things like when to sleep or what to eat.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;So it&amp;apost;s important to put them on a road to recovery by giving them a safe environment, allowing them to choose when to eat and sleep, making them feel at home, offering them kindness and compassion.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>It can be as basic as playing cards with the victims to put them at their ease, she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Each case is different, with this latest being the most extreme one that Reed said she had ever heard about.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;I assume it will take many years for the victims in this case to recover, although we do not know the full details.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a complete one-off.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>How do people who have been held captive find resilience?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Captives in similar situations draw strength from each other, Reed said, just as the three women who escaped this year after 11 years of sexual abuse in Cleveland, U.S., did.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In that notorious case one of the victims, Michelle Knight, credited Gina DeJesus -- with whom she shared a dark room measuring about 7 feet by 11½ feet -- for saving her life.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;I never let her fall, and she never let me fall,&amp;quot; Knight told the trial of her tormentor Ariel Castro.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;She nursed me back to health when I was dying from his abuse.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>My friendship with Gina is the only good thing to come from this situation.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>She returned the favor, at a cost to herself, placing herself in between Castro and DeJesus, taking on physical and sexual abuse herself to protect her friend, said Frank Ochberg, a pioneer in trauma research who testified in the case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Being the oldest, Knight often served as doctor, nurse and pediatrician for Amanda Berry and the young child that Castro fathered.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>She acted as the midwife, when it was born, delivering Berry&amp;apost;s baby in a plastic swimming pool.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Somehow, Knight, Berry and DeJesus kept hope.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>As Knight said, &amp;quot;We said we&amp;apost;ll all get out alive some day and we did.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Castro was sentenced to life imprisonment but was later found hanging in his prison cell.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>How many more victims of domestic slavery are there?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Authorities have rescued about 1,200 men and women in England and Wales since July 2011, according to the Salvation Army.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Many of those victims have endured sexual abuse in brothels, forced labor or domestic servitude.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>UK Special Envoy for Human Trafficking Anthony Steen told CNN he was not surprised by this case as there were likely to be many cases of domestic slavery in the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;We don&amp;apost;t know the number but we know it&amp;apost;s pretty huge.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Domestics are hidden away,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;The difference between slavery when it was manifest in America -- as it was in England -- was that you could see it everywhere,&amp;quot; Steen said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;Since then having abolished it, it&amp;apost;s grown, it&amp;apost;s got bigger and bigger -- in fact they say it&amp;apost;s between 10 and 20 times the size it was in the 1800s.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Steen said the largest number of people involved in slavery in Britain were in brothels, and that group was followed by men held against their will in debt bondage.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>&amp;quot;Shadow City&amp;quot; was the title of one recent report into human trafficking in London, which explored where the abuses were taking place.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;Increasingly the authorities and many residents in London know there is a criminal activity called human trafficking,&amp;quot; it concluded.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>&amp;quot;What they don&amp;apost;t usually know, accurately, is what human trafficking actually constitutes and what forms are taking place around them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Most London residents imagine that it does not touch directly on their lives -- that the exploitation takes place in brothels run by foreign gangs controlling foreign women.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>But it&amp;apost;s nearer than they think.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>The Salvation Army&amp;apost;s Ann Reed said if anyone had concerns about neighbors, they should contact police.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Causes for suspicion could be if there were several people living in a house, people buying large amounts of food, inhabitants struggling physically or those who were malnourished.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>They may not go often, or be under the control of others.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>How do victims of domestic servitude live?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Such victims often sleep on the floor in the kitchen, eat the leftover remains of the household and have no days off, Steen said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>&amp;quot;Domestic slavery is rampant particularly in the Middle East countries, in Africa and in Europe.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>By and large it&amp;apost;s people who have had their passports removed, they have no pay and are exploited and used.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s not trafficking but slavery by any other word, except that you don&amp;apost;t see it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>The problem with this case is that you never know when it will appear: with millions of houses and people it&amp;apost;s all behind closed doors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>This exposes a problem in all western countries.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s not the police you should blame it&amp;apost;s the next-door neighbor, but you don&amp;apost;t know what to look for.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="59">
          <content>&amp;quot;These people will be damaged for life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="60">
          <content>They will never recover.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>