<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2617" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/04/13/world/europe/vatican-pope-cardinals/index.html" date_published="2013-04-13 11:11:41" category="world" author="Hada Messia and Laura Smith-Spark, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Pope Francis tasks cardinals with studying reform of Catholic Church</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Pope Francis asks eight cardinals to look at ways to reform the Catholic Church.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">Vatican: The move follows suggestions made when cardinals met last month.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">The group includes U.S. Cardinal Sean O&amp;apost;Malley from Boston.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="3">The cardinals will hold their first meeting in October, the Vatican said.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-03 07:21:10" annotation_time="30.661667">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Rome Pope Francis has appointed a group of eight cardinals from around the world to look into ways of reforming the Catholic Church, the Vatican said Saturday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="3">The group, which includes U.S. Cardinal Sean O&amp;apost;Malley from Boston, will examine ways to revise the Vatican constitution, Pastor Bonus, which sets the rules for running the Roman Curia, or church hierarchy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="4">The cardinals -- who come from North America, Latin America, Africa, Asia and Europe -- will first meet in October, the Vatican said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">The move follows on from suggestions made during the General Congregations, a series of meetings that brought together all the cardinals last month before they elected Francis as pope, the Vatican said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Rome Pope Francis has appointed a group of eight cardinals from around the world to look into ways of reforming the Catholic Church, the Vatican said Saturday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The group, which includes U.S. Cardinal Sean O&amp;apost;Malley from Boston, will examine ways to revise the Vatican constitution, Pastor Bonus, which sets the rules for running the Roman Curia, or church hierarchy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The cardinals -- who come from North America, Latin America, Africa, Asia and Europe -- will first meet in October, the Vatican said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The move follows on from suggestions made during the General Congregations, a series of meetings that brought together all the cardinals last month before they elected Francis as pope, the Vatican said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The other seven cardinals are: Giuseppe Bertello, president of the Vatican City State governorate; Francisco Javier Errazuriz Ossa from Chile; Oswald Gracias from India; Reinhard Marx from Germany; Laurent Monsengwo Pasinya from the Democratic Republic of the Congo; George Pell from Australia; and Oscar Andres Rodriguez Maradiaga from Honduras.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>An Italian bishop, Monsignor Marcello Semeraro, will act as secretary for the group.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Pope Francis has already been in touch with the chosen cardinals, the Vatican said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The Catholic Church has faced calls for reform in the wake of scandals involving the sexual abuse of children by priests and allegations of corruption.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The Rev. Thomas Rosica, issuing guidance on behalf of the Vatican, said the group of cardinals was just that -- &amp;quot;not a commission, committee or council.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>It &amp;quot;has no legislative power and its main function is to &amp;apost;advise&amp;apost; the pope,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;The group will not in any way interfere in the normal functions of the Roman Curia, which helps the Pope in the daily governance of the Church.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The group&amp;apost;s formation, exactly a month after Francis was elected, shows that the pope &amp;quot;listens attentively&amp;quot; to what the cardinals say, Rosica said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The document the cardinals are studying is the Apostolic Constitution of Pope John Paul II, known as the Pastor Bonus, which was published in 1988.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>CNN Vatican analyst John Allen, who&amp;apost;s also a correspondent for the National Catholic Reporter, wrote that the news was &amp;quot;a signal that major reform may be on the horizon.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;Strikingly, there was only one member of the Roman Curia among the eight cardinals tapped to assist the pope.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The rest come from various parts of the world, with at least one representing each continent,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The group will be coordinated by Rodriguez, from Tegucigalpa, who speaks several languages and was himself seen as possible contender for the papacy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>In Honduras, &amp;quot;Rodriguez has long led the pack in terms of moral authority and social influence,&amp;quot; Allen wrote in a profile ahead of the papal election, or conclave.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
