<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2211" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/02/13/world/meast/mideast-gaza-greek-statue-apollo/index.html" date_published="2014-02-13 12:25:29" category="world" author="Nic Robertson and Talal Abu Rahma , CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Gaza fisherman hooks statue of ancient Greek god Apollo</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6">NEW: &amp;quot;Treasure pulled out of the sea&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Fisherman Jwdat Abu Ghrb says he discovered the statue off Gaza.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">The statue appeared on eBay with a starting price of $500,000, authorities say.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-14 17:21:33" annotation_time="12.5145">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2">Gaza When Jwdat Abu Ghrb spotted a dark shape last summer in the waters off Gaza, where he was diving for fish, he initially thought it was a corpse.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">He described the half-ton object as &amp;quot;treasure pulled out of the sea.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">A local armed brigade took control of the statue, and someone listed it for sale on the online auction site eBay, with a starting price of about $500,000, according to authorities.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Gaza When Jwdat Abu Ghrb spotted a dark shape last summer in the waters off Gaza, where he was diving for fish, he initially thought it was a corpse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;I was afraid,&amp;quot; he told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;I put on my goggles, dove underneath and still couldn&amp;apost;t tell what it was.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>I resurfaced and got some help from other people and family members and came back, and after full four hours of trying we managed to get it out of the water and I was shocked by what I found.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>It was a life-size bronze statue, believed to be a 2,500-year-old depiction of the ancient Greek god Apollo.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>He described the half-ton object as &amp;quot;treasure pulled out of the sea.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;I thought it was made of gold; I was going to be rich,&amp;quot; Ghrb said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;So I took it home to hide it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;But then others got involved.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>A local armed brigade took control of the statue, and someone listed it for sale on the online auction site eBay, with a starting price of about $500,000, according to authorities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The posting raised suspicions among officials in the Ministry of Tourism and Antiquities and the Interior Ministry in Gaza, which is governed by the Palestinian Islamist group Hamas.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The antiquities authority and the Interior Ministry opened an investigation into what they said they suspected was an illegal attempt to sell the work of art.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is against the law to sell an artifact found in the Palestinian territories and Gaza in an illegal manner,&amp;quot; Ahmad Al-Burch, head of the antiquities department at the Ministry of Tourism and Antiquities in Gaza, told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>He said the case was being handled by the Ministry of the Interior, while the antiquities authority looks after the statue.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Authorities there asked that the statue, as a historical artifact found in Gaza, be handed over; they have hidden it from public view.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>But in a Gaza gold store, a man who displayed video of the statue told CNN that he has custody of it and that it is in safe hands, but -- if someone wants to buy it -- that would be possible.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Government officials promise that the statue will not be sold and that they will start restoration and display it after an investigation into its discovery is completed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are not denying that the statue was found in the sea -- as a matter of fact, that is a very authentic and real story,&amp;quot; Al-Burch said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>A green spot -- a sign of decay -- has formed on the leg of the statue, which is exposed to the air.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are trying to preserve the statue to show it for the public in the near future.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>He said the antiquities authority was working on a plan for the statue to be displayed in world-class museums around the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Museum authorities in Geneva, Switzerland, have offered to help repair and preserve the statue, and plan for its eventual display in Gaza, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>For Ghrb and his family, the discovery seems unlikely to land them the financial security they had hoped for with a sale.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>They are instead hoping to net a reward for the find, which has excited archaeologists around the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
