<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2074" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/06/18/world/asia/australia-great-barrier-reef-whc/index.html?iref=allsearch" date_published="2014-06-18 18:10:58" category="world" author="Hilary Whiteman, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Australia given another year to act on Great Barrier Reef</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">World Heritage Committee gives Australia another year to address issues with Great Barrier Reef.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Committee has warned it may be added to danger list.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="22">Reef suffering effects of weather events, coastal development, crown-of-thorns starfish.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="7">Boasts the greatest biodiversity of any World Heritage Site.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-28 13:47:18" annotation_time="69.87434" mapping_time_divergence="17.468584">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1, 2">The World Heritage Committee has given Australia another year to prove it&amp;apost;s doing enough to protect the Great Barrier Reef or suffer the humiliation of having it enter the list of sites in danger.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="4">Stretching 2,000 kilometers down the coast of the state of Queensland, the Great Barrier Reef boasts the greatest biodiversity of any World Heritage Site.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="3">Most of the damage was inflicted by tropical cyclones, the report concluded, as well as coral predation by the crown-of-thorns starfish and coral bleaching, mostly caused by warmer water.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The World Heritage Committee has given Australia another year to prove it&amp;apost;s doing enough to protect the Great Barrier Reef or suffer the humiliation of having it enter the list of sites in danger.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The country has been scrambling to ensure adequate measures are in place after a damning review of the reef&amp;apost;s health and safety at the last committee meeting in 2013.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The World Heritage Committee said on Wednesday it is still concerned about planned coastal developments, including planned new ports and liquified natural gas facilities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>However, World Heritage Center director Kishore Rao said in a statement, &amp;quot;UNESCO is confident the overall direction towards next year&amp;apost;s decision is a positive one.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Australian Environment Minister Greg Hunt declared the year delay &amp;quot;a positive outcome for Australia and we can be proud of our achievements in protecting the Great Barrier Reef World Heritage Area.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Rich in biodiversity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Stretching 2,000 kilometers down the coast of the state of Queensland, the Great Barrier Reef boasts the greatest biodiversity of any World Heritage Site.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s home to hundreds of species of coral, fish, bird and mollusks, but also runs along a busy coastline lined with farms, towns and beaches that attract millions of tourists each year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Conservationists say not enough is being done to protect the region from the burden of business interests, particularly a planned coal port at Abbot Point, near the city of Bowen.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;The first step must be to immediately ban the dumping of dredge spoil in the Great Barrier Reef World Heritage Area.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Dredging and dumping for new port developments pollutes Reef waters, and the majority of Australians want to see an end to this outdated practice,&amp;quot; said the World Wildlife Fund&amp;apost;s Australia reef campaigner Richard Leck.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>In a report released in April, UNESCO &amp;quot;noted with concern&amp;quot; proposals to dump three million cubic meters of dredge spoil inside the World Heritage area from the Abbot Point site.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>It said it also &amp;quot;regrets&amp;quot; the approval for the dredge spoil to be dumped &amp;quot;prior to (the government) having undertaken a comprehensive assessment of alternative and potentially less impacting development and disposal options.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>In a statement following the Committee&amp;apost;s extension of the deadline on Wednesday, Minister Hunt defended the decision, saying the approval of the Abbot Point development &amp;quot;complied with Australia&amp;apost;s obligations under the World Heritage Convention, was subject to rigorous environmental assessment and applied Australia&amp;apost;s world-leading net benefit approach.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;apost;Years of neglect&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The degradation of the Great Barrier Reef has been occurring for decades, according to scientific reports and anecdotal evidence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>In a speech on Tuesday in Washington, D.C., actor and director Leonardo DiCaprio declared he&amp;apost;d seen the &amp;quot;devastation&amp;quot; firsthand.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;What once had looked like an endless underwater utopia is now riddled with bleached coral reefs and massive dead zones,&amp;quot; he said, comparing his experience diving on the Great Barrier Reef 20 years ago to a dive at the same location two years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The same year, in 2012, the then environment minister Tony Burke admitted that years of neglect had contributed to a sharp drop in the reef&amp;apost;s coral coverage.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;There&amp;apost;s no doubt there&amp;apost;s been a level of neglect for decades which if it had been dealt with otherwise we&amp;apost;d be in a much better situation now,&amp;quot; Burke told the Australian Broadcasting Corporation, at the time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>He was responding to a report from the Australian Institute of Marine Science (AIMS) and the University of Wollongong that the reef had lost half of its coral cover in the last 27 years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Most of the damage was inflicted by tropical cyclones, the report concluded, as well as coral predation by the crown-of-thorns starfish and coral bleaching, mostly caused by warmer water.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Battered by cyclones.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Images released this week by the Catlin Seaview Survey show the devastating effects of Cyclone Ita, a category five tropical cyclone, which hit the region in April.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Before and after images show colorful coral snapped and flattened by waves whipped by fierce winds, which smash reefs, especially those not far from the surface.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;There is a myriad of increasing and cumulative impacts on the Great Barrier Reef.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>We can control impacts such as fishing, coastal development and marine debris.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>However we do not have the same control over storms and cyclones,&amp;quot; said Ove Hoegh-Guidberg, Catlin Seaview Survey&amp;apost;s chief scientist.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;Ensuring that our coral can bounce back from these disturbances is at the heart of the matter,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The government says it&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;absolutely committed&amp;quot; to protecting the Great Barrier Reef and is spending around $180 million dollars each year to improve the reef&amp;apost;s health.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>However, it remains to be seen whether it&amp;apost;s enough to protect what the environment minister has in the past called a &amp;quot;vast and priceless ecosystem.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
