<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2347" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/03/31/world/meast/egypt-al-jazeera-trial" date_published="2014-03-31 13:27:13" category="world" author="Ian Lee, Heba Fahmy and Jason Hanna, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Jailed Al Jazeera journalists denied bail</title>
  <keywords>Egypt Al Jazeera Trial,Jailed journalists Egypt</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Journalists were arrested December 29 at a Cairo hotel.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">The three are being held on terrorism-related charges.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">They deny charges, saying they were simply doing their jobs.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="1">The trial has drawn international condemnation from human rights groups.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-02 14:23:36" annotation_time="32.80933">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2, 4">Cairo An Egyptian court on Monday again denied bail to three Al Jazeera journalists who are jailed on terrorism-related charges in a case that has drawn international condemnation from human rights groups.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">The three were arrested December 29 at a Cairo hotel room and later charged with joining what the government says is a terrorist group -- the Muslim Brotherhood -- as well as broadcasting false information and working in Egypt without permits.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">The accused have denied the allegations against them, saying they were simply doing their jobs.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Cairo An Egyptian court on Monday again denied bail to three Al Jazeera journalists who are jailed on terrorism-related charges in a case that has drawn international condemnation from human rights groups.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Correspondent Peter Greste, producer Mohamed Fahmy and producer Baher Mohamed were allowed outside a caged dock to address the court in a hearing Monday, each taking the opportunity to deny allegations that they were affiliated with the banned Islamist group Muslim Brotherhood.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The three were arrested December 29 at a Cairo hotel room and later charged with joining what the government says is a terrorist group -- the Muslim Brotherhood -- as well as broadcasting false information and working in Egypt without permits.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The Egyptian government says they distorted their coverage in favor of ousted President Mohamed Morsy and the Muslim Brotherhood.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The accused have denied the allegations against them, saying they were simply doing their jobs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Fahmy told the court that he and his colleagues worked in public rather than in secrecy, and covered Egypt as they would other countries.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>He questioned how any journalist could be labeled a terrorist.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Their lawyers also took up the issue of Fahmy&amp;apost;s health.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Fahmy, a former CNN producer, injured his shoulder before his arrest in December while working as bureau chief for Al Jazeera English in Cairo.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>He has complained about not getting proper medical treatment while in prison and says that because of the lack of treatment, he no longer has full use of his right arm.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>On Monday, the defense team asked that Fahmy have his shoulder operated on at a hospital.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Earlier this month -- nearly three months after his arrest -- he was taken to a civilian hospital for the first time for a shoulder scan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Baher told the court Monday that his wife was in the final stages of pregnancy and he wanted to see his child when he was born.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Greste said that he and his colleagues posed no threat or danger inside the country or outside.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Human rights groups have criticized the trial, saying the arrests indicate authorities in Egypt are stifling dissent and freedom of the press.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The case comes amid a crackdown on the Muslim Brotherhood after the military&amp;apost;s overthrow of Morsy, Egypt&amp;apost;s first democratically elected president, in July.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Morsy, who had been a Muslim Brotherhood leader, was ousted after mass protests against his rule.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Morsy was elected in 2012, a year after a popular uprising ended Hosni Mubarak&amp;apost;s three decades of one-man rule.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>During Monday&amp;apost;s hearing the court, as it has previously, denied the journalists&amp;apost; request for bail.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The trial was adjourned until April 10.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
