<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2087" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/03/17/world/meast/lebanon-travel-food/index.html" date_published="2013-03-18 03:20:31" category="world" author="Salma Abdelnour, Special for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Beyond hummus and kebabs: Touring a delectable Lebanon</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="12">Many Beirut restaurants serve a different dish of the day at lunchtime, usually something that reminds patrons of their mother&amp;apost;s cooking.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="18">In the town of Becharre, the local specialty is fresh minced lamb rolled up with bulgur wheat to form giant meatballs .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="19">In Tripoli, the iconic pastry shop Abdel Rahman Hallab specializes in regional pastries.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="33">No traveler should turn down an invitation to a Lebanese home for a meal.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 19:38:45" annotation_time="14.0815">
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="1">Just about every Lebanese restaurant in Beirut serves a different dish of the day at lunchtime, usually something deliciously humble that reminds many patrons of their mother&amp;apost;s cooking.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="2">In northern Lebanon, in the town of Becharre near the famous cedar tree forests, the local specialty is kibbeh mishwiyeh: fresh minced lamb rolled up with bulgur wheat to form giant meatballs the size of tennis balls, stuffed with caramelized onions and pine nuts and grilled until crunchy on the outside.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="3">Nearby in Tripoli, Lebanon&amp;apost;s second-largest city, the iconic pastry shop Abdel Rahman Hallab specializes in regional pastries like halawit jibneh - soft ricotta-like cheese rolled in pastry and topped with sugar syrup - and sfiha, small savory pies topped with spicy beef or lamb and pine nuts.</sentence>
      <sentence id="33" ids_highlights="4">Food adventures can keep any determined eater busy every minute of a visit to Lebanon, but even the most restless road-tripper shouldn&amp;apost;t turn down an invitation to a Lebanese home for a meal.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Getting anyone in Lebanon to weigh in on where to find the best shawarma or falafel is asking for trouble.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The country&amp;apost;s most popular pastimes are, without question, eating and debating, so expect a heated argument, especially since Lebanon is jammed with incredible restaurants, street-food stalls and bakeries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Besides eating and talking about food, the Lebanese also love to feed their guests, so meals with friends and family can go on for hours and include dozens of different dishes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Any visitor with a big appetite, a little patience, and an adventurous spirit is bound to eat more and better in Lebanon than virtually anywhere else in the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>I&amp;apost;m biased.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>I&amp;apost;m Lebanese, although living in New York these days.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Two summers ago I moved back to Beirut for a year and wrote my memoir, &amp;quot;Jasmine and Fire: A Bittersweet Year in Beirut.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Although I&amp;apost;d spent my childhood in Beirut during the Lebanese civil war of 1975 to 1990, I&amp;apost;d been exposed to only a fraction of the country&amp;apost;s mind-boggling variety of food.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>So on my recent return to Lebanon, I made a point to go on food adventures across the country, from the cedar-covered mountains in the north down to the ancient city of Tyre in the south.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>For travelers to Lebanon who want to get a deeper sense of the country&amp;apost;s food culture beyond the well-known staples of hummus, tabbouleh and kebabs, Beirut is an excellent place to start.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s packed with classic family-style restaurants, imaginative chefs, street stalls serving food like kaak (sesame bread), and bakeries that turn out fresh Arabic bread and the hot zaatar flatbreads known as man&amp;apost;ouches.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Just about every Lebanese restaurant in Beirut serves a different dish of the day at lunchtime, usually something deliciously humble that reminds many patrons of their mother&amp;apost;s cooking.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Recurring hits include kibbeh - a national specialty made with lamb, bulgur wheat, onions and pine-nuts baked into a savory pie or into meatballs soaked in minty yogurt sauce - or any of a variety of slow-cooked stews known as yakhnes, served over vermicelli-laced rice with garlicky bits of lamb and braised vegetables topped with homemade yogurt.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Lunch also often includes vibrant salads made with local greens like purslane, and savory pastries stuffed with spiced chard and sweet onions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>In Beirut, some excellent places to sample dishes like these and many more are Al Balad - a downtown favorite - and Tawlet, an innovative restaurant in the hopping Mar Mikhael neighborhood.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>After eating around Beirut for a few days, it would be a shame not to take a least a daytrip or two outside the city.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Lebanon is relatively small, so getting up to the northern tip of the country or all the way down south takes only about two hours, barring horrendous traffic.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>In northern Lebanon, in the town of Becharre near the famous cedar tree forests, the local specialty is kibbeh mishwiyeh: fresh minced lamb rolled up with bulgur wheat to form giant meatballs the size of tennis balls, stuffed with caramelized onions and pine nuts and grilled until crunchy on the outside.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Nearby in Tripoli, Lebanon&amp;apost;s second-largest city, the iconic pastry shop Abdel Rahman Hallab specializes in regional pastries like halawit jibneh - soft ricotta-like cheese rolled in pastry and topped with sugar syrup - and sfiha, small savory pies topped with spicy beef or lamb and pine nuts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>With any travel to towns near the border with Syria, like Tripoli, it&amp;apost;s important for travelers to be aware of the changing and potentially volatile situation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Along the Mediterranean coast south of Tripoli is the seafood-centric town of Batroun.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Local restaurants such as Jammal serve bizrieh - tiny fish, fried and piled in huge mounds on platters for guests to eat by hand, and topped only with squirts of fresh lemon.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Batroun also specializes in a wonderful style of kibbeh balls, made with fish instead of meat.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Classic local cafes like The Garage serve Batroun&amp;apost;s renowned sweet-and-tart lemonade, made from the local citrus harvest and served ice-cold.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Just 45 minutes from Beirut is Byblos, a historic coastal city with stunning ancient Roman ruins and a well-preserved Crusader-era castle.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>But among the archeological attractions it would be a shame to miss out on a platter of fresh local Sultan Ibrahim fish at Bab El Mina restaurant.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Fried, drizzled with lemon, and served with crunchy pita bread coated in olive oil, it goes perfectly with a crisp Lebanese beer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Baalbeck, in the Bekaa Valley, is the agricultural heart of Lebanon, and a road-trip there from Beirut leads past the town of Chtaura, where farms produce some of the Middle East&amp;apost;s most sought-after dairy products.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Pick up a labneh (strained yogurt) sandwich drizzled with mint and sea salt and rolled into soft, papery khibz markouk bread.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>About an hour south of Beirut is Tyre, a coastal city dating back to Alexander the Great.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Here fishermen take boats out from the ancient harbor and return with fish to deliver to local restaurants.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The best ones, like Le Phénicien, turn the day&amp;apost;s catch - such as luqqos, a mild white fleshy Mediterranean fish - into simple but exquisitely fresh preparations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Food adventures can keep any determined eater busy every minute of a visit to Lebanon, but even the most restless road-tripper shouldn&amp;apost;t turn down an invitation to a Lebanese home for a meal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>On a lucky day, the main course might be m&amp;apost;loukhiyeh, a fragrant, soupy stew made from mallow leaves topped with tender spiced chicken and served over rice, with a tangy vinegar and onion dressing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>In homes, as at restaurants, the meal will likely start with a mezze - a spread of dishes that usually includes hummus, fattoush (tomato, mint and bread salad), babaghanoush, labneh, and more - but it&amp;apost;s important to leave room for the main course.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Then again, I&amp;apost;ve never managed to take my own advice, especially since the most intent Lebanese hosts won&amp;apost;t let guests leave the table without tasting everything in sight and having seconds.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Advice?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Just surrender.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
