<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2302" link="http://www.cnn.com/2011/09/30/world/meast/iran-christian-pastor/index.html" date_published="2011-09-30 18:07:49" category="world" author="Dan Merica, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Iranian pastor faces death for rape, not apostasy - report</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6, 5">NEW: Iranian official calls Nadarkhani &amp;quot;rapist ... guilty of security-related crimes&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="23">NEW: Official says Iran doesn&amp;apost;t execute people because of their religion.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">Nadarkhani got death sentence for rape and extortion.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="20">He is the leader of a network of house churches in Iran.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-28 09:36:46" annotation_time="102.452675">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="3">Christian Pastor Youcef Nadarkhani will be put to death for several charges of rape and extortion, charges that differ greatly from his original sentence of apostasy, Iran&amp;apost;s semi-official Fars News agency reported Friday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;He is guilty of security-related crimes.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">In a translated Iranian Supreme Court brief from 2010, however, the charge of apostasy is the only charge leveled against Nadarkhani.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="4">Nadarkhani, the leader of a network of house churches in Iran, was first convicted of apostasy in November 2010, a charge he subsequently appealed all the way to the Iranian Supreme Court.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;No one is executed in Iran for their choice of religion,&amp;quot; he added.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Christian Pastor Youcef Nadarkhani will be put to death for several charges of rape and extortion, charges that differ greatly from his original sentence of apostasy, Iran&amp;apost;s semi-official Fars News agency reported Friday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Gholomali Rezvani, the deputy governor of Gilan province, where Nadarkhani was tried and convicted, accused Western media of twisting the real story, referring to him as a &amp;quot;rapist.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>A previous report from the news agency claimed he had committed several violent crimes, including repeated rape and extortion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;His crime is not, as some claim, converting others to Christianity,&amp;quot; Rezvani told Fars.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;He is guilty of security-related crimes.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>In a translated Iranian Supreme Court brief from 2010, however, the charge of apostasy is the only charge leveled against Nadarkhani.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;Mr. Youcef Nadarkhani, son of Byrom, 32-years old, married, born in Rasht in the state of Gilan is convicted of turning his back on Islam, the greatest religion the prophesy of Mohammad at the age of 19,&amp;quot; reads the brief.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The brief was obtained by CNN from the American Center for Law and Justice and was translated from its original Farsi by the Confederation of Iranian Students in Washington.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>It goes on to say that during the court proceeding, Nadarkhani denied the prophecy of Mohammad and the authority of Islam.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;He (Nadarkhani) has stated that he is a Christian and no longer Muslim,&amp;quot; states the brief.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;During many sessions in court with the presence of his attorney and a judge, he has been sentenced to execution by hanging according to article 8 of Tahrir -- olvasileh.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Rezvani, the official from Gilan province, confirmed that his execution is &amp;quot;not imminent&amp;quot; nor is it final.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Mohammadali Dadkhah, the pastor&amp;apost;s lawyer, said through a translator that even in light of the Fars News report, he does not believe Nadarkhani will be put to death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;The case is still in progress,&amp;quot; Dadkhah said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;There&amp;apost;s a 95% that he won&amp;apost;t get the death penalty.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Yes, I still believe that.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Dadkhah spoke briefly of the trial proceedings, stating that he presented documents to the court that should be convincing, including documents from Shi&amp;apost;ite leaders that state the crime does not warrant the possible punishment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is a legal process that should take its course, and it should stand, on its own merits.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>It should succeed,&amp;quot; Dadkhah said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Nadarkhani, the leader of a network of house churches in Iran, was first convicted of apostasy in November 2010, a charge he subsequently appealed all the way to the Iranian Supreme Court.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>After four days of an appeals trial that started Sunday at a lower court in Gilan Province, Nadarkhani refused to recant his beliefs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>That said, Rezvani -- echoing an earlier report from Fars -- insisted that &amp;quot;Nadarkhani&amp;apost;s crime and his death sentence have nothing to do with his beliefs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;No one is executed in Iran for their choice of religion,&amp;quot; he added.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;He is a Zionist and has committed security-related crimes.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The possible execution of Nadarkhani, based on an assumption it is tied to his Christian belief, has elicited responses from the highest levels of the United States government, too.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Secretary of State Hillary Clinton released a statement Friday that said the United States stands with &amp;quot;all Iranians against the Iranian government&amp;apost;s hypocritical statements and actions.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The White House released a statement on Thursday, stating that Nadarkhani &amp;quot;has done nothing more than maintain his devout faith, which is a universal right for people.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;That the Iranian authorities would try to force him to renounce that faith violates the religious values they claim to defend, crosses all bounds of decency and breaches Iran&amp;apost;s own international obligations,&amp;quot; reads the statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Leonard Leo, chairman of the U.S. Commission on International Religious Freedom, says a trial for apostasy in Iran is rare.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>According to him, this is the first apostasy trial since 1990.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Nadarkhani&amp;apost;s trial and his possible execution have engaged American Christians, as well.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Todd Nettleton, spokesman for Voice of the Martyrs, a Christian organization that attempts to assist with persecuted and minority churches around the world, called the news of the new charges proof that international attention on the issue is working.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;They are feeling the attention, they are feeling the weight of the eyes of the world watching how they are treating this man,&amp;quot; Nettleton said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am dumbfounded, though, that at this stage in the game, this is what they would trot out.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Voice of the Martyrs manages a Facebook page that has brought a lot of attention to Nadarkhani&amp;apost;s trial.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>With comments updated by the minute, thousand of people have taken to Facebook to spread the word about the pastor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>In light of this news, Nettleton said the Facebook page would continue to be active.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think our first response will be prayer for pastor Youcef,&amp;quot; Nettleton said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;Prayer that justice will be done and that he will remain faithful no matter that the days ahead may bring for him.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
