<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2524" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/06/20/world/asia/india-floods/index.html" date_published="2013-06-20 05:31:37" category="world" author="Jethro Mullen, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Northern India grapples with &amp;apost;Himalayan tsunami&amp;apost;</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="11">NEW: More than 60,000 people are estimated to be stranded.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="22">NEW: It&amp;apost;s the fastest ever onset of the monsoon season in India, meteorologist says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">Heavy rain has set off floods that have swept away houses and roads.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="10">A local official puts the death toll at 150, but says some villages are still under water.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-02 09:41:08" annotation_time="38.79067">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">Triggered by unusually early and heavy monsoon rains, the floods have swept away buildings, roads and vehicles in the mountainous state of Uttarakhand, which borders Nepal and China.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="4">A local official in Uttarakhand, Om Prakash, said that the death toll in the state had reached 150, but cautioned that he wasn&amp;apost;t able to give an exact estimate since some villages were still inundated, CNN-IBN reported Thursday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="1">More than 60,000 people remain stranded, the network said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="2">It&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;the fastest India&amp;apost;s ever seen the onset of the monsoon season.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Rescue workers in northern India are scrambling to save tens of thousands of people left stranded by devastating floods that have killed as many as 150 people in the region.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>One government official described the flooding as a &amp;quot;Himalayan tsunami.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Triggered by unusually early and heavy monsoon rains, the floods have swept away buildings, roads and vehicles in the mountainous state of Uttarakhand, which borders Nepal and China.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The neighboring state of Uttar Pradesh has also been hit.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;Our hearts go out to the families of those who have lost their lives and those who have suffered injury or loss of property in this huge tragedy,&amp;quot; said Prime Minister Manmohan Singh, who carried out an aerial survey of the affected areas in Uttarakhand on Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>With bad weather hampering rescue efforts and some areas still under water, officials are struggling to gauge the scale of the disaster.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;Very heavy casualties are feared and I cannot give the exact number without a proper survey,&amp;quot; said Uttarakhand Chief Minister Vijay Bahuguna, according to CNN&amp;apost;s sister network CNN-IBN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>He described the severe flooding as a &amp;quot;Himalayan tsunami.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Singh said Wednesday that estimates put the number of people killed in the floods at 102, but added that &amp;quot;it is feared that loss of lives could eventually be much higher.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>A local official in Uttarakhand, Om Prakash, said that the death toll in the state had reached 150, but cautioned that he wasn&amp;apost;t able to give an exact estimate since some villages were still inundated, CNN-IBN reported Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>More than 60,000 people remain stranded, the network said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Flooding hits holy site.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>With Hindu shrines set amid its stunning scenery, Uttarakhand is often referred to as &amp;quot;the Land of Gods.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>At the heart of the recent devastation is the town of Kedarnath, the home of a deeply revered Hindu temple that attracts many pilgrims.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Images from the area have shown the centuries-old holy town, which sits in a deep valley, swamped with mud and rocks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Rescue workers reached the town Wednesday and evacuated hundreds of people to safer areas, CNN-IBN reported, but thousands more remain stuck there.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The temple is intact, but shops and other buildings surrounding it have been severely damaged, it said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;The maximum damage has been in Kedarnath and its vicinity,&amp;quot; Singh said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Extreme weather.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The worst of the heavy rain came in the past few days in a region of India where the monsoon doesn&amp;apost;t usually arrive for another month, according to Pedram Javaheri, a CNN International meteorologist.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;Some areas have seen more than twice their average monthly rainfall totals,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;the fastest India&amp;apost;s ever seen the onset of the monsoon season.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The conditions have now improved somewhat, Javaheri said, predicting that the rain &amp;quot;should be scattered in nature for the next couple of days at least.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The weather has also brought chaos further south, in the Indian capital, New Delhi, where the Yamuna River has reached its highest level since 2010, according to CNN-IBN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Flood waters have flowed out into parts of Delhi, inundating streets, shops and homes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Some water from the river has spilled out onto the city&amp;apost;s Outer Ring Road, potentially disrupting traffic, CNN-IBN reported Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Authorities have relocated more than 5,000 people from affected areas, the network said, citing Delhi Chief Minister Sheila Dikshit as saying the situation is under control.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
