<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2892" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/25/world/europe/ukraine-crisis/index.html?hpt=ieu_c2" date_published="2014-09-25 14:19:33" category="world" author="Laura Smith-Spark, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Ukraine&amp;apost;s Poroshenko eyes EU membership bid in 2020</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">President Poroshenko says reforms will prepare Ukraine for 2020 EU membership bid.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">President says a ceasefire between Ukrainian forces and pro-Russia rebels is holding.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">He and Russian President Vladimir Putin will likely meet in the next three weeks, he says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-18 14:53:18" annotation_time="27.354666">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Ukrainian President Petro Poroshenko outlined a program of social and economic reforms Thursday that he said are aimed at preparing his country to apply for EU membership in 2020.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">Poroshenko also told reporters Thursday in Kiev that a nearly three-week-old ceasefire between Ukraine&amp;apost;s military and pro-Russia rebels in the country&amp;apost;s east is holding.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">Poroshenko said he expected to hold a meeting with Russian President Vladimir Putin within the next three weeks.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Ukrainian President Petro Poroshenko outlined a program of social and economic reforms Thursday that he said are aimed at preparing his country to apply for EU membership in 2020.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Since he took office in June, Poroshenko has pursued a pro-European agenda despite opposition from Russia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;This program foresees about 60 reforms and special programs that will allow Ukraine to prepare for submitting in six years a bid for membership of the European Union,&amp;quot; he said, according to national news agency Ukrinform.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Poroshenko also told reporters Thursday in Kiev that a nearly three-week-old ceasefire between Ukraine&amp;apost;s military and pro-Russia rebels in the country&amp;apost;s east is holding.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>This, he said, was &amp;quot;the first day in many many weeks and months when Ukrainians have not had a single person killed, and not a single person wounded.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Poroshenko said he expected to hold a meeting with Russian President Vladimir Putin within the next three weeks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>He did not specify the venue of the meeting, just saying that it would be held in Europe.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Minsk deal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The ceasefire deal was agreed to following a phone conversation between the two leaders and negotiations between representatives of Kiev, Moscow and the pro-Russia rebels in Minsk, Belarus.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Kiev and the West accuse Moscow of arming and supporting the rebels and of sending Russian troops over the border to fight with them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The Ukrainian Parliament and the European Union last week ratified a political and economic agreement that also includes free trade provisions, though they won&amp;apost;t come into force until the start of 2016.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Former Ukrainian President Viktor Yanukovych&amp;apost;s decision to drop the EU Association agreement late last year in favor of closer ties with Moscow triggered the popular unrest that led to his ouster in February, followed by Russia&amp;apost;s annexation of Ukraine&amp;apost;s Crimea region a month later and months of deadly conflict in eastern Ukraine.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>U.S. support.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>At the same time, Poroshenko appealed to the U.S. Congress for greater support for his military, but the request was rebuffed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The United States has sent nonlethal assistance such as blankets and night vision goggles, but won&amp;apost;t provide lethal aid.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>In his speech to the U.N. General Assembly Wednesday, President Barack Obama again promised that the United States and its allies would support Ukraine, while calling on Russia to follow &amp;quot;the path of diplomacy and peace.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>U.S. Secretary of State John Kerry and Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov discussed the importance of a full and prompt implementation of the Minsk ceasefire agreement during a meeting Wednesday, a senior State Department official said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
