<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2570" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/01/10/world/meast/saudi-arabia-sri-lankan-maid" date_published="2013-01-10 10:42:49" category="world" author="Jethro Mullen, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Outrage over beheading of Sri Lankan woman by Saudi Arabia</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2, 1">Saudi authorities execute Rizana Nafeek, a Sri Lankan woman.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">She was convicted of killing a baby of the family employing her as a housemaid.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="26">But rights groups say her treatment and trial had serious flaws.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="20">The Sri Lankan government says it &amp;quot;deplores&amp;quot; the execution.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 14:52:26" annotation_time="150.56767" mapping_time_divergence="37.64192">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">A young Sri Lankan woman has been beheaded with a sword in a small, dusty town in Saudi Arabia, thousands of miles from the lush jungles and idyllic beaches of the country where she grew up.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Rizana Nafeek arrived in Saudi Arabia in 2005 and spent her first few weeks in Saudi Arabia working as a housemaid to earn money to support her relatives back home who had been displaced by the massive tsunami in the Indian Ocean the year before.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">She then spent the next seven years in Saudi jails as she was accused, charged, convicted and sentenced to death in the killing of her employers&amp;apost; 4-month-old son.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="4">President Mahinda Rajapaksa of Sri Lanka, who had made personal appeals for clemency in Nafeek&amp;apost;s case, said he and his government deplored the decision to go ahead with the execution.</sentence>
      <sentence id="26" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;Rizana was just a child herself at the time of the baby&amp;apost;s death, and she had no lawyer to defend her and no competent interpreter to translate her account,&amp;quot; said Nisha Varia, senior women&amp;apost;s rights researcher at Human Rights Watch.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A young Sri Lankan woman has been beheaded with a sword in a small, dusty town in Saudi Arabia, thousands of miles from the lush jungles and idyllic beaches of the country where she grew up.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Rizana Nafeek arrived in Saudi Arabia in 2005 and spent her first few weeks in Saudi Arabia working as a housemaid to earn money to support her relatives back home who had been displaced by the massive tsunami in the Indian Ocean the year before.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>She then spent the next seven years in Saudi jails as she was accused, charged, convicted and sentenced to death in the killing of her employers&amp;apost; 4-month-old son.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Authorities executed her Wednesday in Dawadmi, about 200 kilometers west of the Saudi capital, Riyadh.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The family said she had strangled the boy, Kayed bin Nayef bin Jazyan al-Otaibi, after being asked to bottle-feed him.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Nafeek said the infant accidentally choked on milk.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>She found herself plunged into the unfamiliar, unfriendly and -- according to many human rights advocates -- unfair Saudi legal system.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>In cases where the death penalty is possible, &amp;quot;defendants are rarely allowed formal representation by a lawyer and in many cases are kept in the dark about the progress of legal proceedings against them,&amp;quot; Amnesty International says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Nonetheless, human rights groups and the Sri Lankan government lobbied Saudi authorities to release her, or at the very least show some leniency in her complicated case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>They argued that the courts had failed to take into account Nafeek&amp;apost;s birth certificate, which showed she was only 17 at the time of the baby&amp;apost;s death in 2005, making her too young to receive the death penalty under international law.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The passport she used to enter the country, which said she was 23 at the time, was inaccurate and had been falsified, they said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Additionally, she had not had access to lawyers during her pre-trial interrogation during which she said she was assaulted and forced to sign a confession under duress, rights groups pointed out.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Right up until the end, they pointed out that the dead boy&amp;apost;s family could still grant Nafeek a pardon or request blood money as compensation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>But those arguments and others, as well as numerous visits by Sri Lankan ministers and members of Nafeek&amp;apost;s family, failed to sway Saudi authorities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The interior ministry statement announcing the execution began with a verse from the Quran, according to SPA, the official Saudi News agency: &amp;quot;O ye who believe!</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>the law of equality is prescribed to you in cases of murder.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The death penalty for Nafeek had been approved by the Supreme Court, the agency reported, and a &amp;quot;high order was issued&amp;quot; to carry out the sentence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The Sri Lankan government and human rights groups have sharply criticized Saudi Arabian authorities for the beheading of Nafeek.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>It shows &amp;quot;once more how woefully out of step they are with their international obligations regarding the use of the death penalty,&amp;quot; said Philip Luther, director of Amnesty International&amp;apost;s Middle East and North Africa program.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>President Mahinda Rajapaksa of Sri Lanka, who had made personal appeals for clemency in Nafeek&amp;apost;s case, said he and his government deplored the decision to go ahead with the execution.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Lawmakers in the Sri Lankan parliament observed a minute of silence Wednesday to mourn her death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>But her case appears to be far from a one-off occurrence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Many of the people executed in Saudi Arabia in recent years have been foreign citizens, according to Amnesty International, most of them &amp;quot;migrant workers from poor and developing countries.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In 2012, Amnesty said it had recorded at least 79 executions in the country, 27 of them of foreigners.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Saudi Arabia also has a history of carrying out the death penalty on people convicted of committing crimes when they were children, according to Human Rights Watch.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;Rizana was just a child herself at the time of the baby&amp;apost;s death, and she had no lawyer to defend her and no competent interpreter to translate her account,&amp;quot; said Nisha Varia, senior women&amp;apost;s rights researcher at Human Rights Watch.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;Saudi Arabia should recognize, as the rest of the world long has, that no child offender should ever be put to death.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
