<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2848" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/05/08/world/asia/afghan-girl-mistreatment/index.html" date_published="2012-05-08 22:43:52" category="world" author="Nick Paton Walsh and Ashley Fantz, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Tortured Afghan teen on attackers: &amp;apost;The same should be done to them&amp;apost;</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Married at 13, Sahar Gul says her husband raped her and various in-laws tortured her.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="16">Three of her attackers were recently sentenced for 10 years.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="19, 18">&amp;quot;Ten years is not enough. They should have been given 50 years,&amp;quot; she told CNN.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-28 14:07:12" annotation_time="30.429335" mapping_time_divergence="10.143111">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">She said her husband, a member of the Afghan Army, raped her.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="2">They each got 10 years.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;Ten years is not enough.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="3">They should have been given 50 years,&amp;quot; the teenager told CNN journalists, who visited her recently in an Afghanistan safe house where more than a dozen other women are being counseled after experiencing horrific treatment.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Last year, people around the world were outraged when they heard the story of Sahar Gul.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The Afghan teen was married off at 13.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>She said her husband, a member of the Afghan Army, raped her.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Enraged because she didn&amp;apost;t immediately get pregnant, her in-laws locked her in a basement for months, torturing her with hot pokers and ripping out her nails.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Ultimately, she said, they wanted to force her into prostitution as punishment for failing her obligation as a woman.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;They told me to go to the basement because there were some guests coming to the house,&amp;quot; she told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;When I went there they came in and tied my hands and feet and pulled me upwards from above.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>They brought very little food for me.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;While going to the bathroom they used to beat me a lot.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>I was crying all this time,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;When they put electric shocks on my feet, I felt like I was going to die at that moment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>I screamed and that&amp;apost;s how our neighbors realized there was something happening.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>For one day and night I was unconscious, feeling dead.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Neighbors heard her cries and called authorities, who rescued the teenager in December.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Last weekend, Gul, now 14, trembled as she stood in court and listened to a Kabul judge hand down sentences to three of her attackers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>They each got 10 years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Her husband is still being sought.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Ten years is not enough.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>They should have been given 50 years,&amp;quot; the teenager told CNN journalists, who visited her recently in an Afghanistan safe house where more than a dozen other women are being counseled after experiencing horrific treatment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;They should be punished in the prison.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>They hurt my eyes and pulled out my nail and hair, and the same should be done to them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>whatever they did to me, the same should be done to them,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Gul has become an international symbol of the struggle for women&amp;apost;s rights in Afghanistan.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The outcome of the case against her relatives has inevitably posed a larger question.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>More than a decade since Western forces invaded Afghanistan, have there been enough real and meaningful advances in women&amp;apost;s rights there?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>If so, will that progress erode after the United States pulls out of the country in 2014 or be diminished while the United States continues to pursue a negotiated peace with the Taliban?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Under Taliban rule from 1996 to 2001, women were banned from classrooms, politics or employment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Women who wanted to leave home had to be escorted by a male relative and were forced to wear burqas.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Those who disobeyed were publicly beaten.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>In some parts of Afghanistan in the late 1990s, locals were encouraged to blacken the windows on their homes so women inside could not be seen.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Rights groups have cited advances since then.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>In 2004, girls were formally guaranteed a right to an education under the Afghan constitution.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Human Rights Watch reports that nearly 2 million Afghan girls are enrolled in school (though only a small number advance past elementary school, rights groups have reported).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Literacy rates are up for girls between 12 and 16, according to a 2011 Oxfam report.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Across Afghanistan, infant mortality rates have dropped and life expectancy has risen, according to Unicef.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Women who once had to quit their jobs have gone back to work as doctors, lawyers and police officers, Oxfam said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>But stories of honor killings, poisoned wells at girls schools and disfigurements persist.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>President Hamid Karzai enacted the 2009 Elimination of Violence Against Women law, intended to help reduce violence against women committed through practices deemed traditional, such as so-called honor killings.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>But the United Nations reported in June 2011 that the violence against women law was being enforced in only 10 of 34 provinces.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Also, from March 2010 to a year later, the Afghan Independent Human Rights Commission registered 2,299 cases of violence against women that, according to the law, would be considered crimes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Gul said she not only has to think about the trauma she&amp;apost;s endured, but also she is still technically married to her attacker, and she fears it may not be safe to carry on living in Afghanistan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think the punishment given by the court to these people worries me.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>The government is trying its best to find [my husband, convicted but on the run],&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;But if tomorrow he finds me, it&amp;apost;s possible he could kill me.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>&amp;quot;I want to go abroad,&amp;quot; she continued.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>&amp;quot;If I sit here, they will find me.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>I want to go to school and study, to become a doctor or a prosecutor, so I can give punishment by myself to these sort of people. &amp;quot;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
