<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2122" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/06/26/world/asia/china-corruption-su-rong/index.html" date_published="2014-06-26 08:19:30" category="world" author="Steven Jiang, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>China&amp;apost;s anti-corruption campaign catches another &amp;apost;tiger&amp;apost;</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Su Rong, former vice chairman of China&amp;apost;s top political advisory body, removed from his post .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">Party: Su under investigation for the &amp;quot;serious violation of laws and Party disciplines&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">Xinhua: Su and his wife profited through bribes and illegal land deals when he ran Jiangxi province.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="1">This is the latest chapter in President Xi Jinping&amp;apost;s crusade against corruption in China.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 15:57:56" annotation_time="199.377">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="4">Beijing More details emerged in state media Thursday about the dismissal of the highest-ranking Chinese official yet since President Xi Jinping launched a massive campaign against corruption -- a lightning rod for public discontent across the country.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Su Rong, a former vice chairman of China&amp;apost;s top political advisory body, was formally removed from his post on Wednesday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">The Party&amp;apost;s disciplinary commission said in a brief online announcement that he is under investigation for the &amp;quot;serious violation of laws and Party disciplines.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">Su, 65, and his wife profited tremendously through bribes and illegal land deals when he ran the southeastern province of Jiangxi, state media reported.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Beijing More details emerged in state media Thursday about the dismissal of the highest-ranking Chinese official yet since President Xi Jinping launched a massive campaign against corruption -- a lightning rod for public discontent across the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Su Rong, a former vice chairman of China&amp;apost;s top political advisory body, was formally removed from his post on Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Though little known outside of China, Su&amp;apost;s position at the Chinese People&amp;apost;s Political Consultative Conference made him a &amp;quot;state leader&amp;quot; in the official hierarchy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The downfall of Su, a senior member of the ruling Communist Party who served as the Party boss in three provinces, was made public on June 14.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The Party&amp;apost;s disciplinary commission said in a brief online announcement that he is under investigation for the &amp;quot;serious violation of laws and Party disciplines.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;apost;Flies and tigers&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>State media has since characterized Su as the biggest &amp;quot;tiger&amp;quot; caught in President Xi&amp;apost;s anti-graft campaign.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>After taking power in late 2012, Xi banned official extravagance -- from banquets to year-end gifts -- and vowed to target &amp;quot;flies and tigers&amp;quot; alike in his fight against corruption when describing his resolve to spare no one regardless of their position.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The state-run Xinhua news agency recently touted the catching of 30 &amp;quot;tigers&amp;quot; after the investigations of Su as well as two other provincial leaders became known.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Su, 65, and his wife profited tremendously through bribes and illegal land deals when he ran the southeastern province of Jiangxi, state media reported.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>He was also implicated in tampering with evidence in a criminal trial and covering up the death toll in the breaching of a local dam, according to state media.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Zhou Yongkang.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Some China watchers have noted Su&amp;apost;s ties to Zhou Yongkang, the former domestic security czar who has been rumored to be under investigation for some time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>State media has reported official probes into many of Zhou&amp;apost;s family members as well as former associates in the domestic security apparatus, state oil industry and Sichuan Province in the southwest -- three places Zhou once ruled.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>If announced, Zhou would replace Su to become the highest-ranking official ever to face corruption charges in the history of the People&amp;apost;s Republic.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>In 2013, some 182,000 officials were disciplined while courts nationwide tried 23,000 corruption cases, according to the Party&amp;apost;s disciplinary commission.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>State media has cited the trial and conviction last year of former high-flying politician Bo Xilai -- though called politically motivated by Bo supporters -- as one prime example of President Xi&amp;apost;s determination to clean up the Party.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;apost;Corruption endemic&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Longtime China observers, however, point to the limits of President Xi&amp;apost;s war on corruption.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;There have been public calls for a law to require officials disclosing their assets.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>There has been no indication that they are going to do that.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>In fact, a number of people calling for this law have ended up in prison,&amp;quot; said Frank Ching, a Hong Kong-based commentator and columnist on Chinese politics.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think people will be much more convinced of the seriousness of this anti-corruption campaign if there were a move to enact such a law.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;Corruption is so widespread and so endemic that campaigns are just not going do it,&amp;quot; he added.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;Something has to be done about the system.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
