<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2663" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/09/16/world/international-adoption-korea-adoptee-advocates/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2013-09-16 04:30:49" category="world" author="Wilfred Chan, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Raised in America, activists lead fight to end S. Korean adoptions</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="11">Fight to end adoptions from South Korea being led by U.S.-Korean adoptees.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9, 8">South Korea pioneered international adoptions in the wake of the Korean War.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">As recently as 2005, South Korea was among the top nations for sending orphans abroad.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="47">U.S. adoptees have returned to Korea to try to improve rights for single mothers.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 16:34:07" annotation_time="63.892" mapping_time_divergence="31.946">
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">South Korea was a pioneer on international adoptions.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">In the aftermath of World War II and Korean War, more than 200,000 children were sent to live with families abroad, according to the Korean Ministry of Health and Welfare.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">As recently as 2005, South Korea was the fourth largest provider of children to U.S. families, sending more than 1,600 orphans that year, according to the U.S. State Department.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="1">But Trenka, who repatriated to South Korea in 2008, is part of a vanguard of American adoptees who have led the fight to stop overseas adoptions from Korea and change the cultural stigma tied to unwed mothers.</sentence>
      <sentence id="47" ids_highlights="4">Korean returnee activists are now fighting to improve government support for single women who have children.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Jane Jeong Trenka, adopted from Korea at the age of six months in 1972, never felt she belonged growing up in a rural Minnesota town.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But decades later the 40-year-old discovered her adoption began with a lie.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>While trying to apply for a visa in 2006, Trenka was told her legal birthday didn&amp;apost;t match birth papers supplied by her orphanage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>After an investigation, Trenka unraveled the mystery: an adoption agency in Korea had given her a fake identity to make her more attractive for adoption, she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;I could see where they lied to get me adopted,&amp;quot; said Trenka.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Her family history and physical description was rewritten to hide the fact that she was in poor health, having been abused by her father.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>And the agency had lied to Trenka&amp;apost;s Korean mother, saying she would be sent to a pair of wealthy Dutch lawyers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>South Korea was a pioneer on international adoptions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>In the aftermath of World War II and Korean War, more than 200,000 children were sent to live with families abroad, according to the Korean Ministry of Health and Welfare.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>As recently as 2005, South Korea was the fourth largest provider of children to U.S. families, sending more than 1,600 orphans that year, according to the U.S. State Department.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>But Trenka, who repatriated to South Korea in 2008, is part of a vanguard of American adoptees who have led the fight to stop overseas adoptions from Korea and change the cultural stigma tied to unwed mothers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;The best option is always for a child to be parented by his or her birth parent,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;Then domestic adoption, and only then intercountry adoption.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;If you take a look at what&amp;apost;s going on in (Korean) adoption reform, all of it is led by adoptees,&amp;quot; said Kevin Haebeom Vollmers, a 36-year old Korean adoptee in Minnesota and publisher of Gazillion Voices, an online magazine on adoption issues.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;ve been disenfranchised for so long, and we&amp;apost;re finally writing our own history, for the first time, on our own terms.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>In 2012, the Korean National Assembly implemented the Special Adoption Law, crafted by Trenka with a coalition of adoptee activists and allies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The law explicitly discourages sending children abroad.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Under the law, birth mothers must nurse babies for seven days before the child can be considered for adoption.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>If a mother chooses adoption, her consent must be verified and her child&amp;apost;s birth registered.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Finally, a mother may choose to revoke the adoption up to six months after her application.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s a paradigm shift,&amp;quot; Trenka said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re checking to make sure things are done ethically and properly.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>In my generation, people did things with blindly, deadly, and unethical speed.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Even before the new law took effect, the number of children being adopted abroad from South Korea has been in decline.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Only 621 South Korean children were adopted by U.S. families in 2012, compared to nearly 1,800 in 2002, according to the U.S. State Department.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;apost;Ungrateful&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Not all adoptees are cheering the reform.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Steve Choi Morrison, 57, is a defender of intercountry adoption and the founder of the Mission to Promote Adoption in Korea (MPAK).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;God came down to adopt human beings as his own children, even when we did not deserve it,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;I believe it is our human duty, that if we have more than people from other nations -- then we should share.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Born in the aftermath of the Korean War and orphaned at age 5, Morrison spent his early childhood wandering streets and sleeping under bridges, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>After moving to an orphanage, he was finally adopted at age 14 to a Christian family in Utah.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;They didn&amp;apost;t have to adopt me, but they did,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;I really, really love them for what they did.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>He opposes the new Korean law&amp;apost;s requirement for mothers to register their children&amp;apost;s birth before adoption, arguing that it counters cultural norms.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;In Korean culture, face-saving is very important,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;Mothers are afraid the birth record will later show up, and that husbands will not marry them later.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>If you force birth mothers to register for adoption, they&amp;apost;re just going to abandon their children.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Korean adoption activist Kim Stoker, 40, disagrees.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Morrison&amp;apost;s criticism is based on &amp;quot;incorrect information,&amp;quot; said Stoker, who was adopted as an infant in 1973 and returned to live permanently in South Korea in 1995.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;After a child is placed in a family, that child will be removed from the birth mother&amp;apost;s registry.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Stoker rejects the idea that the law is not suitable for Korean culture.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>&amp;quot;There&amp;apost;s the idea that Korean culture, as large as it is, and as vast as it is, is somehow static.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>That is not true.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>I&amp;apost;ve lived in the country since 1995, and there&amp;apost;s been tremendous cultural change.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>Fight for single-mother rights.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Korean returnee activists are now fighting to improve government support for single women who have children.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>&amp;quot;Mothers are mothers,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>&amp;quot;If you give them a real chance, most will want to parent their children.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Who is the parent should not be a contest of who has the most stuff.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>Stoker believes South Korea&amp;apost;s adoption reform movement will set an example for other countries.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;re the first generation of international adoptees that are telling our own stories,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>&amp;quot;A lot of the adoptees leaving China, for example, are going to look at our model to see what&amp;apost;s important.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>But Jane Trenka said she&amp;apost;s not ready to celebrate.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>Single mother welfare remains lacking and adoption agencies as well as groups like Steve Morrison&amp;apost;s MPAK are fighting to overturn the Special Adoption Law.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Koreans have a saying, after a mountain, there&amp;apost;s another mountain,&amp;quot; she said with a sigh.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
