<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2723" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/02/world/meast/saudi-arabia-religious-police/index.html?hpt=hp_t3" date_published="2014-09-02 16:09:27" category="world" author="Schams Elwazer, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Saudi Arabia&amp;apost;s &amp;apost;religious police&amp;apost; assault British man and wife in Riyadh</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Video shows Saudi Arabia&amp;apost;s religious police attacking British man and his Saudi wife.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">The couple reportedly used a women-only cashier line at a supermarket in Riyadh.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="15">Office of head of religious police (CPVP) says video is authentic, condemns attack as &amp;quot;unacceptable&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="17">CPVP says four of its members have been transferred to administrative jobs outside Riyadh.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2015-01-30 14:47:30" annotation_time="49.0035">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1"> A video of a British man and his Saudi wife being assaulted by members of Saudi Arabia&amp;apost;s religious police has gone viral across the Arab world.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">The video, which shows a man in a headscarf leaping off a car to attack another man in a parking lot, was filmed after the couple reportedly used a women-only cashier line at a supermarket in Riyadh.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="3">The office of the head of the religious police, officially known as the Committee for the Promotion of Virtue and Prevention of Vice (CPVP), concluded that the video was authentic and condemned the attack on the couple as &amp;quot;unacceptable&amp;quot; in a statement Tuesday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="4">Four members of the religious police have been transferred to administrative jobs outside Riyadh.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A video of a British man and his Saudi wife being assaulted by members of Saudi Arabia&amp;apost;s religious police has gone viral across the Arab world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The video, which shows a man in a headscarf leaping off a car to attack another man in a parking lot, was filmed after the couple reportedly used a women-only cashier line at a supermarket in Riyadh.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>In a statement published on the website of a well-known Saudi writer and blogger, the British man said that while he and his wife were shopping, they noticed three young men who looked &amp;quot;religious&amp;quot; following them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>As they were going through the cashier line reserved for women and families, he said the men &amp;quot;started pushing and shoving&amp;quot; and verbally abusing them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The men followed the couple out to the parking lot, where a crowd of people gathered as the argument continued.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The British national said the three men &amp;quot;attacked&amp;quot; him after he took a photo of them on his phone, according to the online statement attributed to him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;While I was on the ground all three of them proceeded to kick me repeatedly in the head and back,&amp;quot; he said in the statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>He said that his wife got out of the car to defend him and was kicked in the stomach after hitting one of the men.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>In the short mobile phone video, the British man can be heard screaming, &amp;quot;Get off of my wife!</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s my wife, how dare you!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>He said they called the British Embassy and locked themselves in their car until &amp;quot;embassy security arrived&amp;quot; and they were escorted home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The man has been named by Saudi newspapers, but the British Embassy in Riyadh would not confirm his identity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>He did not sign his name to the online statement but Ahmed Al Omran, the blog&amp;apost;s owner, wrote: &amp;quot;I know the man and I have met him a couple of times before.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>He is British, married to a Saudi woman and they have been living in Riyadh for years.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The office of the head of the religious police, officially known as the Committee for the Promotion of Virtue and Prevention of Vice (CPVP), concluded that the video was authentic and condemned the attack on the couple as &amp;quot;unacceptable&amp;quot; in a statement Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The CPVP&amp;apost;s investigation found that the men acted beyond their remit in approaching the couple inside a private shopping center, and that they lied in their accounts of events, according to the statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Four members of the religious police have been transferred to administrative jobs outside Riyadh.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>A British Embassy spokesman said they were providing consular assistance to the British national and &amp;quot;welcome the undertaking taken by the head of the [CVPV] Sheikh Abdullatif Al ash-Sheikh to investigate the incident fully.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The incident has been heavily covered in Saudi and Arab press and generated much discussion online.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The YouTube video has been viewed more than 400,000 times.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>In an apparent reference to the incident, one member of Saudi Arabia&amp;apost;s Consultative Assembly, or Shura Council, addressed the &amp;quot;lack of discipline&amp;quot; among religious police field workers and their &amp;quot;flawed judgment&amp;quot; in a session on Monday, according to the body&amp;apost;s official website.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>