<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2672" link="http://www.cnn.com/2011/10/10/world/europe/ireland-troubles-deaths/index.html" date_published="2011-10-10 23:23:20" category="world" author="Peter Taggart, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Reminders of Irish &amp;apost;troubles&amp;apost; rise to surface</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Man confronts Republic candidate demanding answers for his father&amp;apost;s killing.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">Patrick Kelly was shot dead attempting to rescue a kidnap victim in 1983.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">Family of murdered lawyer Pat Finucane will talk with British Prime Minister Cameron.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="11">Finucane&amp;apost;s family wants inquiry, and says British government was complicit.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-25 09:00:30" annotation_time="32.0545">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">David Kelly confronted McGuinness in Athlone, Ireland, demanding answers about his father, Patrick Kelly, who he said had been shot dead with a trainee police officer as they attempted to rescue a kidnapped businessman in the Republic of Ireland in 1983.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">As shoppers and the media looked on, Kelly demanded that McGuinness name the killers, to which McGuinness replied, &amp;quot;I don&amp;apost;t know who was responsible for the killing of your father.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">Meanwhile, on Tuesday the widow of murdered Catholic Belfast lawyer Pat Finucane and other family members will hold talks with British Prime Minister David Cameron about their demand for a public inquiry into his 1989 killing.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="4">The family says they suspect the British government sanctioned the killing.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The tragedy of Ireland&amp;apost;s violent past seemed close to the surface this week as an Irish presidential candidate was confronted about his former role as an IRA commander, and Britain&amp;apost;s prime minister talked with a family about a Catholic victim of &amp;quot;the troubles.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Irish presidential candidate Martin McGuinness was confronted Monday by a man claiming to be the son of a soldier killed by the Irish Republican Army in the 1980s, as McGuinness campaigned ahead of Election Day, October 27.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>David Kelly confronted McGuinness in Athlone, Ireland, demanding answers about his father, Patrick Kelly, who he said had been shot dead with a trainee police officer as they attempted to rescue a kidnapped businessman in the Republic of Ireland in 1983.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>As shoppers and the media looked on, Kelly demanded that McGuinness name the killers, to which McGuinness replied, &amp;quot;I don&amp;apost;t know who was responsible for the killing of your father.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Kelly then accused McGuinness of having been a member of the IRA&amp;apost;s ruling Army Council at the time of the killing -- which McGuinness denied.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;You are a liar.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>I want justice for my father,&amp;quot; Kelly said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>McGuinness, a former IRA commander and now a leader of the political party Sinn Fein, stepped down from his position as Northern Ireland&amp;apost;s deputy first minister to run for president of the Republic of Ireland.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Northern Ireland is part of the United Kingdom, while the Republic of Ireland is an independent state.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Meanwhile, on Tuesday the widow of murdered Catholic Belfast lawyer Pat Finucane and other family members will hold talks with British Prime Minister David Cameron about their demand for a public inquiry into his 1989 killing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The family says they suspect the British government sanctioned the killing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Finucane, 39, had represented IRA members in many high-profile cases, but he had also represented pro-British, or loyalist, terrorists.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>He was gunned down by a loyalist gang at his Belfast home, in front of his wife and three children.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>His family has long believed the security forces cooperated with the killers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The man convicted of Finucane&amp;apost;s murder was a police informer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>John Finucane was the youngest at the family dinner table on the day of the killing, just 8 years old.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Now a lawyer himself, he will also attend Tuesday&amp;apost;s meeting at Downing Street.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;The meeting is at the request of the prime minister and we expect to be told what his intentions are,&amp;quot; he told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are optimistic and hopeful he will announce there is an inquiry and the inquiry is one we can engage with.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>We are cautiously optimistic, but there have been let-downs over the past 22 years.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Finucane says he has &amp;quot;absolutely no doubt&amp;quot; the state was involved in his father&amp;apost;s murder.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;That&amp;apost;s not just my opinion, that&amp;apost;s the opinion of Sir John Stevens, the most senior policeman in England, when he examined it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s also the opinion of Peter Cory,&amp;quot; a retired Canadian judge, &amp;quot;who was tasked with looking at the evidence in the case to decide whether an inquiry was necessary.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>So it&amp;apost;s not just my family that believe there was collusion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think it&amp;apost;s pretty much accepted that there was collusion in my father&amp;apost;s killing.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The question, he said, is &amp;quot;how high up the chain of command that went.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Finucane added that, &amp;quot;in the absence of a transparent examination of all the relevant evidence, I believe it went as high as the office where I&amp;apost;m going to meet the prime minister.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The British prime minister at the time was Margaret Thatcher.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>While the almost daily violence of the 1970s and 1980s is a thing of the past in Northern Ireland, remnants of &amp;quot;the troubles&amp;quot; remain.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Some terrorist splinter groups remain active and even have the capacity to kill.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Still, the current campaign is on a much smaller scale than in the past.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Sinn Fein, viewed as the IRA&amp;apost;s political wing, is now a key player in the peace process and shares power with its former bitter enemies, pro-British lawmakers, in a coalition government in Belfast.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>But this week&amp;apost;s events show how old wounds still haunt and divide the island.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Finucane believes facing the past is the key to continuing progress.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;The issue of the past is the single most important issue that has the ability to bring both sides of the community here back to a very dark place,&amp;quot; he said, &amp;quot;and unresolved cases like my father&amp;apost;s do nothing but damage the present society.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
