<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2530" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/18/world/meast/isis-threat/index.html?hpt=wo_c2" date_published="2014-09-18 08:15:56" category="world" author="Chelsea J. Carter and Barbara Starr, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Obama: ISIS threat &amp;apost;doesn&amp;apost;t frighten us&amp;apost;</title>
  <keywords>Martin Dempsey ISIS,Islamic State in Iraq and Syria,ISIS,Alan Henning</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="32">NEW: French President says France has carried out its first airstrikes against ISIS.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">President Barack Obama says more than 40 countries have offered assistance.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="14">The U.S. military has approved a plan to strike ISIS in Syria, officials said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="40">ISIS captured 16 villages in northern Syria in the past day, opposition group says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-13 14:40:32" annotation_time="28.169">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">Obama said more than 40 countries, including Arab nations, have offered assistance in the battle against the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria, which calls itself the Islamic State.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="3">The U.S. military has everything it needs to strike ISIS targets in Syria, a plan that officials told CNN is still waiting on Obama&amp;apost;s signoff.</sentence>
      <sentence id="32" ids_highlights="1">France carried out its first airstrikes against ISIS in Iraq on Friday morning, President Francois Hollande announced in a statement.</sentence>
      <sentence id="40" ids_highlights="4">ISIS captured 16 predominantly Kurdish villages in northern Syria over the past 24 hours, a Syrian opposition group said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Washington With approval in hand to arm and train Syrian rebels to fight the ISIS terror group, President Barack Obama said Thursday the plan keeps with &amp;quot;the key principle&amp;quot; of U.S. strategy: No American combat troops on the ground.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;The American troops deployed to Iraq do not and will not have a combat mission,&amp;quot; he said in televised remarks from the White House.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;Their mission is to advise and assist our partners on the ground.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>...We can destroy ISIL without having our troops fight another ground war in the Middle East.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Obama said more than 40 countries, including Arab nations, have offered assistance in the battle against the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria, which calls itself the Islamic State.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The developments came as ISIS advanced its grip on portions of Syria and Iraq, seizing 16 predominantly Kurdish villages near the Turkish border.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The move by ISIS was just one in a series of developments that saw new reports of atrocities emerge and the release of a video of a captive British journalist criticizing the American and British governments.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Citing the Sunni terror group&amp;apost;s brutality, from beheading civilians -- including American journalists James Foley and Steven Sotloff -- to the mass execution of its opponents, Obama said the United States will not back down.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;With their barbaric murder of two Americans, these terrorists thought they could frighten us or intimidate us or cause us to shrink from the world,&amp;quot; Obama said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;But today they are learning the same hard lesson of petty tyrants and terrorists who have gone before, as Americans we do not give into fear.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>When you harm our citizens, when you threaten the United States, when you threaten our allies, it doesn&amp;apost;t frighten us.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>It unites us.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The question now appears to be not if, but when the United States will strike ISIS in its stronghold in northern Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The U.S. military has everything it needs to strike ISIS targets in Syria, a plan that officials told CNN is still waiting on Obama&amp;apost;s signoff.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>ISIS, meanwhile, is modifying its behavior, from the way it communicates to the way it conceals itself, in response to potential U.S. airstrikes in Syria, U.S. military officials told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The officials expressed confidence the airstrikes would be effective.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>As top U.S. military leadership approved a plan to strike ISIS in Syria, the Senate on Thursday gave final congressional approval to Obama&amp;apost;s proposal.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The House approved Obama&amp;apost;s request on Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>U.S. military on deck.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>At the same time, U.S. lawmakers have been debating the best way to stop ISIS.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>In testimony before the House Foreign Affairs Committee, Defense Secretary Chuck Hagel said America&amp;apost;s top military leaders have developed a plan to hit ISIS targets in the terror group&amp;apost;s stronghold in northern Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Obama has been briefed on those plans, which were approved by Hagel and Gen. Martin Dempsey, chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>For weeks, U.S. intelligence and military targeting specialists have been working around the clock on a list of potential targets in Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The list is expected to be shown to Obama one more time, U.S. military officials said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>An analysis of the risks of bombing inside Syria will be included, as well as an assessment of how the destruction of the targets could degrade ISIS, they said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Carrying out airstrikes against ISIS in Syria would be a continuation of the U.S. military operation in Iraq, where American airstrikes are being carried out against the group.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>U.S. airstrikes on Thursday struck an ISIS training camp southeast of Mosul, the group&amp;apost;s stronghold in Iraq, the U.S. military said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Another strike southeast of Baghdad damaged an ISIS ammunition stockpile, according to the military.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>French air support.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>In his remarks, Obama said the United States is building a &amp;quot;broad international coalition.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>As part of that coalition, France will join the air campaign in Iraq, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>France carried out its first airstrikes against ISIS in Iraq on Friday morning, President Francois Hollande announced in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>It used Rafale fighter jets to attack a logistics warehouse used by the group in northeastern Iraq, the statement said, adding that the target had been &amp;quot;reached and completely destroyed.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Further operations will be conducted in the next few days.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Hollande said Thursday that there had been French reconnaissance flights over Iraq this week.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>When officials &amp;quot;identify targets, we will act&amp;quot; in a short time frame, he told reporters in Paris.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Hollande thanked the United Arab Emirates for allowing France to use an air base there.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Hollande stressed that France &amp;quot;will not go beyond&amp;quot; air support and will not send ground troops into Iraq.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Iraq: More than 1,000 soldiers MIA.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>ISIS captured 16 predominantly Kurdish villages in northern Syria over the past 24 hours, a Syrian opposition group said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>ISIS fighters used artillery and tanks against the villages along the Syria-Turkey border, the Syrian Observatory for Human Rights said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Just as in Syria, the crisis in Iraq continues to unfold.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Iraq&amp;apost;s Human Rights Ministry said Thursday that 1,095 Iraqi soldiers still are missing after an ISIS attack in June on a military base formerly known as Camp Speicher.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>ISIS says it killed 1,700 Iraqi troops in the attack.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>The Iraqi government hasn&amp;apost;t released a number of those killed; Human Rights Watch says ISIS executed hundreds of soldiers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>The news came as ISIS released a video of British hostage John Cantlie criticizing the American and British governments for their failure to negotiate for the hostages as other governments have done.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="37">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>In a video posted online, Cantlie -- wearing an orange shirt and seated alone at a desk with a black backdrop -- says he is sending what will be the first in a series of messages on behalf of the group that calls itself the Islamic State.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="38">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Since Cantlie is delivering ISIS propaganda and makes clear in the video he is speaking under duress, CNN is not showing the video on its platforms.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="39">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>In recent weeks, ISIS has drawn growing attention for spewing brutal propaganda across social media -- messages meant both to terrify and recruit Westerners.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>The group appears to have a well-funded, well-organized social media and video production effort.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>Its videos are slickly produced, with high production values, experts say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
