<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2146" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/06/24/world/meast/iraq-developments/index.html" date_published="2014-06-24 21:51:33" category="world" author="Chelsea J. Carter, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Crisis in Iraq: Latest developments</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="29">The United States calculates there are up to 10,000 ISIS fighters in Iraq and Syria.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">ISIS wants to establish a caliphate, or Islamic state, that would stretch into both countries.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="44">UN: At least 757 civilians were killed during the group&amp;apost;s advance in northern Iraq.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-17 14:43:05" annotation_time="12.663">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">ISIS wants to establish a caliphate, or Islamic state, that would stretch from Iraq into northern Syria.</sentence>
      <sentence id="29" ids_highlights="1">The United States calculates there are up to 10,000 ISIS fighters in Iraq and Syria, including those who broke out of prisons in Iraq and Sunni tribesmen, several U.S. officials have told CNN in recent days.</sentence>
      <sentence id="44" ids_highlights="3">At least 757 civilians were killed and 599 were injured during the al Qaeda splinter group&amp;apost;s advance in northern Iraq between June 5 and 22, according to figures released by the United Nations mission in Iraq.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The Iraqi government claimed gains in its fight against militants Tuesday, a day full of dizzying developments.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The quick advance by the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria has seen large portions of northern Iraq fall under its control.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>ISIS wants to establish a caliphate, or Islamic state, that would stretch from Iraq into northern Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Here&amp;apost;s a look at the latest:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>U.S. military advisers arrive in Iraq.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Ninety U.S. military advisers arrived in Iraq on Tuesday as part of the mission President Barack Obama announced last week, Pentagon spokesman Rear Adm. John Kirby said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Those troops will join 40 other U.S. service members, who were already in Iraq working at the embassy in Baghdad and have been reassigned to this new mission, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>U.S. military personnel are supposed to assess the situation on the ground and then &amp;quot;advise and assist&amp;quot; Iraqi military forces as they try to counter the threat from ISIS militants, Kirby said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Fight for Baiji oil refinery.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Iraqi security forces are still fighting ISIS and allied Sunni insurgents at the Baiji oil refinery, Hussain al-Shahristani, the deputy prime of energy affairs, said in a statement released Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>He refuted Arab and Western reports that the oil refinery had fallen into the hands of ISIS, saying they were spreading propaganda for ISIS.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Late Monday, three separate security sources told CNN that ISIS fighters were in control of the Baiji refinery, the sprawling complex that provides much of the fuel needed for domestic consumption.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Iraq&amp;apost;s military spokesman, Maj. Gen. Qassim Atta, told reporters in Baghdad on Tuesday morning that the military was in control of the refinery, a claim that was also carried by state-run Iraqiya TV.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The claim comes a day after Atta told reporters that fighters had launched a new attack and were using bulldozers as they advanced.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>He said the advance was repelled and fighters sustained losses.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>State-run TV reported Iraqi special forces involved in the fight for the refinery killed a militant leader called Abu Qatada.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>It offered no evidence of the death, nor did it detail how he was killed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>CNN cannot independently confirm any of the claims.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The competing claims follow days of reports of a seesaw battle for control of the refinery complex in northern Salaheddin province, about 193 kilometers (120 miles) north of Baghdad.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Kidnapped Indian workers freed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Seventeen Indian workers kidnapped by ISIS in Iraq have been freed, according to India&amp;apost;s External Affairs Ministry.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;Heading home!</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>17 Indians rescued in Iraq from conflict zone were brought to Baghdad and now are heading home,&amp;quot; the ministry said in a post on Twitter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Kirkuk city council leader killed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The head of the Kirkuk city council, Munir Kafili, was killed Tuesday when gunmen shot him, police officials told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Kafili, a minority Turkmen, was driving his car in southern Kirkuk when gunmen opened fire, they said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Kirkuk is an ethnically mixed city, with a population of Sunni, Shiite, Kurds and Turkmen, located about 260 kilometers north of Baghdad.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>10,000 ISIS fighters in Iraq and Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The United States calculates there are up to 10,000 ISIS fighters in Iraq and Syria, including those who broke out of prisons in Iraq and Sunni tribesmen, several U.S. officials have told CNN in recent days.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>It is unknown how many are in Iraq versus Syria because it&amp;apost;s not clear how many go back and forth across the border and how many loyalists joined ISIS as it took over various towns in Iraq, the officials say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The belief is ISIS is currently functioning as an &amp;quot;increasingly capable military force&amp;quot; with &amp;quot;capability and dexterity,&amp;quot; one official said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>One crucial question is whether they will be able to hold onto both new territory and past gains as they take more territory and are &amp;quot;stretched&amp;quot; thin.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The answer lies, officials say, in whether the current support of some Sunnis is a so-called marriage of convenience or a long-term partnership even though the Sunni tribes, to a large extent, do not support the ISIS agenda.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Senior ISIS figures killed?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Two senior ISIS figures -- an Algerian militant named Abu Omar al-Baghdadi and Abu Hafsa, the self-styled governor of Tikrit and Salaheddin provinces -- were killed late Monday in airstrikes in Saddam Hussein&amp;apost;s hometown of Tikrit, Sabah Al-Nouman, a spokesman for Iraq&amp;apost;s counterterrorism service, told CNN on Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Al-Nouman offered no evidence of the deaths, and CNN cannot independently confirm the claim.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>ISIS fighters seized Tikrit during its lightning advance in northern Iraq earlier this month.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>The Iraqi military began an offensive against Tikrit on Sunday, according to reports on Iraqiya TV.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Government paychecks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Prime Minister Nuri al-Maliki&amp;apost;s government announced Tuesday that it will pay government employees who live in &amp;quot;unstable areas&amp;quot; under the control of Iraqi security forces, according to a statement released by the Cabinet.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="37">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Those living in areas &amp;quot;outside of government control&amp;quot; will still be paid, but their paychecks will be held and released when military operations end, it said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="38">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>The Cabinet, according to the statement, has decided to given an &amp;quot;open holiday&amp;quot; to government employees who live in areas under the complete control of ISIS fighters and allied Sunni militants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="39">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Civilian deaths climb.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="40">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>At least 757 civilians were killed and 599 were injured during the al Qaeda splinter group&amp;apost;s advance in northern Iraq between June 5 and 22, according to figures released by the United Nations mission in Iraq.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="41">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>The number of casualties &amp;quot;should be viewed very much as a minimum,&amp;quot; and it includes verified summary executions and extra-judicial killings of civilians, police and soldiers, UNAMI said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="42">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>The casualties occurred in Nineveh, Diyala and Salaheddin provinces, the agency said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="43">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>At least another 318 people were killed, and a further 590 injured during the same period in Baghdad and areas in the south, many of them as a result of at least six separate car bombs, the agency added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="44">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Military spokesman: Iraq regains control of two border crossings.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="45">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Atta, Iraq&amp;apost;s military spokesman, said Iraqi security forces have regained control of two key border crossings after briefing losing them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="46">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>In a briefing aired on state TV, Atta said Iraqi forces, with the help of Sunni local tribes, retook al-Walid, a border town that connects Iraq with Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>He also said Iraqi forces have retaken the Trebil bordering crossing between Iraq and Jordan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="47">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Atta also said Iraqi forces controlled the area between Samarra and the northern border of Baghdad.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="48">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>He also said fighting continues in northern Babylon province, south of Baghdad, with ISIS elements.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>Atta did not detail the fighting nor did he say when it started.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="49">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>He offered no evidence of the claims, and CNN cannot independently confirm the report.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>