<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2859" link="http://cnn.com/2013/12/11/world/meast/syria-civil-war" date_published="2013-12-11 12:01:42" category="world" author="CNN Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Turkey shuts border to Syria</title>
  <keywords>Syria Civil War</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6">NEW: U.S. officials: Fate of rebel commander Salim Idris is uncertain .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">Opposition spokesman calls the move &amp;quot;a temporary measure&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">Aid consists of wood, medical items, non-military equipment like generators, he says .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-09 14:36:26" annotation_time="16.645">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">Syrian National Coalition spokesman Louay Safi called the move &amp;quot;a temporary measure to sort out the situation in northern Syria,&amp;quot; where the Free Syrian Army lost a weapons depot to the Islamic Front in fighting in recent days.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">The aid consisted of wood, medical items, non-military equipment like generators and communication equipment, he said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">Several U.S. administration officials said Wednesday that the fate of Salim Idris, a top rebel commander supported by the West, was uncertain in the wake of the seizure of the warehouse.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Turkey has temporarily closed crossings to and from Syria along its border due to fighting between opposition groups inside Syria, the Turkish Commerce and Customs Ministry said Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The announcement came shortly after the United States and Britain suspended non-lethal aid to the Syrian opposition.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Syrian National Coalition spokesman Louay Safi called the move &amp;quot;a temporary measure to sort out the situation in northern Syria,&amp;quot; where the Free Syrian Army lost a weapons depot to the Islamic Front in fighting in recent days.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The aid consisted of wood, medical items, non-military equipment like generators and communication equipment, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;I can&amp;apost;t give you a particular date but I hope this can be solved,&amp;quot; he added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Several U.S. administration officials said Wednesday that the fate of Salim Idris, a top rebel commander supported by the West, was uncertain in the wake of the seizure of the warehouse.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>U.S. officials said he had left Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>They added that the seizure of the depot, a warehouse, could prove key in shaping how the United States deals with the Syrian opposition.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>U.S. Ambassador to Syria Robert Ford is expected to travel this week to the region to meet with opposition members.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The officials said U.S. authorities were considering expanding their contacts with moderate Islamists who are not affiliated with al Qaeda.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The Islamic Front, which announced its formation last month, is an alliance that includes tens of thousands of fighters from some of Syria&amp;apost;s most powerful Islamist groups, including Ahrar al-Sham, Suqour al-Sham, the Islamic Army and the Tawhid Brigade.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The groups control territory in key areas across Syria and have been fighting forces loyal to President Bashar al-Assad along the critical lines of Damascus and Aleppo, among other places.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The front&amp;apost;s formation has diminished the stature of the Western-backed Free Syrian Army and its leadership abroad, the Syrian National Coalition, as leaders inside the country have sought to distance themselves from a command structure criticized for failing to serve the opposition&amp;apost;s needs on the ground.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The alliance was formed after the al Qaeda-linked Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant -- known as ISIS -- succeeded as the predominant military force in northern Syria, marginalizing and even fighting Syria&amp;apost;s more moderate factions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>ISIS&amp;apost;s largely foreign fighting force poses a threat to rebel groups competing for funding, resources and influence in Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The U.S. government suspended its aid Wednesday amid the instability near the Turkish border, State Department officials said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The suspension does not affect humanitarian aid efforts, they said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The UK Foreign Office, in a statement, said it was &amp;quot;investigating events that took place over the weekend.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>While that investigation is under way, we will not be making any deliveries of equipment to the Supreme Military Council.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;We intend to resume support as soon as we and the SMC are satisfied the conditions on the ground allow the SMC to take safe delivery of equipment provided.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The blockage of passage to Turkey could have implications for refugees.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees reported in September that nearly 500,000 Syrians had registered or were awaiting registration as refugees in Turkey, and those numbers have been increasing since.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Meanwhile, a huge storm dubbed Alexa descended Tuesday and Wednesday on the region, dropping snow and rain whipped by high winds onto Turkey, Syria, Jordan and Lebanon, with the latter most affected, the UNHCR said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In the Bekaa in eastern Lebanon, where thousands of Syrian refugees were living in tents, emergency crews were distributing aid, it said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;Reports from Syria and parts of Turkey spoke of similarly grim conditions there,&amp;quot; it said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The Syrian conflict began in March 2011 after government forces cracked down on peaceful protesters during the Arab Spring movement and is now a full-blown civil war.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The United Nations estimates that more than 100,000 people have died in the conflict.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
