<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2536" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/07/23/world/asia/india-deadly-lunch/index.html" date_published="2013-07-23 10:20:32" category="world" author="Harmeet Shah Singh and Tom Watkins, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Officers hunt down headmistress after Indian school poisoning</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Nine-member team of officers formed to track down the school principal.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">Police intensify presence near her village in Bihar state .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">Authorities record statements from 40 witnesses, including child survivors of the July 16 food poisoning.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 12:55:09" annotation_time="33.453">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">A nine-member team of officers has been formed to investigate and track down the principal, Meena Kumari, police superintendent Sujeet Kumar said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">Police presence is heavy in the village in Bihar state, especially around the principal&amp;apost;s home.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">Authorities have recorded statements from 40 witnesses, including child survivors of the July 16 food poisoning, Kumar said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Patna, India A week after an Indian school served toxic food to students, leaving 23 dead, its headmistress remains missing along with her husband, police said Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>A nine-member team of officers has been formed to investigate and track down the principal, Meena Kumari, police superintendent Sujeet Kumar said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Police presence is heavy in the village in Bihar state, especially around the principal&amp;apost;s home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Authorities have recorded statements from 40 witnesses, including child survivors of the July 16 food poisoning, Kumar said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Residents went on a rampage a day after the toxic meals were served in the local government school, torching at least four police cars.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>In acts of protest, parents of at least three children have buried their kids near the school -- one right in front of the building, according to officials.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Police will ensure the headmistress&amp;apost; safety when she resurfaces or is taken into custody for questioning, authorities said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Pesticides have been found in the food and oil used in the school lunch that sickened 25 others on July 16 in northern India&amp;apost;s Bihar state, police said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Forensic scientists found monocrotophos, an organophosphorus compound used as an insecticide, &amp;quot;in the samples of oil from the container, food remains on the platter and mixture of rice with vegetables in an aluminum utensil,&amp;quot; Assistant Director General Ravinder Kumar told reporters in Patna.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Monocrotophos, which is used for agricultural purposes, is toxic to humans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The cook, Manju Devi, was hospitalized after eating the food she prepared, doctors said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Devi told police that the headmistress did not heed her warning that the mustard oil used to prepare lunch looked and smelled bad.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Instead, the headmistress insisted she continue preparing the meal, officials said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>An investigation found compromised hygiene and sanitation in the school, which was running from a single-room makeshift building.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Experts have said the deaths underscore the problem of food safety in the country, and have prompted discussion on how to improve national school food programs amid news that authorities had warned months ago of safety problems with the state&amp;apost;s school meal program.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Authorities in Bihar -- one of India&amp;apost;s poorest states -- announced that a committee would be formed to improve food preparation in rural schools.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The Bihar students, who were ages 5 to 12, started vomiting soon after their first bite of lunch; some fainted, authorities said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>According to the Indian government, nearly half of India&amp;apost;s children are malnourished.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Since a Supreme Court decision in 2001, government schools in India have been required to provide free meals to students younger than 13.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
