<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2451" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/12/20/world/europe/russia-oligarch-khodorkovsky-pardon/index.html" date_published="2013-12-20 08:58:42" category="world" author="Diana Magnay and Olga Pavlova, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Mikhail Khodorkovsky leaves Russian prison after Putin signs pardon</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="9">NEW: U.S. Secretary of State John Kerry urges reforms in Russian judicial system.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="23">Mikhail Khodorkovsky thanks his family and supporters in statement.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">President Vladimir Putin signed a decree pardoning Khodorkovsky .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="13">The former oil magnate and Kremlin opponent had been in prison since 2003.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-02 10:32:48" annotation_time="130.91933">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="3">Moscow Kremlin critic Mikhail Khodorkovsky arrived in Germany after Russian President Vladimir Putin released him Friday following more than 10 years in prison, the German Foreign Ministry said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="1">U.S. Secretary of State John Kerry welcomed Khodorkovsky&amp;apost;s release.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="4">The oil magnate, who backed an opposition party, had been in prison since 2003 and was convicted in 2005 of tax evasion and fraud.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="2">A statement Thursday on a website set up in support of Khodorkovsky said that it could not confirm plans for a pardon but &amp;quot;all of his family and supporters would of course be elated to see him finally free after ten years of imprisonment.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Moscow Kremlin critic Mikhail Khodorkovsky arrived in Germany after Russian President Vladimir Putin released him Friday following more than 10 years in prison, the German Foreign Ministry said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Khodorkovsky&amp;apost;s son, Pavel, told CNN in a text message that he flew to Germany to meet his father.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>In a statement following his release, Khodorkovsky said he asked Putin to pardon him on November 12, &amp;quot;and I am glad his decision was positive.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>He further said &amp;quot;the issue of admission of guilt was not raised&amp;quot; in the discussion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>He went on to personally thank those who followed his case and supported him and said he was &amp;quot;constantly thinking of those who continue to remain imprisoned.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am very much looking forward to the minute when I will be able to hug my close ones and personally shake hands with all my friends and associates,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;I will welcome the opportunity to celebrate this upcoming holiday season with my family.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>I wish everyone a Merry Christmas and a Happy New Year!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>U.S. Secretary of State John Kerry welcomed Khodorkovsky&amp;apost;s release.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;The United States strongly encourages Russia to pursue reforms that establish a transparent, independent and reliable judicial system that upholds its commitments to human rights, the rule of law and non-discrimination,&amp;quot; Kerry said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Putin signed an amnesty decree for Khodorkovsky, a former Yukos oil tycoon, earlier in the day.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The signature came a day after Putin announced that he planned to pardon Khodorkovsky.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The oil magnate, who backed an opposition party, had been in prison since 2003 and was convicted in 2005 of tax evasion and fraud.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>He was due for release in 2014.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Former German Foreign Minister Hans-Dietrich Genscher apparently was involved in the release, saying he met twice with Putin to discuss the case.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Genscher also arranged the flight on a private jet from Russia and picked Khodorkovsky up at the airport in Berlin.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;He is doing well considering the circumstances,&amp;quot; Genscher told Caren Miosga of CNN affiliate ARD in Germany.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;He looks forward to seeing his family again in a few hours again.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>I heard his conversation with his family members in the car, although I don´t speak Russian.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>It was still moving.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>This is understandable because he had to suffer for 10 years.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Speaking to reporters Thursday, Putin said Khodorkovsky had written a letter appealing for a pardon, citing humanitarian factors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>A statement Thursday on a website set up in support of Khodorkovsky said that it could not confirm plans for a pardon but &amp;quot;all of his family and supporters would of course be elated to see him finally free after ten years of imprisonment.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Putin&amp;apost;s announcement came a day after Russian lawmakers backed a sweeping amnesty law.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The amnesty, to mark the anniversary of the adoption in 1993 of Russia&amp;apost;s post-Communist constitution, will be applied to thousands of Russian prisoners, the state-run RIA Novosti news agency reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>It comes at a time when Russia&amp;apost;s human rights record is in the spotlight, as the country prepares to host the 2014 Winter Olympics in Sochi in February.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Russia has faced international criticism for its treatment of Khodorkovsky, once Russia&amp;apost;s richest man, with countries including the United States accusing it of selective prosecution and abuse of the legal system.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>He has said his prosecution was part of a Kremlin campaign to destroy him and take control of the company he built from privatization deals of the 1990s.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>