<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2565" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/03/20/world/africa/oscar-pistorius-trial/index.html?hpt=hp_t3" date_published="2014-03-20 14:01:40" category="world" author="Richard Allen Greene and Laura Smith-Spark, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Oscar Pistorius to sell Pretoria home for legal costs</title>
  <keywords>Oscar Pistorius trial,Oscar Pistorius house sale</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Oscar Pistorius is selling the home &amp;quot;to cover his increasing legal costs&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">He&amp;apost;s on trial for murder in the death of his girlfriend, Reeva Steenkamp.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">His home, where Steenkamp died, has been sealed since it was handed back to him.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="10">Pistorius &amp;quot;cannot contemplate ever returning to live there again,&amp;quot; a statement says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-26 13:21:22" annotation_time="40.94367">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1, 2">Pretoria Oscar Pistorius -- the standout athlete now on trial accused of the murder of his girlfriend -- plans to sell his Pretoria home &amp;quot;to raise the necessary funds to cover his increasing legal costs,&amp;quot; a statement on his website said Thursday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3, 4">The house has been kept sealed since it was handed back to Pistorius over a year ago, and the athlete &amp;quot;cannot contemplate ever returning to live there again,&amp;quot; it said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Pretoria Oscar Pistorius -- the standout athlete now on trial accused of the murder of his girlfriend -- plans to sell his Pretoria home &amp;quot;to raise the necessary funds to cover his increasing legal costs,&amp;quot; a statement on his website said Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The house is where Reeva Steenkamp was shot dead in February 2013.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Pistorius hasn&amp;apost;t returned since her death, according to the statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>A prosecutor in the Pistorius murder case unexpectedly announced Wednesday that he expects to rest early next week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Pistorius, 27, could take the stand in his defense as early as next week if the case goes ahead as planned.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>He admits firing the shots that killed his girlfriend but has pleaded not guilty to murder, saying he thought she was a burglar and he believed he was acting in self-defense.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The statement, issued by his media representatives, said the sale of his home was forced by an unexpected extension of the trial from the three weeks initially scheduled.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is important to note that Mr. Pistorius has been funding his own defence (sic) from the outset.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Due to the delay in finalising (sic) the trial, the decision to urgently dispose of his single biggest asset, has had to be made,&amp;quot; it said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The house has been kept sealed since it was handed back to Pistorius over a year ago, and the athlete &amp;quot;cannot contemplate ever returning to live there again,&amp;quot; it said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Some of Pistorius&amp;apost; neighbors on the estate have been key witnesses in his trial.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The trial has also seen extensive photographs of the interior of the house, including the bloodstains found in the toilet room where Steenkamp was shot.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The property, in the luxury Silver Woods Estate on the outskirts of Pretoria, was listed in an affidavit filed by Pistorius last February, only days after Steenkamp&amp;apost;s death, as being worth 5 million Rand.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s around $465,000 at current exchange rates.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Pistorius also listed ownership of three other South African properties of lesser value in the affidavit, as well as cash investments, &amp;quot;household furniture and effects, motor vehicles and jewelery.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>His occupational income on the affidavit was listed as about 5.6 million Rand a year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>However, he has not competed professionally as an athlete since he was charged with Steenkamp&amp;apost;s murder.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Pistorius first achieved global fame as an outstanding double amputee sprinter who ran with special prostheses that earned him the nickname &amp;quot;Blade Runner.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
