<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2494" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/12/21/world/asia/india-rape-danger" date_published="2012-12-21 17:14:14" category="world" author="Harmeet Shah Singh and Mallika Kapur, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>New Delhi rape exposes the perils of being a woman in India</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Police say a 23-year-old woman was gang-raped, beaten to near death on a bus in New Delhi.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">The attack sparked protests across India, where data show that rape cases have jumped.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="40">Students talk about their fears, abuse from men, precautions they must take.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="28">Elders say they faced similar attitudes, which only worsened as the city and the country grew.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 14:50:00" annotation_time="31.128" mapping_time_divergence="7.782">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">On Sunday, a 23-year-old woman was gang-raped and beaten to near death on a moving bus in New Delhi, police say.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">The attack sparked furious protests across India, where official data show that rape cases have jumped almost 875% over the past 40 years -- from 2,487 in 1971 to 24,206 in 2011.</sentence>
      <sentence id="28" ids_highlights="4">As young girls, elders, too, faced similar attitudes, which they say only worsened as the city and the country grew.</sentence>
      <sentence id="40" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;The reasons for the high number of female feticide in India include a deep-rooted traditional son preference, continued practice of dowry and concern for safety of the girl child and exploitation and abuse of women and girl children,&amp;quot; Krishna Tirath, India&amp;apost;s women and child development minister, acknowledged in parliament in March 2011.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Bhavyaa Sharma feels vulnerable in the Indian capital.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The 19-year-old student at a leading women&amp;apost;s college in New Delhi fears for her safety when she leaves the campus.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Sexual assaults on women in the city have horrified her and her female friends.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>On Sunday, a 23-year-old woman was gang-raped and beaten to near death on a moving bus in New Delhi, police say.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>She is in intensive care at a city hospital, battling for her life.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The attack sparked furious protests across India, where official data show that rape cases have jumped almost 875% over the past 40 years -- from 2,487 in 1971 to 24,206 in 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>New Delhi alone reported 572 rapes last year and more than 600 in 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;I feel vulnerable here,&amp;quot; said Sharma, accompanied by her classmates.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am very sure about it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Delhi is not safe for women.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Sharma is from Lucknow, the capital of Uttar Pradesh state.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>She joined Miranda House, a women&amp;apost;s residential college in New Delhi, in 2010.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>She&amp;apost;s now close to graduation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>But her stay in the Indian capital hasn&amp;apost;t been without a bitter experience.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>She says she was groped while commuting in a bus in this city.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;It wasn&amp;apost;t traumatic.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>But I cannot forget it, either.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Definitely, I cannot forget it,&amp;quot; Sharma said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>She called her parents back home that day, who tried to comfort her.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Still, she couldn&amp;apost;t hold back her tears.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;I cried the entire night,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Her hostel colleagues shared their own encounters with unwanted behaviors on the streets of New Delhi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>In her first year of college, a group of men stalked Shweta Prakash, 20, and her friends every night they would leave their apartment for dinner.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;quot;It actually freaks you out when people do such things to you ... eye-teasing, passing lewd comments and stalking you.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>They literally rape you with their eyes,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Now, she keeps pepper spray and has enrolled in self-defense taekwondo programs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Prakash and her friends hold each others&amp;apost; hands while walking and text license plate numbers and their location to their parents and others when they travel in a cab or a slow-moving auto-rickshaw.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>As young girls, elders, too, faced similar attitudes, which they say only worsened as the city and the country grew.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;I can speak about my own experience, as a student, in this city -- people are pinching you, touching you, someone is coming close to you.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>This is absolutely the mentality where you look at a woman as an object of sex and (which) you use and abuse,&amp;quot; rights activist Ranjana Kumari said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>As furor about Sunday&amp;apost;s assault rose, some Indian lawmakers even called for treating rape as a capital crime.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The country&amp;apost;s human rights body shot off notices to city police and federal authorities, demanding an explanation of the latest sexual assault.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;The incident has raised the issue of declining public confidence in the law and order machinery in the city, especially in its capacity to ensure safety of women, as a number of such incidents have been reported in the national capital in the recent past,&amp;quot; the National Human Rights Commission said in a statement Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Five people, including the bus driver and a minor, have been arrested in connection with Sunday&amp;apost;s rape, New Delhi police spokesman Rajan Bhagat said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Meantime, some observers say anti-women acts in India stem from the country&amp;apost;s largely patriarchal social setup.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Indians&amp;apost; preference for sons over daughters, for example, has manifested itself in a worrisome population imbalance.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>The 2011 census of the world&amp;apost;s second-most populous nation recorded an alarming drop in the percentage of girls among country&amp;apost;s preschoolers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>For every 1,000 boys up to 6 years old, the census counted 914 girls, a drop from 927 a decade ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s illegal in India to abort a child because of its sex, but such abortions happen, often aided by illegal clinics.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;The reasons for the high number of female feticide in India include a deep-rooted traditional son preference, continued practice of dowry and concern for safety of the girl child and exploitation and abuse of women and girl children,&amp;quot; Krishna Tirath, India&amp;apost;s women and child development minister, acknowledged in parliament in March 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>A senior legal expert says legislation alone cannot resolve anti-women biases.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;More law will only serve to give a sense of something being done, when in fact very little is being done.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>To confront the hatred that is now manifesting itself in the most egregious ways is to move forward as a society,&amp;quot; Ratna Kapur, a professor at Jindal Global Law School, wrote in The Hindu newspaper Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;We need to think about how we can handle women&amp;apost;s equality in ways that are not perceived as threatening.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>That demands greater responsibility on the part of parents as well as society not to raise sons in a way in which they are indoctrinated with a sense of superiority and privilege.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>There is also a need on the part of young men to be actively involved in their schools and communities in advocating women&amp;apost;s equality rights,&amp;quot; she added in her opinion column, headlined &amp;quot;Rape and the crisis of Indian masculinity.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
