<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2829" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/08/08/world/africa/world-war-in-africa/index.html?hpt=iaf_mid" date_published="2014-08-08 12:10:52" category="world" author="Kathleen Bomani, World War I in Africa, Special to CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>The forgotten African battlefields of WW1</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6">As world commemorates the WW1 Centenary, the African story remains a footnote .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">WW1 resulted in huge losses of African lives, had consequences for continent&amp;apost;s future.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="22">Two million African soldiers, workers and porters were directly involved in World War I .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 13:26:25" annotation_time="26.095">
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1, 2">As the world commemorates the Centenary of the Great War, the African side of this story remains a footnote, despite huge losses of human lives and major consequences for the future of the African continent.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="3">All told, two million African soldiers, workers and porters were directly involved in World War I. Though never fully acknowledged, Europe&amp;apost;s Great war was a war of colonials and a colonial theater of war.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A hundred years ago on this day, on August 8th, 1914, the British HMS Asteria and Pegasus protected cruisers bombed Dar-es-Salaam, then the capital of German East Africa, bringing the European so-called &amp;quot;war to end all wars&amp;quot; to the eastern African shores.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The day before, Anglo-French forces constituted of Ghanaian, Nigerian, Sierra Leonean, Gambian and Beninese troops had invaded German Togoland in West Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Among World War I campaigns, the East African one was the longest of all: as the armistice was being signed in Europe on November, 11th 1918, the last of the German forces were still fighting their British counterparts.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Indeed the general who led them only surrendered two weeks later, on November, 25th 1918.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>But who knows any of this, whether in America, in Europe or indeed in Africa?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>As the world commemorates the Centenary of the Great War, the African side of this story remains a footnote, despite huge losses of human lives and major consequences for the future of the African continent.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The East Africa campaign was the opposite of the European war of trenches: it was about mobility, short raids and long treks on foot.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The German Schutztruppe, white German commanders and black African soldiers called askaris, never exceeded 25,000 men.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The British however assembled 150,000 troops: South Africans and Indians at first, joined by Kenyans and Nigerians later on.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>But none of these soldiers would ever have survived, let alone be able to fight, without the unmentioned exploitation of porters.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>For every one soldier, German and British troops used four &amp;quot;native carriers,&amp;quot; including women and children, who howled food supplies, arms and even artillery; cooked, scrubbed and tended to their needs; and died of exhaustion, malnutrition and disease.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Of the 105,000 deaths among British forces during the East Africa campaign, 90% were porters.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>45,000 among the dead were from British East Africa (Kenya) alone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>General Paul von Lettow-Vorbeck, the German commander, is often lauded for his military genius, outwitting the British during four years with barely a fifth of their numbers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Some of the tales written are nothing short of David vs. Goliath.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>But von Lettow-Vorbeck had been ordered not to engage by Berlin.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>As far as I am concerned, his actions would be better described as a war-mongering megalomaniac effort by a military commander responsible for the callous deaths of 300,000 porters, the looting of hundreds of villages and the devastation of years of crops.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>If the death toll had been of German lives, would he have been as celebrated in the scrolls of History?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>It is unclear that askaris actually volunteered to be part of the Schutztruppe, considering just a decade earlier, in 1905, the Germans had violently suppressed one of the largest uprisings against colonial rule on the African continent, the Maji Maji rebellion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>That same year, Germans carried out the first genocide of the century against the Herero in German South West Africa (Namibia).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Terror, subjugation and inhumane practice ruled in the German colonies, and this is how it should be remembered.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>All told, two million African soldiers, workers and porters were directly involved in World War I. Though never fully acknowledged, Europe&amp;apost;s Great war was a war of colonials and a colonial theater of war.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>As I reflect on this day, a public holiday (Nane Nane) for farmers in Tanzania, I remember a hundred years ago 750,000 square miles of land was inundated and destroyed, I remember the farmers who were forcefully dragged into this as porters.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>I remember Africans who fought other Africans for reasons unknown to them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The erasure of Africa&amp;apost;s involvement in World War I, including the ongoing centenary commemorations, painstakingly reminds us that, once again, it is for us to make sure history is told in full.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>My commitment to The World War I in Africa Project finds its roots in this necessity: history should be unearthed and a critical lens applied, especially by us Africans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>What happened in Africa should not stay in Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
