<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2410" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/03/18/world/asia/malaysia-flight-anwar-pilot/index.html" date_published="2014-03-18 11:25:12" category="world" author="Kyung Lah and Tim Hume, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Malaysia&amp;apost;s Anwar Ibrahim: MH370 pilot supported me, but was no hijacker</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Pilot of MH 370 was a supporter of Malaysian opposition leader Anwar Ibrahim.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Anwar was sentenced to 5 years in jail hours before the plane vanished.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">Some have speculated the plane could have been hijacked in response to the sentence.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="8">Anwar says theory is meant to deflect from &amp;quot;incompetent&amp;quot; handling of crisis.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-14 15:27:51" annotation_time="35.658">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Malaysian opposition leader Anwar Ibrahim says the captain of MH 370 is a card-carrying member of his party -- and an extremely distant relative -- but he dismissed suggestions the pilot may have diverted the plane as a political act in his support.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">Hours before the Malaysia Airlines flight vanished en route to Beijing on March 8, Anwar, de facto leader of the People&amp;apost;s Justice Party, was sentenced to five years in jail after a court overturned his 2012 acquittal on a sodomy charge.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">Some media outlets have reported that the plane&amp;apost;s pilot, Zaharie Ahmad Shah, had attended the court hearing, and speculated that the flight&amp;apost;s disappearance may have been a political act in response to the verdict.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="4">He alleged that the speculation had only gained traction as a result of the government trying to deflect attention from its &amp;quot;incompetent&amp;quot; handling of the crisis.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Malaysian opposition leader Anwar Ibrahim says the captain of MH 370 is a card-carrying member of his party -- and an extremely distant relative -- but he dismissed suggestions the pilot may have diverted the plane as a political act in his support.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Hours before the Malaysia Airlines flight vanished en route to Beijing on March 8, Anwar, de facto leader of the People&amp;apost;s Justice Party, was sentenced to five years in jail after a court overturned his 2012 acquittal on a sodomy charge.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Some media outlets have reported that the plane&amp;apost;s pilot, Zaharie Ahmad Shah, had attended the court hearing, and speculated that the flight&amp;apost;s disappearance may have been a political act in response to the verdict.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>As authorities increasingly focused their attentions on events in the cockpit, the homes of Zaharie and First Officer Fariq Abdul Hamid were searched, and a homemade flight simulator found in Zaharie&amp;apost;s home, Malaysian officials revealed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Anwar, who is free pending appeal, told CNN his party had been unable to establish whether Zaharie had been in attendance at court, although a number of his friends had reported he had been &amp;quot;upset and disgusted&amp;quot; by the outcome.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The opposition leader recognized photographs of Zaharie from political meetings, and subsequently established he was a member of his party -- and a distant relative of his daughter-in-law.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>However, he labeled the suggestion that Zaharie could have steered the airliner from its designated flight path as a political act as &amp;quot;grossly unfair&amp;quot; to the missing pilot.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>He alleged that the speculation had only gained traction as a result of the government trying to deflect attention from its &amp;quot;incompetent&amp;quot; handling of the crisis.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think there&amp;apost;s a desperation by the government of the ruling leadership over the manner they managed the whole crisis.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Clearly incompetent, contradictory statements, poor management of the crisis,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;In order to deflect that, their own failure, their own incompetence, they now choose to attack me,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;They fail on every count... They&amp;apost;re now desperate to cast aspersions against me as leader of the opposition.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Malaysian political scientist Wong Chin Huat said that while close scrutiny of the potential motivations of anyone onboard is warranted, he believes the speculated link to Malaysian domestic politics was a &amp;quot;red herring.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;Had the captain intended to cause this incident in protest, there should be clearly some clue.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s pointless to make a political statement in silence, that leaves everyone guessing where you are going,&amp;quot; he said, adding that such drastic actions would be unprecedented in Malaysian politics.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>He had seen no evidence to back up Anwar&amp;apost;s claim that the theory had been promulgated by Malaysian authorities to distract from their handling of the crisis, but said that such an explanation was &amp;quot;very possible.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;You have a one-party state run by princelings that demonstrates very poor leadership and very chaotic coordination -- poor leadership and chaotic coordination that has been distracted from by this red herring,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Malaysian government officials declined to respond to Anwar&amp;apost;s comments.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Anwar has repeatedly said he is innocent of a charge he sodomized a former aide, calling the case against him an attempt by the government to end his political career.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The Malaysian government has consistently denied his accusations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>When asked at a news conference Tuesday about the Anwar angle, Malaysia&amp;apost;s Transport Minister Hishammuddin Hussein said that the issue was above politics, and that speculation linking the plane&amp;apost;s disappearance to Anwar&amp;apost;s sentencing had come from foreign media, not by his government.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
