<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2089" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/06/06/world/asia/pakistan-polio-vaccination/index.html" date_published="2012-06-06 11:36:54" category="world" author="Hilary Whiteman and Reza Sayah, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Bin Laden raid harms Pakistan polio fight</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">CIA intelligence operation harms campaign to eradicate polio in Pakistan.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">Health groups say use of fake vaccination program has increased mistrust.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">198 cases of polio were reported in Pakistan last year, a 15-year high.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="3">The disease is endemic in three countries: Pakistan, Nigeria and Afghanistan.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 19:40:37" annotation_time="86.6325">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="4">She&amp;apost;s just 17 months old, but already Ikra has been paralyzed by polio in one of the three countries in the world where the disease remains endemic.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1, 3">Last year, 198 cases of polio were reported in Pakistan, a 15-year high, and the largest number of cases recorded anywhere in the world, according to the Global Polio Eradication Initiative (GPEI), a joint program to eradicate polio led by the World Health Organization (WHO), United Nations Children&amp;apost;s Fund (UNICEF) and Rotary International.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">Pakistan is causing particular consternation among health officials who say their efforts to vaccinate more children are being frustrated by the CIA&amp;apost;s use of a fake vaccination program last year to gather intelligence on Osama bin Laden.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Nowshera, Pakistan Ikra lies on her mother&amp;apost;s lap, her eyes stained with tears.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>She wants to go and play with the other children, but she can&amp;apost;t even move, her mother says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>She&amp;apost;s just 17 months old, but already Ikra has been paralyzed by polio in one of the three countries in the world where the disease remains endemic.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Last year, 198 cases of polio were reported in Pakistan, a 15-year high, and the largest number of cases recorded anywhere in the world, according to the Global Polio Eradication Initiative (GPEI), a joint program to eradicate polio led by the World Health Organization (WHO), United Nations Children&amp;apost;s Fund (UNICEF) and Rotary International.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Children under the age of five are most vulnerable to the disease, which is spread by a virus and leads to paralysis and, in some cases, death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Since a global vaccination campaign was launched in 1988, the number of cases worldwide has dropped dramatically, although along with Pakistan, polio is still endemic in Afghanistan and Nigeria, according to the GPEI.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Pakistan is causing particular consternation among health officials who say their efforts to vaccinate more children are being frustrated by the CIA&amp;apost;s use of a fake vaccination program last year to gather intelligence on Osama bin Laden.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>In a letter to CIA director General David Petraeus in February, InterAction, which represents nearly 200 U.S.- based non-government organizations, expressed &amp;quot;deep concern&amp;quot; about the fake campaign.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;Among other factors, international public health officials point to the distrust of vaccines and immunization campaigns as contributing to the lack of progress in eradicating the disease in Pakistan,&amp;quot; it said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;This distrust is only increasing in light of reports about the CIA campaign,&amp;quot; it added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Bin Laden was killed in a raid by U.S. Navy SEALs in May 2011 at a heavily fortified compound in Abbottabad, in northeastern Pakistan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Local news reports linked Pakistani doctor Shakeel Afridi to the U.S. intelligence operation, alleging he tried to gain access to bin Laden&amp;apost;s compound through the fake vaccination scheme.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Pakistan recently sentenced Afridi to 33 years in jail for providing financial and medical assistance to the now defunct militant group Lashkar-e-Islam.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Officials originally told CNN Afridi was charged with treason for spying for the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;The incident with Dr. Shakeel Afridi definitely impacted not only our polio vaccinations but other vaccination programs as well,&amp;quot; said Arshad Ahmad Khan, a doctor at Nowshera health department in the country&amp;apost;s northwest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Alem Zeb said he rejected free polio vaccination drops for his children, aged 7 and two, because they were &amp;quot;poison.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;The polio drops destroy the sperm,&amp;quot; he told CNN from his home in Peshawar, in the country&amp;apost;s northwest.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s a campaign by the West to disable Muslim children,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;The U.S. provides funds to destroy Muslims and to make them slaves through such campaigns,&amp;quot; he added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Aid groups have recruited religious leaders to assure anxious parents that the vaccinations are not part of Western plan to sterilize their children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;We go from door to door in every neighborhood to people who refuse [to vaccinate their children] and for whatever reasons they give, and assure them,&amp;quot; said Mohammad Asim Head of the religious school called Idara-e-Taleem-ul-Quran in comments distributed by UNICEF.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;For some, a visit by the Imam is good enough,&amp;quot; he added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>At the start of this year, the Global Polio Eradication Initiative (GPEI) launched an Emergency Action Plan with the aim of vaccinating enough children to halt transmission of the disease by the end of this year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>So far their blitz has succeeded in reducing the number of cases so far this year, with only 16 recorded in Pakistan at end of May, compared to 36 during the same period last year, according to a joint statement from aid groups.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>However, to stop polio transmission completely, aid groups said at least 95% of all children in Pakistan must be immunized during multiple campaigns throughout the country each year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Oral drops need to be administered several times to each child before they become fully immunized.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
