<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2533" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/08/20/world/meast/syria-unrest" date_published="2012-08-20 07:51:35" category="world" author="the CNN Wire Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Obama warns Syria not to cross &amp;apost;red line&amp;apost;</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="19">NEW: A Japanese journalist is killed, the government says Tuesday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="18">At least 150 people were killed across Syria on Monday, opposition activists say.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">Obama calls the movement or use of chemical or biological weapons a &amp;quot;red line&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="29">Violence flares in Daraa, where peaceful anti-regime protests started in March 2011.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-14 15:40:22" annotation_time="95.185">
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;We have communicated in no uncertain terms with every player in the region that that&amp;apost;s a red line for us and that there would be enormous consequences if we start seeing movement on the chemical weapons front or the use of chemical weapons.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="2">At least 150 people were killed Monday, including two children and their mother in Daraa, the opposition Local Coordination Committees of Syria said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="1">A Japanese journalist was killed during a gun battle in Aleppo, the Japanese foreign ministry said Tuesday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="29" ids_highlights="4">Daraa province, where the conflict began in March 2011 as peaceful anti-government demonstrations, has suffered heightened violence in recent days.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Syrian President Bashar al-Assad should heed U.S. warnings to neither use nor move chemical or biological weapons, lest he risk crossing a &amp;quot;red line&amp;quot; and provoke a U.S. military response, President Barack Obama said Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;We cannot have a situation where chemical or biological weapons are falling into the hands of the wrong people,&amp;quot; Obama told reporters at the White House.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have been very clear to the Assad regime -- but also to other players on the ground -- that a red line for us is we start seeing a whole bunch of chemical weapons moving around or being utilized.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;That would change my calculus; that would change my equation.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Obama added that U.S. officials are monitoring the situation &amp;quot;very carefully&amp;quot; and have put together a number of contingency plans.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have communicated in no uncertain terms with every player in the region that that&amp;apost;s a red line for us and that there would be enormous consequences if we start seeing movement on the chemical weapons front or the use of chemical weapons.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Obama&amp;apost;s remarks appeared to ratchet up his stance on the matter.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Last month, talking about Syrian forces, he told a VFW convention, &amp;quot;They will be held accountable by the international community and the United States should they make the tragic mistake of using those weapons.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The Syrian regime &amp;quot;probably has the largest and most advanced chemical warfare program in the Arab world,&amp;quot; Michael Eisenstadt, director of the military and security studies program at the Washington Institute for Near East Policy, told CNN last month.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>It includes &amp;quot;thousands of tube and rocket artillery rounds filled with mustard-type blister agents, thousands of bombs filled with the nerve agents sarin and possibly VX, and binary-type and cluster CW warheads filled with nerve agents for all its major missile systems.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;Its CW infrastructure is believed to include several production facilities and numerous storage sites, mostly dispersed throughout the western half of the country,&amp;quot; Eisenstadt said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Syria is thought to have a biological warfare research and development program, but is not known to have offensive biological warfare agents, Eisenstadt said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The nation is not a party to the Organization for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s the body of the Chemical Weapons Convention dedicated to eliminating the weapons.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Israeli President Shimon Peres has said his country too is preparing contingency plans to attack Syria&amp;apost;s chemical weapons arsenal if Israel is directly threatened.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>In September 2007, Israeli jets bombed a building in Syria that the U.N. nuclear agency eventually concluded was &amp;quot;very likely a nuclear reactor.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Obama&amp;apost;s warning on Monday came as Muslims in Syria celebrated the second of three days of feasting to honor the end of the holy month of Ramadan, with the holiday&amp;apost;s message of amity and tolerance contrasting sharply with reality.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>At least 150 people were killed Monday, including two children and their mother in Daraa, the opposition Local Coordination Committees of Syria said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>A Japanese journalist was killed during a gun battle in Aleppo, the Japanese foreign ministry said Tuesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Mika Yamamoto, 45, worked for the independent Japan Press news agency and had been reporting on the Free Syrian Army.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Her body was taken to Turkey, where officials were working to get more information, the ministry said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Also among the dead in Syria were 10 bodies discovered splayed on the ground in the Damascus suburb of Qaboun.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Video posted by activists showed at least one of the victims lying on his back, blindfolded, his arms stretched above his head.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Others showed victims with bruised flesh and dark red splotches on their clothes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>CNN cannot authenticate the video.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Another video, said to have been shot Sunday in the town of Talbeesa, north of Homs, showed children being pushed on swings.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The swings are attached to the gun of a tank on which adults are standing, chanting, &amp;quot;Victory for the rebels!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>In a third video, showing the same tank, a man says to the camera, &amp;quot;We will enter Homs with this tank and liberate all of Syria, God willing!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Daraa province, where the conflict began in March 2011 as peaceful anti-government demonstrations, has suffered heightened violence in recent days.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>It is also the home province of Vice President Farouq al-Sharaa, who rebels say has defected from the regime.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>On Sunday, the charred bodies of 20 people were discovered in the Daraa city of Hirak, and 31 other people were killed in the province, the LCC said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Government forces executed 14 people in Daraa hours after they were detained, the opposition network said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Hirak took another beating Monday, when mortars and rockets rained down on the city, the LCC said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Since the Syrian crisis began 17 months ago, more than 20,000 people -- most of them civilians -- have been killed, opposition activists say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
