<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2261" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/15/world/meast/isis-western-captives/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-09-15 09:42:30" category="world" author="Jethro Mullen, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>How many more Western captives is ISIS holding?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="18">ISIS is believed to be have at least two more U.S. captives.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="18">It is also holding hostages from other Western countries.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="9">The latest beheading video identified a British citizen.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="25">It&amp;apost;s not known who&amp;apost;s holding U.S. journalist Austin Tice, who disappeared in 2012.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-28 09:31:51" annotation_time="44.048664">
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="3">In the video of Haines&amp;apost; killing, the black-clad ISIS executioner places his hand on another hostage, whom he identifies as Alan Henning, a British citizen.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="1, 2">CNN National Security Analyst Peter Bergen reports that ISIS is understood to be holding at least two other American citizens, as well as hostages from additional Western countries.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="4">Tice, a freelance journalist who was contributing articles to The Washington Post and other news outlets, disappeared in Syria in August 2012.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The beheading of British aid worker David Haines by ISIS has intensified fears for other Western hostages being held by the jihadist group.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Haines&amp;apost; grisly execution follows those of American journalists James Foley and Steven Sotloff in recent weeks -- all of them shown in videos posted online.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>ISIS militants have killed thousands of Syrians and Iraqis in their violent onslaught aimed at building an Islamic caliphate across a wide area of territory.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>But the beheading of Western captives carries greater shock value beyond the region -- and works as a powerful propaganda tool for a group that has drawn members from Western Europe and North America.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;ISIS looks at this as a low cost strategy,&amp;quot; said Peter Neumann, professor of security studies at King&amp;apost;s College London.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;They are seeing that in order to capture the world&amp;apost;s attention and recruit people, they no longer need to take down the World Trade Towers or hit the Pentagon.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>As the United States builds an international coalition to take on the Sunni extremist group in both Iraq and Syria, uncertainty remains about exactly how many more Western hostages the militants have in their possession.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Has ISIS identified any of its other Western captives?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>In the video of Haines&amp;apost; killing, the black-clad ISIS executioner places his hand on another hostage, whom he identifies as Alan Henning, a British citizen.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The implied threat is clear.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Sotloff appeared in the same way in the video of Foley&amp;apost;s beheading.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Haines appeared similarly in the video of Sotloff&amp;apost;s death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>On Sunday, Henning&amp;apost;s family distributed an image of him holding a child at a refugee camp on the Syria-Turkey border.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The family asked media to use this image rather than the one of Henning in an orange jumpsuit kneeling beside his captor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Are any other Americans being held?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>ISIS is believed to be holding a number of Americans, a U.S. official told CNN in August after Foley&amp;apost;s execution.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The official, who spoke on condition of anonymity, declined to identify them or say exactly how many Americans are being held.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>CNN National Security Analyst Peter Bergen reports that ISIS is understood to be holding at least two other American citizens, as well as hostages from additional Western countries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Two Italian women were reported in August to be among the militant group&amp;apost;s newest captives.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>A Dane and a Japanese national were said to be seized along with the two Italians.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s hard to know how many captives there are because governments, employers and families tend to keep kidnappings quiet for fear of putting the victims in greater danger while negotiators work to secure their release.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Have the identities of any missing Americans been made public?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The family of one missing U.S. journalist, Austin Tice, has talked to the media about his case.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>But it&amp;apost;s not clear which group in Syria&amp;apost;s brutal civil war might be holding him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Tice, a freelance journalist who was contributing articles to The Washington Post and other news outlets, disappeared in Syria in August 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>A shaky video uploaded to YouTube in October 2012 showed Tice blindfolded and in obvious distress.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>It was unclear who the people holding him were.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The U.S. State Department said at the time that it believed Tice was in the custody of the Syrian government -- but the regime of President Bashar al-Assad hasn&amp;apost;t admitted detaining him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Tice&amp;apost;s parents spoke last week to CBS This Morning about their concerns for their 33-year-old son.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;I do not accept that he is missing, I live in a place where he is coming home,&amp;quot; said Debra Tice, his mother.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>She described hearing the news of the killings of Foley and Sotloff as &amp;quot;a gut punch.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>What about other journalists?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The Committee to Protect Journalists estimates that about 20 journalists are missing in Syria -- most of them local, some from outside Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>It says many of them are believed to be held by ISIS.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Altogether, more than 80 journalists have been abducted in Syria since the country&amp;apost;s civil war started, according to the CPJ.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Some have been freed, others killed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Often a media blackout on journalists&amp;apost; abductions is lifted generally in best- and worst-case scenarios.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Which Westerners have been released in Syria?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>American journalist Peter Theo Curtis was handed over to U.N. peacekeepers in August by al-Nusra Front, a Syrian rebel group with al Qaeda ties, after almost two years in captivity.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Qatari officials helped secure his release, his family said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Two Spanish journalists -- Javier Espinosa and Ricardo Garcia Vilanova -- were freed in March.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>At the time of their capture, their newspaper said the journalists&amp;apost; captors were reported to be members of a group linked to ISIS.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Four French journalists -- Nicolas Henin, Pierre Torres, Didier Francois and Edouard Elias -- were released in April.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>And a Danish photographer, Daniel Rye Ottosen, was freed in June, the Danish Foreign Ministry said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>Why are some hostages freed and others killed?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>A multitude of factors are at work, including who the captors are and where the captives come from.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Different Western governments take different approaches to kidnappings.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Britain and the United States are known to take hard line, refusing to negotiate with terrorists or pay ransoms.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>But some European governments are believed to have handed over cash to terrorist groups to ensure the release of their citizens.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>An investigation by The New York Times found that al Qaeda and its affiliates have netted at least $125 million in ransoms since 2008, with much of the revenue reportedly coming from France -- although the French government denied paying money to terrorists.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="37">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>What about getting the hostages out by force?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="38">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>The United States and other countries attempted hostage rescues, but these have achieved mixed results.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="39">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>In 2012, Navy SEALs saved U.S. aid worker Jessica Buchanan and fellow aid worker Poul Thisted of Denmark after three months&amp;apost; captivity in Somalia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="40">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>But the attempts can also go badly wrong.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>Linda Norgrove, a kidnapped British aid worker, was accidentally killed by a U.S. grenade during a SEAL rescue effort in Afghanistan in 2010.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="41">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>U.S. special operations forces went into Syria in July to try to retrieve Foley and other ISIS captives.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>But the mission failed after the commandos were unable to find the hostages.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="42">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>The British government said earlier this month an attempt was made to rescue Haines &amp;quot;some time ago&amp;quot; but was unsuccessful.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="59">
          <content>It declined to provide details on what happened.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
