<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2784" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/09/20/world/meast/syria-civil-war/index.html" date_published="2013-09-20 12:13:14" category="world" author="Samira Said. Joe Sterling and Barbara Starr, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Syria submits &amp;apost;initial disclosure&amp;apost; of chemical weapons stockpiles</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Organization for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons is the world&amp;apost;s chemical arms watchdog.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">The normal 60-day process for declaring arms is being cut to seven days for Syria.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="8">This fast-tracking of the disclosure of chemical weapons is &amp;quot;irregular,&amp;quot; an official says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="38, 33">Secretary of States John Kerry says: &amp;quot;Time is short&amp;quot;.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-19 10:55:53" annotation_time="10.953">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Syria has begun detailing its chemical weapons arsenal, releasing an &amp;quot;initial declaration&amp;quot; of its stockpile, a spokesman for the U.N.-backed Organization for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons said Friday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;This is irregular,&amp;quot; Luhan said, explaining that this level of fast-tracking the disclosure of chemical weapons &amp;quot;has never been done before.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">The normal 60-day process for declaring arms is being expedited to seven days &amp;quot;because of the extraordinary concern about Syria&amp;apost;s weapons,&amp;quot; he said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="33" ids_highlights="4">Speaking ahead of next week&amp;apost;s U.N. General Assembly meeting, Kerry said Thursday that while &amp;quot;the complete removal of Syria&amp;apost;s chemical weapons is possible here, through peaceful means,&amp;quot; urgency is needed.</sentence>
      <sentence id="38" ids_highlights="4">&amp;quot;Time is short.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Syria has begun detailing its chemical weapons arsenal, releasing an &amp;quot;initial declaration&amp;quot; of its stockpile, a spokesman for the U.N.-backed Organization for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons said Friday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>More details about Syrian President Bashar al-Assad&amp;apost;s chemical weapons program are expected within the next day or two, spokesman Michael Luhan said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The international chemical weapons watchdog has been charged with overseeing the removal of al-Assad&amp;apost;s chemical weapons arsenal from Syria, part of a U.S.-Russian plan aimed at averting American military airstrikes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The information submitted by Syria is now being reviewed by the OPCW, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The group&amp;apost;s executive council -- which was to meet Sunday at The Hague, Netherlands -- has postponed the meeting until sometime next week, Luhan said, because &amp;quot;more time is needed&amp;quot; to review Syria&amp;apost;s chemical weapons disclosure and agree to put in place a framework for the U.S.-Russia plan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>This jibes with a timeline in the U.S.-Russian deal forged last week in Geneva, Switzerland, to begin destroying Syria&amp;apost;s chemical arsenal.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Under the Geneva framework deal, al-Assad was given a week beginning last Saturday to declare the weapons program.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is irregular,&amp;quot; Luhan said, explaining that this level of fast-tracking the disclosure of chemical weapons &amp;quot;has never been done before.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The normal 60-day process for declaring arms is being expedited to seven days &amp;quot;because of the extraordinary concern about Syria&amp;apost;s weapons,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;Until now, each country has been typical.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The United States, Russia, Libya, India, none have been in a state of war or conflict,&amp;quot; Luhan said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Once the group has received Syria&amp;apost;s full declaration, Luhan said, &amp;quot;we have to go through it in detail and plan how to conduct the on-the-ground inspection mission, to verify the accuracy of the declaration and put seals on all the materials to make sure they are secure.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>A technical briefing on the Syria mission that was to have been held Monday will be rescheduled once a new date has been set for the executive council meeting.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Officials report Syria moving stockpiles.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The Syrian regime is again moving around its stockpile of chemical weapons, leaving the United States trying to figure out what al-Assad will do next with his deadly arsenal, officials say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>CNN has learned that the U.S. intelligence community is closely watching the latest developments as diplomats try to form a plan for al-Assad to relinquish those stockpiles to international control.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>One U.S. official with access to the latest intelligence on Syria tells CNN the regime &amp;quot;is actively moving its stockpiles in the last 24 hours.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The official, speaking on condition of anonymity, says the latest intelligence information shows there is movement at additional sites beyond what the United States had observed in the last two weeks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s continuous but still unclear what they are really doing,&amp;quot; the official said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Officials don&amp;apost;t know whether the weapons are being moved to account for the stockpiles to the United Nations or to hide them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>One official confirmed the Obama administration received specific information in recent months from Russia that the chemical weapons are secure.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>That assessment came from communications between Moscow and Damascus.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The U.S. intelligence community also has continued to use satellite imagery, intercepts and human sources on the ground inside Syria to develop its own picture.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The United States has no reason to believe the weapons are not secure.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>But as CNN previously reported, there is also disagreement within the intelligence community about whether the United States knows the location of the entire stockpile.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>High-stakes diplomacy playing out.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The stakes over halting the Syrian civil war heightened after an August 21 chemical weapons attack outside Damascus that the United States estimates killed about 1,400 people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The United States and other Western nations blame al-Assad&amp;apost;s forces for the attack.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Russia and Syria say they think rebels used the weapons.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Citing international norms against the use of chemical weapons, President Barack Obama called for the authorization to use military force in Syria and wanted Congress to approve that move.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>As the United States threatened force to degrade al-Assad&amp;apost;s ability to carry out more chemical weapons attacks, a diplomatic opportunity arose between Russia and the United States to put Syria&amp;apost;s stockpile under international control.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>U.S. Secretary of State John Kerry and Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov hammered out a deal in Geneva last week compelling Syria to accept the agreement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Speaking ahead of next week&amp;apost;s U.N. General Assembly meeting, Kerry said Thursday that while &amp;quot;the complete removal of Syria&amp;apost;s chemical weapons is possible here, through peaceful means,&amp;quot; urgency is needed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The U.N. Security Council must be prepared to act next week, Kerry said, citing the U.N. chemical weapons report about the attack.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>While the report did not blame any side for the attack, Kerry said that it offered &amp;quot;crucial details,&amp;quot; making the case implicating al-Assad &amp;quot;only ... more compelling.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Russia called the report &amp;quot;distorted&amp;quot; and said it was based on insufficient information.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Despite the diplomacy, the United States hasn&amp;apost;t dropped its threat of force and is wary, saying Syria could be using the diplomacy as a stalling tactic.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;Time is short.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Let&amp;apost;s not spend time debating what we already know,&amp;quot; Kerry said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The United Nations estimates more than 100,000 people have died since March 2011, a period in which harsh government crackdowns against protesters devolved into an all-out civil war.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Another 2 million people have fled their homeland, and more than 4.25 million have been displaced within Syria, the United Nations says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
