<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2593" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/02/16/world/pay-solar-africa/index.html" date_published="2012-02-16 12:45:11" category="world" author="Eoghan Macguire, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Pay-as-you-go solar power lights up rural Africa</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Pay-as-you-go solar aims to bring affordable electricity to rural Africa.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">Technology aims to replace harmful environmental products such as kerosene lamps.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">Service allows users to light their homes for as little as $1 a week.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-18 13:18:06" annotation_time="52.704666">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Pay-as-you-go products may be synonymous with mobile phones but a solar energy service in Africa is harnessing the popular business model to bring affordable electricity to the continent&amp;apost;s remotest communities.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">Users then have the option of purchasing the energy the device produces for as little as $1 a week.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">The technology aims to replace environmentally harmful lighting practices such as burning kerosene oil, which contributes 190 million tons of annual CO2 emissions according to studies conducted by the Berkley Laboratory at the University of California and can cost users up to 10 times as much.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Pay-as-you-go products may be synonymous with mobile phones but a solar energy service in Africa is harnessing the popular business model to bring affordable electricity to the continent&amp;apost;s remotest communities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>IndiGo solar enables rural households far removed from their country&amp;apost;s electrical grid to generate their own power via a photovoltaic panel and battery pack.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Users then have the option of purchasing the energy the device produces for as little as $1 a week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The technology aims to replace environmentally harmful lighting practices such as burning kerosene oil, which contributes 190 million tons of annual CO2 emissions according to studies conducted by the Berkley Laboratory at the University of California and can cost users up to 10 times as much.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;Pay-as-you-go solar is a good system as we now have light inside,&amp;quot; says Nyungura James Ode, a farmer from Mantarra Village in South Sudan and one of the first to sign up to the project.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;(We) can do more work at home and be more productive farming.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Light is better (and) mothers can tend to baby at night more easily, give medicine, change clothes and diaper,&amp;quot; he adds.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>See also: Solar lamps replacing kerosene.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The system -- which can light two small rooms for seven hours at a time and charge small portable devices such as mobile phones -- has been designed and manufactured by British based solar technology company, Eight19.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>It works in a similar fashion to mobile phone top-up cards.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>When users want to purchase electricity produced by their solar pack they buy a scratch card from a local vendor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The card costs roughly $1 and reveals a code that grants access to the electricity for a week when dialed into the battery.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>This allows users to keep a close eye on the amount they spend and consume.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;We don&amp;apost;t have to spend more money,&amp;quot; says Ode. &amp;quot;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>[I am] saving three to five South Sudanese Pounds a week,&amp;quot; -- between $1.20 and $1.80.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>So far, remote towns in Kenya, Malawi, South Sudan and Zambia have adopted the IndiGo electrification scheme.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Yet while the practical gains for villagers used to living without electricity are obvious, the environmental benefits have thus far been harder to gauge.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The first solar packs were only introduced in September 2010, making verifying claims as to their long term green credentials difficult.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>See also: Amazing solar powered gadgets.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>But according to Steve Andrews, CEO of UK based charity, SolarAid, pay-as-you-go solar could revolutionize rural African development.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;(This) approach has the potential to bring electricity supply to these people without a traditional grid; just as mobile phones have brought telephony to those people without a need for a telephone landline system,&amp;quot; says Andrews.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;Indigo is a potential game changer in bringing clean, safe lighting and electricity to the world&amp;apost;s poorest people,&amp;quot; he adds.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Such enthusiastic proclamations as to the technology&amp;apost;s environmental potential are echoed by Dr Simon Bransfield-Garth, CEO of Eight19.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>He says that his company hopes to make a considerable dent on global carbon emissions through IndiGo.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;We (Eight19) aim to eliminate the use of kerosene for lighting in Africa by the end of the decade,&amp;quot; he explains.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>But in order to meet such ambitious targets, Bransfield-Garth is quick to cite the need to keep improving and developing the IndiGo product.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;At the moment we&amp;apost;ve focused on the entry product as we want to get scale but as time progresses we want to encourage people to install larger solar systems with greater capabilities,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;So, in the future, if you pay a little extra you will be able to generate enough electricity to power items such as televisions, radios and fridges.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>This could mean providing access to similar levels of electricity that you get in most big cities,&amp;quot; he adds.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
