<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2567" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/04/16/world/africa/oscar-pistorius-trial/?hpt=bosread" date_published="2014-04-16 07:47:07" category="world" author="Faith Karimi and Emily Smith, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Oscar Pistorius trial enters new phase after cross-examination</title>
  <keywords>Oscar Pistorius,Reeva Steenkamp,Oscar Pistorius murder trial,Oscar Pistorius testifies</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="35">After Thursday&amp;apost;s session, the trial will be postponed until May 5 .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Prosecutor has accused the athlete of inconsistencies and contradictions .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">The defense calls forensics expert Roger Dixon.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="5">He disputes a pathologist&amp;apost;s explanation of victim Reeva Steenkamp&amp;apost;s back wounds.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-03 05:19:43" annotation_time="40.549">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">During cross-examination, prosecutor Gerrie Nel accused the athlete of inconsistencies and contradictions in his testimony.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3, 4">Defense attorney Barry Roux called forensics expert Roger Dixon, who disputed a conclusion by a pathologist on the cause of Steenkamp&amp;apost;s back wounds.</sentence>
      <sentence id="35" ids_highlights="1">The trial will be postponed until May 5 after Thursday&amp;apost;s session per the state&amp;apost;s request, the judge said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>After five days of relentless cross-examination that left Oscar Pistorius quivering, sobbing and fumbling, the athlete&amp;apost;s defense team now has a chance to discredit the prosecution by presenting its witnesses.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>During cross-examination, prosecutor Gerrie Nel accused the athlete of inconsistencies and contradictions in his testimony.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>His aim is to prove that Pistorius intentionally shot and killed his girlfriend, Reeva Steenkamp, after a heated argument in the early hours of Valentine&amp;apost;s Day last year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The defense team now gets its chance to cast doubt on that account and prove that the star sprinter shot his girlfriend through a closed bathroom door after mistaking her for an intruder.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Defense attorney Barry Roux called forensics expert Roger Dixon, who disputed a conclusion by a pathologist on the cause of Steenkamp&amp;apost;s back wounds.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The pathologist said they were made by a bullet ricochet.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Dixon said they were made by a magazine rack.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The autopsy said they were made by a blunt, hard object.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Nel took every opportunity to discredit Dixon, including questioning his ballistics evidence when he said none of the bullets missed Steenkamp, while the state expert had said one did.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;You see how irresponsible it is to make inferences in areas where you&amp;apost;re not an expert?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Nel told him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>At one point, Judge Thokozile Masipa ordered the state prosecutor to be less aggressive in his questioning.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Valentine&amp;apost;s Day card.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Pistorius has maintained he was terrified when he heard noises from the bathroom.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>When he entered the bathroom and heard a noise behind the closed toilet door, he pulled the trigger without thinking, believing an intruder was inside.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>And in an apparent bid to show their romance was not as rocky as portrayed by the prosecution, Pistorius on Tuesday read a card that Steenkamp had planned to give him on Valentine&amp;apost;s Day.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;Roses are red, violets are blue, I think today is a good day to tell you that I love you,&amp;quot; the message read.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Last week, Pistorius, 27, took the stand for the first time since the trial started on March 3 to testify about what happened on the fateful day.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>During his cross-examination, the prosecution released details of his relationship with the model and law school graduate, which began in November 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>It included text messages retrieved from their phones.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Nel accused him of acting selfishly toward Steenkamp, picking on her and shunning a declaration of love that she sent via a phone message.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The court also heard audio recordings Dixon had made of a cricket bat striking a door similar to the one in Pistorius&amp;apost; toilet, and of gunshots fired through the door.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Prosecution witnesses have testified to hearing a woman scream, followed by gun shots, but the defense disputes their testimony, saying the only scream came from Pistorius after he had fired the fatal shots.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The trial was later adjourned for the day.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Gripping trial.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>If Pistorius is found guilty of premeditated murder, he faces 25 years to life in prison.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The defense team will call 14 to 17 witnesses, Roux said when he opened his case.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The trial is scheduled to continue until the middle of May.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Masipa will decide the verdict in collaboration with two experts called assessors.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>South Africa does not have jury trials.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The trial has gripped South Africa and sports fans worldwide who considered Pistorius a symbol of triumph over physical adversity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>His disabled lower legs were amputated when he was a baby, but he went on to achieve global fame as the &amp;quot;Blade Runner,&amp;quot; winning numerous Paralympic gold medals on the steel blades fitted to his prostheses.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Only those in the courtroom saw Pistorius on the stand, because he chose not to testify on camera.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>His testimony could be heard in an audio feed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The trial will be postponed until May 5 after Thursday&amp;apost;s session per the state&amp;apost;s request, the judge said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
