<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2314" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/07/11/world/europe/ireland-abortion/index.html" date_published="2013-07-11 07:46:31" category="world" author="Michael Martinez and Ben Brumfield, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Irish Parliament passes exception to abortion ban</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="27">NEW: Human Rights Watch says the bill fails women in Ireland by not going far enough.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">The final bill includes a provision allowing abortion if the mother is at risk of suicide.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">The majority government supports the bill.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="4">Conservative and progressive lawmakers argue over various amendments.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-15 21:03:08" annotation_time="25.9675">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">The vote was 127-31 in favor of the bill.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="4">Conservative and progressive lawmakers argued over amendments to the draft law.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">Religious lawmakers and church leaders are upset over a provision allowing abortion if a pregnant woman is acutely at risk of committing suicide.</sentence>
      <sentence id="27" ids_highlights="1">Human Rights Watch said the new legislation failed Ireland&amp;apost;s women by not going far enough to reform the country&amp;apost;s abortion laws.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Irish lawmakers overwhelmingly passed new legislation early Friday that allows abortions if the mother&amp;apost;s life is at risk.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Members of Parliament in the devoutly Catholic country spent hours before its passage debating the Protection of Life During Pregnancy Bill 2013.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The vote was 127-31 in favor of the bill.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Conservative and progressive lawmakers argued over amendments to the draft law.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Religious lawmakers and church leaders are upset over a provision allowing abortion if a pregnant woman is acutely at risk of committing suicide.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>They called it a &amp;quot;Trojan horse&amp;quot; leading to easy abortion access and wanted it removed, but the provision was included in the final bill, according to The Irish Times.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>A woman can&amp;apost;t just threaten to commit suicide and expect to receive an abortion, according to the bill.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Two psychiatrists and an obstetrician must certify that the risk of suicide is &amp;quot;real and substantial.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Female lawmakers introduced an amendment to permit abortions if a woman becomes pregnant after incest or rape, but later shelved it when it ran into resistance, the Times reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>In its final provisions, the bill underlines existing Irish laws to protect the fetus.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;It shall be an offense to intentionally destroy unborn human life,&amp;quot; it reads.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>A woman who violates the law could face a maximum penalty of 14 years in prison.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The bill has proved divisive even within the government.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>European Affairs Minister Lucinda Creighton, who was opposed to elements of the legislation, resigned Thursday, Prime Minister Enda Kenny confirmed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Doctors and hospital personnel involved in illegal abortions face the same punishment, according to the bill.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The issue was brought to the forefront last year when a 31-year-old woman died after doctors refused to perform a life-saving abortion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Savita Halappanavar went into a hospital in Galway, Ireland, in October, complaining of severe back pain.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Doctors established Halappanavar, who was 17 weeks pregnant, was having a miscarriage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>But they did not terminate the pregnancy, afraid the law would not allow it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Three days after the request for a termination was made, the fetus died and was removed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Four days later, Savita died of a blood infection.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Public outrage over her death likely hastened the passage of the new legislation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>It was proposed after a 2010 ruling by the European Court of Human Rights, but had been moving slowly through the legislative system.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The European Court of Human Rights found that Ireland&amp;apost;s failure to regulate access to abortion had led to a violation of its human rights obligations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Twenty years ago, the Irish Supreme Court ruled abortions are allowed when there is a real and substantial risk to the life of the mother.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>But the ruling was never enacted into law, meaning there was little clarity for doctors or patients as to when an abortion could not take place.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Human Rights Watch said the new legislation failed Ireland&amp;apost;s women by not going far enough to reform the country&amp;apost;s abortion laws.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>It did &amp;quot;the bare minimum&amp;quot; to comply with the European court ruling, and did not address other issues such as the rights of women who are pregnant as a result of rape, it said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;The new law does add clarity, but requiring women to seek multiple approvals from health professionals may delay or defeat access to legal abortions,&amp;quot; said Gauri van Gulik, women&amp;apost;s rights advocate for Human Rights Watch.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;Ultimately it does little to improve the draconian restrictions on abortions.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
