<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2256" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/01/02/world/africa/egypt-mubarak-trial/index.html" date_published="2012-01-02 09:50:38" category="world" author="Mohamed Fadel Fahmy, For CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Hosni Mubarak trial set to begin in Egypt</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">NEW: The verdict date will depend on how long defense and victims&amp;apost; lawyers take.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Mubarak could learn his fate before the end of the month, a lawyer says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">Mubarak is charged with ordering the killing of protesters.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="8">Many Egyptians are critical of the court proceedings and worry he may be acquitted .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-02 14:22:56" annotation_time="57.77">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2, 3">Cairo Former Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak, accused of ordering protesters killed, could face a verdict before the end of the month, a lawyer involved in the trial said Monday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">Adel Saeed, an official spokesman for the general prosecutor&amp;apost;s office, confirmed that there is &amp;quot;a possibility&amp;quot; of a verdict by January 25, depending on how long prosecutors and lawyers for the victims and the defense take to present their cases, plus the time the judge needs &amp;quot;to review all the documents and evidence presented.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="4">Many Egyptians are critical of the court proceedings and some worry that Mubarak may be acquitted of the murder charges.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Cairo Former Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak, accused of ordering protesters killed, could face a verdict before the end of the month, a lawyer involved in the trial said Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;I expect a verdict before January 25, the anniversary of the revolution,&amp;quot; lawyer Khaled Abu Bakr said, referring to the beginning of the uprising that ended Mubarak&amp;apost;s 30-year rule in February.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Prosecutors will have three days to present their case starting Tuesday, said Abu Bakr, a civil rights lawyer representing families of the victims.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Adel Saeed, an official spokesman for the general prosecutor&amp;apost;s office, confirmed that there is &amp;quot;a possibility&amp;quot; of a verdict by January 25, depending on how long prosecutors and lawyers for the victims and the defense take to present their cases, plus the time the judge needs &amp;quot;to review all the documents and evidence presented.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The former president also faces corruption charges.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>He has pleaded not guilty.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Mubarak was wheeled into court in a gurney Monday for a brief hearing that was described as &amp;quot;procedural,&amp;quot; to allow a judge to decide on specific requests presented by the lawyers during last weeks&amp;apost; session, Abu Bakr said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Many Egyptians are critical of the court proceedings and some worry that Mubarak may be acquitted of the murder charges.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Five police officers accused of killing protesters were acquitted last week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The killings in question took place in front of a police station near downtown Cairo during January 28 and 29.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;Most people panicking after the verdict do not know that two families of the victims involved in this case have withdrawn the charges against the officers, &amp;quot; Abu Bakr said. &amp;quot;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Their case was considered self-defense because the officers were defending their police station, which is different than the cases of those protesters killed by snipers from a distance in Tahrir (Square,)&amp;quot; the center of protests against Mubarak.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Mubarak&amp;apost;s health has been in question since his detention began in April 2011 after reports of his cancer and heart problems surfaced in the media.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Hauled away from the courthouse on his hospital gurney, Mubarak hid his face and covered his eyes from TV cameras.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Former Egyptian Interior Minister Habib El Adly, six of his aides and two of Mubarak&amp;apost;s sons are also on trial on a variety of charges.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Sons Gamal and Alaa, who also were present in the courtroom&amp;apost;s cage, have also pleaded not guilty.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The trial is expected to resume &amp;quot;almost daily&amp;quot; starting this week, as announced by the judge handling the case during its previous session.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>About 840 people died and more than 6,000 were wounded in the 18 days of uprising that toppled Mubarak, according to Amnesty International.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
