<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2413" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/10/18/world/africa/mali-shrines/index.html" date_published="2012-10-19 01:57:42" category="world" author="Amir Ahmed, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Mali Islamists destroy tombs in Timbuktu</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">Residents say 3 mausolea were destroyed.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">They were all U.N. World Heritage sites.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="18">Islamist militants regard such shrines as idolatrous.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-03 05:16:12" annotation_time="29.404665">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">Three four-wheel-drive trucks carrying at least 30 armed fighters arrived Thursday morning at three mausolea -- all U.N. World Heritage sites -- in the southern Timbuktu neighborhood of Kabara, two residents told CNN by phone.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">The mausolea, one of which held the remains of a religious leader and the founder of the neighborhood, were destroyed within an hour, Ag Mohamed said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="3">Islamist militants regard such shrines as idolatrous and thus prohibited by their religion.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Al Qaeda-linked rebels in northern Mali destroyed historic and religious landmarks in Timbuktu on Thursday, claiming the relics are idolatrous, residents told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Three four-wheel-drive trucks carrying at least 30 armed fighters arrived Thursday morning at three mausolea -- all U.N. World Heritage sites -- in the southern Timbuktu neighborhood of Kabara, two residents told CNN by phone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;They started destroying the first mausoleum&amp;apost;s wooden door with their axes,&amp;quot; said Ibrahim Ag Mohamed, a guide.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;Then they went inside and burned the cloth covering the grave before destroying the building with picks and axes.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The mausolea, one of which held the remains of a religious leader and the founder of the neighborhood, were destroyed within an hour, Ag Mohamed said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;The local Islamists were reinforced by between 30-40 men carrying Kalashnikovs and axes,&amp;quot; said Sankoum Sissoko, another resident.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;They started destroying the mausolea and didn&amp;apost;t finish until they had turned the tomb into rubble,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Area residents, too afraid to try to stop the destruction, simply watched, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;After the attack, the Islamists told the people that worshiping saints is not right, according to their form of Islam, and the destruction was necessary,&amp;quot; he continued.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Thursday&amp;apost;s attack was at least the fourth this year on Timbukto&amp;apost;s historic tombs, said Osmane Halle, the former mayor of Timbuktu.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>International outrage has been growing over the destruction of the West African nation&amp;apost;s shrines.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The United States and a number of other nations have condemned previous attacks on Mali&amp;apost;s historic tombs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Chaos has rocked the country since March, when a military ruler overthrew the democratically elected president, shaking what had been one of West Africa&amp;apost;s most stable democracies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The coup leader stepped down in May and transferred power to a civilian transitional government, but uncertainty looms.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Ethnic Tuareg rebels and other Islamist militants have taken advantage of the uncertainty to seize control of the northern portion of the country, including Timbuktu.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Ansar Dine, an al Qaeda-linked group claiming control of the city, is blamed for the attacks on historical landmarks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The picturesque city, considered an important destination for Islamic scholars, features a number of ancient and prominent burial sites.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Islamist militants regard such shrines as idolatrous and thus prohibited by their religion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>They have targeted Sufi shrines, which they say they are sacrilegious.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Sufism is a mystical dimension of Islam considered offbeat by Islamic hardliners, who frown upon it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The Sufis, who took Islam to much of sub-Saharan Africa, dance, pray and preach using drama and humor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;If the Islamists continue in this way, there will be nothing left of Timbuktu&amp;apost;s sacred heritage that made it famous all over the world,&amp;quot; Halle said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;I ask the international community to help Mali find a solution to the country&amp;apost;s problem, no matter if it&amp;apost;s a military intervention or negotiations, this has to end.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Last week, the U.N. Security Council approved a resolution that gave regional leaders until November 19 to provide plans for an international military intervention that would oust rebels from northern Mali.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The resolution, which passed by a unanimous vote, calls for retaking the region from al-Qaeda-linked rebels.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>In a similar attack in 2001, the Taliban destroyed ancient Buddhist relics in Afghanistan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
