<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2508" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/06/18/world/asia/shah-india-rape-crisis/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-06-18 05:27:40" category="world" author="Gayatri Rangachari Shah" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>No quick fix for India&amp;apost;s rape crisis</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Northern India has experienced especially brutal violence, with a spate of brutal rapes.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="44">Gayatri Rangachari Shah: Indians have to shift their cultural mindset towards women.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="16">The conviction rate in rape cases has declined over the past few years.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="22">Political insensitivity is not helping victims feel safe coming forward.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-25 09:41:23" annotation_time="46.65567" mapping_time_divergence="11.663918">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">In the past few weeks, the north of India has experienced especially brutal violence, particularly in the state of Uttar Pradesh.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="3">Although the number of rape cases registered in the state increased from 1563 in 2010 to 1963 in 2012, the state&amp;apost;s conviction rate for such cases declined from 2010 to 2012, from 45.1 percent to 31.5 percent, according to data from the National Bureau of Crime Statistics (NBCS).</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="4">Political insensitivity is not helping to foster a climate in which victims of sexual violence feel safe coming forward.</sentence>
      <sentence id="44" ids_highlights="2">For a start, Indians have to shift our cultural mindset.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Mumbai&amp;apost;s moviegoers are getting used to seeing a police-issued public service clip before the start of films, encouraging them to come forward to report crimes against women.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a relevant message, given the regular reports of grisly gang rapes and murders roiling the nation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>In the past few weeks, the north of India has experienced especially brutal violence, particularly in the state of Uttar Pradesh.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>On May 27, the alleged gang rape and hanging of two teenage girls, age 14 and 15, in Badaun district made headlines.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Two weeks later, the body of a 45-year-old alleged gang rape victim was found hanging from a tree in Bahraich district.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Since then, a 16-year-old girl was found hanged from a tree in Moradabad district, allegedly after having been raped.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>In Kushinagar, an 18-year-old was apparently raped by two people and dumped in a pond.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>And just days ago came news of another gang rape in Badaun, that of a 32-year-old woman.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>After the infamous December 2012 rape and death of a physiotherapy student in New Delhi, the rape of a photojournalist in Mumbai in August last year and the rapes of several foreign visitors to India, the specter of a crisis haunts India.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;Clearly, rape is nothing new,&amp;quot; says Madhu Kishwar, a pioneering feminist and academic who founded Manushi, a journal on women&amp;apost;s issues, more than 40 years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;What&amp;apost;s new is the increased brutalization of the rape victims.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s an epidemic of brutality.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Kishwar notes a heightened frustration and angst amongst young men facing limited options in life as a factor in the wave of sexual violence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Beyond that, she also points to general lawlessness in states like Uttar Pradesh, where politics is highly criminalized.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Uttar Pradesh, with 200 million people, is India&amp;apost;s most populous state and ranks fourth across all states and union territories in rape crimes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Although the number of rape cases registered in the state increased from 1563 in 2010 to 1963 in 2012, the state&amp;apost;s conviction rate for such cases declined from 2010 to 2012, from 45.1 percent to 31.5 percent, according to data from the National Bureau of Crime Statistics (NBCS).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>This trend mirrors what&amp;apost;s happening nationally.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>While the total number of rape cases in India registered a 12 percent increase between 2010 and 2012, the conviction rate declined from 17.1 percent to 14.3 percent, resulting in fewer convictions in 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>(In the majority of these cases, the rape offenders were known to victims.).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Yet domestic data belies this, given that in 2012, the latest year for which official data is available, 24,923 rape cases were registered nationally, according to the NBCS.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>This is almost certainly a reflection of the under-reporting of crimes of sexual violence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Political insensitivity is not helping to foster a climate in which victims of sexual violence feel safe coming forward.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Mulayam Singh Yadav, the head of the Samajwadi Party, which governs Uttar Pradesh, courted controversy when he decried stricter punishments for rapists after laws were overhauled last year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>He was quoted as suggesting that boys make such mistakes, and that rapists shouldn&amp;apost;t be awarded the death penalty.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>His Australian educated son, Akhilesh Yadav, who is the state&amp;apost;s chief minister, also misstepped.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>When probed by journalists about the increase in rapes in his state, he retorted in Hindi: &amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s not as though you faced danger.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The Samajwadi Party is hardly alone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Boorish politicians across party lines have made repugnant statements, including calling rape &amp;quot;accidental&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;sometimes right, sometimes wrong.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Such thoughts reflect Indian society&amp;apost;s deep-rooted patriarchy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>We rank 132 out of 187 countries on gender inequality, according to the UNDP&amp;apost;s Human Development Report, lower even than neighboring Pakistan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>A 2014 report by Dasra, a Mumbai based philanthropic foundation says that almost 70 percent of women in India face some form of domestic violence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>In their book &amp;quot;An Uncertain Glory,&amp;quot; economists Amartya Sen and Jean Dreze write that Indian women&amp;apost;s participation in the workforce beyond the home &amp;quot;remains extremely low by international standards, and shows little sign of increasing&amp;quot; -- a situation attributed in part to &amp;quot;negative social attitudes towards women&amp;apost;s work outside the household.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Poverty and poor sanitation are a blight on India.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Forty percent of schools in India do not have separate toilets for girls, leading to higher school drop out rates for girls as they attain puberty and perpetuating the cycle of low female literacy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Lack of access to toilets plays a role in making women vulnerable to assaults.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>The two teenage cousins killed in the Badaun assaults had stepped out to relieve themselves when they were abducted.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Caste oppression also continues to be a real issue.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>In Uttar Pradesh, caste certainly played a factor in some of the crimes, which reflected a pattern of higher caste men feeling entitled to victimize lower caste victims with relative impunity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>But, as is often the case with all things Indian, generalizations have their limits.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The rape of a photojournalist in Mumbai last August had nothing to do with caste and everything to do with young men attacking a woman for sport.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;Each case has to be looked at individually,&amp;quot; says Kishwar.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;It would be a mistake to lump them all into one group.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>How, then, do we restore faith in our society and tackle this menace?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>For a start, Indians have to shift our cultural mindset.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>We must give women wider berth in employment opportunities to foster economic independence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>The idea of woman as personal property, which leads to a sense of male entitlement, has to be eradicated.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>Marital rape, currently not legally recognized, must be criminalized.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>In the short-term, we need better law enforcement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>The police need to step up their game nationally, but especially in places like beleaguered Uttar Pradesh.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Victims should be encouraged to come forward to report crimes with the expectation they will be treated with care.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>More policewomen need to be recruited, and dedicated cells for violent sexual crimes must be the norm in police stations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Mandatory gender sensitivity training and quicker response times to crimes should be built into police performance evaluation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>Conviction rates need to go up, but justice also needs to be timely.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>Indians recently took pride in peacefully electing a new government, one that took the reins in New Delhi promising change.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>A priority for them in delivering on that promise must be to ensure women&amp;apost;s security.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
