<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2370" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/10/21/world/asia/north-korea-bae-mother/index.html" date_published="2013-10-21 15:29:00" category="world" author="Paula Hancocks, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Kenneth Bae&amp;apost;s mother tells of heartbreak after leaving imprisoned son</title>
  <keywords>Kenneth Bae,Myunghee Bae,North Korea,Kenneth Bae&amp;apost;s mother</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Myunghee Bae says seeing son at a Pyongyang hospital was a &amp;quot;very happy moment&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">She was granted a five-day visa to North Korea and three short visits with Kenneth Bae.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="8, 7">He was sentenced in May to 15 years of hard labor after being found guilty of &amp;quot;hostile acts&amp;quot; .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="14">&amp;quot;Please give him mercy and give him amnesty to send him home,&amp;quot; mother asks government.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 18:30:18" annotation_time="43.097336" mapping_time_divergence="10.774334">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Talking exclusively to CNN, Bae said it was a &amp;quot;very happy moment.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">Bae was granted a five-day visa to North Korea and three short visits with her son, Kenneth; a total of six hours, in which she says there was not one moment&amp;apost;s silence.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="3">Kenneth Bae, an American citizen, was arrested in November of last year and sentenced in May to 15 years of hard labor.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="3">The North Korean regime says he was found guilty of &amp;quot;hostile acts&amp;quot; and attempts to topple the government.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="4">Although Bae was unable to meet with North Korean officials to plead her son&amp;apost;s case, she wants to make her message to them clear: &amp;quot;Please give him mercy and give him amnesty to send him home.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Walking into a Pyongyang hospital room to greet her imprisoned son, Myunghee Bae was overcome with emotion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Talking exclusively to CNN, Bae said it was a &amp;quot;very happy moment.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>At the same time, I could not believe he was a prisoner in North Korea; a new realization.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Bae was granted a five-day visa to North Korea and three short visits with her son, Kenneth; a total of six hours, in which she says there was not one moment&amp;apost;s silence.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;He said he&amp;apost;s being treated very fairly,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;He was taken to a special labor camp, so he was the only prisoner, and a whole lot of people have to stay with him, guards and doctors.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Kenneth Bae, an American citizen, was arrested in November of last year and sentenced in May to 15 years of hard labor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The North Korean regime says he was found guilty of &amp;quot;hostile acts&amp;quot; and attempts to topple the government.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>His mother says he has a profound love for the country and its people, and any offense he caused was not intentional.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;Always, he wanted to help the people over there, help the country,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;He always thought that way, but apparently he misunderstood their system, so a lot of things he realized -- he did some harm to their country.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Bae added that her son&amp;apost;s Christian faith was so strong, he wanted to convey his feelings.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>North Korea is officially an atheist state and has punished missionaries in the past.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Although Bae was unable to meet with North Korean officials to plead her son&amp;apost;s case, she wants to make her message to them clear: &amp;quot;Please give him mercy and give him amnesty to send him home.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>We apologize as a family on his behalf, but his health cannot sustain any longer if he is sent back to the labor camp again.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Bae was forced to work in the camp for three months until his health deteriorated.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>His mother says his illnesses include diabetes, an enlarged heart, gallstones, back and neck pains, and high cholesterol.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Bae says he looked better when she met him than he appeared in the footage of his hospitalization in August.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>But that brings its own concerns.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;My worst fear is to send him back to the labor camp because his health seems a little bit improved, that&amp;apost;s my worst fear.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Because I don&amp;apost;t think his body can endure eight hours labor a day, six days a week.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Previous Americans detained in North Korea have been released when high-profile visitors have traveled to the country to plead their case.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Most notably, former Presidents Bill Clinton and Jimmy Carter went on two separate occasions in 2010.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Bae believes her son&amp;apost;s case has not encouraged such attention, as relations between Washington and Pyongyang hit a new low this year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Myunghee Bae says it has been an agonizing 11 months, not only for her, but also for Kenneth Bae&amp;apost;s wife and three children.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;They all had a very hard time, and I think we all as a family felt helpless.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>We could not do anything for him, only sending letters ... we don&amp;apost;t have any power to bring him home.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The most heart-breaking part of the trip for Bae was leaving Pyongyang and walking out of the hospital without her son.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;It was very hard; I cannot express my pain and my heartache to leave him behind as a prisoner in North Korea.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>How long will it take to see him again?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
