<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2116" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/07/29/world/asia/china-investigation/index.html" date_published="2014-07-29 10:42:27" category="world" author="Steven Jiang, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>China probing retired security czar Zhou Yongkang</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="10">NEW: &amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s almost certain&amp;quot; Zhou would be put on trial, a longtime political observer says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">Zhou had been on the nine-member Politburo Standing Committee.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">He had been rumored to be under house arrest before Tuesday&amp;apost;s announcement.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="9">If indicted, he would be the highest-ranking PRC official ever to face corruption charges .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-09 10:51:30" annotation_time="17.2305">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">Before stepping down in late 2012, Zhou, 71, was one of the nine members that formed the Politburo Standing Committee, China&amp;apost;s top decision-making body that effectively rules the country of more than 1.3 billion people.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">Zhou himself had been rumored to be under house arrest before Tuesday&amp;apost;s announcement.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="4">If indicted, Zhou would become the highest-ranking official ever to face corruption charges in the history of the People&amp;apost;s Republic.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s almost certain the he would be put on trial and appear in public,&amp;quot; said Professor Willy Lam with Chinese University of Hong Kong, a longtime commentator on Chinese politics.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Beijing After months of intense political rumors, China&amp;apost;s ruling Communist Party announced Tuesday an official probe into a retired senior leader for suspected &amp;quot;serious disciplinary violation.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Zhou Yongkang, the former domestic security czar, was placed under investigation in accordance with Party regulations, the Central Commission for Discipline Inspection said in a one-line statement without elaborating.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Before stepping down in late 2012, Zhou, 71, was one of the nine members that formed the Politburo Standing Committee, China&amp;apost;s top decision-making body that effectively rules the country of more than 1.3 billion people.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Under his watch, the domestic security budget swelled to surpass that of the military in the name of &amp;quot;maintaining stability,&amp;quot; as a widening income gap between the rich and the poor as well as growing discontent over official corruption fueled social unrest nationwide.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Amid an intensifying anti-corruption campaign launched by President Xi Jinping, many political analysts and ordinary citizens have noted ties between an increasing number of disgraced officials and Zhou in recent months.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Zhou himself had been rumored to be under house arrest before Tuesday&amp;apost;s announcement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>State media have reported official anti-corruption probes into many of Zhou&amp;apost;s family members as well as former associates in the domestic security apparatus, state oil industry and southwestern Sichuan province -- three places Zhou once ruled.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Three of his former senior aides were arrested early this month.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>If indicted, Zhou would become the highest-ranking official ever to face corruption charges in the history of the People&amp;apost;s Republic.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s almost certain the he would be put on trial and appear in public,&amp;quot; said Professor Willy Lam with Chinese University of Hong Kong, a longtime commentator on Chinese politics.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;The important thing is that Xi Jinping has proven he&amp;apost;s powerful enough to break this taboo of never incriminating former Politburo Standing Committee members -- and in the future he can use this anti-corruption card to thrash his political enemies.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The news on Zhou came on the heels of the downfall of several former high-ranking officials, including a retired top general of the 2 million-strong People&amp;apost;s Liberation Army.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Gen. Xu Caihou, a former vice chairman of the Central Military Commission, which runs the world&amp;apost;s largest standing army, was expelled from the Communist Party and handed over to prosecutors after being found to have accepted bribes, state-run Xinhua news agency reported early this month.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Xu was also a member of the Politburo before retiring in 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>State media have characterized Xu as a big &amp;quot;military tiger&amp;quot; caught in the massive anti-graft campaign spearheaded by Xi, who is also the commander-in-chief.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Xi banned official extravagance -- from banquets to year-end gifts -- and vowed to target &amp;quot;tigers and flies&amp;quot; alike in his fight against corruption.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>He resolved to spare no one, regardless of position.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>CCTV recently touted the capture of 35 &amp;quot;tigers&amp;quot; since Xi took power less than two years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Some 182,000 officials were disciplined in 2013, while courts nationwide tried 23,000 corruption cases, according to the Communist Party&amp;apost;s disciplinary commission.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>State media have cited the trial and conviction last year of former high-flying politician Bo Xilai -- a protégé of Zhou -- as a prime example of Xi&amp;apost;s determination to clean up the party, though Bo supporters called the case against him politically motivated.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;Now everybody is really scared -- and this would have a big impact on the behavior of senior Party members,&amp;quot; said Lam, the political analyst.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;But nobody expects corruption to be eradicated.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>It is built into the system, a system without checks and balances.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
