<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2246" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/04/23/world/meast/middle-east-hollywood-films-censorship-survey/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-04-24 02:37:25" category="world" author="Yenni Kwok, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Hollywood movies in Arab countries: A love and hate relationship</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Almost half of Arab residents in six Middle East and North African countries say they watch Hollywood movies.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">But more than a third say American films have content that is &amp;quot;harmful to morality.&amp;quot; .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="11">More than two-thirds agree that films or other entertainment programs should be banned if they are deemed to be offensive. .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 19:41:18" annotation_time="10.327">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1"> Arab residents in the Middle East and North Africa may enjoy Hollywood blockbusters, but they are also wary of the content, saying it is potentially &amp;quot;harmful to morality,&amp;quot; a study finds.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">According to the survey 45% of respondents say they watch Hollywood movies, but 34% say American films have content that is &amp;quot;harmful to morality.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="3">More than two-thirds agree that films or other entertainment programs should be banned if they are deemed to be offensive.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Arab residents in the Middle East and North Africa may enjoy Hollywood blockbusters, but they are also wary of the content, saying it is potentially &amp;quot;harmful to morality,&amp;quot; a study finds.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The &amp;quot;Entertainment Media Use in the Middle East&amp;quot; survey, commissioned by Northwestern University and the Doha Film Institute, interviewed more than 6,000 people -- both nationals and expats -- in Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Lebanon, Egypt, Tunisia and the United Arab Emirates.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>According to the survey 45% of respondents say they watch Hollywood movies, but 34% say American films have content that is &amp;quot;harmful to morality.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Only 15% say U.S.-made films are good for morality -- as opposed to 71% who feel the same about Arab movies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The respondents are also conflicted about other foreign films.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>While two-thirds say people benefit from watching movies from different parts of the world, 65% say they prefer films that portray their own culture.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>More than half (54%) say films are an important source of information about their own culture.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>It is no surprise that an overwhelming number prefer Arab films, which are favored by more than 80% of overall respondents.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>In contrast, only around half of the citizens surveyed say they enjoy American and European movies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>A large majority of respondents believe entertainment should be regulated for both romantic and violent content.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>More than two-thirds agree that films or other entertainment programs should be banned if they are deemed to be offensive.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Respondents in Saudi Arabia and Egypt show the strongest support for censorship -- 76% and 77% respectively.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Tunisia appears to be the most tolerant of all, but still more than half of its respondents support censorship.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;These apparently contradictory findings really are not, but reflect how the Arab world is coping with globalization and still grappling to preserve local culture,&amp;quot; Everette E. Dennis, dean and CEO of Northwestern University in Qatar, says in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>In early March, three Gulf countries -- Qatar, the UAE and Bahrain -- announced that Hollywood biblical blockbuster &amp;quot;Noah&amp;quot; could not be screened in cinemas, saying the depiction of Noah -- whom Muslims revere as a prophet -- is taboo in Islam.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Two months earlier, in January, censors in the UAE and Qatar cut more than 40 minutes of the three-hour-long &amp;quot;Wolf of Wall Street,&amp;quot; a Martin Scorsese-directed portrayal of a wayward stock trader, due to &amp;quot;foul language and explicit content,&amp;quot; angering moviegoers in both countries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Yet, the Northwestern University-Doha Film Institute survey shows that 72% of Qatari residents and 68% of Emirati residents generally support banning offensive content.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Hollywood films are not the only ones that ran aground in the Middle East and North Africa.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Qatar pulled Bollywood erotic horror flick &amp;quot;Raaz 3&amp;quot; from theaters in 2012 and, along with the UAE, banned Indian comedy &amp;quot;Grand Masti&amp;quot; last year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>In 2012, a Tunisian court fined the head of a private TV station 2,400 Tunisian dinars (around $1,400) after his Nessma TV aired &amp;quot;Persepolis,&amp;quot; a French-American animated film whose depiction of God was slammed by some religious leaders as offensive to Islam.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>