<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2957" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/07/23/world/meast/mideast-hamas-endgame/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-07-23 06:38:40" category="world" author="Mariano Castillo, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>What is Hamas&amp;apost; endgame in Gaza?</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Hamas has a number of stated goals.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="10, 8">Some, like the destruction of Israel, are repudiated globally.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="21">Hamas also wants an end to Israeli control in Gaza.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 16:05:30" annotation_time="72.26234">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">What are the goals for Hamas, the organization that governs Gaza and is considered a terrorist organization by many Western powers?</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">The destruction of Israel.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="2">It&amp;apost;s a demand that is globally repudiated as outrageous.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="3">Reports of civilian casualties in Gaza -- without the context of rockets being fired at Israel -- play into Hamas&amp;apost; media strategy, he said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>For three weeks now, Hamas and Israel have been locked in a deadly battle.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Each side points to the other for provoking the conflict, which has left scores -- mainly civilians -- dead.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>And yet, a cease-fire seems unlikely, in part because the sides don&amp;apost;t feel they have accomplished their goals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>What are the goals for Hamas, the organization that governs Gaza and is considered a terrorist organization by many Western powers?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>And what is it willing to settle for to end the bloodshed?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>What Hamas wants:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>1.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The destruction of Israel.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>This mission is written into the preamble of Hamas&amp;apost; founding document: &amp;quot;Israel will exist and will continue to exist until Islam will obliterate it.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a demand that is globally repudiated as outrageous.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>It is unrealistic for Hamas to think that it can somehow destroy Israel.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>As long as Hamas leaders latch on to that as an endgame, the result will be continued flare-ups for years to come.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Some Hamas leaders have stated a willingness to accept peace with Israel under certain conditions, the Council on Foreign Relations notes in a report.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>For instance, they want Palestinian refugees to be able to return.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>But such voices are not being heard in the current conflict.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>If Hamas is incapable of destroying Israel, it might still be dedicated to scaring Israelis off the contested land, journalist Jeffrey Goldberg at The Atlantic posits.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;The goal of Hamas - the actual, overarching goal - is to terrorize the Jews of Israel, through mass murder, into abandoning their country,&amp;quot; Goldberg wrote.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;If generations of Palestinians have to be sacrificed to that goal, well, Hamas believes such sacrifices are theologically justified.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>CNN Middle East analyst Michael Oren, a former Israeli ambassador to the United States, suggests a different type of war -- a media campaign by Hamas.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;Hamas knows it can&amp;apost;t destroy Israel with its rockets or tunnels, but it can create a legal and international situation where Israel can no longer legitimately defend itself,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Reports of civilian casualties in Gaza -- without the context of rockets being fired at Israel -- play into Hamas&amp;apost; media strategy, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>2.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>An end to the Israeli blockade.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Although Israel withdrew its forces from Gaza in 2005 and dismantled Israeli settlements, Palestinians say they continue to live under occupation to this day.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Palestinians argue that Israel still maintains effective control of Gaza, making it an occupied territory.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Israel controls Gaza&amp;apost;s borders, waters and airspace -- and oversees what goods make it into the territory.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>CNN&amp;apost;s Ben Wedeman recently spoke with Ismail Haniyeh, who is essentially the prime minister of Gaza.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The Hamas member gave his demands -- namely, an immediate end to what he called the Israeli aggression.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>He wants border crossings to Israel and Egypt opened.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>In a 2012 interview with CNN, Hamas leader Khaled Meshaal had a similar message.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;The resistance is a means to an end,&amp;quot; Meshaal told CNN&amp;apost;s Christiane Amanpour.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;The endgame is to end occupation but the international community is not enabling us to do this.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>They are biased towards Israel.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Hamas wants a cease-fire, Hamas spokesman Osama Hamdam said of the current conflict, but it wants assurances that the Palestinians will be able to live peacefully.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;No one is talking against having a cease-fire.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>But we want a fair cease-fire to protect our own people for a long time, to protect them from the Israeli military attacks, from the siege, from the arrests,&amp;quot; Hamdam told CNN&amp;apost;s Wolf Blitzer.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>3.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>The release of prisoners.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>In 2011, a captured Israeli soldier, Gilad Shalit, was released by Hamas in exchange for more than a thousand Palestinian prisoners held in Israel.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Many have since been re-arrested.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Dozens of other Palestinians were arrested in the aftermath of the June 12 kidnapping of three Israeli teenagers, an incident which precipitated the current fighting.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>There is a precedent of Palestinian prisoners being released in negotiations with Hamas.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>This demand by Hamas is also among the most straightforward it has presented.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;Israel is not respecting its commitment by releasing and then arresting prisoners released,&amp;quot; said Zaki Chehab, a leading Arab journalist and political editor of Hayat.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s a sign that Israel has not respected its commitment.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>The conditions that Hamas is making is not something unjustified, he told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>&amp;quot;They have a right to make a request because they&amp;apost;ve been under siege.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>4.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Rally support at home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Some analysts argue that Hamas is engaged in a battle with Israel to shore up support among Palestinians.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>Many Palestinians believe that Israel has no intention of finding long-term peace, and they are likely to support Hamas in greater numbers if they view the militants as standing up for their rights.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>&amp;quot;Hamas gains strength from the feeling of many Palestinians of despair that they see settlement growth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>They don&amp;apost;t believe that Israel has any intention of giving them a state of their own.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>And so when Hamas says what good is there for us to accept Israel&amp;apost;s right to exist since Israel will never give us a state anyway, that makes Hamas stronger,&amp;quot; CNN political commentator Peter Beinart said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>During the last prolonged outbreak between the two sides in 2012, many concluded that Hamas gained credibility at the expense of other Palestinian leadership factions, according to a Council on Foreign Relations report.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>In the period since 2012, Hamas has seen the number of governments friendly to it diminish, and its influence wane.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>&amp;quot;Hamas finds itself in a very difficult situation, and has for a couple years now,&amp;quot; writes Natan B. Sachs, a fellow at Brookings&amp;apost; Center for Middle East Policy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>&amp;quot;Since 2012, when Egypt was governed by a president from the Muslim Brotherhood (Hamas&amp;apost; parent organization), Hamas&amp;apost; fortunes have declined precipitously.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="59">
          <content>Strapped for cash and possibly losing popularity, Hamas operatives may have decided that they had little to lose in entering a conflict.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="60">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s possible, Sachs said, that Hamas militants may not always be under the control of its political wing, and that this current conflict is the result of Hamas losing control of its cadres.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
