<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2914" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/12/07/world/africa/central-african-republic-unrest" date_published="2013-12-07 14:52:45" category="world" author="Nima Elbagir and Laura Smith-Spark, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Uneasy truce in town at heart of Central African Republic unrest</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="21">NEW: The number of African Union troops will rise from 3,500 to 6,000, France says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="25, 37">NEW: French troops have arrived in the war-torn northern city of Bossangoa .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">A ceasefire between rival Muslim and Christian militias brings some respite there.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="16, 12">Aid group Medecins Sans Frontieres says refugees urgently need international help.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 16:05:00" annotation_time="79.901665" mapping_time_divergence="39.950832">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="3">Bossangoa, Central African Republic A ceasefire negotiated between rival Muslim and Christian militias brought a brief respite Saturday to a Central African Republic town after two days of violent clashes.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="4">Julian Donald overseeing a hospital in Bossangoa managed by Doctors Without Borders, or Medecins Sans Frontieres, said the aid group had worked through the violence, almost overwhelmed by the flood of patients.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="4">The Central African Republic desperately needs more help from the outside world.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="1">The number of African Union peacekeeping troops in the country will increase to 6,000 -- up from the current 3,500 -- the French presidency said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="2">By Saturday evening, some of them had arrived in the northern city of Bossangoa.</sentence>
      <sentence id="37" ids_highlights="2">A French Defense Ministry statement early Saturday said three helicopters and hundreds more troops had arrived in Bangui.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Bossangoa, Central African Republic A ceasefire negotiated between rival Muslim and Christian militias brought a brief respite Saturday to a Central African Republic town after two days of violent clashes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The truce between the Muslim Seleka militia and the Christian anti-Balaka in Bossangoa allowed aid agencies to begin assessing the needs of the population caught in the midst of the violence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>At the Ecole Liberte school, where a makeshift displaced camp sprang up in September to harbor fleeing Muslims, the numbers swelled during the clashes from around 2,500 displaced to nearly 10,000.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The people there are in need of almost everything: food, water and shelter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Over in a Catholic Church compound where 35,000 Christians sought refuge from the Seleka militias in September, the camp is more established, but water and food supplies are dwindling and there is very little shelter from the elements.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Malaria and malnutrition are all too common among the camps&amp;apost; denizens.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>A tense standoff had developed earlier between the Seleka and the regional peacekeeping force, FOMAC, after the militia threw grenades into the compound in an attempt to storm it.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>A soldier from FOMAC was killed during an exchange of fire.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>There is still no official death toll, but witnesses at the Ecole Liberte camp told CNN at least 19 Muslims were killed in what has become a spiraling cycle of retribution between the two communities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The anti-Balaka began targeting Muslims after tens of thousands of Christians were forced to flee their homes as Seleka militias marauded through the countryside.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;apost;Extremely dire circumstances&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Julian Donald overseeing a hospital in Bossangoa managed by Doctors Without Borders, or Medecins Sans Frontieres, said the aid group had worked through the violence, almost overwhelmed by the flood of patients.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have been fully operational the entire time,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;I can&amp;apost;t give you any numbers right now, I&amp;apost;m sorry, all I can say is it&amp;apost;s still ongoing.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>But the work he and his agency do is not enough, Donald said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The Central African Republic desperately needs more help from the outside world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;A situation where you have hundreds of thousands of people who through no fault of their own are living in extremely dire circumstances, I would hope that the international community would mobilize to provide them assistance,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;The fact that we haven&amp;apost;t seen it happen yet is a tragedy.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Some help could be on the way.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>On Thursday, the U.N. Security Council unanimously approved a resolution approving military intervention in the Central African Republic by an African Union-led force, backed by French troops, to protect civilians, restore humanitarian access and stabilize the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The number of African Union peacekeeping troops in the country will increase to 6,000 -- up from the current 3,500 -- the French presidency said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>French forces arrive.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>France has named this mission in its former colony Operation Sangaris, after a species of butterfly there.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>There will be 1,600 troops in the Central African Republic by the end of Saturday, French President Francois Hollande said at the Peace and Security in Africa Summit in Paris.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>By Saturday evening, some of them had arrived in the northern city of Bossangoa.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>France&amp;apost;s goal is for the nation to be able to hold elections once security is restored, in the same way that France helped Mali return to democracy, Hollande said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>France&amp;apost;s intervention in the Central African Republic is for humanitarian reasons, not to fight terrorism, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>There have not been many incidents of violence in the country Saturday, Hollande added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The start of the French soldiers&amp;apost; new operation in the CAR capital was announced Friday morning by Defense Minister Jean-Yves Le Drian on the French radio station RFI.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>About 185 miles south of Bossangoa, Bangui has also been rocked by two days of clashes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Many have flocked to the city&amp;apost;s airport, hoping to find safety there.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;We estimate at least at 400 to 500 people have been killed so far in Bangui and the killings continue,&amp;quot; Peter N. Bouckaert, emergencies director for Human Rights Watch, told CNN Saturday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;Two hundred and eighty bodies were recovered as of yesterday, but the Red Cross tells us there are more bodies on the streets that they are working to recover.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Medecins Sans Frontieres said Friday that at least 92 bodies had been brought to the morgue of a hospital where its staff is working.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Another 170 people have been treated for injuries, including gunshot, machete or knife wounds, it said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Air sorties.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>A French Defense Ministry statement early Saturday said three helicopters and hundreds more troops had arrived in Bangui.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>French troops have been out on patrol in a bid to restore calm to the city, which remains tense, as well as working to safeguard French nationals and secure the airport, the statement said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>Aerial sorties have also been launched above the capital to signal the French forces&amp;apost; presence to armed forces thought to be opposed to them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="34">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Back at the Catholic Church compound in Bossangoa, people scattered, screaming, as the unfamiliar boom of a low-flying jet swept over them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="35">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>The horror soon turned to laughs of jubilation, however, with shouts of &amp;quot;The French!</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>The French!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="36">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Desperate for help from the outside world, they hoped the sonic boom was a sign from the French forces that they would soon be there too.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
