<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2432" link="http://www.cnn.com/2011/09/26/world/americas/mexico-editor-decapitated/index.html " date_published="2011-09-26 22:45:31" category="world" author="the CNN Wire Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Mexican editor&amp;apost;s death linked to work with social media</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Message reportedly found near the body blames social networks.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">The 39-year-old editor&amp;apost;s decapitated body was found Saturday in Nuevo Laredo.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="8">&amp;quot;There seems to be no way out of this horror,&amp;quot; says Reporters Without Borders.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-21 18:46:37" annotation_time="39.558502">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Though no investigation has yet been carried out, a message was found next to the body indicating that she was killed by members of organized crime &amp;quot;in retaliation for the information that the victim had distributed in social networks denouncing the activities of criminals in Nuevo Laredo,&amp;quot; the human rights group said in a statement posted on its website.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">The decapitated body of Maria Elizabeth Macias, the editor of Primera Hora, a daily newspaper based in Nuevo Laredo in the eastern state of Tamaulipas, was found Saturday morning.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;There seems to be no way out of this horror,&amp;quot; it said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>MEXICO CITY Amnesty International said Monday that a newspaper editor whose decapitated body was found over the weekend in the Mexican border town of Nuevo Laredo appears to have been targeted by a drug gang carrying out a reprisal for her work on social networks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Though no investigation has yet been carried out, a message was found next to the body indicating that she was killed by members of organized crime &amp;quot;in retaliation for the information that the victim had distributed in social networks denouncing the activities of criminals in Nuevo Laredo,&amp;quot; the human rights group said in a statement posted on its website.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The decapitated body of Maria Elizabeth Macias, the editor of Primera Hora, a daily newspaper based in Nuevo Laredo in the eastern state of Tamaulipas, was found Saturday morning.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;The message is a clear threat to the users of social networks in the regions of greater violence in Mexico,&amp;quot; the Amnesty statement said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>It noted that two other people were found in Nuevo Laredo on September 14 along with a message that also indicated they had been killed in retaliation for their social network postings.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;These three killings seem to represent an alarming strategy to intimidate social network users so that they will give up communicating information related to the violence.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Macias, 39, was the fourth woman journalist to be killed this year in Mexico, Reporters Without Borders said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;There seems to be no way out of this horror,&amp;quot; it said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;apost;The country is immersed in an all-out war and just writing the word &amp;apost;narcos&amp;apost; or &amp;apost;trafficking&amp;apost; can cost you your life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>What will be left of freedom of information while the barbarity continues?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Citing unidentified sources, it said Macias used online social networks to report about organized crime along the border and blogged under the name &amp;quot;La Nena de Nuevo Laredo,&amp;quot; which translates as &amp;quot;Nuevo Laredo Girl.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>According to Reporters Without Borders, the Tamaulipas state attorney general&amp;apost;s office said two computer keys, a music player, several cables and the following message were found near her body:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;Ok Nuevo Laredo live on the social networks, I am La Nena de Laredo and I am here because of my reports and yours ... for those who don&amp;apost;t want to believe it, this has happened to me because of my actions, because I trusted SEDENA (the army) and MARINA (the navy)... Thank you for your attention.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Att: La Nena de Laredo... zzz&amp;quot;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The Z presumably refers to the Zeta drug cartel.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>A spokeswoman for the attorney general&amp;apost;s office would not confirm the Reporters Without Borders report.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Earlier this month, attackers left threats mentioning two websites on signs beside mutilated bodies in northern Mexico.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>A woman had been hogtied and disemboweled and left dangling from a bridge in Nuevo Laredo.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>A bloodied man next to her was hanging by his hands.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Signs left near the bodies declared the pair, both apparently in their 20s, were killed for posting denouncements of drug cartel activities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
