<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2716" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/02/05/world/europe/russia-sochi-stray-dogs" date_published="2014-02-05 10:26:49" category="world" author=" Ivan Watson, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Russians: Sochi rounding up, killing stray dogs before Winter Olympics</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Russian animal rights activists accuse authorities of campaign to exterminate street dogs .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="19">Government-backed shelter met with distrust by animal rights groups .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="15">Reports of the widespread culling of animals put city and Olympic officials on the defensive.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-13 14:44:03" annotation_time="33.79">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">In the countdown to the Winter Games, Russian animal rights activists have accused city authorities of ramping up a campaign to exterminate street dogs through the use of poison.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="3">Reports of the widespread culling of animals have put city and Olympic officials on the defensive.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="2">But the announcement of new government-backed shelter was met with deep distrust by members of the grassroots network of animal rights activists in Sochi.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Sochi, Russia The Olympic city has a dog problem.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Thousands of stray canines wander the streets and suburbs of Sochi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>They can be seen loping through the recently completed parks and housing developments that have sprung up around what was once a sleepy Black Sea resort.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>In the countdown to the Winter Games, Russian animal rights activists have accused city authorities of ramping up a campaign to exterminate street dogs through the use of poison.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Yulia Krasova says she witnessed the long, agonizing death of a street dog when she walked out of a movie theater in Sochi two weeks ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;At first I thought someone beat the dog,&amp;quot; she recalled.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;The dog jumped up and started running around in circles.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Then she fell down and started spitting up ... I called the veterinarian.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>He said there is a 100% guarantee the dog was poisoned.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Krasova filmed the dying dog with her cell phone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>So did Irina Gutnik, another Sochi resident.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Gutnik said she encountered a dog convulsing and barking in fear and pain in Sochi&amp;apost;s Bitka neighborhood in December.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;They always poison the street dogs here,&amp;quot; Krasova said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;But in December it got terrible ... they began poisoning the animals terribly before the Olympics.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Reports of the widespread culling of animals have put city and Olympic officials on the defensive.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;All stray dogs that are found on the Olympic Park are collected by a professional veterinary contractor for the well-being of the people on the Park and the animals themselves,&amp;quot; the Sochi 2014 Organizing Committee said in a statement this week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;All healthy animals are released following their health check.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Vladimir Makarenko, the head of the administration for Sochi&amp;apost;s Hostinski district, said volunteers were welcome to take stray dogs to a brand new shelter recently opened on the outskirts of the city.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>But the announcement of new government-backed shelter was met with deep distrust by members of the grassroots network of animal rights activists in Sochi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;Over the last couple of days, when this uproar began, they built this new shelter just for the media,&amp;quot; said Vlada Provotorova, a dentist who built her own make-shift shelter to protect dogs from extermination.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Animal rights activists in Sochi sent CNN photos of three recent contracts signed between the Sochi city government and Basia Services, a company headquartered in Rostov-on-Don.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>In one of the documents, dated May 24, 2013, the city government agreed to pay the company 99,450 rubles [roughly $2,800] for the &amp;quot;trapping and gathering of neglected animals.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>CNN made several attempts to speak by phone with executives at Basia Services.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Company representatives declined to respond to allegations their employees poisoned street animals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>As alarm grows among Russian dog lovers, some animal rights activists have taken matters into their own hands.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Last month, one Muscovite, Igor Airapetyan, drove all the way to Sochi to pick up a van-load of street dogs that he then &amp;quot;evacuated&amp;quot; to the Russian capital.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Video of the journey trip was posted on a Facebook page titled &amp;quot;Death in Sochi.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Meanwhile, Provotorova and several friends continue to donate time and money to feed, house and sterilize the dozen street dogs they placed in a small kennel they built on the outskirts of Sochi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>This week, the dogs barked and wagged their tails madly when Provotorova and several other volunteers arrived with fresh supplies of dog food.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are protecting them from Basia,&amp;quot; said Provotorova said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;I don&amp;apost;t blame the Olympics,&amp;quot; said Dina Filippova, as she scrubbed out the kennels with a mop.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>&amp;quot;We don&amp;apost;t have a sterilization program, so there is a huge amount of stray dogs here and authorities try to control them.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>They can&amp;apost;t.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Filippova, a lawyer living in Sochi, argued Russia needs new legislation for the protection and management of animals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;In Russia, you can abuse animals and it&amp;apost;s not a crime.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>You can buy and adopt an animal and release it on the street, it&amp;apost;s not a crime,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;You have no legal obligation to sterilize your dog or cat.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Filippova and Provotorova both conceded that their families often accused them of being &amp;quot;crazy&amp;quot; about animals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>But one of their fellow volunteers had another explanation for why she devoted so much time to caring and feeding for homeless animals.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;At my age I prefer taking care of animals,&amp;quot; said Valentina Slivat, who described herself as a &amp;quot;simple Soviet nurse&amp;quot; who worked at a hospital in Sochi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>A fluffy street dog named &amp;quot;Pushistik&amp;quot; followed Slivat constantly around the kennel, and periodically leaped into her arms.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;People have hands, legs, brains.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>But animals have been abandoned.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>We need to save them,&amp;quot; the nurse said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
