<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2106" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/07/01/world/meast/syria-unrest" date_published="2013-07-01 15:16:29" category="world" author="Joe Sterling, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Catholic group posts video of what it says is monk&amp;apost;s beheading</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7">Catholic Online: &amp;quot;Martyrdom isn&amp;apost;t an ancient phenomenon&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="19">Christians have been caught in the Syrian civil war&amp;apost;s crossfire.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="14">Sources say the militants are linked to Jabhat al-Nusra, Catholic Online says.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-11 17:57:53" annotation_time="53.640995" mapping_time_divergence="17.880331">
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;It is very important the world knows that Christians are being murdered for their faith, and that martyrdom isn&amp;apost;t an ancient phenomenon,&amp;quot; Catholic Online said in a report Monday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="3">Catholic Online cites local sources linking the militants who killed the monk to Jabhat al-Nusra, an Islamist rebel group regarded as a terrorist entity by the United States.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="2">Christians in Syria have been caught in the crossfire of the country&amp;apost;s civil war, in which a government dominated by minority Alawite Muslims is squaring off with a rebellion dominated by Sunni Muslims.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A Catholic website has posted a gruesome video, claiming it shows Syrian rebels beheading a monk.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Catholic Online -- a news and information outlet -- put the video on its website Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>It shows the slaughtering of three people in northern Syria&amp;apost;s Idlib province.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The site says one of the three is Father Francois Murad.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Those carrying out the acts &amp;quot;speak Arabic with a broken accent, saying that through this act, they are applying the law of God,&amp;quot; Catholic Online says.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>People in the crowd appear to be taking videos of the executioners.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;It is very important the world knows that Christians are being murdered for their faith, and that martyrdom isn&amp;apost;t an ancient phenomenon,&amp;quot; Catholic Online said in a report Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;This should make it clear to Christians around the world what jihadists are about.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Make no mistake.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Catholics and Christians around the globe are under dire threat, particularly from the spread of militant Islam.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Until the threat is recognized and taken seriously, martyrdoms like this will continue.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>A Vatican spokesman said he was not aware of any video showing the execution of the monk, whose death the Vatican announced last week.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The office of the Custodians of the Holy Sepulchre in Jerusalem said to its knowledge there is no such video.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Catholic Online cites local sources linking the militants who killed the monk to Jabhat al-Nusra, an Islamist rebel group regarded as a terrorist entity by the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;The video CLEARLY depicts the beheadings of these victims,&amp;quot; Catholic Online said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;DO NOT follow the link unless you are over the age of 18, and are prepared to view content of this nature.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The images renew the daily fears of Christians in the Middle East.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>They have had a longtime presence in the region and have faced violence, persecution and displacement in recent years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Christians in Syria have been caught in the crossfire of the country&amp;apost;s civil war, in which a government dominated by minority Alawite Muslims is squaring off with a rebellion dominated by Sunni Muslims.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>They&amp;apost;ve also faced hostility in other places, such as Iraq during the war last decade and in Egypt in recent years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Last week, the Vatican noted the monk&amp;apost;s death in a news release, saying it occurred June 23 in Gassanieh -- a predominantly Christian village in the district of Jisr al-Shughur in the province of Idlib, near the border with Turkey.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;The village had been under attack from Islamist rebels for the past few weeks, forcing the majority of the population to flee,&amp;quot; the Vatican said, citing the Rev. Pierbattista Pizzaballa, head of all Franciscans in the Holy Land.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;When Fr.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Francois tried to oppose resistance to defend the nuns and other people, the guerrillas shot him, killing him,&amp;quot; it said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The violence in Syria since March 2011 has been well-recorded in homemade videos that have surfaced daily.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Constant examples of brutality by President Bashar al-Assad&amp;apost;s forces have emerged.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Over the past year, there also have been a growing number of images showing rebel brutality.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>More than 100,000 people have been killed in the conflict, which began as peaceful opposition to the al-Assad regime.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>As the regime cracked down on the protesters, the conflict morphed into a full-blown civil war.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
