<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2939" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/01/13/world/americas/peru-van-der-sloot-sentence/index.html" date_published="2012-01-13 17:36:26" category="world" author="the CNN Wire Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Van der Sloot sentenced to 28 years for Peru murder</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">NEW: With time served, Joran van der Sloot will be released in 2038.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">Judges order van der Sloot to pay about $74,500 in reparations.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="7">He&amp;apost;s also ordered expelled from Peru after completing his sentence.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="2">Van der Sloot was visibly upset after the sentencing.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-18 14:55:35" annotation_time="18.341">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="4">Van der Sloot, who was visibly upset after the decision was issued, admitted this week to killing Stephany Flores in his Lima hotel room.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">With time served, it means van der Sloot is scheduled to be released June 10, 2038.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2, 3">The judges ordered van der Sloot expelled from Peru at the end of his sentence and ordered him to pay 200,000 Peruvian new soles, or about $74,500, in reparations to Flores&amp;apost; closest relatives.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Peruvian judges on Friday sentenced Dutch national Joran van der Sloot to 28 years in prison and ordered him to pay thousands of dollars in reparations for the killing of a 21-year-old Peruvian woman in 2010.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Van der Sloot, who was visibly upset after the decision was issued, admitted this week to killing Stephany Flores in his Lima hotel room.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The judges said they took his confession into account, but they still gave him a sentence two years short of the 30-year maximum.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>With time served, it means van der Sloot is scheduled to be released June 10, 2038.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The defendant, 24, stood for much of the more than two-hour session and perspired through his green t-shirt.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>He drank three cups of water and frequently wiped his face.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The judges ordered van der Sloot expelled from Peru at the end of his sentence and ordered him to pay 200,000 Peruvian new soles, or about $74,500, in reparations to Flores&amp;apost; closest relatives.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Van der Sloot confessed to robbery in addition to murder, admitting that he stole Flores&amp;apost; belongings, including 850 soles (more than $300), credit cards, and the victim&amp;apost;s van as a means to leave the country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>He fled to Chile and was arrested a few days later.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>It was an apparent attempt to win a more lenient sentence, using a plea called an &amp;quot;anticipated conclusion of the process&amp;quot; under Peruvian law.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Five days earlier, the three judges delayed the start of van der Sloot&amp;apost;s trial after he declined to give a plea after expressing reservations about the &amp;quot;aggravating factors&amp;quot; tied to admitting his guilt.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Van der Sloot&amp;apost;s attorney, Jose Luis Jimenez, pressed earlier this week for a shorter sentence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Jimenez claimed that his client was under special stress the day the 2010 murder occurred, which marked five years after Alabama teenager Natalee Holloway went missing in Aruba.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Van der Sloot -- who, with two others, was among the last people seen with Holloway - was detained twice, but never charged, in the high-profile international case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;He was pointed at and persecuted.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The world had been against him for five years before this case, for a murder he said he never committed and for which there is no evidence whatsoever,&amp;quot; said Jimenez.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Investigators have said they believe van der Sloot killed Flores after she found something related to the Holloway case on his computer while visiting him in his hotel room.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The two met while van der Sloot was in town for a poker tournament.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Judges on Friday recounted the crime in detail.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>They described how Flores hit van der Sloot in the face after reading the item on Holloway, leading him to hit her in the face with his elbow.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Flores fainted and van der Sloot tried to strangle her, but she was still breathing and so he suffocated her with his shirt.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Van der Sloot then tried to clean the room by removing the sheets and changing his bloodied shirt, they said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>He was ultimately caught while traveling alone in a taxi near the Chilean central coastal city of Vina del Mar.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Holloway&amp;apost;s body has never been found, and no one has been charged in relation to the case in Aruba.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>But van der Sloot does face possible extradition to the United States in a related matter.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>In June 2010, a federal grand jury in Alabama indicted him on charges of wire fraud and extortion after allegations surfaced that he tried to extort $250,000 from Holloway&amp;apost;s mother, Beth.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Van der Sloot offered to provide what turned out to be bogus information about the whereabouts of Holloway&amp;apost;s remains in exchange for the money, according to the indictment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>He was allegedly given a total of $25,000, and authorities believe he used that money to travel to Peru for the poker tournament.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Thursday, about six and a half years after Holloway went missing, Alabama Probate Judge Alan King signed an order declaring the teenager legally dead.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
