<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2547" link="http://cnn.com/2012/07/14/world/europe/uk-olympics-security/index.html" date_published="2012-07-14 11:20:42" category="world" author="Laura Smith-Spark, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Olympic security firm G4S may lose $77m over guard shortfall</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="10">G4S says it &amp;quot;deeply regrets&amp;quot; it is unlikely to deliver all the promised security staff.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">The company stands to lose up to $77m, it says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="3">The government said this week it will bring in 3,500 extra troops to cover the gap.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="1">The London Olympics open in less than two weeks.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-12 16:14:15" annotation_time="27.2035">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2, 4">The contractor responsible for providing security guards for the Olympic Games said Saturday it stands to lose up to $77 million after failing to recruit enough staff, less than two weeks before the event opens in London.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">The company has come under heavy scrutiny this week after the government was forced to announce the deployment of 3,500 extra military personnel to cover the shortfall.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="1">G4S &amp;quot;deeply regrets that, despite the relentless efforts of so many of its people, it is unlikely to deliver in full its obligations to LOCOG, to the government and to everyone with an interest in these Games.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The contractor responsible for providing security guards for the Olympic Games said Saturday it stands to lose up to $77 million after failing to recruit enough staff, less than two weeks before the event opens in London.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>G4S chief executive Nick Buckles said he was &amp;quot;deeply disappointed&amp;quot; the firm was unable to live up to its contract with the London 2012 organizing group, LOCOG.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The company has come under heavy scrutiny this week after the government was forced to announce the deployment of 3,500 extra military personnel to cover the shortfall.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The deployment means that 17,000 troops will be on duty in the United Kingdom during the Games, compared with the 9,500 currently in Afghanistan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>G4S had been expected to recruit a staff of about 10,400 as part of a total security force of 23,700 for the Olympic and Paralympic Games.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The contractor said this week that while 4,000 are already at work across 100 venues, more than 9,000 are still going through the training and vetting process.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>In a statement Saturday, the company said it had &amp;quot;encountered significant difficulties in processing applicants in sufficient numbers through the necessary training, vetting and accreditation procedures.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>As a result, we will be unable to deliver all of the necessary workforce numbers.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>That failure is likely to cost the firm between £35m and £50m ($54 million -$77 million), it said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>G4S &amp;quot;deeply regrets that, despite the relentless efforts of so many of its people, it is unlikely to deliver in full its obligations to LOCOG, to the government and to everyone with an interest in these Games.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The company will meet the cost of the additional military deployment, it said, and &amp;quot;is also incurring other significant costs as it endeavours to meet the contract challenges.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>It also expressed its gratitude to those military personnel who will be deployed on short notice to fill the gap.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;In partnership with the military and LOCOG, we are working flat out around the clock to resolve the situation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>We are determined that together we will deliver a successful and secure Games,&amp;quot; Nick Buckles said, quoted in the statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Britain is on a heightened state of alert ahead of the Games, which open on July 27.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Home Secretary Theresa May said Thursday that &amp;quot;there is no question of Olympic security being compromised.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>But opposition lawmakers have described the situation as a &amp;quot;shambles,&amp;quot; saying it raises concerns over the government&amp;apost;s grip on the preparations for the Olympics and Paralympics.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>LOCOG chairman Sebastian Coe said Friday he was &amp;quot;extraordinarily impressed with&amp;quot; private contractor G4S so far.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Coe said he was happy with the security staff on site and that while G4S has &amp;quot;challenges,&amp;quot; it would get there.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Olympic organizers have agreed to give 10,000 tickets to the armed forces to compensate for the short-notice deployment, the Ministry of Defence said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The questions over security staff come as Britain gears up to welcome many of the visiting teams&amp;apost; officials this weekend ahead of the athletes&amp;apost; arrival on Monday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>One headache was removed for organizers with the reopening Friday of the main highway linking Heathrow airport with central London.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The busy M4 motorway had been closed for a week for emergency repairs to a viaduct.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>