<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2839" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2013/03/22/world/asia/myanmar-clashes/index.html?iref=allsearch" date_published="2013-03-22 08:08:44" category="world" author="Phyo Wai Lin. Jethro Mullen and Kocha Olarn, CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Toll rises in Myanmar amid clashes between Buddhists, Muslims</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">Four townships in central Myanmar under a state of emergency, the president says .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">The rioting has driven thousands of people from their homes, officials say.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="2">Clashes started with a dispute between a Muslim shop owner and Buddhist sellers.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="3">Last year, ethnic violence in western Myanmar left scores of people dead.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-29 15:17:42" annotation_time="47.7995">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="3">Members of the Buddhist and Muslim communities in Meiktila township have clashed this week after a dispute between a Muslim gold shop owner and two Buddhist sellers Wednesday ignited simmering communal tensions.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2, 4">Rioters have set fire to houses, schools and mosques, prompting thousands of residents to flee their homes amid unrest that had echoes of sectarian troubles that killed scores of people in western Myanmar last year.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">Late Friday night, President Thein Sein announced on state television that four townships in the affected region are under a state of emergency.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Buddhist monks and others armed with swords and machetes Friday stalked the streets of a city in central Myanmar, where sectarian violence that has left about 20 people dead has begun to spread to other areas, according to local officials.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Members of the Buddhist and Muslim communities in Meiktila township have clashed this week after a dispute between a Muslim gold shop owner and two Buddhist sellers Wednesday ignited simmering communal tensions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Rioters have set fire to houses, schools and mosques, prompting thousands of residents to flee their homes amid unrest that had echoes of sectarian troubles that killed scores of people in western Myanmar last year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Late Friday night, President Thein Sein announced on state television that four townships in the affected region are under a state of emergency.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The United Nations and the United States have expressed concern about the violence in the lakeside city about 100 kilometers (60 miles) south of Mandalay.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Win Htein, an opposition member of parliament for Meiktila, said the number of dead in the city has risen to about 20 by his estimate -- most of them Muslims -- after charred bodies were found in the streets.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;I have not seen this scale of violence before in my life,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am very sad.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The community used to live in peace.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Myanmar is emerging from decades of military repression and has taken a number of significant steps toward democracy in recent years under President Thein Sein.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>But it has been plagued by bouts of ethnic violence that some analysts say are a byproduct of the changing political climate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Burning mosques.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>A group of about 100 Buddhists, including some monks, went around Meiktila on Thursday night torching mosques, said Police Lt. Col. Aung Min, and while most of them have returned home, some are still wandering the streets, carrying weapons.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Although Aung Min declined to provide an official death toll, he said the violence had spread to a nearby town, Win Twin, where a mosque was burned down overnight.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>He said about 1,000 Muslims had taken temporary shelter in a soccer stadium in Meiktila, where about 30% of the 100,000 residents are estimated to be Muslims.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Win Htein said he believed that more than 5,000 Buddhists had fled to monasteries around the city to escape the violence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Many members of both communities had lost their homes, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Journalists in the city who tried to take photos of the clashes said they were threatened by Buddhists, some of them monks, who were holding sticks and knives.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Violence in Rakhine.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>In the western state of Rakhine, tensions between the majority Buddhist community and the Rohingya, a stateless ethnic Muslim group, boiled over into clashes that killed scores of people and left tens of thousands of others living in makeshift camps last year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Most of the victims were Rohingya.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;The ongoing intercommunal strife in Rakhine State is of grave concern,&amp;quot; the International Crisis Group said in a November report.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;And there is the potential for similar violence elsewhere, as nationalism and ethno-nationalism rise and old prejudices resurface.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>A failure by authorities to address deepening divisions between the communities could result in a resumption of violence in the future, the report said, &amp;quot;which would be to the detriment of both communities, and of the country as a whole.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Vijay Nambiar, special adviser to the U.N. secretary-general on Myanmar, on Thursday expressed &amp;quot;deep sorrow at the tragic loss of lives and destruction&amp;quot; in Meiktila this week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>He called for &amp;quot;firm action&amp;quot; from Myanmar authorities, combined with &amp;quot;the continued fostering of communal harmony and preservation of peace and tranquility among the people.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Win Htein, the local lawmaker, said that he believed there were now about 1,000 police officers in the area.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>He said he had spoken to Aung San Suu Kyi, the Nobel laureate and leader of the opposition National League for Democracy, who had said local authorities should use police to control the situation according to the law.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The U.S. ambassador to Myanmar, Derek Mitchell, said Thursday that he was &amp;quot;deeply concerned&amp;quot; about the reports of violence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>