<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2230" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/04/07/world/meast/yemen-military-shakeup/index.html" date_published="2012-04-07 11:23:48" category="world" author="Hakim Almasmari, For CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Gunmen attack Yemen&amp;apost;s main airport</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Officials: Mohammed Saleh al-Ahmar threatens to bring down aircraft if his demands aren&amp;apost;t met.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">He is one of several relatives of former President Ali Abdullah Saleh to be sacked.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="23">The military shakeup is part of promised reforms by the new president .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="5">Saleh was forced to step down in February.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-10 13:21:59" annotation_time="27.719666">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">Two officials at Sanaa International Airport told CNN that the former commander of Yemen&amp;apost;s air force had warned he would bring down any civil aircraft departing or arriving the airport unless his demands are met.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">The commander, Mohammed Saleh al-Ahmar, is one of several relatives of the former president who were replaced in a major military shakeup.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="4">Ali Saleh was forced to step down from power in February.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="3">The restructuring of the military was part of the negotiated power transfer deal and was promised by the new president.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Gunmen loyal to former Yemeni President Ali Abdullah Saleh attacked the country&amp;apost;s main airport with mortars Saturday, forcing authorities to cancel flights, witnesses and officials said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Two officials at Sanaa International Airport told CNN that the former commander of Yemen&amp;apost;s air force had warned he would bring down any civil aircraft departing or arriving the airport unless his demands are met.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The commander, Mohammed Saleh al-Ahmar, is one of several relatives of the former president who were replaced in a major military shakeup.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Al-Ahmar refused to give up his post.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Ali Saleh was forced to step down from power in February.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Al-Ahmar, the half-brother of the former president, was given a new position as assistant to the minister of defense in Friday&amp;apost;s presidential decree, but has refused to leave his air force post.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The officials said he threatened to cause chaos if three opposition military officials are not removed from their military posts along with him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The airport was not allowing flights to arrive or depart the country due to the tension, according to security officials at the airport who wished to remain anonymous.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Friday&amp;apost;s shakeup was announced in a statement by a spokesman for the Yemeni Embassy in Washington and attributed to current President Abdu Rabu Mansour Hadi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;President Hadi promised major change in the military, and tonight that promise was delivered,&amp;quot; said Mohammed Albasha, the embassy spokesman.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is the biggest military shakeup in modern Yemen history.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Another of the sacked Salehs was the former president&amp;apost;s nephew, Tareq Saleh, who had been head of the presidential guard.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Two prominent members of Ali Saleh&amp;apost;s family remained in powerful military posts however after Friday&amp;apost;s shakeup.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>They are Brig. Gen. Ahmed Ali Abdullah Saleh, who is the former president&amp;apost;s son and head of the Republican Guard, and Brig. Gen. Yahya Mohammed Abdullah Saleh, the former president&amp;apost;s nephew and head of Central Security Forces.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Minutes after the military decrees were announced, a senior opposition leader&amp;apost;s residence was heavily shelled.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Opposition parties condemned the attacks on the residential compound of Hameed al-Ahmar, president of the opposition Dialogue Committee.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;Attacks on al-Ahmar come in retaliation against the president&amp;apost;s orders to remove senior Ali Saleh aides from their military positions,&amp;quot; said Fowzy al-Jaradi, the spokesman for al-Ahmar&amp;apost;s office.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The military committee, the country&amp;apost;s highest security authority, warned all political and military factions to be cautious and urged them to help in defusing the current tension.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Opposition factions in Yemen have refused to participate in the anticipated national dialogue unless complete military reforms take place first.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Anti-government demonstrators demanded last year that all of the former president&amp;apost;s relatives be replaced.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>After months of massive street protests, Ali Abdullah Saleh finally stepped down in February in exchange for immunity, as part of a power transfer deal brokered by the six-nation Gulf Cooperation Council.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>However, he remained president of the ruling General People&amp;apost;s Congress party.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The restructuring of the military was part of the negotiated power transfer deal and was promised by the new president.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>