<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2026" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/05/14/world/anti-semitism-global-survey/index.html" date_published="2014-05-14 13:39:47" category="world" author="Josh Levs, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>&amp;apost;Unprecedented&amp;apost; global study finds 1 in 4 adults anti-Semitic</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Survey finds 26% of the world&amp;apost;s adults are &amp;quot;deeply infected&amp;quot; with anti-Semitism, the ADL says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Nearly half have never heard of the Holocaust.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="15">In the U.S., 9% believed the majority of negative stereotypes.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="20">Three in four adults have never met a Jewish person.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-06 22:02:19" annotation_time="51.659">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">One in four adults worldwide are &amp;quot;deeply infected with anti-Semitic attitudes,&amp;quot; the Anti-Defamation League announced, in releasing results of an unprecedented global survey.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">Nearly half have never heard of the Holocaust, and only a third believe historical descriptions are accurate, the survey found.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="3">In the United States, 9% of respondents believed the majority of the stereotypes.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="4">Three quarters of the people surveyed said they&amp;apost;ve never met a Jewish person.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>One in four adults worldwide are &amp;quot;deeply infected with anti-Semitic attitudes,&amp;quot; the Anti-Defamation League announced, in releasing results of an unprecedented global survey.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Nearly half have never heard of the Holocaust, and only a third believe historical descriptions are accurate, the survey found.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Carried out by First International Resources and commissioned by the Anti-Defamation League, the survey included 53,100 adults in 102 countries representing 88% of the world&amp;apost;s adult population.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>In native languages, it asked people whether certain traditionally anti-Semitic statements are probably true or false, including that Jews have too much power over international markets, global media, and the U.S. government; that they &amp;quot;don&amp;apost;t care about what happens to anyone but their own kind,&amp;quot; and that &amp;quot;Jews are responsible for most of the world&amp;apost;s wars.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The survey then calculated how many believed that at least six of the 11 stereotypes were probably true.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>In the Middle East and North Africa, 74% did.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>In Eastern Europe, one in three did, and in Western Europe and sub-Saharan Africa, nearly one in four believed most of the stereotypes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Overall, 26% believed at least six of the stereotypes -- a figure representing an estimated 1.1 billion people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The most widely believed stereotype was that Jews are more loyal to Israel than to the countries in which they live.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;For the first time we have a real sense of how pervasive and persistent anti-Semitism is today around the world,&amp;quot; ADL National Director Abraham Foxman said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;The data from the Global 100 Index enables us to look beyond anti-Semitic incidents and rhetoric and quantify the prevalence of anti-Semitic attitudes across the globe.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>We can now identify hotspots, as well as countries and regions of the world where hatred of Jews is essentially nonexistent.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>In Laos, only 0.2% of the adult population holds anti-Semitic views, the survey found.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Also at the bottom of the list were the Philippines, Sweden and the Netherlands.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>In the United States, 9% of respondents believed the majority of the stereotypes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The highest levels were found in the Palestinian territories at 93% and Iraq at 92%.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Yemen, Algeria, Libya and Tunisia were next.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>In Asia, less than a quarter of respondents had heard of the Holocaust and believed historical accounts are accurate.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>In sub-Saharan Africa, that figured dropped to 12%; in the Middle East and North Africa, 8%.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Three quarters of the people surveyed said they&amp;apost;ve never met a Jewish person.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>That figure includes most of the people who believe a majority of the anti-Semitic stereotypes are probably true.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
