<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2456" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/03/30/world/us-navy-ship-reef/index.html" date_published="2013-03-30 16:22:48" category="world" author="Brad Lendon, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Minesweeper lifted from Philippine reef</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">The grounded U.S. Navy minesweeper was removed from a Philippine reef Saturday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8">The Guardian is estimated to have damaged about 4,000 square meters of the reef.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">The USS Guardian ran aground on January 17.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 19:44:10" annotation_time="10.7835">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">What was left of the former U.S. Navy minesweeper was lifted off a Philippine reef on Saturday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">It was the last of the four sections of the wood and fiberglass hull the USS Guardian had been cut into in the effort to remove it from where it ran aground on January 17.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">The Guardian is estimated to have damaged about 4,000 square meters (about 43,000 square feet) of the reef, a UNESCO World Heritage site that is home to about 500 species of fish and 350 species of coral, as well as whales, dolphins, sharks, turtles and breeding seabirds.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The Guardian is gone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>What was left of the former U.S. Navy minesweeper was lifted off a Philippine reef on Saturday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;The stern was lifted around 1:50 p.m.,&amp;quot; Philippine Coast Guard Palawan District head Commodore Enrico Efren Evangelista told the state-run Philippine News Agency.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>It was the last of the four sections of the wood and fiberglass hull the USS Guardian had been cut into in the effort to remove it from where it ran aground on January 17.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The 250-ton stern segment was placed aboard a waiting barge.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;As the hull has been removed, the team is now shifting their effort to collecting minor debris that remains on the reef,&amp;quot; the head of the salvage operation, Navy Capt. Mark Matthews, said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;We also have a collaborative team from the U.S. and the Philippines beginning to assess the condition of the reef.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The Guardian is estimated to have damaged about 4,000 square meters (about 43,000 square feet) of the reef, a UNESCO World Heritage site that is home to about 500 species of fish and 350 species of coral, as well as whales, dolphins, sharks, turtles and breeding seabirds.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The Navy has pledged to clean up the debris created when waves stripped off pieces of fiberglass covering the wooden hull of the ship and to try to restore the reef as much as possible.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;(With this complete) the second phase which is the assessment and recovery phase (for the damaged reef) begins,&amp;quot; Evangelista said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;Every salvage operation presents unique challenges.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>It has been difficult to extract the Guardian without causing further damage to the reef, but the U.S. Navy and SMIT salvage team with support from other companies and the government of the Philippines have really done a superb job.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>I could not be more proud,&amp;quot; Matthews said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;We continue to work closely with the Philippine Coast Guard, Navy and Tubbataha Reef Park Rangers, and we are grateful for the support we have received to remove Guardian and minimize further damage to the reef.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>An investigation into the grounding is ongoing, but Navy officials said in January that the U.S. National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency, which prepares the digital navigation charts used by the Navy, has reported the location of the reef was misplaced on a chart by nine miles.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>While the removal of the stern from the reef may visually mark the end of the Guardian, the ship was officially stricken from the U.S. Navy registry in February.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Navy communications now refer to it as the Ex-Guardian.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>It has been replaced in the Pacific by the USS Warrior, which arrived at the U.S. naval base in Sasebo, Japan, earlier this month.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The Guardian&amp;apost;s crew will take over operation of the Warrior.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
