<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2919" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/06/17/world/europe/g8-summit" date_published="2013-06-17 04:19:48" category="world" author="Kevin Liptak and Catherine E. Shoichet, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>U.S. and Russia still don&amp;apost;t see eye to eye on Syria</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">NEW: On Syria, Putin says he and Obama &amp;quot;agreed to push the parties to the negotiating table&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8">NEW: Obama says it&amp;apost;s important to make sure chemical weapons don&amp;apost;t proliferate in Syria.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="29">Cameron: G8 summit aims to &amp;quot;fire up our economies and drive growth&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="27">Obama says negotiations for a U.S.-EU trade deal will start in Washington.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 19:47:59" annotation_time="14.3395">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">Putin said he and Obama &amp;quot;agreed to push the parties to the negotiating table.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="2">On Monday, Obama stressed the importance of making sure chemical weapons &amp;quot;are neither used nor subject to proliferation&amp;quot; in Syria -- a topic that Putin didn&amp;apost;t mention in his public remarks after meeting with the U.S. president.</sentence>
      <sentence id="27" ids_highlights="4">The first round of negotiations for a trans-Atlantic trade agreement between the United States and the European Union will take place next month in Washington, Obama said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="29" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;The whole point of this meeting ... is to fire up our economies and drive growth and prosperity around the world.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Russian President Vladimir Putin says he still doesn&amp;apost;t see eye to eye with the United States on Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But &amp;quot;all of us have the intention to stop the violence in Syria ... and to solve this situation peacefully,&amp;quot; Putin said Monday after a meeting with U.S. President Barack Obama at the Group of Eight Summit in Northern Ireland.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Putin said he and Obama &amp;quot;agreed to push the parties to the negotiating table.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>But the Russian president didn&amp;apost;t specify who could be involved in Syria talks, when they would take place or what their end goal would be.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The G8 summit comes days after the United States pledged to play a greater role in assisting Syrian rebels, citing evidence that President Bashar al-Assad&amp;apost;s regime used chemical weapons against the rebels and his own people.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The move was backed by seven of the eight nations represented at this week&amp;apost;s conference in Loch Erne, while Russia remains the sole G8 nation supporting al-Assad.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>And global leaders at the conference are poised to pressure Putin over his support for Syria&amp;apost;s government.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>On Monday, Obama stressed the importance of making sure chemical weapons &amp;quot;are neither used nor subject to proliferation&amp;quot; in Syria -- a topic that Putin didn&amp;apost;t mention in his public remarks after meeting with the U.S. president.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Russia has downplayed the claims of chemical weapons use, and Putin has opposed outside intervention into the county&amp;apost;s 2-year-old internal conflict.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>On Sunday, Putin sharply criticized the decision to provide arms to Syrian rebels, referencing a widely circulated video of an opposition fighter appearing to eat the heart of a dead solider.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Speaking to reporters in London after meeting with British Prime Minister David Cameron, Putin warned against arming Syrian rebels &amp;quot;who kill their enemies and eat their organs.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Do you want to support these people?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Do you want to supply arms to these people?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Putin asked.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The White House announcement last week that it was increasing the &amp;quot;size and scope&amp;quot; of its material support to Syrian rebels came after months of political debate over the U.S. role in the conflict.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Great Britain and France, two other G8 members, were strong backers of the May decision to end the European Union arms embargo on Syria, and both countries asserted that al-Assad&amp;apost;s regime had used chemical weapons before the United States did.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The meeting between Obama and Putin Monday was the first time the two leaders have spoken face to face since last year&amp;apost;s G-20 summit in Mexico.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s in Russia&amp;apost;s interest to join us in applying pressure on Bashar al-Assad to come to the table in a way that relinquishes his power and his standing in Syria, because we don&amp;apost;t see any scenario where he restores his legitimacy to lead the country,&amp;quot; Obama&amp;apost;s deputy national security adviser Ben Rhodes noted before Monday&amp;apost;s meeting.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Other G8 nations have expressed similar viewpoints, calling on Russia to back United Nations intervention in Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Russia&amp;apost;s permanent position on the United Nations Security Council has made action through that body difficult for countries intent on removing al-Assad from power.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>After meeting with Putin on Monday, Obama said the possibility of negotiations remains on the table.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;We want to try to resolve the issue through political means, if possible,&amp;quot; Obama said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Before this week&amp;apost;s meetings, the U.S. president spoke by videoconference with the leaders of Britain, France, Italy and Germany to discuss &amp;quot;ways to support a political transition to end the conflict&amp;quot; in Syria, the White House said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The White House has not yet publicly specified what exact steps it would take to support members of Syria&amp;apost;s opposition, though sources have told CNN small arms, ammunition and possibly anti-tank weapons would be part of the assistance package.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>On Friday, Rhodes said further discussions with other nations were necessary to determine next steps.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Though Syria will likely dominate discussions behind the scenes at this week&amp;apost;s summit, leaders began the conference Monday by heralding a possible trade deal they said could create millions of jobs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The first round of negotiations for a trans-Atlantic trade agreement between the United States and the European Union will take place next month in Washington, Obama said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;I believe that we can form an economic alliance as strong as our diplomatic and security alliances,&amp;quot; he told reporters after the leaders of eight of the world&amp;apost;s most powerful nations kicked off their meeting.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;The whole point of this meeting ... is to fire up our economies and drive growth and prosperity around the world.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>... There&amp;apost;s no better way than by launching these negotiations on a landmark deal between the European Union and the United states of America,&amp;quot; Cameron said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Cameron, the host of this week&amp;apost;s conference, named the problem of tax avoidance by large corporations as a central issue for G8 leaders to resolve at this year&amp;apost;s summit.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The British prime minister hopes to secure agreements among nations on sharing tax information, with the goal of ensuring global companies aren&amp;apost;t able to dodge tax bills.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The measure met resistance from firms&amp;apost; chief executives, though Cameron said he&amp;apost;s willing to withstand corporate ire for a fairer global tax system.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;You don&amp;apost;t get anywhere unless you are prepared to give the lead and perhaps make a few enemies along the way,&amp;quot; Cameron said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;In setting the G8 agenda around trade, tax and transparency, yes, you are taking on some vested interests, you are taking on some difficult decisions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>But actually will it help both the developing world and us in the West?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>I believe it can.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>While in Europe, Obama will also likely be forced to defend U.S. Internet surveillance techniques that were disclosed in a series of newspaper articles in early June.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>The intelligence programs, which were previously considered top secret, involved large tech companies who operate globally, including Facebook, Google and Yahoo.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
