<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="3003" link="http://cnn.com/2013/09/30/world/africa/kenya-mall-verjee-witness/index.html" date_published="2013-09-30 16:54:40" category="world" author="Zain Verjee, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Zain Verjee: I can&amp;apost;t get image of Westgate bodies out of my mind</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="20">Zain Verjee describes how Kenya&amp;apost;s national conversation has changed to security.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="27">Verjee, a Nairobi native, says the coming together of all Kenyans has been powerful.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="14">&amp;quot;Kenyans like us, are thinking of great escapes in ways we never did before,&amp;quot; Verjee writes.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-11 00:21:14" annotation_time="20.379">
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="3">Kenyans like us, are thinking of great escapes in ways we never did before.</sentence>
      <sentence id="20" ids_highlights="1">The national conversation has changed to security.</sentence>
      <sentence id="27" ids_highlights="2">Yet the coming together of all Kenyans has been powerful.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>I can&amp;apost;t get the image of the bodies lying near the freezer at Westgate out of my mind, and recognizing two of the victims, their bodies splayed, their blood splashed against the stark white floor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>There is a picture of an empty blue twin stroller, abandoned on the rooftop that I&amp;apost;ve walked on countless times.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>There are pictures we did not air on CNN because they were simply too gruesome.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>It felt more shocking because this was a mall as familiar to me as the back of my hand.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;Westgate was like home to us,&amp;quot; said my father to me over dinner in the kitchen this evening.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>And he was right - the mall was practically our second home -- it&amp;apost;s where we met our friends, did the household groceries, and banking.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>I&amp;apost;d often call home from London to find my parents at the new tapas joint sipping sangria, before that at Urban Burgers, Planet Yogurt or Artcaffe.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Looking around now at our kitchen, the tea, coffee, white asparagus, beads, my favorite ice-cream (toff n&amp;apost;choc with nuts) wine glasses, mobile phones, are all from Westgate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;Where shall we go shopping now,&amp;quot; asked mum?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;Nakumatt Ukay?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>she said referring to a red brick shopping center 100 meters away from Westgate.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;But it&amp;apost;s in the basement,&amp;quot; said dad, &amp;quot;there&amp;apost;s no emergency exit.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Let&amp;apost;s not go there.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Kenyans like us, are thinking of great escapes in ways we never did before.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Wherever we are, what&amp;apost;s the quickest route out?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>We are on edge on the streets, in our cars, and nervous in malls.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>I was at a clothes shop at the Sarit Center mall looking for a new shirt to buy before presenting the &amp;quot;Westgate Attack Special,&amp;quot; programme and something clattered to the floor.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>We all jumped in fear.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Friends and family are thinking twice about whether to go for dinner, lunch, run basic errands, and determine what could be safe and what is not.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The national conversation has changed to security.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Each passing day brings greater revelations about the terrorist plot and the government&amp;apost;s response.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Every Kenyan I have spoken to is angry, about intelligence failures, and operational failures.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Kenyans are acutely aware gunmen from Westgate escaped and many say our government has not provided us with sufficient answers: How?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Where?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>When?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Why?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Yet the coming together of all Kenyans has been powerful.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The diverse community has pulled together -- all races, all tribes that are often source of tension in Nairobi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Our politicians, bitter rivals, have supported the president.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>In the short term Kenyans expect to take an economic blow with fewer tourists coming here, less investment, less confidence amid the threat of further attacks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>For the long term, many point to 9/11 in New York or 7/7 in London and note how life went on, and those cities bounced back.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Kenya is the economic powerhouse of east Africa, that won&amp;apost;t change.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Kenyans are resilient, that won&amp;apost;t change.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Kenya leads the region in creativity, media, free press, biotechnology, arts, music, literature, none of that will change.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Kenya attracts investment opportunities around the world, that won&amp;apost;t change.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Life will go back to normal: The matatu mini vans will break traffic rules, the traffic will be horrendous, the horses will race at N&amp;apost;gong on Sunday, Mama Mbogas will sell their fresh vegetables, someone will order a cold Tusker beer, and the hot smell of the Kenyan earth after it rains will rise, and so will the nation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
