<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2295" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/02/14/world/africa/south-africa-pistorius-photos/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-02-14 09:43:08" category="world" author="Robyn Curnow, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Intimate photos show Oscar Pistorius, Reeva Steenkamp before her death</title>
  <keywords>Oscar Pistorius,Reeva Steenkamp</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="22">Photos show Oscar Pistorius and Reeva Steenkamp together not long before her death.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">One shows Steenkamp hanging over his shoulders, as he tenderly holds her fingers.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">Another shows her nestling into his shoulder as he holds her in his arms.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="4">Pistorius goes on trial for Steenkamp&amp;apost;s slaying next month; he says he shot her by mistake.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-10 13:24:00" annotation_time="47.354664">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="4">He denies the charge, saying he mistook her for a home invader.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2, 3">In one, Steenkamp wraps her arms around Pistorius, hanging over his shoulders as he tenderly holds on to her fingers.</sentence>
      <sentence id="22" ids_highlights="1">While the photos prove nothing with regard to Pistorius&amp;apost; guilt or innocence, they give an insight into the couple&amp;apost;s shared experiences and apparent intimacy before her death.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Johannesburg The photos of Oscar Pistorius and girlfriend Reeva Steenkamp appear to show a young couple in love.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The series of images, given exclusively to CNN by a source close to Pistorius, come as the Olympic runner faces a bleak anniversary: one year since he shot his girlfriend dead at his home on Valentine&amp;apost;s Day.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Pistorius will go on trial accused of Steenkamp&amp;apost;s murder early next month.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>He denies the charge, saying he mistook her for a home invader.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The intimate pictures -- some of the final images of the 29-year-old model, taken in the weeks and months before her death -- show the couple looking relaxed and happy.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>In one, Steenkamp wraps her arms around Pistorius, hanging over his shoulders as he tenderly holds on to her fingers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>They grin happily at the camera.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The couple are at the beach, with blue waters glistening behind them, and appear relaxed, casually dressed and in sunglasses.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Another blurry picture was taken in a kitchen.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The fridge magnets are as much in focus as Steenkamp&amp;apost;s smiling face as she sits on her boyfriend&amp;apost;s lap.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>She looks dressed up for a night out in a sleeveless black dress with gold trim that sets off her sleek blond hair.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Again, they are holding on to each other tightly.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The third image is more intimate and passionate, as Pistorius holds Steenkamp protectively in his arms.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>His eyes are closed as she seems to nestle into him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The photo is not just a holiday picture, but an aching reminder of a relationship and a life cruelly ended on Valentine&amp;apost;s Day a year ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;apost;Devastating accident&amp;apost; or murder?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Pistorius, who won world fame for his achievements as a double-amputee runner, fatally shot his girlfriend of three months in the early hours of February 14, when he fired through a bathroom door in his home.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Her death at the hands of an athlete regarded as South Africa&amp;apost;s golden boy shocked the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Pistorius does not deny shooting Steenkamp, a law school graduate with a burgeoning TV and fashion career, but says it was a &amp;quot;devastating accident.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Police say it was murder and will try to prove in court that the couple had an argument before the shots were fired, legal experts say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>The trial, which starts on March 3 before a high court judge, is expected to attract international interest.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>While the photos prove nothing with regard to Pistorius&amp;apost; guilt or innocence, they give an insight into the couple&amp;apost;s shared experiences and apparent intimacy before her death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>In a statement released on his website on the anniversary of the shooting, Pistorius said: &amp;quot;The loss of Reeva and the complete trauma of that day, I will carry with me for the rest of my life.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In a recent statement, Barry and June Steenkamp, Reeva&amp;apost;s parents, said they would like to thank people for their condolences.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;We understand and empathize with friends who have lost a child through violence or abuse,&amp;quot; they said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
