<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2921" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/01/21/world/asia/afghanistan-grossman-talks/index.html" date_published="2012-01-21 07:05:22" category="world" author="the CNN Wire Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>U.S. envoy in Afghanistan to discuss peace, Taliban</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="6">President Hamid Karazi recently met with the militant Hizb-i-Islami group.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">He says Afghanistan &amp;quot;is not a place for foreigners to do their political experiments&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="13">The U.S. special envoy will meet with Karzai again Sunday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="28">Secret talks between the United States and the Taliban have taken place since 2010.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-02 10:30:30" annotation_time="28.109335">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">Afghanistan is not a place for foreigners to do their political experiments or a laboratory that every few years they test a new political system.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="1">Karzai recently met with the party of warlord Gulbuddin Hekmatyar, head of the militant Hizb-i-Islami.</sentence>
      <sentence id="13" ids_highlights="3">U.S. diplomat Marc Grossman is set to meet Karzai again Sunday in discussions aimed at a achieving a peaceful resolution to Afghanistan&amp;apost;s conflict.</sentence>
      <sentence id="28" ids_highlights="4">Secret talks between the United States and the militant Taliban began in November 2010, sources said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Kabul, Afghanistan America&amp;apost;s special envoy to the region talked peace and reconciliation with Hamid Karzai in Kabul Saturday, while the Afghan president made it clear that Afghans should be in the driver&amp;apost;s seat.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>To that end, Karzai, in an address to the Afghan parliament, said the government and its peace council were making every effort to bring an end to the bloodshed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Afghan nation is the owner of the peace process and any peace talks,&amp;quot; Karzai said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;No other country or organization has the right to deprive the Afghan nation to this right.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Afghanistan is not a place for foreigners to do their political experiments or a laboratory that every few years they test a new political system.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Karzai recently met with the party of warlord Gulbuddin Hekmatyar, head of the militant Hizb-i-Islami.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;It was a positive meeting and happened in a good atmosphere,&amp;quot; said a senior Afghan official with direct knowledge of the talks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The official, who did not want to be identified because the talks were confidential, said Hizb-i-Islami supports the process of negotiating with the armed opposition and more talks are planned.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The meeting with Hekmatyar served as a signal from Karzai to the United States that peace talks encompass other radical groups besides the Taliban.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Hizb-i-Islami has attacked U.S. forces and Hekmatyar is on America&amp;apost;s most-wanted list of terrorists.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Another group, the Haqqani network, is another controversial branch of the insurgency accused of receiving sanctuary and support from Pakistan.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s not clear what role it will play in the peace process.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>U.S. diplomat Marc Grossman is set to meet Karzai again Sunday in discussions aimed at a achieving a peaceful resolution to Afghanistan&amp;apost;s conflict.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Karzai is expected to reiterate the the importance of Afghan control over a complex process.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am pleased to be in Kabul to consult with the government of Afghanistan,&amp;quot; Grossman said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;The United States stands ready to assist in any way we can an Afghan-led reconciliation process to find a peaceful end to this conflict.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>I look forward to calling on President Karzai and discussing next steps.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Karzai&amp;apost;s spokesman Aimal Faizi declined to give details of the talks with Grossman.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>But another senior Afghan official, who also wished to remain anonymous, said Saturday&amp;apost;s conversation went well and included &amp;quot;all aspects&amp;quot; of the peace process.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Grossman has been meeting secretly with Taliban negotiators for more than a year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Last week, U.S. senior administration officials said the United States could inch closer toward peace talks with the Taliban if Karzai blesses the negotiations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;We don&amp;apost;t have any idea standing here today what the outcome of such discussions could be,&amp;quot; U.S. Secretary of State Hillary Clinton said last week.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think all of us are entering into it with a very realistic sense of what is possible.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>And that includes, of course, President Karzai and his government, which after all bear the ultimate responsibility and the consequences of any such discussions.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Clinton acknowledged last week that discussions about opening up a Taliban office in Qatar and transferring some Taliban prisoners held at Guantanamo Bay were part of the U.S. support for Afghan reconciliation efforts.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>She stressed that nothing had been concluded, but said she was sending Grossman to Kabul and Qatar for further consultations.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Diplomatic sources said that depending on the outcome of the talks with Karzai, Grossman could have another meeting with the Taliban.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Secret talks between the United States and the militant Taliban began in November 2010, sources said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Senior U.S. officials and diplomatic sources said German officials brokered initial meetings with Tayeb al-Agha, an aide to Taliban leader Mullah Omar.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>The sources said after a series of meetings, Agha was able to prove his good faith as an interlocutor with key Taliban leaders.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The idea is for the talks to be Afghan-led, senior officials said, with as much U.S. participation as the Afghans need and want.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The talks would be the product of what officials call &amp;quot;confidence-building measures,&amp;quot; such as the opening of the office in Qatar&amp;apost;s capital Doha and a Taliban renunciation of terrorism in exchange for the release of five Taliban members being detained at Guantanamo Bay.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Clinton said last week no transfers were imminent, but Grossman&amp;apost;s talks in Kabul are expected to address the possible release of the detainees.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Once described as preconditions for peace talks to occur, Clinton now says insurgents must lay down their arms, accept the Afghan constitution and end ties with al Qaeda as &amp;quot;necessary outcomes&amp;quot; of the discussions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Grossman&amp;apost;s visit to Afghanistan also comes days after Pakistan&amp;apost;s government, embroiled in a squabble between civilian and military leaders, declined a visit from Grossman, according to a senior Pakistani government official.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>&amp;quot;His visit could fuel anti-American sentiments and create trouble for the government, which is already surrounded by storms,&amp;quot; the official said Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>The official asked not to be named because he is not authorized to speak to the media on this subject.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>A U.S. State Department official said Grossman wanted to go to Pakistan, but the Pakistani government declined for the time being.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
