<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2170" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/01/10/world/africa/egypt-violence/index.html" date_published="2014-01-10 14:35:58" category="world" author="Mohammed Tawfeeq, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Egypt protests: Crowds, police clash ahead of constitution vote</title>
  <keywords>Egypt protests,Muslim Brotherhood,Mohamed Morsy</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="8">Islamist group supporters protest an upcoming vote on a new constitution.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="8">The constitution would ban religious parties and give the military more power.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">Clashes were reported Friday in at least three cities.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-21 16:46:11" annotation_time="56.444">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="3">Protesters in parts of Egypt rallied Friday against the government and a vote on a constitution that would ban religious parties, leading to clashes with security forces or demonstrators&amp;apost; opponents in at least three cities, Egyptian media reported.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="1, 2">The alliance has focused its ire on Egypt&amp;apost;s January 14-15 referendum on a new constitution, which would not only ban religious parties but also put more power in the hands of the military.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Protesters in parts of Egypt rallied Friday against the government and a vote on a constitution that would ban religious parties, leading to clashes with security forces or demonstrators&amp;apost; opponents in at least three cities, Egyptian media reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The demonstrations are the latest by members or supporters of the Muslim Brotherhood, the Islamist group that has regularly protested Egypt&amp;apost;s interim government since Brotherhood-backed President Mohamed Morsy was ousted in a coup in July.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Muslim Brotherhood supporters clashed with opponents in parts of Cairo after Morsy loyalists tore down posters supporting the proposed constitution, on which Egyptians will vote Tuesday and Wednesday, the semiofficial Ahram Online news outlet reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>In Giza, security forces fired tear gas at Morsy supporters to disperse their march there, Ahram Online reported.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The demonstrators began to march after Friday prayers and clashed with police in various parts of the city, Ahram Online said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Clashes also broke out in al-Sabah city in Suez province, where security forces fired tear gas at a pro-Morsy march, according to the state-run Middle East News Agency.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The Muslim Brotherhood-led National Alliance to Support Legitimacy had called for protests, MENA said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The alliance has focused its ire on Egypt&amp;apost;s January 14-15 referendum on a new constitution, which would not only ban religious parties but also put more power in the hands of the military.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The alliance has called for a boycott of the referendum.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Muslim Brotherhood supporters have continued their protests, even though the government declared the group a terrorist organization last month.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The government has threatened to arrest anyone who attends Muslim Brotherhood protests or provides financial support to the organization.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Supporters of the organization demand the reinstatement of Morsy, who became the country&amp;apost;s first democratically elected president in 2012, and the full restoration of their political and social rights.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The interim government blames the group for coordinated attacks on churches and government facilities, including a recent bombing of a police headquarters that left 16 dead and more than 100 injured.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The military ousted Morsy on July 3 after he was accused of pursuing an Islamist agenda and excluding other factions from the government.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Morsy&amp;apost;s supporters say that the deposed president wasn&amp;apost;t given a fair chance and that the military has returned to the authoritarian practices of longtime ruler Hosni Mubarak, who was deposed in a popular uprising in 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Morsy is awaiting trial in several cases, including one in which he and 14 other Muslim Brotherhood members face charges stemming from December 2012 protests over a constitution he shepherded into effect.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Egyptian authorities have accused Morsy and his staff of ordering supporters to attack protesters after guards and members of the Interior Ministry refused to do it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Morsy and four others are charged with inciting violence, but they are not accused of using force.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Eleven others are charged with killing three men, torturing 54 people, using force and possessing weapons.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>That trial, delayed Wednesday, is expected to resume on February 1.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Morsy, who says he still is Egypt&amp;apost;s legitimate president, has refused to recognize the court&amp;apost;s authority and has yet to accept legal representation for the proceeding.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
