<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2486" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/12/14/world/africa/graca-machel-10-things/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2013-12-14 13:28:27" category="world" author="Faith Karimi, CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Nelson Mandela: 10 things to know about his wife, Graca Machel</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="16">Graca Machel was reluctant to marry Nelson Mandela.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="14">Her nickname was Jackie Kennedy .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">Mandela has said she made him bloom &amp;quot;like a flower&amp;quot; .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-10 15:16:18" annotation_time="12.2126665">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="3">Nelson Mandela once said his wife, Graca Machel, makes him &amp;quot;bloom like a flower.&amp;quot;</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="2">She has something in common with the Kennedys: In Mozambique, she was nicknamed Jackie Kennedy.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="1">It wasn&amp;apost;t love at first sight: After they met, she was reluctant to marry him or discuss their relationship in public.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Nelson Mandela once said his wife, Graca Machel, makes him &amp;quot;bloom like a flower.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Despite her reluctance to marry him at first, they&amp;apost;ve been inseparable since they tied the knot on his 80th birthday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Here are 10 things to know about the woman who was at the international icon&amp;apost;s side to the very end.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>She&amp;apost;s been first lady of two nations: Before she got married to the South African anti-apartheid icon, Machel was the first lady of Mozambique.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Her husband, President Samora Machel, died in a mysterious plane crash in 1986.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>She was much younger: When they got married in 1998, she was 52.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>But she says their advanced age made their relationship better.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;We were grown up; we were settled; we knew the value of a companion, of a partner,&amp;quot; she says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>She separated the man from the icon: At the beginning of their relationship, Machel says, there was a conflict between the man she married and the world&amp;apost;s perception of him.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;The aura around him was a bit confusing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>But then I learned to live with it, in terms of separating the two,&amp;quot; she told CNN&amp;apost;s Robyn Curnow in a rare interview in 2008.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>South Africa wasn&amp;apost;t always in love with her: Protective of their beloved Madiba, the nation did not warm up to a foreign first lady at first.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>She remained in the background at the beginning, and then slowly won them over with her loyalty and laid-back demeanor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>She has something in common with the Kennedys: In Mozambique, she was nicknamed Jackie Kennedy.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Not just for her class and grace, but because of the tragedy that befell her husband while in office.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>It wasn&amp;apost;t love at first sight: After they met, she was reluctant to marry him or discuss their relationship in public.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>But Mandela wooed her the old-fashioned way, occasionally giving his bodyguards headaches as president when he&amp;apost;d make unannounced stops to buy her chocolates.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>She&amp;apost;s kindred spirits with Mandela: Machel has something in common with her freedom fighter husband.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>While living in Mozambique, she was outspoken against the Portuguese colonial government.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>She&amp;apost;s qualified in her own right: She served as minister of education and culture in Mozambique for more than 10 years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>She is especially passionate about youth education, and has served as an expert on children&amp;apost;s issues for the United Nations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>She&amp;apost;s Mandela&amp;apost;s third wife: Mandela was first married to Evelyn Mase, but their marriage ended in divorce.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>In his biography &amp;quot;Long Walk to Freedom,&amp;quot; Mandela has said Mase made him choose between family and politics.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>He later married Winnie Mandela, a firebrand who became his voice when he was in prison.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>After their contentious divorce in 1996, Mandela married Machel two years later.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Their wedding was private: Despite Mandela&amp;apost;s larger-than-life status, they got married on his birthday 15 years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Their wedding was a low-key event attended by close family and friends.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
