<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2560" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/07/15/world/africa/oscar-pistorius-bar/index.html?hpt=hp_t3" date_published="2014-07-15 14:16:41" category="world" author="Susannah Cullinane, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Oscar Pistorius leaves nightclub after dispute</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Oscar Pistorius is accused of murdering his girlfriend Reeva Steenkamp in February 2013.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">Pistorius admits killing Steenkamp but denies murder, saying he mistook her for an intruder.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">He was involved in a dispute at a nightclub Saturday, his spokeswoman says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="2">Pistorius subsequently posted a series of tweets, his first activity on Twitter since February.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-14 15:29:14" annotation_time="63.536">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="3">South African sprinter Oscar Pistorius was involved in a nightclub dispute over the weekend, after another patron &amp;quot;started to aggressively interrogate him&amp;quot; on matters relating to his murder trial, his spokeswoman says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="4">Reports of the incident and subsequent tweets by Pistorius -- his first activity on Twitter since the one-year anniversary of his girlfriend&amp;apost;s death -- have grabbed headlines in South Africa and around the world.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">Pistorius, 27, is accused of murdering his girlfriend Reeva Steenkamp, 29, on February 14, 2013.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">The Olympic sprinter admits firing the bullets that killed Steenkamp, but denies murder, saying he mistakenly thought he was defending himself from an intruder.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>South African sprinter Oscar Pistorius was involved in a nightclub dispute over the weekend, after another patron &amp;quot;started to aggressively interrogate him&amp;quot; on matters relating to his murder trial, his spokeswoman says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Reports of the incident and subsequent tweets by Pistorius -- his first activity on Twitter since the one-year anniversary of his girlfriend&amp;apost;s death -- have grabbed headlines in South Africa and around the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Pistorius, 27, is accused of murdering his girlfriend Reeva Steenkamp, 29, on February 14, 2013.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The Olympic sprinter admits firing the bullets that killed Steenkamp, but denies murder, saying he mistakenly thought he was defending himself from an intruder.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>South African media reported Monday that Pistorius had been involved in an altercation Saturday at the VIP Room in the Sandton area of Johannesburg.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Pistorius&amp;apost; spokeswoman Anneliese Burgess confirmed to CNN Tuesday that her client had been at the venue with one of his cousins, sitting in a VIP section, when he was approached by another patron.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;The individual, according to my client, started to aggressively interrogate him on matters relating to the trial.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>An argument ensued during which my client asked to be left alone,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;Oscar soon thereafter left the club with his cousin.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>My client regrets the decision to go to a public space and thereby inviting unwelcome attention.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The day after the incident, Pistorius tweeted a photo montage showing him with children on prosthetics or stumps.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The text accompanying the photos reads, &amp;quot;You have the ability to make a difference in someones life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Sometimes it&amp;apost;s the simple things you say or do that can make someone feel better or inspire them.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>This was followed by a second tweet, in which the sprinter posted a photographed passage from &amp;quot;Man&amp;apost;s Search for Meaning,&amp;quot; a book by Holocaust survivor Viktor Frankl.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The text says love is the &amp;quot;ultimate and highest goal&amp;quot; and describes how a man with nothing &amp;quot;may still find bliss ... in the contemplation of his beloved.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;In a position of utter desolation, when a man cannot express himself in positive action, when his only achievement may consist in enduring his sufferings in the right way -- an honorable way -- in such a position man can, through loving contemplation of the image he carries of his beloved, achieve fulfillment,&amp;quot; it says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Pistorius posted a third tweet Monday, a prayer written across a photo of a misty river -- credited to the Christian website crosswalk.com.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The text reads: &amp;quot;Lord, today I ask that you bathe those who live in pain in the river of your healing.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Amen.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The postings have prompted messages of support, bewilderment and condemnation on the social media site, with some Twitter users questioning why Pistorius had visited a nightclub while on trial.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Pistorius&amp;apost; murder trial has been adjourned until August 7, when closing arguments are scheduled to begin.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
