<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2124" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/07/13/world/asia/china-tv-anchor-detained/index.html" date_published="2014-07-13 18:34:06" category="world" author="Steven Jiang, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>China&amp;apost;s star TV anchor arrested before airtime</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Rui Chenggang is known for his &amp;quot;big get&amp;quot; interviews and his nationalistic sentiment.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">Prosecutors took Rui into custody just before the start of &amp;quot;Economic News&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4">Rui&amp;apost;s patron Guo Zhenxi was detained in June for allegedly accepting bribes.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="2">Rui&amp;apost;s detention is the latest twist in a widening anti-corruption campaign in China.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-14 12:12:40" annotation_time="20.903">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1, 4">The detention of the controversial TV anchor, known for his &amp;quot;big get&amp;quot; interviews as well as nationalistic sentiment, is the latest twist in a widening anti-corruption campaign in China.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">Prosecutors took Rui into custody less than an hour before the start of &amp;quot;Economic News,&amp;quot; which his co-anchor presented alone.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">Speculation about Rui&amp;apost;s troubles began last month when his longtime patron Guo Zhenxi, the head of state-run CCTV&amp;apost;s financial news channel, was detained for allegedly accepting bribes.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Beijing Rui Chenggang&amp;apost;s anchor chair was left empty for Friday night&amp;apost;s national newscast on China Central Television after prosecutors detained the star journalist shortly before airtime, according to state media.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The detention of the controversial TV anchor, known for his &amp;quot;big get&amp;quot; interviews as well as nationalistic sentiment, is the latest twist in a widening anti-corruption campaign in China.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Prosecutors took Rui into custody less than an hour before the start of &amp;quot;Economic News,&amp;quot; which his co-anchor presented alone.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Speculation about Rui&amp;apost;s troubles began last month when his longtime patron Guo Zhenxi, the head of state-run CCTV&amp;apost;s financial news channel, was detained for allegedly accepting bribes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Several other senior figures at the channel were also implicated, the government said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;apost;Face of New China&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Rui, 37, denied in a statement last month that he was under investigation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>He tweeted last month to his 10 million followers on Sina Weibo -- China&amp;apost;s equivalent of Twitter -- a philosophical conversation between two ancient Zen masters that implied time would eventually clear his name.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>State media cited CCTV sources on Saturday as saying that Rui&amp;apost;s detention was closely linked to Guo&amp;apost;s case, as well as an investigation into his own possible profiting from using CCTV resources.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Rui, who&amp;apost;s known for wearing designer suits and driving fast cars, commands more social media followers than any other CCTV personality and has been called the &amp;quot;face of the New China&amp;quot; by his admirers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>His official CCTV bio says he has interviewed hundreds of business and political leaders around the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Rui, who is fluent in English, began his broadcast career at CCTV&amp;apost;s English-language service, but his stardom soared under Guo after the young journalist jumped to the network&amp;apost;s financial news channel in 2008.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>An unapologetic self-promoter, he has authored two popular autobiographical books touting his friendship with the world&amp;apost;s rich and powerful.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Controversial figure.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Rui became a more divisive public figure as his celebrity grew.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>He successfully led a controversial campaign to kick Starbucks out of Beijing&amp;apost;s Forbidden City in 2007, calling the American coffee shop&amp;apost;s presence in the historic palace museum an encroachment on Chinese culture.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>He grabbed a global spotlight in 2010 when U.S. President Barack Obama said he would give the final question at a news conference in Seoul to South Korean media.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m actually Chinese, but I think I get to represent the entire Asia,&amp;quot; Rui said as he grabbed the mic to ask a long-winded question on how Obama might prevent his policies from being misinterpreted.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>At an economic forum in northeastern China the following year, Rui asked Gary Locke, then the U.S. ambassador to China, a question that some critics called a nationalistic publicity stunt.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Others applauded it as a sign of an increasingly confident China standing up to the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;My colleagues told me you flew economy class from Beijing to Dalian,&amp;quot; Rui asked Locke.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;Was that a reminder that the U.S. still owes China money?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Locke replied that it was standard government policy for American diplomats and other officials to fly coach.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>&amp;apost;Tigers and flies&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Rui&amp;apost;s detention came on the heels of the downfall of several former high-ranking officials, including a retired top general of the 2 million-strong People&amp;apost;s Liberation Army.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Gen. Xu Caihou, a former vice chairman of the Central Military Commission that runs the world&amp;apost;s largest standing army, was expelled from the ruling Communist Party and handed over to prosecutors after being found to have accepted bribes, state-run Xinhua news agency reported early this month.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Xu was also a member of the Politburo, China&amp;apost;s decision-making body, before retiring in 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>State media have characterized Xu as a big &amp;quot;military tiger&amp;quot; caught in the massive anti-graft campaign launched by President Xi Jinping, who is also the commander in chief.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Xi banned official extravagance -- from banquets to year-end gifts -- and vowed to target &amp;quot;tigers and flies&amp;quot; alike in his fight against corruption, launched after he became head of the Communist Party in late 2012.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>He resolved to spare no one, regardless of position.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Xinhua recently touted the capture of 30 &amp;quot;tigers&amp;quot; since Xi took power.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Zhou Yongkang.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Some China watchers have noted ties between an increasing number of disgraced officials and Zhou Yongkang, the former domestic security czar who has been rumored to be under investigation for some time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Guo, the CCTV executive who was Rui&amp;apost;s patron, has long been linked to a protege of Zhou.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>State media have reported official probes into many of Zhou&amp;apost;s family members as well as former associates in the domestic security apparatus, state oil industry and southwestern Sichuan province -- three places Zhou once ruled.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>If he is actually charged, Zhou would become the highest-ranking official ever to face corruption charges in the history of the People&amp;apost;s Republic.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Some 182,000 officials were disciplined in 2013, while courts nationwide tried 23,000 corruption cases, according to the Communist Party&amp;apost;s disciplinary commission.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>State media have cited the trial and conviction last year of former high-flying politician Bo Xilai -- which Bo supporters called politically motivated -- as one prime example of Xi&amp;apost;s determination to clean up the party.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;apost;Endemic corruption&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Longtime China observers, however, point to the limits of Xi&amp;apost;s war on corruption.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>&amp;quot;Corruption is so widespread and so endemic that campaigns are just not going to do it,&amp;quot; said Frank Ching, a Hong Kong-based commentator and columnist on Chinese politics.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;Something has to be done about the system.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>&amp;quot;There have been public calls for a law to require officials disclosing their assets.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>There has been no indication that they are going to do that.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>In fact, a number of people calling for this law have ended up in prison,&amp;quot; Ching said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>&amp;quot;I think people will be much more convinced of the seriousness of this anti-corruption campaign if there were a move to enact such a law.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
