<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2820" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/05/21/world/asia/china-xinjiang-explosions/index.html" date_published="2014-05-22 02:26:57" category="world" author="Jethro Mullen, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Terrorist attack kills dozens in China&amp;apost;s tense Xinjiang region</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="14">NEW: U.S. says the attack is an &amp;quot;outrageous act of violence against innocent civilians&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="3">The Chinese President calls for terrorists to be &amp;quot;severely&amp;quot; punished.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="5">The explosions have killed 31 people and wounded more than 90, Xinhua says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="2">China says the attack is &amp;quot;a serious violent terrorist incident&amp;quot;.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-14 19:50:50" annotation_time="16.5835">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="4">China&amp;apost;s Ministry of Public Security said the attack in the heavily policed city of Urumqi was &amp;quot;a serious violent terrorist incident&amp;quot; and vowed to crack down on its perpetrators.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="2">President Xi Jinping called for the terrorists behind it to be &amp;quot;severely&amp;quot; punished.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="3">The vehicles then exploded, according to Xinhua, which said at least 31 people were killed and more than 90 wounded.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;This is a despicable and outrageous act of violence against innocent civilians, and the United States resolutely opposes all forms of terrorism,&amp;quot; White House Press Secretary Jay Carney said in a statement.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>A series of explosions tore through an open-air market in the capital of the volatile western Chinese region of Xinjiang on Thursday, killing dozens of people and wounding many more, state media reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>China&amp;apost;s Ministry of Public Security said the attack in the heavily policed city of Urumqi was &amp;quot;a serious violent terrorist incident&amp;quot; and vowed to crack down on its perpetrators.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>President Xi Jinping called for the terrorists behind it to be &amp;quot;severely&amp;quot; punished.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Two SUVs slammed into shoppers gathered at the market in Urumqi at 7:50 a.m. Thursday, and explosives were flung out of the vehicles, China&amp;apost;s official news agency Xinhua said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The vehicles then exploded, according to Xinhua, which said at least 31 people were killed and more than 90 wounded.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Some of the photos circulating on social media suggested a hellish scene, with bodies strewn on the ground amid burning wreckage.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Others showed flames and smoke billowing out of the end of a tree-lined street guarded by police officers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;apost;An enormous sound&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;I heard an enormous sound, then I looked out from my balcony,&amp;quot; said a resident of a building near the explosion who would only give his surname, Shan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>He told CNN that trees obscured much of his view of the scene, but that he &amp;quot;could see there was chaos, with people injured.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Many of the victims caught in the blasts were elderly people who regularly visited the morning market, Xinhua reported.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s mainly people coming to trade vegetables, especially the elderly who get up early and buy vegetables to cook,&amp;quot; Shan said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The U.S. government condemned the attack.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is a despicable and outrageous act of violence against innocent civilians, and the United States resolutely opposes all forms of terrorism,&amp;quot; White House Press Secretary Jay Carney said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>String of recent attacks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Chinese authorities have stepped up security measures in Xinjiang in recent months amid a series of attacks within the region and in major Chinese cities outside it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>On Wednesday, the day before the blasts, Xinhua reported that 39 people had been sentenced to prison in the past two months for &amp;quot;inciting violence&amp;quot; in Xinjiang.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>But the devastating blasts Thursday suggest the government is facing a foe determined to wreak havoc.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Thursday&amp;apost;s attack at the market comes less than a month after an explosion hit a train station in Urumqi, killing three people and wounding 79 others.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>That blast took place on April 30, just after Xi had wrapped up a visit to the region.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Ethnic tensions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Chinese officials have linked a mass knife attack in March that killed 29 people at a train station in the southwestern city of Kunming to Islamic separatists from Xinjiang.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>They have also blamed separatists for an attack in Beijing&amp;apost;s Tiananmen Square in October in which a car rammed into a pedestrian bridge and burst into flames, killing two tourists and the three occupants of the vehicle.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>The knife-wielding assailants in the Kunming attack and the people in the car that hit Tiananmen were identified as Uyghurs, a Turkic-speaking, predominantly Muslim ethnic group from Xinjiang.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Ethnic tensions between Uyghurs and Han Chinese people, millions of whom have migrated to resource-rich Xinjiang in recent decades, have repeatedly boiled over into deadly riots and clashes with authorities in recent years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Some Uyghurs have expressed resentment over harsh treatment from Chinese security forces and Han people taking the lion&amp;apost;s share of economic opportunities in Xinjiang.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The Han are the predominant ethnic group in China, making up more than 90% of the overall population.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Shift in target.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>The pattern of ethnic violence in the region goes back decades, according to James Leibold, an expert in ethnic relations in China at La Trobe University in Melbourne.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;But what&amp;apost;s new, and what I think is significant, is that we have a shift in target,&amp;quot; Leibold said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have a targeting of innocent civilians, places where innocent civilians gather -- an attempt to maim innocent civilians in large numbers.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>The other change is that the violence has &amp;quot;seeped outside&amp;quot; the borders of Xinjiang into other parts of China, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>It remains unclear who exactly is behind the high-profile attacks in recent months.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Chinese officials have pointed to a murky separatist group, the East Turkestan Islamic Movement (ETIM), which they have blamed for violent acts in the past.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>East Turkestan is the name used by many Uyghur groups to refer to Xinjiang.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>But analysts are divided about the extent of the ETIM&amp;apost;s activities and its links to global terrorist networks like al Qaeda.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;Generally, the government response is to blame terrorists without providing many details,&amp;quot; Leibold said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>&amp;quot;So I suspect it&amp;apost;s going to be very difficult to get to the bottom of this incident like previous ones.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
