<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2745" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/12/24/world/africa/somalia-pirate-rescue/index.html" date_published="2012-12-24 13:48:51" category="world" author="Catherine E. Shoichet and Neda Farshbaf, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Ship crew held for 1,000 days rescued off coast of Yemen</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5, 1">Official: The hostages&amp;apost; 1,000 days in captivity was the longest anyone has been held by pirates.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">Their rescue was the result of a two-week operation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="4, 3">One member of the ship&amp;apost;s crew reportedly committed suicide; another was killed by pirates.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="9">International Maritime Bureau says the hostages show signs of physical abuse and illness.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-29 13:28:25" annotation_time="78.41367">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">They were trapped at sea for 1,000 days, held on their own ship by Somali pirates off the coast of Yemen.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="3">Conditions were so harsh on the ship that one member of the 24-person crew reportedly committed suicide by jumping overboard.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="3">Another was killed by pirates.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">Over the weekend, troops from the Puntland Maritime Police Force rescued the 22 hostages remaining on the Panama-flagged vessel, ending the longest time anyone has been held hostage by pirates, according to Michael Howlett, deputy director of the International Maritime Bureau.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">Sunday&amp;apost;s rescue was the result of a two-week operation, the International Maritime Bureau said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="4">They showed signs of physical abuse and illness after their time in captivity, the International Maritime Bureau said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>They were trapped at sea for 1,000 days, held on their own ship by Somali pirates off the coast of Yemen.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>A petition pushing for their release described hostages huddled in tight spaces aboard the MV Iceberg 1, given only rice and water to survive.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Conditions were so harsh on the ship that one member of the 24-person crew reportedly committed suicide by jumping overboard.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Another was killed by pirates.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Over the weekend, troops from the Puntland Maritime Police Force rescued the 22 hostages remaining on the Panama-flagged vessel, ending the longest time anyone has been held hostage by pirates, according to Michael Howlett, deputy director of the International Maritime Bureau.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are greatly relieved to hear that they are safe after their terrible ordeal,&amp;quot; said Peter Swift, chairman of the Maritime Piracy Humanitarian Response Programme, which has been tracking the ship&amp;apost;s saga.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Sunday&amp;apost;s rescue was the result of a two-week operation, the International Maritime Bureau said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Mohamed Abdulrahman, director of the maritime force that led the mission, said Monday that the rescued hostages -- who hailed from Yemen, India, Pakistan, Ghana, Sudan and the Philippines -- were in good health at a military base in Puntland, a semiautonomous region of Somalia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>They showed signs of physical abuse and illness after their time in captivity, the International Maritime Bureau said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;We hope that both public and private organizations will work to ensure that the released hostages, as well as their families, receive all the necessary support and assistance they will require both immediately and longer term as they recover from the trauma and deprivation that they have suffered since being kidnapped,&amp;quot; Swift said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>In March 2010, pirates hijacked the ship, which had been transporting mechanical equipment and was en route to the United Arab Emirates, the European Union Naval Force Somalia reported at the time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;Whilst this is a successful rescue operation, our thoughts are with the remaining 139 hostages still held by pirates, 28 of whom have been there for just under two years,&amp;quot; the International Maritime Bureau said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>On Sunday, officials from the bureau, which monitors pirate attacks, said that heavily armed pirates had kidnapped four people after attacking an Italian supply vessel off the coast of Nigeria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>In October, the bureau reported that sea piracy had fallen to its lowest level worldwide since 2008 as a result of increasing policing by international naval forces.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
