<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2918" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/05/21/world/meast/syria-unrest/index.html" date_published="2012-05-21 09:40:27" category="world" author="the CNN Wire Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>U.S. ambassador: NATO has no plans for military intervention in Syria</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="14">NEW: At least six people have been killed Monday, according to opposition activists .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">The U.S. ambassador to NATO says the Syrian uprising is unlike Libya&amp;apost;s.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">At least 60 people were killed across Syria on Sunday, opposition activists say .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-14 13:53:51" annotation_time="30.888">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2">The U.S. ambassador to NATO says the alliance has no plans for military intervention in the Syrian crisis, as reports of deaths mount by the dozens and diplomatic efforts have yet to stymie the bloodshed.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">On the same day Daalder spoke, at least 60 people were killed in Syria&amp;apost;s 14-month crisis, opposition activists said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="1">The United Nations says at least 9,000 people have been killed since initially peaceful protests against President Bashar al-Assad erupted in March 2011.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>The U.S. ambassador to NATO says the alliance has no plans for military intervention in the Syrian crisis, as reports of deaths mount by the dozens and diplomatic efforts have yet to stymie the bloodshed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Ivo Daalder told reporters late Sunday there is &amp;quot;no planning going on that&amp;apost;s related to a NATO role in Syria.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;As it relates to NATO planning, a NATO ally has to come forward and request that type of planning.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>So that&amp;apost;s a circumstance that hasn&amp;apost;t taken place,&amp;quot; the ambassador said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;d obviously take any requests of that nature seriously if it were to be made.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Daalder also said that NATO, along with European allies and Arab partners, has provided assistance to the Syrian opposition, including political and diplomatic support.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;We&amp;apost;ve also decided, however, that a military intervention of the nature that we did in Libya would further militarize the situation in ways that wouldn&amp;apost;t necessarily protect civilian life,&amp;quot; Daalder said. &amp;quot;.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>... Unlike Libya, you don&amp;apost;t have pockets of the country that can be protected by civilian protection zones.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>You&amp;apost;ve got security forces intermingled with the population, and that introduction of greater military intervention from outside or arms to groups within Syria could further militarize the conflict in a counterproductive way.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>On the same day Daalder spoke, at least 60 people were killed in Syria&amp;apost;s 14-month crisis, opposition activists said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Among the dead, at least 40 were killed in the northwestern city of Hama, where a neighborhood sustained heavy shelling by government troops, said the Local Coordination Committees of Syria, a network of opposition activists.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>On Monday, activists said, six people died across the country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The deaths included three unidentified bodies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The United Nations says at least 9,000 people have been killed since initially peaceful protests against President Bashar al-Assad erupted in March 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Opposition activists put the toll at more than 11,000.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Syria&amp;apost;s government, meanwhile, said it buried 18 more members of its security forces who died battling &amp;quot;armed terrorist groups&amp;quot; around the country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>CNN cannot independently verify reports of deaths and violence because the Syrian government has severely restricted access by international media.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The fighting has continued despite a peace plan brokered by former U.N. Secretary-General Kofi Annan, now a special envoy for the United Nations and the Arab League.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
