<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2178" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/23/opinion/lemmon-emma-watson/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-09-23 10:58:57" category="world" author="Gayle Tzemach Lemmon" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Emma Watson gives feminism new life (Opinion)</title>
  <keywords>Emma Watson,United Nations,speech,gender equality,feminism</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Emma Watson gives a rousing speech at the United Nations about gender inequality .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="23">Gayle Lemmon: Watson is the latest star to illuminate the rebranding of feminism.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="28">She says that to date we have seen a lot of promise and much less progress .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="37">Lemmon: The hard part is to take action and make changes to create a fairer world .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-03 12:46:33" annotation_time="45.79433">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1"> Emma Watson lent her name and her glittery profile to the cause of feminism at the United Nations, and in the process got places that rarely cover this eight-letter &amp;quot;f&amp;quot; word to pay attention.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="2">Indeed, Watson&amp;apost;s star is only the latest to illuminate the rebranding of feminism.</sentence>
      <sentence id="28" ids_highlights="3">The retaking of the &amp;quot;feminist&amp;quot; label by cultural luminaries lending their platform to the issue is laudable, but to date we have seen a lot of promise and much less progress.</sentence>
      <sentence id="37" ids_highlights="4">But now comes the hard part: the action to make the change and in the process create a world that is fairer for everyone.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Emma Watson lent her name and her glittery profile to the cause of feminism at the United Nations, and in the process got places that rarely cover this eight-letter &amp;quot;f&amp;quot; word to pay attention.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;How can we effect change in the world when only half of it is invited or feel welcome to participate in the conversation?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Watson said in a speech about gender equality that received a standing ovation and has gone viral.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;Men -- I would like to take this opportunity to extend your formal invitation.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Gender equality is your issue, too,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Rarely do &amp;quot;E!</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Online&amp;quot; and U.N. Women tweet the same speech.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>But this wasn&amp;apost;t just any speech.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>It focused on the role of men and questioned the demonization of the term &amp;quot;feminism.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;Why has the word become such an uncomfortable one?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>I think it is right I am paid the same as my male counterparts.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>I think it is right that I should make decisions about my own body.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>I think it is right that women be involved on my behalf in the policies and decisions that will affect my life.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>I think it is right that socially, I am afforded the same respect as men,&amp;quot; Watson said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;My life is a sheer privilege because my parents didn&amp;apost;t love me less because I was born a daughter.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>My school did not limit me because I was a girl.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>My mentors didn&amp;apost;t assume that I would go less far because I might give birth to a child one day.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>These influences are the gender equality ambassadors that made me who I am today.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>They may not know it but they are the inadvertent feminists needed in the world today.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>We need more of those.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Watson gave the speech in light of the U.N. launch of the HeForShe campaign, which aims to engage men to stop violence against women.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>We live in a world in which 100 million girls globally are expected to be married off before age 18 in the next 10 years, a world in which even in the United States a girl can find herself plucked against her will from a New York classroom and forced by relatives to marry against her will in a country she has never known, a world in which 31 million girls of elementary school age remain out of school, a world in which two-thirds of the world&amp;apost;s 774 million illiterate citizens are female.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Indeed, Watson&amp;apost;s star is only the latest to illuminate the rebranding of feminism.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>As Jessica Bennett wrote on Time.com, Beyonce put the word &amp;quot;FEMINIST&amp;quot; in a blaze of full-stage glory at the MTV Video Music Awards, &amp;quot;making Sunday the sixth-highest day for volume of conversation about feminism since Twitter began tracking this year (the top three were days during #YesAllWomen).&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Beyonce also penned a piece last year arguing that &amp;quot;men have to demand that their wives, daughters, mothers and sisters earn more - commensurate with their qualifications and not their gender.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Equality will be achieved when men and women are granted equal pay and equal respect.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>The question now is how to translate all the high-profile feminizing into visible, on-the-ground gains in the lives of ordinary women and men.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The retaking of the &amp;quot;feminist&amp;quot; label by cultural luminaries lending their platform to the issue is laudable, but to date we have seen a lot of promise and much less progress.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>One example: On the media front women are embarrassingly absent from editorial pages still content to feature women&amp;apost;s voices a fraction of the time.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Women &amp;quot;are less likely than men to be sources or appear in authoritative roles in news stories, are depicted less frequently than males and less prominently, such as appearing further down in the columns, with fewer quotes or only paraphrased.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>(A recent Washington Post review of a Civil War book noted that the author&amp;apost;s prose seemed &amp;quot;to have been borrowed from the pages of a women&amp;apost;s magazine.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Rarely have I spotted such a reference to GQ or Esquire.).</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>In entertainment, research from the Geena Davis Institute on Gender in Media found in a survey of recently released films that there are &amp;quot;2.24 male characters for every female character.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Only 30.9% of the speaking characters are female.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>On the economic front, &amp;quot;after a gradual rise in the 1980s and 1990s, the women&amp;apost;s-to-men&amp;apost;s earnings ratio peaked at 81% in 2005 and 2006.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>So, the talk about access to opportunity for everyone is terrific.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>But now comes the hard part: the action to make the change and in the process create a world that is fairer for everyone.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>One that does justice to the ambition of girls in any and every corner of the world, and to our own hopes for a more stable, secure and prosperous future.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>It will take a village.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>One boosted by a lot of high-wattage celebrities helping to light the way.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Follow us on Twitter @CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Join us on Facebook/CNNOpinion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>