<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2975" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/06/26/world/meast/iraq-syria-questions" date_published="2014-06-26 14:15:19" category="world" author="CNN&amp;apost;s Arwa Damon, Ashley Fantz, Tim Lister and Raja Razek" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Why would Syria bomb Iraq? Your questions answered</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7">ISIS wants to create an Islamic state across Sunni areas of Iraq and Syria .</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="25">Syrian response to ISIS inside its borders has been fairly muted until now.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="1">But Syrian regime bombed ISIS positions in Syria recently and reportedly bombed in Iraq.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-08-26 11:57:09" annotation_time="24.239">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="3">Syrian warplanes reportedly targeted Iraq this week.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">ISIS includes mostly Sunni militants who want to create an Islamic state across Sunni areas of Iraq and Syria.</sentence>
      <sentence id="25" ids_highlights="2">Bashar al-Assad&amp;apost;s regime knows where ISIS bases are inside Syria, but its response to ISIS has been fairly muted for months.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Syrian warplanes reportedly targeted Iraq this week.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Scores of civilians were killed at markets and gas stations in Anbar province Tuesday, local leaders told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>A militant group called ISIS, the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria, has been pushing into Iraq, shaking the country, its leadership and, in turn, threatening the region.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>But what does it mean that Syria reportedly is now attacking its neighbor?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Here are some answers to get you up to speed:.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>What does ISIS want, and how is that related to Iraq and Syria?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>ISIS includes mostly Sunni militants who want to create an Islamic state across Sunni areas of Iraq and Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>In the towns it controls in Syria, it has imposed Sharia law.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Women must be covered, music is prohibited, girls and boys must not mingle at school.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The group&amp;apost;s tactics are so ruthless even al Qaeda has distanced itself.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>For example, ISIS kidnapped more than 140 Kurdish schoolboys in Syria last month and forced them to take daily lessons in radical Islamic theory, according to the Syrian Observatory for Human Rights, a London-based monitoring group.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The militant group was born in Iraq, initially called the Islamic State of Iraq, an umbrella organization headed by al Qaeda.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The group&amp;apost;s leader, Abu Bakr al Baghdadi, served four years in a U.S. prison camp for insurgents, at Bucca in southern Iraq.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>He was released in 2009.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The Islamic State in Iraq relocated to Syria and eventually became known by its new name, the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Is ISIS capable of getting what it wants?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Regrouping and strengthening in Syria, ISIS became well-financed and highly organized.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Today, the group has grown large enough to divide the entire region along sectarian lines, experts say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>ISIS has produced and attracted more jihadists and foreign fighters than the war in Iraq ever did.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>It has more suicide bombers at its disposal, more heavy weaponry and vehicles and more money than any other terrorist organization in the world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>It also has launched an intensive and sophisticated media campaign with flashy videos directed at Westerners, enticing them to join the fight.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>ISIS has also employed a classic guerilla warfare tactic -- the militants live among civilians.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>It would be difficult to target these militants in general strikes without injuring or killing innocent people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Why would Syria reportedly bomb Iraq now?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Bashar al-Assad&amp;apost;s regime knows where ISIS bases are inside Syria, but its response to ISIS has been fairly muted for months.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The existence of ISIS has helped to justify the Syrian government&amp;apost;s often-used line that it is fighting &amp;quot;terrorists,&amp;quot; and opposition activists have long accused the regime of allowing the group to operate and grow, pointing to the government&amp;apost;s constant barrel bombing of civilian neighborhoods in places such as Aleppo, while ISIS positions remain largely untargeted.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>But since the militant group has taken over large parts of northern Iraq recently, Syria has intensified its targeted campaign of ISIS positions, particularly in Raqqa, Syria, where ISIS has operated its headquarters for some time.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Damascus denies bombing positions in Iraq, but several sources, including an eyewitness and the head of the Anbar provincial council, said Syrian warplanes launched this week&amp;apost;s strikes.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>CNN is seeking a response from the Syrian government.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s unlikely al-Assad anticipated that ISIS would achieve such impressive and significant victories in Iraq.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>The only weapon Syrians have in the border area is air power; Syrian ground forces pulled out long ago.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Bombing Iraq now serves to clip ISIS&amp;apost; wings a little.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>How are the Iraqi and Syrian conflicts linked?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Under Iraqi Prime Minister Nuri al-Maliki, the Iraqi government has gradually become closer to the Syrian regime.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>They share allies such as Iran and Hezbollah and enemies such as al Qaeda, ISIS, Sunni extremists and Saudi Arabia, too.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>The old colonial borders in the region are disappearing, and a conflict is emerging that is more Sunni versus Shiite.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Al-Maliki, some experts said, stoked that sectarian tension even more in a speech Wednesday in which the Shiite leader slammed Sunnis.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>He blamed his political rivals for &amp;quot;coordinating&amp;quot; the crisis in Iraq and accused Sunnis of collaborating with militants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>What are the Iraq military&amp;apost;s shortcomings?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Iraq is using its air force -- what&amp;apost;s left of it -- to fight back against ISIS.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Iraq has initiated airstrikes, but targeting the group means putting a scope on constantly moving targets.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>ISIS uses pickups, not tanks.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Without precise intelligence from the ground, battling ISIS is tough.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>And it&amp;apost;s critical to remember that Iraq lost virtually all its air power with the 2003 U.S. invasion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>The Iraqi army crumbled in the face of ISIS&amp;apost; advances.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>The governor of Kirkuk told CNN that the Iraq force is a &amp;quot;checkpoint army,&amp;quot; meaning that it is able to set up and run checkpoints but isn&amp;apost;t sophisticated enough to fight ISIS cells.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>The Iraqi army also tends to use a counterproductive strategy of rounding up individuals as a method of control, aggravating the local population.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>Finally, the Iraqi military is up against a terror organization more powerful than anything that the U.S. military was battling and struggled to overcome.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Why has U.S. air power not been used against ISIS in Iraq?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Many experts believe that U.S. airstrikes in Iraq are far too risky and might not deliver the results the United States wants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>Again, consider that ISIS is mixed among the civilian population.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>Airstrikes may kill innocent people.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>And there are logistical questions that have to be answered.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="54">
          <content>Where would the air power come from?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="55">
          <content>Bases in Turkey perhaps?</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="56">
          <content>Would Turkey give its green light?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="57">
          <content>Also, some in Iraq perceive that the United States put al-Maliki in power and supported his regime for years, and U.S. interference with air power might not be welcomed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="58">
          <content>The United States has to worry about Iran, too.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="59">
          <content>U.S. strikes in Iraq could undermine progress Iran and the United States have made on the issue of nuclear weapons.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="60">
          <content>Also, ISIS is not the only group fighting to gain control of Iraq.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="61">
          <content>Sunni insurgent groups that were active during the U.S.-led invasion have also joined in the battle.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="62">
          <content>Sunni tribal leaders all oppose al-Maliki and view him and his Shiite-dominated government as a bigger threat to the country than ISIS.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="63">
          <content>Members of insurgent groups not aligned with ISIS could be killed, possibly creating a new set of enemies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="64">
          <content>Any U.S. airstrikes in Iraq could further deepen the divide if there&amp;apost;s a perception the action was done to bolster al-Maliki&amp;apost;s government.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="65">
          <content>It could also further alienate Sunni groups whose support eventually will be needed for any sort of political process to succeed in the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
