<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2069" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/04/15/world/africa/nigeria-girls-abducted" date_published="2014-04-15 19:29:26" category="world" author="Aminu Abubakar, for CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>As many as 200 girls abducted by Boko Haram, Nigerian officials say</title>
  <keywords>Girls abducted in Nigeria,Boko Haram abducted school girls</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7, 3">The girls were sleeping in their dormitories when Boko Haram attacked.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="10">Some girls managed to escape when abductors&amp;apost; vehicles broke down.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="18">Boko Haram is against western education, has launched several attacks on schools.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-25 09:29:06" annotation_time="70.82166" mapping_time_divergence="23.607222">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">Dozens of gunmen stormed the Government Girls Secondary School in Chibok, about 130 km (81 miles) west of Maiduguri, on Monday night as the students slept in their dormitories, officials said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;The Boko Haram attackers came to town around 9 p.m. and made straight for the school where they had a gun battle with soldiers stationed at the school and killed two soldiers,&amp;quot; said Chibok resident Maina Babagana.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="2">A student who was among about a dozen girls who managed to escape from their abductors recounted her ordeal.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="3">Boko Haram, which translates as &amp;quot;western education is sin,&amp;quot; is known to have carried out deadly attacks on other schools in the northeast.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>As many as 200 girls were abducted from their boarding school in northeastern Nigeria by heavily armed Boko Haram Islamists who arrived in trucks, vans and buses, officials and witnesses said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The group has recently stepped up attacks in the region, and its leader released a video last month threatening to kidnap girls from schools.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Dozens of gunmen stormed the Government Girls Secondary School in Chibok, about 130 km (81 miles) west of Maiduguri, on Monday night as the students slept in their dormitories, officials said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>They engaged the soldiers guarding the school in a lengthy gun battle and then herded the girls onto vehicles.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;Many girls were abducted by the rampaging gunmen who stormed the school in a convoy of vehicles,&amp;quot; said Emmanuel Sam, an education official in Chibok.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Sam could not say exactly how many girls were kidnapped, but one student who managed to get away said at least 200 students were taken.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;The Boko Haram attackers came to town around 9 p.m. and made straight for the school where they had a gun battle with soldiers stationed at the school and killed two soldiers,&amp;quot; said Chibok resident Maina Babagana.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The gunmen then burned homes and businesses in the town in Borno state as they fled with the girls, witnesses said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>A military spokesman in the region declined to comment on the abduction, saying the Nigerian Defence Ministry would issue statement later.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>A student who was among about a dozen girls who managed to escape from their abductors recounted her ordeal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;They forced us into trucks, buses and vans, some of which were carrying food stuffs and petrol.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>They left with us in a convoy into the bush,&amp;quot; said the student, who declined to be named for security reasons.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;A group of motorcyclists flanked the convoy to ensure none of us escaped.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>At one point, one of the trucks broke down and the girls on that vehicle were transferred to another one, the student said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The broken down truck was set on fire, she added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>When another vehicle broke down and the men tried to fix it, &amp;quot;some of us jumped out of the vehicles and ran into the bush.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>We later found our way back to Chibok,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Boko Haram, which translates as &amp;quot;western education is sin,&amp;quot; is known to have carried out deadly attacks on other schools in the northeast.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>In a clip released by the group March 23, leader Abubakar Shekau threatened to launch raids and abduct girls from schools.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>In early March, Borno state government closed all of its 85 secondary schools and sent more than 120,000 students home following increasing Boko Haram attacks on schools.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
