<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2874" link="http://cnn.com/2012/04/25/world/europe/britain-madeleine-mccann/index.html?hpt=ismore " date_published="2012-04-25 10:41:56" category="world" author="the CNN Wire Staff" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>UK police say missing girl Madeleine McCann may still be alive</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Madeleine McCann vanished during a 2007 family vacation in Portugal.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="4">London&amp;apost;s Metropolitan Police release an image of how the girl might look now .</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="7">They say evidence uncovered during a review of the case gave new hope.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="17">A family spokesman says the new report is no more credible than others.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-09-29 13:34:58" annotation_time="33.347668">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">London British girl Madeleine McCann, who vanished during a 2007 family vacation in Portugal, may still be alive, UK authorities said Wednesday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="2">London&amp;apost;s Metropolitan Police on Wednesday released a new image of the girl created in collaboration with the family that shows how Madeleine might look at age 9.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;As a result of evidence uncovered during the review, they now believe there is a possibility Madeleine is still alive and are appealing for anyone who is able to provide direct information as to her whereabouts to contact the team,&amp;quot; police said in a statement, without disclosing any details on the possibility of new leads.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="4">A spokesman for the girl&amp;apost;s parents said the latest report is no more credible than other tips that proved incorrect over the years.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>London British girl Madeleine McCann, who vanished during a 2007 family vacation in Portugal, may still be alive, UK authorities said Wednesday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Madeleine was a few days shy of her fourth birthday when she disappeared from her family&amp;apost;s holiday apartment in Praia da Luz as her parents dined in a nearby tapas restaurant with friends.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Despite a huge police investigation, massive coverage in the Portuguese and British media, and a public riveted on social media, she remains missing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>London&amp;apost;s Metropolitan Police on Wednesday released a new image of the girl created in collaboration with the family that shows how Madeleine might look at age 9.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Her ninth birthday is May 12.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>An investigative review formed in May last year has been going through details from the case.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;As a result of evidence uncovered during the review, they now believe there is a possibility Madeleine is still alive and are appealing for anyone who is able to provide direct information as to her whereabouts to contact the team,&amp;quot; police said in a statement, without disclosing any details on the possibility of new leads.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Investigators are combing through about 100,000 pages of information for more details, authorities said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>&amp;quot;The intention is to identify from that material investigative opportunities which we will then present to the Portuguese authorities who retain primacy for the investigation,&amp;quot; police said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;Officers have so far identified around 195 such opportunities within the historic material, and are also developing what they believe to be genuinely new material.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Detective Chief Inspector Andy Redwood, who is leading a team of more than 35 officers focused on the McCann case, said they &amp;quot;will continue to put Madeleine McCann at the heart of everything we do.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Redwood has visited Portugal seven times since the disappearance and has regular contact with the girl&amp;apost;s parents.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The investigation is split equally down two lines -- one assuming that Madeleine is dead, the other that she is alive, police said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Since her disappearance, her parents have appealed for help and said there&amp;apost;s a chance she may still be alive.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Frequent reports of sightings of her in various parts of the world have sparked frenzies.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Last year, a report of a girl bearing a resemblance to the child created a spike on social media.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>A spokesman for the girl&amp;apost;s parents said the latest report is no more credible than other tips that proved incorrect over the years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Portuguese investigators closed the case in July 2008.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
