<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2244" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/05/25/world/meast/syria-violence" date_published="2013-05-25 13:23:04" category="world" author="Amir Ahmed and Tom Watkins, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Hezbollah leader acknowledges fighters&amp;apost; presence in Syria</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="11">&amp;quot;We will make victory there!&amp;quot; Nasrallah says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">Opposition group says the dead include women and children.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="21">Government blames &amp;quot;terrorists&amp;quot; .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 16:27:10" annotation_time="98.20966" mapping_time_divergence="32.736553">
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">The Local Coordination Committees of Syria said the fatalities included women and children.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;Regarding this battle, like all the battles before it, our men are there and we will make victory there,&amp;quot; he said to cheers.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="3">&amp;quot;In today&amp;apost;s Syria, terrorism is killing tolerance; ignorance is killing logic; barbarity is overwhelming civility,&amp;quot; Syrian National Coalition Acting Chairman George Sabra told reporters.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Hezbollah forces are fighting on the side of the Syrian government in the strategic town of Qusayr against rebels, its leader said Saturday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;Syria is the backbone of the resistance (in the region) and its main supporter,&amp;quot; Hezbollah Secretary-General Hassan Nasrallah said in a speech broadcast live on Hezbollah-owned Al Manar Television.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;The resistance will never stand by while its backbone is exposed.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The pro-regime and pro-Iranian Shiite militia, based in Lebanon, is regarded as a terrorist group by the U.S. government and Sunni countries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Nasrallah&amp;apost;s 75-minute speech marked the first time he has acknowledged Hezbollah forces are fighting in the conflict.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>It came shortly after an opposition group said that shelling by Hezbollah fighters had killed at least 30 people in the strategically important western Syrian town of Qusayr.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The Local Coordination Committees of Syria said the fatalities included women and children.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Another opposition group, the Syrian Observatory for Human Rights, said that 27 of the dead were rebel fighters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The Free Syrian Army said it had killed 45 members of Hezbollah.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>In eastern Lebanon&amp;apost;s Bekaa Valley, thousands of Hezbollah supporters watched the speech on a big screen.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;Regarding this battle, like all the battles before it, our men are there and we will make victory there,&amp;quot; he said to cheers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Nashrallah accused the rebel forces of belonging to extremist religious movements, and said Hezbollah forces were acting to protect Lebanon.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;If the armed groups control Syria or specific Syrian provinces, especially those on the Lebanese border, then we consider them a great threat to Lebanon, the unity of the nation and all Lebanese, not just Hezbollah or Shiites in Lebanon.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Hezbollah fighters represent only a tiny minority of foreign fighters in Syria, Nasrallah said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;Tens of thousands of (rebel foreign) fighters did not bother the so-called Friends of Syria countries whose representatives met in Amman a couple of days ago,&amp;quot; he said, referring to the opposition umbrella group, which met in Jordan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;But the interference of a small group from Lebanese Hezbollah was considered a foreign intervention.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>We never interfered (in Syria) until a few months ago, so I am completely honest with you.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Nasrallah said the government in Damascus has always been willing to negotiate a peaceful resolution with rebels, but that the opposition -- hopeful that President Bashar al-Assad would be ousted -- has refused to do so.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>For its part, the government-run Syrian Arab News Agency said government forces were carrying out an operation against &amp;quot;armed terrorist groups&amp;quot; in the town, and had killed large numbers of them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>In Istanbul, Turkey, a Syrian opposition leader called for weapons, fighters and other aid.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;In today&amp;apost;s Syria, terrorism is killing tolerance; ignorance is killing logic; barbarity is overwhelming civility,&amp;quot; Syrian National Coalition Acting Chairman George Sabra told reporters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Referring to Hezbollah forces, he said, &amp;quot;You are heading in the wrong direction.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The resistance should not be in the north, in Qusayr or Daraya.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Due to sectarianism and blindly following the most tyrant regime in the world, some Lebanese are sent to Syria.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
