<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2579" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/07/10/world/asia/pakistan-tribal-area-operation/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-07-11 02:44:28" category="world" author="Sophia Saifi, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Pakistan&amp;apost;s ground offensive leaves ghost town</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="33">Miranshah remains empty after Pakistan military operation in North Waziristan.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">The region had become &amp;quot;a hub and safe haven&amp;quot; for militants, says army commander.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="8">North Waziristan pummeled by air strikes before ground troops moved in.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="33">New militant group claims several parts of Waziristan are under its control.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-14 15:29:23" annotation_time="51.523">
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2">Maj. General Zafar Khan, the commander of the Pakistan army&amp;apost;s 7th Division and the man in charge of the operation, told CNN that in the months leading up to campaign, the region had become &amp;quot;a hub and safe haven&amp;quot; for militants -- foreign and local -- in Pakistan.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="3">For almost three weeks, North Waziristan, a mountainous region bordering Afghanistan, was pummeled by a series of air strikes before ground troops moved in.</sentence>
      <sentence id="33" ids_highlights="1, 4">As we&amp;apost;re leaving North Waziristan, we find that a new militant group called Lashkar-e-Saif has declared its existence, claiming that the regions of &amp;quot;Spinwam, Dosalli, Razmak, Dattakheil, Shawal, Shava and other parts of Waziristan are under the full control of Taliban while security forces are only controlling Mirali Bazaar and Miranshah Bazaar.&amp;quot;</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>In a tea shop in Miranshah, a dusty town in northeastern Pakistan, an empty kettle hangs on a hook waiting to be used, while flies hover over baskets piled high with sweetmeats drying out in the July sunshine.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The surrounding streets are unusually quiet -- no children playing, no old men selling fruit, no whir of machinery from local workshops.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The buzz of life has been replaced by deathly silence in the largest town in Pakistan&amp;apost;s troubled North Waziristan.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Much of it now lies in ruin, its population nowhere to be seen.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>In a rare visit organized by Pakistan&amp;apost;s military, I was one of the few journalists transported into the region where the army has been waging a full-scale ground offensive against militants since mid-June.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The operation has been named Zarb-e-Azb after a famous sword of the prophet Muhammad.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Maj. General Zafar Khan, the commander of the Pakistan army&amp;apost;s 7th Division and the man in charge of the operation, told CNN that in the months leading up to campaign, the region had become &amp;quot;a hub and safe haven&amp;quot; for militants -- foreign and local -- in Pakistan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>For almost three weeks, North Waziristan, a mountainous region bordering Afghanistan, was pummeled by a series of air strikes before ground troops moved in.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>According to Khan, 80% of Miranshah and its surrounding areas have been cleared of militants.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Unfortunately, the local population appears to have been cleared too.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The head of Pakistan&amp;apost;s Inter Services Public Relations (ISPR), Maj. General Asim Bajwa, guides us through various compounds recovered in the town, which is now back under military control.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Leaving the 7th division base, we&amp;apost;re driven through a land of beige, past villages such as Machis, which has been hit by drone strikes and now lies abandoned.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Soldiers stand guard outside a suspected al Qaeda compound near the village.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>According to Bajwa, recovered pamphlets and papers indicate it was used by fighters affiliated with the terror network.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>We&amp;apost;re led down a series of steep steps inside the compound, and we find ourselves in a cold, labyrinth of tunnels, with only the dim light from our torches to guide us.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Bajwa tells us the tunnels &amp;quot;go on for at least two kilometers.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s a formidable operating base for militants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The drive to the town proper is surreal: vintage film music plays as the soldiers accompanying us discuss the Germany-Brazil World Cup match the previous night.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Outside our windows, we see troops searching blast-damaged and hollowed-out buildings.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>We&amp;apost;re told not to stray from the group since the area has not been completely cleared of improvised explosive devices (IEDs) -- the signature bomb of militants in the region.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>According to Maj. General Khan, at least 23 tons of IED-making equipment has been recovered from Miranshah.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>In the courtyard of a house in the battered remains of the town&amp;apost;s bazaar, guns and ammunition have been displayed in abstract designs, bullets placed in macabre symmetry.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Military officials tell us that this was the compound used by the East Turkestan Islamic Movement -- a murky terror group blamed for attacks in other countries in the wider region such as China.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>We&amp;apost;re shown the in-house dental clinic that they had established for themselves.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Alleged terrorists get toothaches, too, it would seem.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>A mosque provides the front for another underground hideout; a series of steps lead up to a bookshelf that opens up like a door into a secret passageway that we&amp;apost;re told was used as an escape route.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>It seems that no one was captured.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Maj. General Khan says leaders of other groups such as the Pakistan Taliban fled into Afghanistan before the ground operation began.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;They now manage things from across the border,&amp;quot; he says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Military sources say over 400 militants have been killed in this operation, but information about which groups they are affiliated with is vague.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Meanwhile, the number of internally displaced people from North Waziristan has now reached over 876,000, according to figures released by the FATA Disaster Management Authority, Pakistan&amp;apost;s federal government organization that administers the Federally Administered Tribal Areas.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Despite the access, details about the captured militants seem opaque.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>As we&amp;apost;re leaving North Waziristan, we find that a new militant group called Lashkar-e-Saif has declared its existence, claiming that the regions of &amp;quot;Spinwam, Dosalli, Razmak, Dattakheil, Shawal, Shava and other parts of Waziristan are under the full control of Taliban while security forces are only controlling Mirali Bazaar and Miranshah Bazaar.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>The military denies the existence of any such group.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;We will never let militants return to North Waziristan,&amp;quot; Khan tells the press in this valley in the foothills of the Hindu Kush Mountains.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Yet the very next day, Abidullah Abid, the spokesperson of the shadowy Lashkar-e-Saif claims they &amp;quot;will welcome security forces with bullets in Waziristan.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>This month of alleged gains by the Pakistani Army, it would seem is only the beginning for operation Zarb-e-Azb.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
