<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2255" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/08/18/world/asia/north-korea-catholic-church/index.html?hpt=ias_mid" date_published="2014-08-18 05:59:04" category="world" author="K.J. Kwon and Paula Hancocks, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Hopes for Christianity in North Korea</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="7">North Korea is accused of widespread religious persecution.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="17">Father John Park has been making regular visits to a church in the North.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="18">But many commentators say followers of the North&amp;apost;s state-controlled church are fake.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-14 12:20:47" annotation_time="14.539">
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="1">North Korea is accused of widespread religious persecution and the United States claims its few state-run churches exist simply to give the appearance of religious freedom.</sentence>
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="2">Father Park has been holding mass annually at a church in Pyongyang for North Korean Catholic followers despite criticism that they may be &amp;quot;fake&amp;quot; believers.</sentence>
      <sentence id="18" ids_highlights="3">Over the course of 14 years traveling to the North, he said he&amp;apost;s interacted with many of the church&amp;apost;s congregation and believes they&amp;apost;re genuine.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Seoul They were once referred to as the &amp;quot;Vatican&amp;apost;s spies.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>But one Christian hopes attitudes towards missionaries are changing in North Korea.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Father John Park has been a welcome and regular guest at Pyongyang&amp;apost;s only recognized Catholic Church since 2000.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;When we first arrived at Changchung Church, North Korean followers came out ... then immediately rushed to a nun who traveled with me and jumped up and down bursting into tears,&amp;quot; said Father Park, a South Korean priest with Missionaries of the Sacred Heart.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;These people haven&amp;apost;t seen a nun in 50 years.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>That&amp;apost;s when I realized that they are indeed followers.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>North Korea is accused of widespread religious persecution and the United States claims its few state-run churches exist simply to give the appearance of religious freedom.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;apost;Silent church&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Its Catholic Church is known as the &amp;quot;silent church.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>It has no ties with the Vatican and there is not one single residing priest in the country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>There are strict controls over what is permitted -- many religious processes such as confession are out of the question.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>A confidential one-on-one conversation between a South Korean -- even if that person is a priest -- and a North Korean is impossible and both could be accused of espionage.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>In the 1970s, Pyongyang proudly insisted that the country was &amp;quot;free from religious superstitions,&amp;quot; according to South Korea&amp;apost;s Unification Ministry.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The reclusive regime is officially atheist.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Then for no apparent reason, the authorities in the North created a small number of churches and temples in the late 1980s, all of them under very strict government control.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>And Changchung Catholic Church was one of them.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Father Park has been holding mass annually at a church in Pyongyang for North Korean Catholic followers despite criticism that they may be &amp;quot;fake&amp;quot; believers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Over the course of 14 years traveling to the North, he said he&amp;apost;s interacted with many of the church&amp;apost;s congregation and believes they&amp;apost;re genuine.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>He recalled one man, known only as &amp;quot;Mr. Cha,&amp;quot; who died four years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>&amp;quot;Mr. Cha was a follower before the Korean War and his dream since young was to become a priest.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>He lived alone waiting for a chance to either go to China or Rome to become a priest.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>In 1945, North Korea had an estimated 50,000 Catholics, according to the South Korean Catholic Bishops Conference of Korea (CBCK).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Around 20,000 are believed to have defected to China before Japan&amp;apost;s long occupation of the Korean peninsula was ended at the end of World War II.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>There was also around 300 foreign and local clergy in the North during the time, most of whom went missing, were executed or died in prison, according to the CBCK.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Aging church.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Many followers at Changchung Church were baptized before the Korean War (1950-53), and many have died, Father Park said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>He believes the congregation has dropped from about 150 to 100 since 2000.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;A lot of people are ailing and if followers from the older generation die, things could get difficult.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>There may not be too many followers in North Korea but we should open-mindedly help and support them,&amp;quot; Father Park said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>&amp;quot;Like a mindset of a shepherd, we should treat them with warm heart,&amp;quot; he added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>North Korea&amp;apost;s state-run Korean Catholic Association claims it has about 3,000 &amp;quot;registered Catholics,&amp;quot; while the United Nations puts the number at 800.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Nevertheless, members of religious groups, as well as the groups themselves, are often criticized as being fake.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;The North Korean government is tolerant of a small controlled religious presence within the country or is willing to fake such presence,&amp;quot; said Andrei Lankov, an associate professor in social sciences at Kookmin University in South Korea.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>&amp;quot;Even if some members are true believers, they are selected by the government.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>The police authorities, the secret police, is checking your background,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>North Korea&amp;apost;s constitution does allow its people to practice religion.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>However, in the same constitution, it also says it won&amp;apost;t allow it to be &amp;quot;used for drawing in foreign forces or for harming the State or social order.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Kenneth Bae, an American citizen who was sentenced to 15 years of hard labor in North Korea, was accused of bringing down the government through religious activities.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>And he is not the only missionary to be detained in the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;From their (North Korea&amp;apost;s) point of view, it is a very real threat.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Right now, Christianity seems to be their most dangerous ideological challenge to the existing regime,&amp;quot; said Lankov.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
