<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2775" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/10/26/world/asia/afghanistan-unrest/index.html" date_published="2012-10-26 07:43:23" category="world" author="Masoud Popalzai and Chelsea J. Carter, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Suicide bomber at Muslim mosque shatters holiday that celebrates peace</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">NEW: &amp;quot;I saw dozens of people lying on the ground covered in blood,&amp;quot; a witness says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="7">At least 40 people have been killed in the suicide blast, a spokesman says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="8">The death toll is likely to climb given the size and timing of the blast, he says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="7">The explosion occurred as worshipers were leaving morning prayers .</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-06 22:49:42" annotation_time="18.283">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;I saw dozens of people lying on the ground covered in blood,&amp;quot; Zain-ul-Obdin said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="7" ids_highlights="2, 4">At least 40 people were killed and more than 50 wounded in the attack that came as worshipers were leaving Friday morning prayers marking the beginning of Eid al-Adha, Lal Mohammad Ahmadzai, a spokesman for the northern Afghanistan police chief, told CNN.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="3">The death toll was likely to rise given the size and timing of the explosion, said Ministry of Interior spokesman Sediq Seddiqi.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Kabul, Afghanistan It was supposed to be a day of happiness, a moment to mark the start of a Muslim holiday that celebrates peace as the faithful observe the height of the Hajj, the annual pilgrimage to Mecca.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>It was that kind of day that Zain-ul-Obdin said was needed by the people in Afghanistan&amp;apost;s Faryab province, where suicide bombings and insurgent attacks have taken their toll on the population.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The people did not get that day.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>It was erased by a suicide bomber who left bodies broken and bloodied outside Eid Gah Mosque in the provincial city of Maimana.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;I saw dozens of people lying on the ground covered in blood,&amp;quot; Zain-ul-Obdin said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Among them were the bodies of children, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>At least 40 people were killed and more than 50 wounded in the attack that came as worshipers were leaving Friday morning prayers marking the beginning of Eid al-Adha, Lal Mohammad Ahmadzai, a spokesman for the northern Afghanistan police chief, told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>The death toll was likely to rise given the size and timing of the explosion, said Ministry of Interior spokesman Sediq Seddiqi.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>There was no immediate claim of responsibility, but Seddiqi laid the blame for the attack squarely at the feet of Taliban leader Mullah Omar.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;Their target and their main objective is to attack and kill as many people as possible,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Eid al-Adha, also known as Feast of Sacrifice, is considered a joyous holiday for Muslims.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>It commemorates when God appeared to Abraham -- known as Ibrahim to Muslims -- in a dream and asked him to sacrifice his son as an act of obedience.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The mosque had been so packed that Zain-ul-Obdin and his neighbors were forced to pray just beyond the front doors of the mosque.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>It was this misfortune at being unable to get into the mosque that may have saved his life.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>When the sermon was over, he was among the first to leave the grounds, he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>At the same time, the bomber -- said to be dressed in a police uniform -- waded into the crowd leaving the mosque and detonated his explosives.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Coming at the start of the Eid holiday, the attack drew swift condemnation from neighboring Pakistan as well as the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;This violence undertaken at a place of worship, and during Eid, once again shows the insurgency&amp;apost;s callous hypocrisy and disregard for religion and faith,&amp;quot; said Marine Gen. John Allen, commander of the International Security Assistance Force.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Pakistan&amp;apost;s Foreign Ministry vowed to stand by Afghanistan in the fight on terrorism.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The U.S. Embassy in Kabul said the attack demonstrated &amp;quot;the insurgency&amp;apost;s lack of respect for religion, faith and its disregard for the safety and security of the Afghan people.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
