<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2020" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/12/10/world/africa/i-have-29-children-ethiopia/index.html" date_published="2013-12-10 11:18:24" category="world" author="Linda Roth, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>&amp;apost;I have 29 children&amp;apost;: The &amp;apost;mothers&amp;apost; to Ethiopia&amp;apost;s most vulnerable kids</title>
  <keywords>ethiopia,Yekokeb Berhan</keywords>
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">Ethiopian group is helping highly vulnerable children.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="10, 24">Volunteers care for 25 disadvantaged children, many of whom are HIV positive.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="14">They give their homes, incomes, time, to help the kids.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-01 15:51:45" annotation_time="61.535004" mapping_time_divergence="41.023335">
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">The woman who needs the wheelchairs is one of the 20,000 volunteers for Yekokeb Berhan, a USAID-funded program trying to help half a million highly vulnerable children.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="2">Each volunteer will take in 25 of those kids as her own.</sentence>
      <sentence id="14" ids_highlights="3">More often than not, assistance is needed in multiple areas -- and that means these volunteers have had to become master networkers -- calling on friends, family, neighbors, local businessmen and faith leaders to get the kids what they need.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="2">Everyone except the youngest toddler is HIV positive.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Addis Ababa, Ethiopia On the outskirts of Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, in the dusty crowded neighborhood of Akaki, I&amp;apost;ve just been treated to a traditional Ethiopian coffee ceremony.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The beans are roasted and the coffee boiled in front of you then served piping hot with a heaping spoonful of sugar and a side of freshly popped corn.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>As I step out onto the dirt road to leave, one of my hosts wants to ask a question: do I know anyone who can donate some wheelchairs, so adults don&amp;apost;t&amp;apost; have to carry disabled children on their backs to school anymore?</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>I wish I did.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The woman who needs the wheelchairs is one of the 20,000 volunteers for Yekokeb Berhan, a USAID-funded program trying to help half a million highly vulnerable children.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The name means &amp;quot;Light from the Stars&amp;quot; in Amharic, and is meant to reflect the resiliency of children.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>After spending a week working with the volunteers here, I have no doubt those wheelchairs are going to find their way, due to the resiliency of the adults.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Yekokeb Berhan volunteers are chosen by community committees and given training in health, parenting, budgeting and life skills.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Then they go out into communities, to find and identify the most vulnerable children.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Each volunteer will take in 25 of those kids as her own.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;I have 29 children&amp;quot; says Sintayehu Kenna, a mother of four (plus 25), &amp;quot;I can&amp;apost;t separate them from my own.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>I love them. &amp;quot;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The program&amp;apost;s philosophy is that the way to help children is to help their families.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>More often than not, assistance is needed in multiple areas -- and that means these volunteers have had to become master networkers -- calling on friends, family, neighbors, local businessmen and faith leaders to get the kids what they need.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Leyela Ayele, from the Kolfe neighborhood, tells me about a family of eight in which the father was sick and the mother was the breadwinner until she had a heart attack and died.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Ayele volunteered to foster the six kids.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>One of the boys was malnourished and Ayele went to every health center in the area, telling doctors about him, until she found one to admit and treat him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>She visited the local bakery and convinced the owner to provide breakfasts for another child.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>And she linked up the eldest with a government association that gave a scholarship to study hairdressing.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Volunteers receive a stipend of about $10 a month to cover phone and transportation costs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>They are expected to give about 15-20 hours a week, but I found they all are giving much, much more.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Alemitu Yemes has 31 kids, four of her own, two foster kids plus her 25 kids from the program.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>She&amp;apost;s given a small room in her compound, rent free, to a family of five.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Everyone except the youngest toddler is HIV positive.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Yemes is working to keep the kids in school and making sure the family keeps to their anti-viral medical regime.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>&amp;quot;We don&amp;apost;t want them to be dependent,&amp;quot; she says, &amp;quot;I&amp;apost;m telling them to be self-reliant and we are all working towards that together.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Yekokeb Berhan is also working in conjunction with local government and 40 civil society organizations to recruit, train and supervise the volunteers all over the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>In Ethiopia, formal education doesn&amp;apost;t begin until age seven.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>So, the Hiwot Integrated Development Association (HIDA) struck a deal with the local government.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>HIDA would renovate and supply an early childhood development center if the government would pay the teachers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>That partnership resulted in new brightly colored classroom expanded to serve 128 children, many of them considered highly vulnerable.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Amharic and English are taught, and on the day I visited, I was treated to a version of the nursery rhyme Mary Had a Little Lamb.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>But the backbone of the Yekokeb Berhan program is the individual volunteers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>A majority of the women I met were single mothers with big families of their own.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Some work as bread makers and vegetable sellers, but about half of those I spoke with seemed to have no other support.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>But yet everyone I met said it was their moral obligation to help others.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>&amp;quot;Even after they turn 18 years we will still help them, by linking them up with the woreda (local government) and getting them skill training and jobs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>We will empower our graduated children,&amp;quot; says Gete Tefera, who has two children of her own, plus her 25 fosters.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>On my last day in Addis, I met with a group of women entrepreneurs in a half-built concrete mid-rise with broken windows, which will one day be a youth center.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>Through Yekokeb Berhan&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;Community Self-Help Savings Group&amp;quot; each is getting help with a new venture and for the first time in their lives, saving money.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>The women enthusiastically describe their plans: one is switching from selling bananas to housewares, because the latter doesn&amp;apost;t spoil; another is expanding her business from selling used clothes to new.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>But the profits will not be all theirs.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>As part of the program, two birr a week, about 10 cents, has got to go into a kitty to help out those in need.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Before I leave, one woman says there are a lot of kids in the neighborhood unable to go to school because of poor eyesight.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>She wants to know if I know anyone who can get them the glasses they need.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>I don&amp;apost;t.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>But I&amp;apost;m going to look into it.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
