<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2375" link="http://www.cnn.com/2012/05/30/world/africa/kenya-somalia/index.html" date_published="2012-05-30 15:46:06" category="world" author="David McKenzie, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Kenyan forces take Somali town from militants</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Kenyan troops now control Afmadow, an official says.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">The town is considered a key step in the campaign against Al-Shabaab.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="11">African Union troops last week launched an offensive against the militants.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-14 17:35:10" annotation_time="22.129002">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;We now control Afmadow with our troops,&amp;quot; Maj. Emmanuel Chirchir told CNN.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">Military analysts believe that Afmadow is a key step in Kenya&amp;apost;s campaign against Al-Shabaab, the Islamic militant group they have been fighting since they entered Somalia in October of last year.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="3">Last week, the African Union Mission in Somalia (AMISOM) said it, along with Somali troops, had launched an offensive against militants in the Afgoye corridor, a densely-populated enclave near the volatile Somali capital of Mogadishu.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Nairobi, Kenya Kenyan soldiers, as part of African Union forces in Somalia, captured the key Al-Shabaab-controlled town of Afmadow on Wednesday, according to a Kenyan Defence Force spokesman.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;We now control Afmadow with our troops,&amp;quot; Maj. Emmanuel Chirchir told CNN.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The operation started early Wednesday, he said, with KDF forces capturing the town of Hayo.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Six Al-Shabaab militants were killed in that operation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;(The troops) then moved straight onto Afmadow,&amp;quot; said Chirchir.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Military analysts believe that Afmadow is a key step in Kenya&amp;apost;s campaign against Al-Shabaab, the Islamic militant group they have been fighting since they entered Somalia in October of last year.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>The town would serve as a staging point for any move on Kismayo, Al-Shabaab&amp;apost;s stronghold in southern Somalia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;Afmadow is an important administrative town that was supplying Al-Shabaab fighters with money.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>It was their nerve center,&amp;quot; said Chirchir.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>&amp;quot;After the fall of Amfadow there is only Kismayo.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Last week, the African Union Mission in Somalia (AMISOM) said it, along with Somali troops, had launched an offensive against militants in the Afgoye corridor, a densely-populated enclave near the volatile Somali capital of Mogadishu.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The corridor, which has been controlled by the al Qaeda-backed Al-Shabaab, is populated with one of the largest populations of internally displaced people.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The African Union said the militants have blocked many aid agencies from operating in the area.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The campaign was &amp;quot;going well,&amp;quot; AMISOM spokesman, Lt. Col. Paddy Nkunda said last week.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;Al-Shabaab tried to fight, but they know they are about to lose Afgoye and our soldiers broke through their early resistance.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Al-Shabaab announced in February that it was tightening its ties to al Qaeda.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>It has long been considered a terrorist movement by the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Al-Shabaab has waged an insurgency against Somalia&amp;apost;s feeble Transitional Federal Government since 2007, but has suffered recent setbacks in its heartland in southern Somalia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>AMISOM and government forces drove Al-Shabaab fighters from the center of Mogadishu last year, while Kenyan troops crossed into southern Somalia in October to hit back for a rash of kidnappings it blamed on the group.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Despite their efforts, however, Al-Shabaab has continued to launch terror attacks in the capital.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>In a second operation, 14 Al-Shabaab militants were killed and 10 others injured Tuesday when a Kenyan Defense Forces naval ship engaged with militants at an Al-Shabaab seaport watch station, the KDF said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;The incident occurred when a KDF naval ship was conducting routine sea patrol in the vicinity of (the) port of Kismayu,&amp;quot; according to a KDF statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Two on-shore structures were destroyed, officials said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Elsewhere, in Fafadun, 20 Al-Shabaab militants surrendered to KDF, officials said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
