<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2898" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/04/05/world/africa/car-ban/?hpt=bosread" date_published="2014-04-05 23:34:36" category="world" author="Susanna Capelouto, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>U.N. chief warns against repeat of Rwanda in Central African Republic</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">UN Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon tells Central African Republic not to repeat Rwandan genocide.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">Christian and Muslim militias have been battling for control in the nation.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="12">Chad pulls 850 troops from African-led peacekeeping force after allegation of attack by its soldiers.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="21">Preparations for a U.N. peacekeeping force are under way, but it would need Security Council approval.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-10 21:11:05" annotation_time="16.341333">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">U.N. Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon on Saturday warned officials in the embattled Central African Republic not to repeat the mistakes that led to the Rwanda genocide 20 years ago.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">They have since been forced out of power, but Christian and Muslim militias continue to battle for control.</sentence>
      <sentence id="12" ids_highlights="3">Just before the U.N. published its preliminary findings of the attack, Chad decided to withdraw its 850 troops from the peacekeeping force, a move the chairwoman of the African Union said is understandable.</sentence>
      <sentence id="21" ids_highlights="4">He said there are preparations for a U.N. presence in the Central African Republic, but peacekeepers &amp;quot;will not arrive right away,&amp;quot; as their deployment depends on decisions from the Security Council.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>U.N. Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon on Saturday warned officials in the embattled Central African Republic not to repeat the mistakes that led to the Rwanda genocide 20 years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>In a speech to the country&amp;apost;s National Transitional Council in the capital city, Bangui, the leader of the international body also urged the world not to &amp;quot;look away&amp;quot; from the nation&amp;apost;s turmoil.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;Some say this is a forgotten crisis,&amp;quot; Ban said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;I am here to help make sure the world does not forget.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The Central African Republic, a former French colony, plunged into chaos last year after a coalition of mostly Muslim rebels ousted President Francois Bozize.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>They have since been forced out of power, but Christian and Muslim militias continue to battle for control.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>Thousands have died during the fighting and 2.2 million people, about half the country&amp;apost;s population, are in need of humanitarian aid, according to the U.N.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>More than 650,000 people are still internally displaced, and nearly 300,000 have fled to neighboring countries in search of refuge.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The latest setback comes in the form of charges by the U.N.&amp;apost;s human rights office that soldiers from neighboring Chad attacked civilians in a Bangui market last month.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>According to a preliminary report from the U.N. High Commissioner for Human Rights, the soldiers killed nearly 30 civilians and injured 300 more on March 29.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Investigators said the Chadian soldiers were not part of the African-led peacekeeping force, which is meant to stabilize the Central African Republic, but a group that appeared to have returned to Chad after the attack.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Just before the U.N. published its preliminary findings of the attack, Chad decided to withdraw its 850 troops from the peacekeeping force, a move the chairwoman of the African Union said is understandable.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Dr. Nkosazana Dlamini-Zuma said Chad had been the target of repeated attacks by Christian militia elements and unfounded allegations by a number of actors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;The stigmatization of the Chadian contingent has contributed to the establishment of a climate of insecurity and hostility for which the nationals of that country had paid a heavy price,&amp;quot; Dlamini-Zuma said in a statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>In his speech Saturday, Ban stressed that the international community has an obligation to act, warning that the Central African Republic is &amp;quot;at risk of partition.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;The international community failed the people of Rwanda 20 years ago,&amp;quot; Ban said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;And we are at risk of not doing enough for the people of the C.A.R. today.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>In 1994, Hutu extremists in Rwanda targeted ethnic Tutsis and moderate Hutus in a three-month killing spree that left an estimated 800,000 people dead.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>After his visit to the Central African Republic, the U.N. Secretary-General travels to Rwanda for the ceremonies observing the 20th anniversary of the genocide there.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Ban thanked the African Union-led peacekeeping force, as well as the French forces, for their efforts to maintain order in the country.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>He said there are preparations for a U.N. presence in the Central African Republic, but peacekeepers &amp;quot;will not arrive right away,&amp;quot; as their deployment depends on decisions from the Security Council.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
