<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2386" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/07/05/world/europe/vatican-pope-sainthood/index.html" date_published="2013-07-05 11:16:48" category="world" author="Hada Messia, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Late Pope John Paul II to get sainthood, Vatican says</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="1">Pope John Paul II will be declared a saint.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">Pope John XXIII also achieved sainthood.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="8">John Paul II was the third-longest serving pope in history.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-14 17:35:28" annotation_time="15.268">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="1">Rome The Roman Catholic Church will declare the late Pope John Paul II a saint, the Vatican announced Friday.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2">Pope John XXIII, who convened the Vatican II council in the 1960s, will also be declared a saint, the Vatican said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="8" ids_highlights="3">Pope John Paul II, the third-longest serving pope in history, died in April 2005 at the age of 84.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Rome The Roman Catholic Church will declare the late Pope John Paul II a saint, the Vatican announced Friday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Pope Francis signed the decree Friday morning, the Vatican said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>John Paul was pope from 1978 until his death in 2005, and was in a way the first rock star pontiff, drawing vast crowds as he crisscrossed the globe.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>At his funeral, thousands of pilgrims gathered in St. Peter&amp;apost;s Square and chanted &amp;quot;Santo subito&amp;quot; -- Sainthood now!</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>The Polish-born pope was fast-tracked to beatification and became &amp;quot;the blessed&amp;quot; John Paul II barely six years after his death, the fastest beatification in centuries.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Pope John XXIII, who convened the Vatican II council in the 1960s, will also be declared a saint, the Vatican said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>No date has been announced for the canonization ceremony.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Pope John Paul II, the third-longest serving pope in history, died in April 2005 at the age of 84.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>He had suffered from Parkinson&amp;apost;s disease, arthritis and other ailments for several years before his death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>During his tenure, he became the most widely traveled pope in history and canonized more saints than any other pope.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>His papacy included a lot of firsts.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>He was the first modern pope to visit a synagogue and the first pope to visit Cuba.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>There are essentially three steps to becoming a Catholic saint after death.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>First, the title &amp;quot;venerable&amp;quot; is formally given by the pope to someone judged to have exhibited &amp;quot;heroic virtues.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Second, a miracle must be attributed to the deceased person&amp;apost;s intervention, allowing beatification.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>Canonization -- or sainthood -- requires a second attributed miracle.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>In 2010, Pope Emeritus Benedict XVI approved John Paul&amp;apost;s first reported miracle: a French nun supposedly cured of Parkinson&amp;apost;s disease.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>Sister Marie-Simon-Pierre, a nun whose order prayed to the pope after he died, said she was cured of the disease, an ailment that also afflicted John Paul.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The second miracle reportedly occurred in Costa Rica, where a woman said she recovered from a severe brain injury thanks to the intervention of John Paul, sources told CNN Vatican analyst John Allen.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Patrick Kelly, executive director of the Blessed John Paul II Shrine in Washington, explained the church&amp;apost;s process for investigating reported miracles.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;A team of doctors first examine the miracle.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>Secondly, the team of theologians look at the miracles, and then they discuss amongst themselves the legitimacy and all the facts surrounding the miracles,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Despite being so beloved, John Paul didn&amp;apost;t live up to expectations at a crucial moment in the church&amp;apost;s history, as revelations of sexual abuse scandals involving thousands Catholic priests erupted across the world in the early 2000s, critics say.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In the United States alone, the scandal involved more than 16,400 victims or alleged victims and cost the church $2.6 billion in settlements, therapy bills, lawyers&amp;apost; fees and care for priests removed from ministry, according to the U.S. Conference of Catholic Bishops.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>John XXIII was famed for calling the Second Vatican Council in 1962, which ushered in great changes in the Roman Catholic Church&amp;apost;s relationship with the modern world.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>He was pope from 1958 to 1963, and was beatified by Pope John Paul II in 2000.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
