<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2940" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/02/26/world/europe/vatican-benedict-title/index.html" date_published="2013-02-26 12:13:51" category="world" author="Hada Messia and Laura Smith-Spark, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>Vatican reveals Pope Benedict&amp;apost;s new title</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="2">Benedict XVI will keep his name and still be addressed as &amp;quot;his holiness&amp;quot; after he resigns.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="24, 23">He will give up the red mantle and shoes of the pope and dress in a simple white robe.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="11">As he leaves office at 8 p.m. Thursday, the Swiss Guards will leave Castel Gandolfo.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="15">Cardinals are already gathering in Rome ahead of their meeting to choose the pope&amp;apost;s successor.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-19 10:56:45" annotation_time="33.788" mapping_time_divergence="8.447">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="1">The pontiff will keep the name Benedict XVI and still be addressed as &amp;quot;his holiness&amp;quot; once he retires, Vatican spokesman Federico Lombardi told reporters at the Vatican.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="3">At the moment that Benedict&amp;apost;s papacy ends, at 8 p.m. local time, the Swiss Guards -- the soldiers who for more than five centuries have protected the pope and his residence -- will leave the gates of Castel Gandolfo.</sentence>
      <sentence id="15" ids_highlights="4">Meanwhile, the cardinals who must elect the new pope are already gathering in Rome, Lombardi said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="23" ids_highlights="2">He will wear a simple white cassock, without the customary red mantle of the pontiff.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="2">He will also no longer wear red shoes, probably adopting instead the brown shoes that he received as a gift in Leon, Mexico, during a trip last year.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Rome With only two full days left of Pope Benedict XVI&amp;apost;s papacy, more details emerged Tuesday of what the future holds both for the retiring pontiff and the cardinals who will choose his successor.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>The pontiff will keep the name Benedict XVI and still be addressed as &amp;quot;his holiness&amp;quot; once he retires, Vatican spokesman Federico Lombardi told reporters at the Vatican.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>He will also be known as pope emeritus, emeritus pope or Roman pontifex emeritus.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The guidance clears up questions about how Benedict -- the first pope to resign in almost 600 years -- should be addressed as he moves into a life of seclusion and prayer after his Thursday resignation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Benedict will hold his final general audience Wednesday, for which 50,000 tickets have been given out, Lombardi said, though many more people than that could show up.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>Benedict will arrive in his Popemobile, which will drive around St. Peter&amp;apost;s Square among the faithful before the pope gives the address.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>He won&amp;apost;t give the usual brief personal greetings to people afterward but will meet delegations of heads of state in Vatican City later.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Benedict will meet with the cardinals who are already in Rome on Thursday morning.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The 85-year-old will then be flown by helicopter to Castel Gandolfo, the pope&amp;apost;s summer residence near Rome, in the afternoon.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The church bell will toll and he will make his very last public appearance, greeting crowds from a balcony there.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>At the moment that Benedict&amp;apost;s papacy ends, at 8 p.m. local time, the Swiss Guards -- the soldiers who for more than five centuries have protected the pope and his residence -- will leave the gates of Castel Gandolfo.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>He will from that point have Vatican police protection instead.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Benedict will stay there until work to restore a monastery within the Vatican grounds is completed later in the spring.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Cardinals gather.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Meanwhile, the cardinals who must elect the new pope are already gathering in Rome, Lombardi said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>The dean cardinal will on March 1 summon the cardinals to a general congregation, Lombardi said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>That could come as soon as March 4, although the date is not yet fixed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The cardinals will then decide exactly when to hold the conclave, during which they vote for the new pontiff.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Special prayers will be said during the &amp;quot;sede vacante,&amp;quot; or empty seat, period, seeking guidance for the election of the new pope.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The cardinals will lead the prayers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>After his resignation, Benedict -- who cited the frailty of age as the reason he resigned -- will no longer use the Fisherman&amp;apost;s Ring, the symbol of the pope, Lombardi said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>The ring will be destroyed, along with Benedict&amp;apost;s papal seal, after his departure from office.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>He will wear a simple white cassock, without the customary red mantle of the pontiff.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>He will also no longer wear red shoes, probably adopting instead the brown shoes that he received as a gift in Leon, Mexico, during a trip last year.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>Swirling rumors.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Benedict shocked the Roman Catholic world when he announced his resignation two weeks ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>His final week in office has been clouded by scandal, with allegations swirling in the Italian media that gay clergy may have made themselves vulnerable to blackmail by male prostitutes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>The Vatican vehemently denied the allegations Saturday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Vatican Secretary of State Tarcisio Bertone said it was &amp;quot;deplorable&amp;quot; that as the time for the Roman Catholic cardinals to elect a new pope approaches, a rash of &amp;quot;often unverified, unverifiable or completely false news stories&amp;quot; has appeared.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Benedict also moved up the resignation Monday of a Scottish archbishop linked over the weekend by a British newspaper to inappropriate relationships with priests.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Cardinal Keith O&amp;apost;Brien, the archbishop of Scotland, told the pope in November that he would resign effective on his 75th birthday, on March 17.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>But Benedict decided to make the resignation effective immediately in light of the pope&amp;apost;s imminent resignation, the Scottish Catholic Media Office said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>The announcement came a day after a report by the British Sunday newspaper The Observer that three priests and one former priest leveled allegations against O&amp;apost;Brien that date back 30 years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Speaking in London on Tuesday, one of Britain&amp;apost;s most senior Roman Catholics, the former Archbishop of Westminster, Cardinal Cormac Murphy-O&amp;apost;Connor, described the circumstances of O&amp;apost;Brien&amp;apost;s resignation as &amp;quot;very sad.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Murphy-O&amp;apost;Connor said that it was O&amp;apost;Brien&amp;apost;s decision to step down and that he had not been forced or asked to do so.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>He described O&amp;apost;Brien as a &amp;quot;very honest man.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>An apostolic administrator, most likely a senior bishop, will examine the allegations against O&amp;apost;Brien, Murphy-O&amp;apost;Connor said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>He also said he was in no doubt that there needs to be reform within the Roman Catholic Church and that the issues being raised now need to be addressed &amp;quot;at the highest level.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
