<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2604" link="http://www.cnn.com/2013/01/13/world/asia/india-new-gang-rape/index.html" date_published="2013-01-13 10:06:46" category="world" author="Faith Karimi and Harmeet Shah Singh, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Police: 7 men gang rape bus passenger in India</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="4">The bus speeds past the woman&amp;apost;s stop.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="6">Police: The bus driver and his helper take the woman somewhere.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">Five other men allegedly join in to assault the woman through the night.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-03 07:15:35" annotation_time="37.129665">
      <sentence id="4" ids_highlights="1">The bus sped past her stop, police said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="2, 3">The bus driver and his helper then took the married 29-year-old woman to an undisclosed address where five others joined the two men and raped her throughout the night, police said.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>In an incident eerily similar to a sexual assault that sent shock waves worldwide, Indian police say a woman was gang-raped over the weekend by seven men after she boarded a bus at night.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Police have arrested all seven suspects, including the bus driver, after the alleged Friday night attack in the Gurdaspur district of Punjab state.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Just like a gang rape in New Delhi that sparked international outrage last month, the new attack occurred after the woman got on a bus.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>The bus sped past her stop, police said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>By that time, the woman was the only passenger.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The bus driver and his helper then took the married 29-year-old woman to an undisclosed address where five others joined the two men and raped her throughout the night, police said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;They threatened me with a sharp edged weapon and did wrong things with me,&amp;quot; the victim told CNN&amp;apost;s sister station, CNN-IBN.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>&amp;quot;They kept me confined all through the night and forced me to do what they want.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>The next day, the suspects dropped her off at her village, where she informed her family and alerted police, according to authorities.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>The alleged attack bears a similarity to a December 16 gang rape where attackers assaulted a woman after she boarded a bus.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>The men also brutally beat her and her male companion, robbed them of their belongings and later dumped them by the side of a road.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Both New Delhi and Gurdaspur are in northern India.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The latest incident in Gurdaspur has not spurred an outbreak of protests in the country and there was no immediate evidence of visible injuries to the woman, contrasting with the violent manner in which last month&amp;apost;s New Delhi victim was attacked.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>The Delhi incident triggered rallies nationwide and an uproar over the treatment of women.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>The badly beaten 23-year-old woman was flown to Singapore for treatment after the attack.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>She died about two weeks later while undergoing treatment.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>Five men were charged with murder, rape and kidnapping, and face the death penalty if convicted.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>A juvenile court is determining the age of a sixth suspect, who claims to be 17 and not old enough to be tried as an adult.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>At the time, the government pledged stronger laws against sexual assaults.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The number of reported rapes in India -- a country where a cultural stigma keeps many victims from reporting the crime -- has increased drastically, from 2,487 in 1971 to 24,206 in 2011, according to official figures.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>Most women in India have stories of sexual harassment and abuse on public transportation or on the streets, said Seema Sirohi, of the Indian Council on Global Relations.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>