<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2219" link="http://www.cnn.com/2011/10/18/world/meast/israel-shalit-profile" date_published="2011-10-18 07:18:45" category="world" author="Richard Allen Greene, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Gilad Shalit: Israeli captive freed at last</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="5">NEW: Shimon Peres: &amp;quot;Our eyes are wet and our hearts are proud&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="1">Palestinians abducted Israeli soldier Shalit in 2006 when he was 19.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="19">Shalit&amp;apost;s parents camped out in front of the Israeli prime minister&amp;apost;s office for more than a year.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="40">Israel inked a deal to get him back in exchange for more than 1,000 Palestinian prisoners.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-12-14 15:23:15" annotation_time="47.554">
      <sentence id="1" ids_highlights="2">Gilad Shalit was a 19-year-old enlisted man guarding an Israeli army post when Palestinian militants attacked his tank, killed the two men he was serving with and took him prisoner more than five years ago.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;Our eyes are wet and our hearts are proud,&amp;quot; Israeli President Shimon Peres declared.</sentence>
      <sentence id="19" ids_highlights="3">Shalit&amp;apost;s parents led a 12-day march from their home in northern Israel to Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu&amp;apost;s office in Jerusalem in June 2010 and camped out in a tent there until last week.</sentence>
      <sentence id="40" ids_highlights="4">The Israeli public overwhelmingly supports the agreement to release more than 1,000 prisoners in exchange for Shalit, according to a poll published in the Israeli daily Yedioth Ahronoth the day before his handover by Hamas to Egyptian security.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Gilad Shalit was a 19-year-old enlisted man guarding an Israeli army post when Palestinian militants attacked his tank, killed the two men he was serving with and took him prisoner more than five years ago.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Israelis are overjoyed that he went free on Tuesday in exchange for more than 1,000 Palestinian prisoners.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have experienced the rebirth of a son,&amp;quot; Shalit&amp;apost;s father said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>It has been &amp;quot;an exhausting and long struggle.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>&amp;quot;Our eyes are wet and our hearts are proud,&amp;quot; Israeli President Shimon Peres declared.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have become ourselves again.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;He really is the child of us all,&amp;quot; said Daniel Taub, Israel&amp;apost;s ambassador to the United Kingdom, noting that almost all Israelis do military service.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Shalit told Egypt&amp;apost;s state-owned Nile TV after his release Tuesday that it was &amp;quot;exciting&amp;quot; to meet many of the people who &amp;quot;have worked very hard in order to release me.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>I would like to thank them for all this effort.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>He said he received the news of a possible deal to free him a week ago, &amp;quot;but I felt it for the last month.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>... I was afraid that the negotiations could go wrong.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>Much of Israel came to a halt in a nationwide demonstration earlier this year in response to a Facebook campaign that went viral.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>On March 15, cars pulled to the side of the road, schools halted classes and Israeli President Shimon Peres paused at a conference in the southern Israeli city of Eilat.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>Israelis were not the only ones marking the soldier&amp;apost;s captivity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>&amp;quot;Jews across the world have been pining for Gilad Shalit&amp;apost;s release for over five years,&amp;quot; said William Daroff, a vice president of the Jewish Federations of North America.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>&amp;quot;Thousands of us have had an empty chair at our Passover seder tables reserved for Gilad,&amp;quot; he said, referring to the celebratory meal that marks the beginning of Passover.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;We have prayed for his release.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>We have met with his parents, we have sat with his family in their tent outside the prime minister&amp;apost;s residence, we have marched for Gilad&amp;apost;s release.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Shalit&amp;apost;s parents led a 12-day march from their home in northern Israel to Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu&amp;apost;s office in Jerusalem in June 2010 and camped out in a tent there until last week.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Soon after the protest camp was set up, the British government demanded Shalit&amp;apost;s &amp;quot;immediate and unconditional release.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;His detention is unjustifiable and unacceptable,&amp;quot; the British Foreign Office said on Shalit&amp;apost;s 24th birthday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>In June of this year, the United States condemned Shalit&amp;apost;s captivity &amp;quot;in the strongest possible terms,&amp;quot; according to a White House statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>America &amp;quot;joins other governments and organizations around the world&amp;quot; in calling for his immediate freedom, the statement said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>French President Nicolas Sarkozy said Tuesday his thoughts were with the victims&amp;apost; families of the Palestinian prisoners released under the terms of the deal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>&amp;quot;Gilad could not pay for everybody,&amp;quot; Sarkozy said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>Asked what he missed most during his captivity, Shalit told Nile TV Tuesday he missed his family.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>&amp;quot;I missed going out and meeting people,&amp;quot; he said.&amp;apost;.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>Shalit traveled via Egypt because it acted as a mediator between Israel and Hamas.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Asked why he thought the Egyptians succeeded and others did not, he said, &amp;quot;I think the Egyptians were successful because they have good relations with Hamas and with Israel.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>On whether he will help bring about the release of thousands of Palestinian prisoners in Israeli jails, Shalit said, &amp;quot;I will be glad if they are released, as long as they do not return to fighting Israel.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>And he said he hopes the deal that brought about his release &amp;quot;will move the peace process forward.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Shalit was born August 28, 1986, in the Israeli coastal city of Naharia and moved with his family to western Galilee two years later.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>He has two brothers and was an outstanding science student in high school, his family says.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>An Israeli military operation immediately after his capture failed to free him, and he was held incommunicado throughout his captivity.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>His family calls it a violation of international law that organizations such as the Red Cross were not allowed to see him and that they were only able to get one letter to him.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>The last proof he was alive came in a video in 2009 in which the noticeably thin young man held a newspaper dated September 14.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>In the video, he talks about his family, saying: &amp;quot;I miss them very much, and I am longing for the day when I will see them again.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>The day after his capture, a trio of Palestinian groups, including members of Hamas, Fatah and Islamic Jihad, said they would release him in exchange for all female Palestinian prisoners and all security prisoners under the age of 18 held by Israel, the Shalit family said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>In the end, Israel is releasing significantly more than the Palestinians originally demanded -- despite the objections of at least some Israeli families who do not want to see the killers of their relatives released.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>The Israeli public overwhelmingly supports the agreement to release more than 1,000 prisoners in exchange for Shalit, according to a poll published in the Israeli daily Yedioth Ahronoth the day before his handover by Hamas to Egyptian security.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Israel&amp;apost;s ambassador to London summed up the mixed feelings many experienced in his country as they waited for their most famous captive to taste freedom.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>&amp;quot;Seeing Gilad coming home ... is really coming home to every family.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>But at the same time it&amp;apost;s very bittersweet,&amp;quot; Taub said, since &amp;quot;every one of us in some way has been touched by terrorism.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
