<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2810" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/06/18/world/asia/pakistan-taliban-polio/index.html" date_published="2012-06-18 09:24:45" category="world" author="Reza Sayah, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Taliban to U.S.: End drone strikes in Pakistan, or no more polio vaccines</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">The leader of a Taliban faction in North Waziristan says drone strikes are worse than polio.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="9">The U.S. believes the district is a haven for the Haqqani network and other militant groups.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="10">It&amp;apost;s not clear how the Taliban&amp;apost;s decree will impact the polio eradication campaign.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="5">Pakistan is one of three countries that have yet to eradicate polio.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-02 19:46:17" annotation_time="11.79">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">&amp;quot;Almost every resident of North Waziristan has become a mental patient because of the drone strikes, which are worse than polio,&amp;quot; the statement continued.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="4">Pakistan remains one of only three countries that have yet to eradicate polio.</sentence>
      <sentence id="9" ids_highlights="2">Bahadur commands the faction of the Taliban based in North Waziristan, the district Washington believes is the main safe haven for the Haqqani network and other militant groups fueling the insurgency in Afghanistan.</sentence>
      <sentence id="10" ids_highlights="3">It&amp;apost;s not clear how Bahadur&amp;apost;s decree will impact the polio eradication campaign in North Waziristan or in nearby districts, where he doesn&amp;apost;t wield as much power.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Islamabad, Pakistan A Taliban commander in northwest Pakistan has announced a ban on polio vaccines for children as long as the United States continues its campaign of drone strikes in the region, according to a statement by the Taliban.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;Polio drops will be banned in North Waziristan until the drones strikes are stopped,&amp;quot; said the statement, released Saturday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>&amp;quot;Almost every resident of North Waziristan has become a mental patient because of the drone strikes, which are worse than polio,&amp;quot; the statement continued.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>&amp;quot;On one hand, the U.S. spends millions of dollars to eliminate polio, while on the other hand it kills hundreds with the help of its slave, Pakistan.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>Pakistan remains one of only three countries that have yet to eradicate polio.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The country&amp;apost;s polio campaign made headlines last year when a Pakistani doctor was linked to a CIA operation to verify Osama bin Laden&amp;apost;s whereabouts with a door-to-door vaccination campaign in the town of Abbottabad, where the al Qaeda leader was hiding before he was killed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>U.S. officials have said the plan did not work, but aid groups and Pakistani health officials have said the CIA&amp;apost;s alleged meddling with a vaccination campaign undermined Pakistan&amp;apost;s efforts to eradicate polio.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Taliban commander Hafiz Gul Bahadur made the decision on the vaccination ban after consulting with other Taliban leaders, according to the statement.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Bahadur commands the faction of the Taliban based in North Waziristan, the district Washington believes is the main safe haven for the Haqqani network and other militant groups fueling the insurgency in Afghanistan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s not clear how Bahadur&amp;apost;s decree will impact the polio eradication campaign in North Waziristan or in nearby districts, where he doesn&amp;apost;t wield as much power.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>It is widely believed that Bahadur is allied with the Haqqani network and provides shelter for the group in North Waziristan.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>The United States has pushed Pakistan to launch an offensive against the militant groups in North Waziristan, but Pakistani military officials have resisted, saying their troops are stretched too thin.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>In April, U.S. President Barack Obama&amp;apost;s chief counterterrorism adviser John Brennan acknowledged the use of U.S. drones.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>&amp;quot;Yes, in full accordance with the law -- and in order to prevent terrorist attacks on the United States and to save American lives -- the United States government conducts targeted strikes against specific al Qaeda terrorists, sometimes using remotely piloted aircraft, often referred to publicly as drones,&amp;quot; Brennan said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
