<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2394" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/07/14/world/africa/libya-airport-battle" date_published="2014-07-15 00:42:32" category="world" author="Jomana Karadsheh, CNN " highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Libyan government may request international troops</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="11">NEW: Government says commanders who fire on civilian buildings will face charges.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="2">Rockets reportedly struck the airport and at least two people were killed.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="6">Libyan government says it may request international troops to help stop the violence.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="24">U.N. removes its staff in Tripoli for first time since revolution.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-03 14:15:54" annotation_time="31.12">
      <sentence id="2" ids_highlights="2">In a statement aired on a private Libyan television channel, one of the three main Zintan groups in Tripoli said that at least two members of the force defending positions at the airport were killed in a rocket attack.</sentence>
      <sentence id="6" ids_highlights="3">The government in a written statement said early Tuesday that it discussed at an emergency session &amp;quot;a potential request for international forces to solidify the state&amp;apost;s capabilities&amp;quot; at an emergency session.</sentence>
      <sentence id="11" ids_highlights="1">It said any commander that orders attacks on civilian facilities, including the airport, will face charges of murder.</sentence>
      <sentence id="24" ids_highlights="4">It was the first time the U.N. staff in Tripoli had left since the revolution.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>Tripoli, Libya Fighting continued Monday as rival Libyan militias battled for Tripoli International Airport and the interim government said it was considering asking for international military help.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>In a statement aired on a private Libyan television channel, one of the three main Zintan groups in Tripoli said that at least two members of the force defending positions at the airport were killed in a rocket attack.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Al-Qaaqaa brigade said at least three other people were wounded.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>A photo posted on several Zintan Facebook pages showed a makeshift clinic set up inside the airport&amp;apost;s main terminal.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>CNN could not independently verify when the image was taken.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>The government in a written statement said early Tuesday that it discussed at an emergency session &amp;quot;a potential request for international forces to solidify the state&amp;apost;s capabilities&amp;quot; at an emergency session.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>While Libyan officials have called for calm, the government is weak and militias outnumber and outgun its security forces.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>Many of the armed groups are on the state&amp;apost;s payroll.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>These circumstances make it very difficult for the government to gain control over this latest increasingly volatile and violent situation.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Still the government on Tuesday called for an immediate halt to the fighting and for the militias to withdraw within a week at least 20 kilometers (12 miles) from the airport.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>It said any commander that orders attacks on civilian facilities, including the airport, will face charges of murder.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>A resident who lives near the airport told CNN families in the area are fearful they will be killed or injured by what appears to them as indiscriminate shelling.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>The Libyan government statement said peacekeepers might give it a chance to build a suitable army and police force.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>More rocket attacks.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Local media reported earlier Monday that rockets had hit the airport.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>A CNN crew could hear sporadic gunfire and explosions in the direction of the airport.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>The government said the customs building, maintenance building and some national security department planes had been destroyed.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>It also said 90% of the airliners parked there had been damaged as had the control tower.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>The damage to the planes, many of which belong to the two national airlines, is in the hundreds of millions of dollars, the government said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>The United Nations announced that it had evacuated its staff.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;This is a temporary measure,&amp;quot; the United Nations said in a written statement.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;Staff will return as soon as security conditions permit.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>The United Nations, which stood by the Libyan people in their revolution in 2011, will not abandon them as they seek to build a democratic state.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>It was the first time the U.N. staff in Tripoli had left since the revolution.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The U.S. embassy updated its security message for Americans in the country, cautioning them to stay away from the airport, Airport Road and another nearby street.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>It said it could only provide limited emergency services to U.S. citizens.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>No air traffic.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>All flights in and out of the airport have been suspended.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>Brigades from the Zintan militia have controlled the airport since the Libyan civil war in 2011.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>Other militias have tried to wrest control of the airport from the Zintan brigades for years.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>Armed vehicles gathered in the area overnight before fighting broke out around dawn Sunday, witnesses said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Nine people were killed that day and 25 others wounded, the government said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>Tensions remain.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Even though Libyans successfully toppled the 42-year rule of Moammar Gadhafi in 2011, the country is far from stable.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>Armed militias are now the biggest challenge.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>The international community has largely agreed that the key to resolving Libya&amp;apost;s crisis is national dialogue.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>But a weak central government -- combined with militias split along regional, tribal and ideological lines -- has added to the challenge.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>The U.S. State Department said this past weekend it was concerned the fighting could lead to widespread conflict and backed the new government.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>&amp;quot;We affirm our support for Libya&amp;apost;s democratic transition and urge the seating of the new Council of Representatives as soon as possible,&amp;quot; the statement added.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>&amp;quot;Finally, we stress the vital role Libya&amp;apost;s Constitution Drafting Assembly plays in building the new country for which Libyans sacrificed so much during the revolution.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
