<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2272" link="http://www.cnn.com/2014/03/06/world/europe/ukraine-crimea-locals/index.html" date_published="2014-03-06 19:57:41" category="world" author="Elizabeth Landau, Diana Magnay and Ben Wedeman, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false" mapping_error_divergence_mapping="false">
  <title>In Crimea: &amp;apost;We will protect our lands from Western extremists&amp;apost;</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="30">Crimean supporters of Russia gather in public.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="17">One woman says they will protect the land from &amp;quot;Western extremists&amp;quot;.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="34">In Yalta, Alex Shiroki says hotels are closing .</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="42">He is considering leaving Crimea if it becomes part of Russia.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-10-20 17:09:31" annotation_time="173.527" mapping_time_divergence="43.38175">
      <sentence id="17" ids_highlights="2">&amp;quot;Our grandparents protected our land from the SS, and we will protect our land from Western extremists,&amp;quot; one woman shouted.</sentence>
      <sentence id="30" ids_highlights="1">In the seaside resort city of Yalta, Alex Shiroki observed a crowd of hundreds gathered Wednesday by a monument to Vladimir Lenin, singing songs and waving flags in support of Russia.</sentence>
      <sentence id="34" ids_highlights="3">With tourism as a main industry in the city, several hotels are closing their doors, with at least one big hotel firing personnel, Shiroki said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="42" ids_highlights="4">If Crimea does become part of Russia, as Shiroki suspects it probably will, he will consider leaving the country.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>&amp;quot;Are you for Ukraine or for Russia?&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>Alex Shiroki&amp;apost;s boss asked him Thursday.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>Shiroki, 35, from Yalta, opposes the Russian invasion, and the proposed rejoining of Crimea to Russia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>But he carefully said his views are &amp;quot;something in the middle&amp;quot; -- just in case his opinion could affect his job.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>His boss supports Russia.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;He says that Russia is more rich than Ukraine and we will have stability,&amp;quot; Shiroki said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;Most of (the) people think like that.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s amazing how normal life continues to appear in some parts of Crimea.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>People still go to work, to restaurants, to bars.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>But tensions continue to mount in the region, where lawmakers voted Thursday in favor of rejoining Russia and having a referendum in 10 days.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>Many people are sincerely grateful for the Russian presence, said Maria Zaborovska, 24, who lives in Crimea and is translating for international radio journalists.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>&amp;quot;I don&amp;apost;t know if they fully realize -- if they know what it means,&amp;quot; Zaborovska said of the pro-Russia supporters.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>Many of them were born in the Soviet Union and speak Russian, she said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>As to how they would benefit from Crimea becoming part of Russia, people who support breaking off from Ukraine don&amp;apost;t seem to have answers, she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Zaborovska herself is against the Russian invasion.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>In the main square in Simferopol, a crowd gathered Wednesday in support of Russia, waving flags.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;Our grandparents protected our land from the SS, and we will protect our land from Western extremists,&amp;quot; one woman shouted.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>&amp;quot;Thank you Russia for protecting us.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Biscuits with Crimean jam were served up at a pro-Russian militia recruitment center, with a portrait of Russian President Vladimir Putin watching over.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Anna Bardina a Russia supporter, told CNN&amp;apost;s Diana Magnay that she has been receiving threatening texts from far right elements, and even death threats from Chechnya.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>&amp;quot;Russia is far more stable,&amp;quot; she said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>&amp;quot;They have no economic problems, not like here where we have movements like the Maidan and are in a political and economic mess,&amp;quot; she said, referring to the popular pro-European street rallies that led to the ouster of Ukrainian President Viktor Yanukovych.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Areas around military bases showcase the bubbling tensions.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>Wednesday, outside the headquarters of the Ukrainian navy in Sevastopol, women tried to sneak up to windows and shove food through to the soldiers inside.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The facility is surrounded by pro-Russian civilians who call themselves a &amp;quot;civil defense group,&amp;quot; backed up by masked, armed men in green combat fatigues, presumed to be Russian soldiers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>A woman with her young daughter, bringing soup and meatballs to her husband inside, was turned away.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>So was a Sevastopol Red Cross worker who tried to bring in supplies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>&amp;quot;There are no problems with food,&amp;quot; one of the men told him.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>&amp;quot;Anyone who wants to eat can go home.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>In the seaside resort city of Yalta, Alex Shiroki observed a crowd of hundreds gathered Wednesday by a monument to Vladimir Lenin, singing songs and waving flags in support of Russia.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>He thought the pro-Russian presence would be even bigger.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>Shiroki doesn&amp;apost;t mind people expressing their opinion, but the latest string of political developments has him depressed.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>&amp;quot;It&amp;apost;s happening so fast that I am kind of lost and disoriented by all of this,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>With tourism as a main industry in the city, several hotels are closing their doors, with at least one big hotel firing personnel, Shiroki said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;Smaller hotels, they just closed because maybe they think there is no hope of having tourists in summer,&amp;quot; he said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s unclear if they will re-open.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>For now, the region is largely blocked off by troops and vacationers are likely making other plans in the face of obvious tensions.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Shiroki has not seen any of the presumably Russian soldiers in unmarked green uniforms, as his friends have encountered in other cities such as Simferopol.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>As a joke, people refer to these troops as &amp;quot;polite armed people,&amp;quot; Shiroki said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>One of Shiroki&amp;apost;s friends brought food to Ukrainian soldiers at a military base in Perevalnoe, near Simferopol, and told Shiroki he was stopped by soldiers about 20 times on the way.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>After answering many questions, he was able to deliver the food through a gate, but could not go inside.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>If Crimea does become part of Russia, as Shiroki suspects it probably will, he will consider leaving the country.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>Shiroki has been studying Polish, so Poland could be an option, or perhaps elsewhere in Europe or the United States.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>&amp;quot;If you dislike living in a place ruled by a power you dislike, maybe you should change your life,&amp;quot; Shiroki said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
