<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="2125" link="http://edition.cnn.com/2014/09/05/world/asia/china-isis/index.html?iid=article_sidebar" date_published="2014-09-05 12:18:59" category="world" author="Jaime A. FlorCruz, CNN" highlights_mapped="true" mapping_error="false">
  <title>Chinese national &amp;apost;captured&amp;apost; fighting for ISIS</title>
  <keywords />
  <summaries>
    <highlights>
      <sentence id="1" ids_article_sentences="3">Iraqi Army has captured Islamic State in Iraq and Syria fighter from China, report said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="2" ids_article_sentences="5">If true, he would be first Chinese national caught fighting with ISIS militants.</sentence>
      <sentence id="3" ids_article_sentences="16">One Chinese commentator assumes the man is Uighur, a Muslim minority group.</sentence>
      <sentence id="4" ids_article_sentences="36">Beijing has stepped up efforts to appease local dissatisfaction and curb violence.</sentence>
    </highlights>
    <gold_standard annotation_date="2014-11-13 14:13:25" annotation_time="19.973999">
      <sentence id="3" ids_highlights="1">The Iraqi Army has captured an Islamic State in Iraq and Syria fighter from China, the Baghdad-datelined report said.</sentence>
      <sentence id="5" ids_highlights="2">If true, he would be the first Chinese national to have been caught fighting with ISIS militants.</sentence>
      <sentence id="16" ids_highlights="3">It remains unclear if the captured Chinese national is actually Uighur, a Muslim minority group in Xinjiang, but Gao seems to assume so.</sentence>
      <sentence id="36" ids_highlights="4">Beijing has stepped up its carrot-and-stick efforts to appease local dissatisfaction and curb violence.</sentence>
    </gold_standard>
  </summaries>
  <article>
    <paragraph id="1">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="1">
          <content>&amp;quot;URGENT,&amp;quot; read the Iraqi News headline of its September 3 posting.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="2">
          <content>&amp;quot;First Chinese ISIS fighter captured in Iraq says Ministry of Defense.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="2">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="3">
          <content>The Iraqi Army has captured an Islamic State in Iraq and Syria fighter from China, the Baghdad-datelined report said.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="4">
          <content>Two pictures accompanied the report: one showed the captured militant in fatigue pants and a bloodied shirt, lying on the ground; another showed him escorted by an Iraqi soldier, his face seemingly swollen.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="3">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="5">
          <content>If true, he would be the first Chinese national to have been caught fighting with ISIS militants.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="4">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="6">
          <content>&amp;quot;We are not able to verify whether or not the information is true,&amp;quot; said Chinese foreign ministry spokesman Qin Gang, responding to a foreign reporter&amp;apost;s question.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="7">
          <content>&amp;quot;I cannot confirm the information for you.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="5">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="8">
          <content>It&amp;apost;s not clear how many Chinese nationals may be fighting with the ISIS.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="9">
          <content>Wu Sike, until recently China&amp;apost;s special envoy to the Middle East, earlier stated that there could be about 100 of them, but Qin Gang said he had no specific numbers or estimates.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="6">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="10">
          <content>Chinese netizens&amp;apost; reaction was typically visceral.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="11">
          <content>&amp;quot;Kill them!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="12">
          <content>commented &amp;quot;Hellen&amp;quot; on the Iraqi News website.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="13">
          <content>&amp;quot;we chinese are glad to see these muslims&amp;apost; death!&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="7">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="14">
          <content>If such reports are true, said Chinese commentator Victor Gao, &amp;quot;this will be an additional evidence that terrorism in China has a strong international connection.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="15">
          <content>Terrorism does not care about national borders.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="8">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="16">
          <content>It remains unclear if the captured Chinese national is actually Uighur, a Muslim minority group in Xinjiang, but Gao seems to assume so.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="9">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="17">
          <content>&amp;quot;In China terrorism is raising its ugly head and is spreading from Xinjiang to other parts of China.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="18">
          <content>The underlying drivers for terrorism are mainly the congruence of domestic and international forces at play among some extreme elements of the Uighur minority in Xinjiang,&amp;quot; he added.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="10">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="19">
          <content>Xinjiang, a resource-rich and strategically located region in northwest China, for years has been beset by ethnic violence, which the government blames on &amp;quot;fenliefenzi&amp;quot; (&amp;quot;separatists&amp;quot;).</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="20">
          <content>Uighur exiles and rights activists, however, blame the unrest on Beijing&amp;apost;s allegedly repressive and discriminatory policies.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="11">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="21">
          <content>A spate of violent incidents have been blamed on the Uighurs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="12">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="22">
          <content>In March, more than 10 masked people, dressed in identical black outfits and wielding machetes, stabbed passengers in Kunming Railway Station in Yunnan province, thousands of miles away from Beijing, killing 29 people and injured 143 others.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="23">
          <content>Police killed four of the attackers and arrested one woman.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="13">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="24">
          <content>In May, terrorists used car bombs to attack an open-air market in Urumqi, the region&amp;apost;s capital, leaving 39 dead and 94 injured.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="14">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="25">
          <content>The police later blamed the knife and bomb attacks on members of the East Turkistan Islamic Movement (ETIM), an Islamist group founded in 1993 by Uighur militants seeking an independent state in Xinjiang called East Turkistan.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="15">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="26">
          <content>The ETIM has been accused by the China and the U.S. of having ties with al Qaeda, but security analysts disagree on whether such ties actually exist.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="27">
          <content>Uighur exile groups claim that Beijing uses the ETIM as a red herring to rationalize its repressive policies against the Uighurs.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="16">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="28">
          <content>If the Iraqi News report is true, said M. Taylor Fravel, an international relations professor at MIT, it shows that &amp;quot;radicalization transcends boundaries and regions, threatening not only countries in the Middle East but also China and the West.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="29">
          <content>That said, Uighurs have a long history of fighting overseas.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="30">
          <content>I believe that Uighurs fought against the Soviets in Afghanistan, for example.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="31">
          <content>So the phenomenon is not a new one.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="17">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="32">
          <content>In 2006, the U.S. captured 22 Uighur militants fighting in Afghanistan with suspected links to al Qaeda.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="33">
          <content>They were imprisoned in Guantanamo for five to seven years and later released after they were reclassified as no longer enemy combatants.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="34">
          <content>Instead of repatriating them to China, however, they were sent to Palau and Bermuda.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="18">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="35">
          <content>&amp;quot;China will surely use this to underscore the challenges it faces in maintaining stability in Xinjiang, but I don&amp;apost;t think that this will alter the policies being pursued, which seem to be increasing instability and not decreasing it,&amp;quot; MIT&amp;apost;s Fravel said.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="19">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="36">
          <content>Beijing has stepped up its carrot-and-stick efforts to appease local dissatisfaction and curb violence.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="20">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="37">
          <content>Speaking in a two-day conference on Xinjiang in May, President Xi Jinping promised to enhance &amp;quot;ethnic unity&amp;quot; in Xinjiang while creating more jobs, providing accessible education and improving people&amp;apost;s livelihoods.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="21">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="38">
          <content>Xi also pledged to respect the local residents&amp;apost; legitimate religious rights and local customs &amp;quot;in accordance with laws and regulations.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="22">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="39">
          <content>But Xi also called for a massive &amp;quot;nets spread from the earth to the sky&amp;quot; to combat terrorists, stating that the stability of Xinjiang is &amp;quot;strategically vital to the country&amp;apost;s reform and development as well as national security.&amp;quot;</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="23">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="40">
          <content>In response to the spate of violent attacks, China has launched a one-year campaign against terrorism.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="24">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="41">
          <content>Chinese police in various cities have held anti-terrorism drills using sophisticated equipment such as satellite vans, armored cars and modern weapons.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="25">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="42">
          <content>Bulk purchasers of gasoline are now required to provide identification, secure permits from local police stations and use only approved containers.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="26">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="43">
          <content>In some places, sales of large knives are controlled or banned.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="27">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="44">
          <content>Local courts in Xinjiang have been given instructions to deal with terror cases in a &amp;quot;harsh and quick&amp;quot; manner.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="45">
          <content>In June, China executed 13 people convicted of organizing and leading terrorist groups.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="28">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="46">
          <content>China&amp;apost;s critics fear the campaign could lead to more repressive policies toward Uighurs, widening ethnic divide.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="29">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="47">
          <content>For years tensions have been simmering between the Han Chinese and the Uighur minority nationality.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="30">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="48">
          <content>I saw tensions boil over in the streets of Urumqi in July 2009, when thousands of angry Uighur residents, some wielding knives and sticks, rioted in the streets and attacked Han Chinese, prompting the authorities to call in truckloads of Chinese soldiers.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="49">
          <content>Nearly 200 people died in the ethnic clashes.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="31">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="50">
          <content>Authorities blame separatists for fomenting violence, but critics of China&amp;apost;s policies say the root of the problem is widespread alienation among the region&amp;apost;s Muslim Uighur population who resent strict controls on religion and local culture.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="32">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="51">
          <content>Uighurs also resent the influx into the region of Han Chinese migrants, who tend to dominate the local industry and commerce.</content>
        </sentence>
        <sentence id="52">
          <content>They complain they are being left behind by rapid economic development, and are unable to partake of the benefits from the region&amp;apost;s rich resources.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph id="33">
      <sentences>
        <sentence id="53">
          <content>All these, critics say, have made Xinjiang a breeding ground for malcontents.</content>
        </sentence>
      </sentences>
    </paragraph>
  </article>
</document>
